Learning Horizontal Connections in a Sparse

Coding Model of Natural Images

Authored by:

Bruno A. Olshausen

Pierre Garrigues

Abstract

It has been shown that adapting a dictionary of basis functions to the
statistics of natural images so as to maximize sparsity in the coeﬃcients
results in a set of dictionary elements whose spatial properties resemble
those of V1 (primary visual cortex) receptive ﬁelds. However, the resulting
sparse coeﬃcients still exhibit pronounced statistical dependencies, thus
violating the independence assumption of the sparse coding model. Here,
we propose a model that attempts to capture the dependencies among
the basis function coeﬃcients by including a pairwise coupling term in the
prior over the coeﬃcient activity states. When adapted to the statistics
of natural images, the coupling terms learn a combination of facilitatory
and inhibitory interactions among neighboring basis functions. These
learned interactions may oﬀer an explanation for the function of horizontal
connections in V1, and we discuss the implications of our ﬁndings for
physiological experiments.

1 Paper Body

Over the last decade, mathematical explorations into the statistics of natural
scenes have led to the observation that these scenes, as complex and varied as
they appear, have an underlying structure that is sparse [1]. That is, one can
learn a possibly overcomplete basis set such that only a small fraction of the
basis functions is necessary to describe a given image, where the operation to
infer this sparse representation is non-linear. This approach is known as sparse
coding. Exploiting this structure has led to advances in our understanding of
how information is represented in the visual cortex, since the learned basis set
is a collection of oriented, Gabor-like ﬁlters that resemble the receptive ﬁelds in
primary visual cortex (V1). The approach of using sparse coding to infer sparse
representations of unlabeled data is useful for classiﬁcation as shown in the
framework of self-taught learning [2]. Note that classiﬁcation performance re-
lies on ﬁnding ?hard-sparse? representations where a few coeﬃcients are nonzero
while all the others are exactly zero. An assumption of the sparse coding model

1

is that the coeﬃcients of the representation are independent. However, in the
case of natural images, this is not the case. For example, the coeﬃcients corre-
sponding to quadrature pair or colinear Gabor ﬁlters are not independent. This
has been shown and modeled in the early work of [3], in the case of the re-
sponses of model complex cells [4], feedforward responses of wavelet coeﬃcients
[5, 6, 7] or basis functions learned using independent component analysis [8, 9].
These dependencies are informative and exploiting them leads to improvements
in denoising performance [5, 7]. We develop here a generative model of image
patches that does not make the independence assumption. The prior over the
coeﬃcients is a mixture of a Gaussian when the corresponding basis 1

function is active, and a delta function centered at zero when it is silent as
in [10]. We model the binary variables or ?spins? that control the activation
of the basis functions with an Ising model, whose coupling weights model the
dependencies among the coeﬃcients. The representations inferred by this model
are also ?hard-sparse?, which is a desirable feature [2]. Our model is motivated
in part by the architecture of the visual cortex, namely the extensive network
of horizontal connections among neurons in V1 [11]. It has been hypothesized
that they facilitate contour integration [12] and are involved in computing border
ownership [13]. In both of these models the connections are set a priori based
on geometrical properties of the receptive ﬁelds. We propose here to learn the
connection weights in an unsupervised fashion. We hope with our model to gain
insight into the the computations performed by this extensive collateral system
and compare our ﬁndings to known physiological properties of these horizontal
connections. Furthermore, a recent trend in neuroscience is to model networks
of neurons using Ising models, and it has been shown to predict remarkably
well the statistics of groups of neurons in the retina [14]. Our model gives a
prediction for what is expected if one ﬁts an Ising model to future multi-unit
recordings in V1.

2 A non-factorial sparse coding model Let x ? Rn be an image patch, where
the xi ?s are the pixel values. We propose the following generative model: m X
x = ?a + ? = ai ?i + ?, i=1

n?m
where ? = [?1 . . . ?m ] ? R is an overcomplete transform or basis set, and
the columns ?i are its basis functions. ? ? N (0, ?2 In ) is small Gaussian noise.
Each coeﬃcient ai = si2+1 ui is a Gaussian scale mixture (GSM). We model the
multiplier s with an Ising model, i.e. s ? {?1, 1}m T 1 T has a Boltzmann-Gibbs
distribution p(s) = Z1 e 2 s W s+b s , where Z is the normalization constant.
If the spin si is down (si = ?1), then ai = 0 and the basis function ?i is silent.
If the spin si is up (si = 1), then the basis function is active and the analog
value of the coeﬃcient ai is drawn from a Gaussian distribution with ui ? N (0,
?i2 ). The prior on a can thus be described as a ?hard-sparse? prior as it is a
mixture of a point mass at zero and a Gaussian. The corresponding graphical
model is shown in Figure 1. It is a chain graph since it contains both undirected
and directed edges. It bears similarities to [15], which however does not have
the intermediate layer a and is not a sparse coding model. To sample from
this generative model, one ﬁrst obtains a sample s from the Ising model, then

2

samples coeﬃcients a according to p(a — s), and then x according to p(x — a)
? N (?a, ?2 In ). W1m s1

s2
a1
a2
sm W2m am
?
x1
x2
xn
Figure 1: Proposed graphical model The parameters of the model to be
learned from data are ? = (?, (?i2 )i=1..m , W, b). This model does not make
any assumption about which linear code ? should be used, and about which
units should exhibit dependencies. The matrix W of the interaction weights in
the Ising model describes these dependencies. Wij ¿ 0 favors positive correlations
and thus corresponds to an excitatory connection, whereas Wij ¡ 0 corresponds
to an inhibitory connection. A local magnetic ﬁeld bi ¡ 0 favors the spin si to
be down, which in turn makes the basis function ?i mostly silent. 2

3 Inference and learning 3.1 Coeﬃcient estimation We describe here how
to infer the representation a of an image patch x in our model. To do so, we
ﬁrst compute the maximum a posteriori (MAP) multiplier s (see Section 3.2).
Indeed, a GSM model reduces to a linear-Gaussian model conditioned on the
multiplier s, and therefore the estimation of a is easy once s is known. Given s
= s?, let ? = {i : s?i = 1} be the set of active basis functions. We know that
?i ? / ?, ai = 0. Hence, we have x = ?? a? + ?, where a? = (ai )i?? and ??
= [(?i )i?? ]. The model reduces thus to linear-Gaussian, where a? ? N (0, H
= diag((?i2 )i?? )). We have a? — x, s? ? N (?, K), where K = (??2 ?? ?T?
+ H ?1 )?1 and ? = ??2 K?T? x. Hence, conditioned on x and s?, the Bayes
Least-Square (BLS) and maximum a posteriori (MAP) estimators of a? are the
same and given by ?. 3.2 Multiplier estimation The MAP estimate of s given x
is given byPs? = arg maxs p(s — x). Given s, x has a Gaussian distribution
N (0, ?), where ? = ?2 In + i : si =1 ?i2 ?i ?Ti . Using Bayes? rule, we can
write p(s — x) ? p(x — s)p(s) ? e?Ex (s) , where 1 T ?1 1 1 x ? x + log
det ? ? sT W s ? bT s. 2 2 2 We can thus compute the MAP estimate using
Gibbs sampling and simulated annealing. In the Gibbs sampling procedure, the
probability that node i changes its value from si to s?i given x, all the other
nodes s?i and at temperature T is given by ?1

?Ex p(si ? s?i —s?i , x) = 1 + exp ? , T Ex (s) =
where ?Ex = Ex (si , s?i ) ? Ex (s?i , s?i ). Note that computing Ex requires
the inverse and the ? and ? be the covariance matrices corresponding to the
determinant of ?, which is expensive. Let ? proposed state (s?i , s?i ) and
current state (si , s?i ) respectively. They diﬀer only by a rank 1 matrix, ? = ?
+ ??i ?T , where ? = 1 (s?i ? si )? 2 . Therefore, to compute ?Ex we can take
advantage i.e. ? i i 2 of the Sherman-Morrison formula ? ?1 = ??1 ? ???1 ?i (1
+ ??Ti ??1 ?i )?1 ?Ti ??1 ? (1) and of a similar formula for the log det term

? = log det ? + log 1 + ??Ti ??1 ?i . log det ?

3

(2)
Using (1) and (2) ?Ex can be written as T
?Ex =
?1
2
1 1 ?(x ? ?i ) ? log 1 + ??Ti ??1 ?i 2 1 + ??Ti ??1 ?i 2
? ? X + (s?i ? si ) ? Wij sj + bi ? . j6=i
The transition probabilities can thus be computed eﬃciently, and if a new
state is accepted we update ? and ??1 using (1). 3.3 Model estimation Given
, x(N ) } of image patches, we want to learn the
a dataset D = {x(1) , .
parameters ? = P (i) (?, (?i2 )i=1..m , W, b) that oﬀer the best explanation of
the data. Let p? (x) = N1 N i=1 ?(x ? x ) be the empirical distribution. Since
in our model the variables a and s are latent, we use a variational expectation
maximization algorithm [16] to optimize ?, which amounts to maximizing a
lower bound on the log-likelihood derived using Jensen?s inequality XZ p(x, a,
s — ?) da, log p(x — ?) ? q(a, s — x) log q(a, s — x) a s 3
where q(a, s — x) is a probability distribution. We restrict ourselves to the
family of point mass distributions Q = {q(a, s — x) = ?(a ? a ?)?(s ? s?)},
and with this choice the lower bound on the log-likelihood of D can be written
as L(?, q)

.

.

= Ep? [log p(x, a ?, s? — ?)]
(3) s?, (?i2 )i=1..m )] + Ep? [log p(? s—
a— = Ep? [log p(x — a ?, ?)] + Ep? [log p(? — {z } — {z L?
L?
We perform coordinate ascent in the objective function L(?, q).
}
—{z
LW,b
W, b)] . }
3.3.1 Maximization with respect to q We want to solve maxq?Q L(?, q),
which amounts to ﬁnding arg maxa,s log p(x, a, s) for every x ? D. This is
computationally expensive since s is discrete. Hence, we introduce two phases
in the algorithm. In the ﬁrst phase, we infer in the usual sparse coding model
where the prior over a Q the coeﬃcients Q is factorial, i.e. p(a) = i p(ai ) ? i
exp{??S(ai )}. In this setting, we have Y X 1 a ? = arg max p(x—a) e??S(ai )
= arg min 2 kx ? ?ak22 + ? S(ai ). (4) a a 2? i i With S(ai ) = —ai —, (4) is
known as basis pursuit denoising (BPDN) whose solution has been shown to be
such that many coeﬃcient of a ? are exactly zero [17]. This allows us to recover
the sparsity pattern s?, where s?i = 2.1[a?i 6= 0] ? 1 ?i. BPDN can be solved
eﬃciently using a competitive algorithm [18]. Another possible choice is S(ai )
= 1[ai 6= 0] (p(ai ) is not a proper prior though), where (4) is combinatorial
and can be solved approximately using orthogonal matching pursuits (OMP)
[19]. After several iterations of coordinate ascent and convergence of ? using
the above approximation, we enter the second phase of the algorithm and reﬁne
? by using the GSM inference described in Section 3.1 where s? = arg max

4

p(s—x) and a ? = E[a — s?, x]. 3.3.2 Maximization with respect to ? We want
to solve max? L(?, q). Our choice of variational posterior allowed us to write
the objective function as the sum of the three terms L? , L? and LW,b (3), and
hence to decouple the variables ?, (?i2 )i=1..m and (W, b) of our optimization
problem. Maximization of L? . Note that L? is the same objective function as
in the standard sparse coding problem when the coeﬃcients a are ﬁxed. Let {?
a(i) , s?(i) } be the coeﬃcients and multipliers (i) corresponding to x . We have
L? = ?

N 1 X (i) Nn kx ? ?? a(i) k22 ? log 2??2 . 2 2? i=1 2
We add the constraint that k?i k2 ? 1 to avoid the spurious solution where
the norm of the basis functions grows and the coeﬃcients tend to 0. We solve
this ?2 constrained least-square problem using the Lagrange dual as in [20].
Maximization of L? . The problem of estimating ?i2 is a standard variance
estimation problem for a 0-mean Gaussian random variable, where we only
consider the samples a?i such that the spin s?i is equal to 1, i.e. X 1 ?i2 = (a?i
(k) )2 . (k) card{k : s?i = 1} k : s? (k) =1 i

Maximization of LW,b . This problem is tantamount to estimating the
parameters of a fully visible Boltzmann machine [21] which is a convex opti-
mization problem. We do gradient ascent in LW,b , ?L ?L where the gradients
are given by ?WW,b = ?Ep? [si sj ] + Ep [si sj ] and ?bW,b = ?Ep? [si ] + Ep
[si ]. ij i We use Gibbs sampling to obtain estimates of Ep [si sj ] and Ep [si ]. 4
Note that since computing the parameters (? a, s?) of the variational pos-
terior in phase 1 only depends on ?, we ﬁrst perform several steps of coordinate
ascent in (?, q) until ? has converged, which is the same as in the usual sparse
coding algorithm. We then maximize L? and LW,b , and after that we enter
the second phase of the algorithm.

4 Recovery of the model parameters Although the learning algorithm relies
on a method where the family of variational posteriors q(a, s — x) is quite
limited, we argue here that if data D = {x(1) , . . . , x(N ) } is being sampled
according to parameters ?0 that obey certain conditions that we describe now,
then our proposed learning algorithm is able to recover ?0 with good accuracy
using phase 1 only. Let ? be the coherence parameter of the basis set which
equals the maximum absolute inner product between two distinct basis func-
tions. It has been shown that given a signal that is a sparse linear combination
of p basis functions, BP and OMP will identify the optimal basis functions and
their coeﬃcients provided that p ¡ 21 (? ?1 + 1), and the sparsest representation
of the signal is unique [19]. Similar results can be derived when noise is present
(? ¿ 0) [22], but we restrict ourselves to the noiseless case for simplicity. Let
ksk? be the number of spins that are up. We require (W0 , b0 ) to be such that
P r ksk? ¡ 12 (? ?1 + 1) ? 1, which can be enforced by imposing strong negative
biases. A data point x(i) ? D thus has a high probability of yielding a unique
sparse representation in the basis set ?. Provided that we have a good estimate
of ? we can recover its sparse representation using OMP or BP, and therefore
identify s(i) that was used to originally sample x(i) . That is we recover with
high probability all the samples from the Ising model used to generate D, which
allows us to recover (W0 , b0 ). We provide for illustration a simple example of

5

model recovery where n P= 7 and m = 8. Let (e1 , . . . , e7 ) be an orthonormal
basis in R7 . We let ?0 = [e1 , . . . e7 , ?17 i ei ]. We ﬁx the biases b0 at ?1.2
such that the model is suﬃciently sparse as shown by the histogram of ksk? in
Figure 2, and the weights W0 are sampled according to a Gaussian distribution.
The variance parameters ?0 are ﬁxed to 1. We then generate synthetic data by
sampling 100000 data from this model using ?0 . We then estimate ? from this
synthetic data using the variational method described in Section 3 using OMP
and phase 1 only. We found that the basis functions are recovered exactly (not
shown), and that the parameters of the Ising model are recovered with high
accuracy as shown in Figure 2. 4

14
x 10
b0
sparsity histogram
W0
0
12
0.2
?1
10 ?2
8
0.1 1
2
3
2 0
4
5
6
7 0
b
6 4
0
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
W 0.2
0.1 0
0
?0.1
?0.1
?1
?0.2

6

?0.2
?2
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
Figure 2: Recovery of the model. The histogram of ksk? is such that the
model is sparse. The parameters (W, b) learned from synthetic data are close
to the parameters (W0 , b0 ) from which this data was generated.

5 Results for natural images We build our training set by randomly selecting
16 ? 16 image patches from a standard set of 10 512 ? 512 whitened images as in
[1]. It has been shown that change of luminance or contrast have little inﬂuence
on the structure of natural scenes [23]. As our goal is to uncover this structure,
we subtract from each patch its own mean and divide it by its standard deviation
such that our dataset is contrast normalized (we do not consider the patches
whose variance is below a small threshold). We ﬁx the number of basis functions
to 256. In the second phase of the algorithm we only update ?, and we have
found that the basis functions do not change dramatically after the ﬁrst phase.
Figure 3 shows the learned parameters ?, ? and b. The basis functions resemble
Gabor ﬁlters at a variety of orientations, positions and scales. We show the
weights W in Figure 4 according to 5

?
? 2 1 0 0
50
100
150
200
250
150
200
250
b 0 ?0.5 ?1 0
50
100
Figure 3: On the left is shown the entire set of basis functions ? learned
on natural images. On the right are the learned variances (?i2 )i=1..m (top)
and the biases b in the Ising model (bottom). the spatial properties (position,
orientation, length) of the basis functions that are linked together by them.
Each basis function is denoted by a bar that indicates its position, orientation,
and length within the 16 ? 16 patch. ?i

(a) 10 most positive weights
?j
?k

7

Wij ¡ 0 Wik ¿ 0
(b) 10 most negative weights (c) Weights visualization
(d) Association ﬁelds
Figure 4: (a) (resp.

(b)) shows the basis function pairs that share the
strongest positive (resp. negative) weights ordered from left to right. Each
subplot in (d) shows the association ﬁeld for a basis function ?i whose posi-
tion and orientation are denoted by the black bar. The horizontal connections
(Wij )j6=i are displayed by a set of colored bars whose orientation and posi-
tion denote those of the basis functions ?j to which they correspond, and the
color denotes the connection strength (see (c)). We show a random selection of
36 association ﬁelds, see www.eecs.berkeley.edu/ garrigue/nips07.html for the
whole set. We observe that the connections are mainly local and connect basis
functions at a variety of orientations. The histogram of the weights (see Figure
5) shows a long positive tail corresponding to a bias toward facilitatory con-
nections. We can see in Figure 4a,b that the 10 most ?positive? pairs have
similar orientations, whereas the majority of the 10 most ?negative? pairs have
dissimilar orientations. We compute for a basis function the average number of
basis functions sharing with it a weight larger than 0.01 as a function of their
orientation diﬀerence in four bins, which we refer to as the ?orientation proﬁle?
in Figure 5. The error bars are a standard deviation. The resulting orientation
proﬁle is consistent with what has been observed in physiological experiments
[24, 25]. We also show in Figure 5 the tradeoﬀ between the signal to noise ratio
(SNR) of an image patch x and its reconstruction ?? a, and the ?0 norm of
the representation k? ak0 . We consider a ? inferred using both the Laplacian
prior and our proposed prior. We vary ? (see Equation (4)) and ? respectively,
and average over 1000 patches to obtain the two tradeoﬀ curves. We see that at
similar SNR the representations inferred by our model are more sparse by about
a factor of 2, which bodes well for compression. We have also compared our
prior for tasks such as denoising and ﬁlling-in, and have found its performance
to be similar to the factorial Laplacian prior even though it does not exploit the
dependencies of the code. One possible explanation is that the greater sparsity
of our inferred representations makes them less robust to noise. Thus we are
currently investigating whether this 6

property may instead have advantages in the self-taught learning setting in

improving classiﬁcation performance. T

(W,? ?) correlation
coupling weights histogram
110
12
100
0.08
5000 0.06
4000
W ij
0.04 0.02
3000

8

0
2000 ?0.02
80 8
6
0.05
0.1
?0.06 0
0.15
weights
0.2 —? Ti ? j —
0.3
?2
0.4
60 50
2
40
0
0.1
70
4
?0.04
0
Laplacian prior proposed prior
90
10
1000 0 ?0.05
tradeoﬀ SNR?sparsity
orientation proﬁle 14
0.1
sparsity
6000
0.12
average # of connections
7000
?? / 4
0
?/4
?/2
1
2
3
4
orientation bins
30 20 5
6
7

9

8
9
10
11
12
13
SNR
Figure 5: Properties of the weight matrix W and comparison of the tradeoﬀ
curve SNR - ?0 norm between a Laplacian prior over the coeﬃcients and our
proposed prior. To access how much information is captured by the second-
order statistics, we isolate a group (?i )i?? of 10 basis functions sharing strong
weights. Given a collection of image patches that we sparsify using (4), we
obtain a number of spins (? si )i?? from which we can estimate the empirical
distribution pemp , the Boltzmann-Gibbs distribution pIsing consistent with
ﬁrst and second order correlations, and the factorial distribution pf act (i.e.
no horizontal connections) consistent with ﬁrst order correlations. We can see
in Figure 6 that the Ising model produces better estimates of the empirical
distribution, and results in better coding eﬃciency since KL(pemp ——pIsing
) = .02 whereas KL(pemp ——pf act ) = .1. ?1

10
factorial model Ising model ?2
10
Empirical probaility
all spins down
?3
10
all spins up 3 spins up
?4
10
?5
10
?5
10
?4
10
?3
10
?2
?1
10
10
Model probability
Figure 6: Model validation for a group of 10 basis functions (right). The
empirical probabilities of the 210 patterns of activation are plotted against the
probabilities predicted by the Ising model (red), the factorial model (blue), and
their own values (black). These patterns having exactly three spins up are

10

circled. The prediction of the Ising model is noticably better than that of the
factorial model.

6 Discussion In this paper, we proposed a new sparse coding model where
we include pairwise coupling terms among the coeﬃcients to capture their de-
pendencies. We derived a new learning algorithm to adapt the parameters of
the model given a data set of natural images, and we were able to discover
the dependencies among the basis functions coeﬃcients. We showed that the
learned connection weights are consistent with physiological data. Furthermore,
the representations inferred in our model have greater sparsity than when they
are inferred using the Laplacian prior as in the standard sparse coding model.
Note however that we have not found evidence that these horizontal connections
facilitate contour integration, as they do not primarily connect colinear basis
functions. Previous models in the literature simply assume these weights ac-
cording to prior intuitions about the function of horizontal connections [12, 13].
It is of great interest to develop new models and unsupervised learning schemes
possibly involving attention that will help us understand the computational
principles underlying contour integration in the visual cortex. 7

2 References

[1] B.A. Olshausen and D. J. Field. Emergence of simple-cell receptive ﬁeld prop-
erties by learning a sparse code for natural images. Nature, 381(6583):607?609,
June 1996. [2] R. Raina, A. Battle, H. Lee, B. Packer, and A.Y. Ng. Self-taught
learning: Transfer learning from unlabeled data. Proceedings of the Twenty-
fourth International Conference on Machine Learning, 2007.
[3] G. Zetzsche
and B. Wegmann. The atoms of vision: Cartesian or polar? J. Opt. Soc. Am.,
16(7):1554? 1565, 1999. [4] P. Hoyer and A. Hyv?arinen. A multi-layer sparse
coding network learns contour coding from natural images. Vision Research,
42:1593?1605, 2002.
[5] M.J. Wainwright, E.P. Simoncelli, and A.S. Willsky.
Random cascades on wavelet trees and their use in modeling and analyzing nat-
ural imagery. Applied and Computational Harmonic Analysis, 11(1):89?123,
July 2001.
[6] O. Schwartz, T. J. Sejnowski, and P. Dayan. Soft mixer as-
signment in a hierarchical generative model of natural scene statistics. Neural
Comput, 18(11):2680?2718, November 2006.
[7] S. Lyu and E. P. Simoncelli.
Statistical modeling of images with ﬁelds of gaussian scale mixtures.
In Ad-
vances in Neural Computation Systems (NIPS), Vancouver, Canada, 2006. [8]
A. Hyv?arinen, P.O. Hoyer, J. Hurri, and M. Gutmann. Statistical models
of images and early vision. Proceedings of the Int. Symposium on Adaptive
Knowledge Representation and Reasoning (AKRR2005), Espoo, Finland, 2005.
[9] Y. Karklin and M.S. Lewicki. A hierarchical bayesian model for learning
non-linear statistical regularities in non-stationary natural signals. Neural Com-
putation, 17(2):397?423, 2005. [10] B.A. Olshausen and K.J. Millman. Learning
sparse codes with a mixture-of-gaussians prior. Advances in Neural Information
Processing Systems, 12, 2000. [11] D. Fitzpatrick. The functional organization
of local circuits in visual cortex:
insights from the study of tree shrew striate

11

[12] O. Ben-Shahar and S. Zucker.
cortex. Cerebral Cortex, 6:329?41, 1996.
Geometrical computations explain projection patterns of long-range horizontal
connections in visual cortex. Neural Comput, 16(3):445?476, March 2004. [13]
L. Zhaoping. Border ownership from intracortical interactions in visual area
v2. Neuron, 47:143?153, 2005. [14] E. Schneidman, M.J. Berry, R. Segev, and
W. Bialek. Weak pairwise correlations imply strongly correlated network states
in a neural population. Nature, April 2006.
[15] G. Hinton, S. Osindero, and
K. Bao. Learning causally linked markov random ﬁelds. Artiﬁcial Intelligence
and Statistics, Barbados, 2005. [16] M.I. Jordan, Z. Ghahramani, T. Jaakkola,
and L.K. Saul. An introduction to variational methods for graphical models.
Learning in Graphical Models, Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999.
[17] S.S.
Chen, D.L. Donoho, and M.A. Saunders. Atomic decomposition by basis pur-
suit. SIAM Review, 43(1):129?159, 2001. [18] C.J. Rozell, D.H. Johnson, R.G.
Baraniuk, and B.A. Olshausen. Neurally plausible sparse coding via competi-
tive algorithms. In Proceedings of the Computational and Systems Neuroscience
(Cosyne) meeting, Salt Lake City, UT, February 2007. [19] J.A. Tropp. Greed
is good: algorithmic results for sparse approximation. IEEE Transactions on
Information Theory, 50(10):2231?2242, 2004. [20] H. Lee, A. Battle, R. Raina,
and A.Y. Ng. Eﬃcient sparse coding algorithms. In Advances in Neural In-
formation Processing Systems 19, pages 801?808. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA,
2007.
[21] D.H. Ackley, G.E. Hinton, and T.J. Sejnowski. A learning algo-
rithm for boltzmann machines. Cognitive Science, 9(1):147?169, 1985. [22] J.A.
Tropp. Just relax: convex programming methods for identifying sparse signals
in noise.
IEEE Transactions on Information Theory, 52(3):1030?1051, 2006.
[23] Z. Wang, A.C. Bovik, and E.P. Simoncelli. Structural approaches to image
quality assessment. In Alan Bovik, editor, Handbook of Image and Video Pro-
cessing, chapter 8.3, pages 961?974. Academic Press, May 2005. 2nd edition.
[24] R. Malach, Y. Amir, M. Harel, and A. Grinvald. Relationship between
intrinsic connections and functional architecture revealed by optical imaging
and in vivo targeted biocytin injections in primate striate cortex. Proc. Natl.
Acad. Sci. U.S.A., 82:935?939, 1993. [25] W. Bosking, Y. Zhang, B. Schoﬁeld,
and D. Fitzpatrick. Orientation selectivity and the arrangement of horizontal
connections in the tree shrew striate cortex. J. Neuroscience, 17(6):2112?2127,
1997.
8

12

