Optimal ROC Curve for a Combination of

Classiﬁers

Authored by:

Marco Barreno
Alvaro Cardenas

J. D. Tygar

Abstract

We present a new analysis for the combination of binary classiﬁers. We
propose a theoretical framework based on the Neyman-Pearson lemma
to analyze combinations of classiﬁers.
In particular, we give a method
for ﬁnding the optimal decision rule for a combination of classiﬁers and
prove that it has the optimal ROC curve. We also show how our method
generalizes and improves on previous work on combining classiﬁers and
generating ROC curves.

1 Paper Body

We present an optimal way to combine binary classiﬁers in the Neyman-Pearson
sense: for a given upper bound on false alarms (false positives), we ﬁnd the set
of combination rules maximizing the detection rate (true positives). This forms
the optimal ROC curve of a combination of classiﬁers. This paper makes the
following original contributions: (1) We present a new method for ﬁnding the
meta-classiﬁer with the optimal ROC curve. (2) We show how our framework
can be used to interpret, generalize, and improve previous work by Provost and
Fawcett [1] and Flach and Wu [2]. (3) We present experimental results that
show our method is practical and performs well, even when we must estimate
the distributions with insuﬃcient data.
In addition, we prove the following
results: (1) We show that the optimal ROC curve is composed in general of 2n
+ 1 diﬀerent decision rules and of the interpolation between these rules (over the
2n space of 2 possible Boolean rules). (2) We prove that our method is optimal
in this space. (3) We prove that the Boolean AND and OR rules are always
part of the optimal set for the special case of independent classiﬁers (though
in general we make no independence assumptions). (4) We prove a suﬃcient
condition for Provost and Fawcett?s method to be optimal.

2
Background

1

Consider classiﬁcation problems where examples from a space of inputs X are
associated with binary labels {0, 1} and there is a ﬁxed but unknown probability
distribution P(x, c) over examples (x, c) ? X ? {0, 1}. H0 and H1 denote the
events that c = 0 and c = 1, respectively. A binary classiﬁer is a function f : X
? {0, 1} that predicts labels on new inputs. When we use the term ?classiﬁer?
in this paper we mean binary classiﬁer. We address the problem of combining
results from n base classiﬁers f1 , f2 , . . . , fn . Let Yi = ﬁ (X) be a random
variable indicating the output of classiﬁer ﬁ and Y ? {0, 1}n = (Y1 , Y2 , .
.
, Yn ). We can characterize the performance of classiﬁer ﬁ by its detection
.
rate (also true positives, or power) PDi = Pr[Yi = 1—H1 ] and its false alarm
rate (also false positives, or test size) PF i = Pr[Yi = 1—H0 ]. In this paper we
are concerned with proper classiﬁers, that is, classiﬁers where PDi ¿ PF i . We
sometimes omit the subscript i. 1

The Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) curve plots PF on the x-
axis and PD on the y-axis (ROC space). The point (0, 0) represents always
classifying as 0, the point (1, 1) represents always classifying as 1, and the point
(0, 1) represents perfect classiﬁcation.
If one classiﬁer?s curve has no points
below another, it weakly dominates the latter. If no points are below and at
least one point is strictly above, it dominates it. The line y = x describes a
classiﬁer that is no better than chance, and every proper classiﬁer dominates
this line. When an ROC curve consists of a single point, we connect it with
straight lines to (0, 0) and (1, 1) in order to compare it with others (see Lemma
1). In this paper, we focus on base classiﬁers that occupy a single point in ROC
space. Many classiﬁers have tunable parameters and can produce a continuous
ROC curve; our analysis can apply to these cases by choosing representative
points and treating each one as a separate classiﬁer. 2.1

The ROC convex hull
Provost and Fawcett [1] give a seminal result on the use of ROC curves for
combining classiﬁers. They suggest taking the convex hull of all points of the
ROC curves of the classiﬁers. This ROC convex hull (ROCCH) combination
rule interpolates between base classiﬁers f1 , f2 , . . . , fn , selecting (1) a single
best classiﬁer or (2) a randomization between the decisions of two classiﬁers for
every false alarm rate [1]. This approach, however, is not optimal: as pointed
out in later work by Fawcett, the Boolean AND and OR rules over classiﬁers can
perform better than the ROCCH [3]. AND and OR are only 2 of 22 possiblen
Boolean rules over the outputs of n base classiﬁers (n classiﬁers ? 2n possible
outcomes ? 22 rules over outcomes). We address ﬁnding optimal rules. n

2.2
The Neyman-Pearson lemma
In this section we introduce Neyman-Pearson theory from the framework of
statistical hypothesis testing [4, 5], which forms the basis of our analysis. We
test a null hypothesis H0 against an alternative H1 . Let the random variable Y
have probability distributions P (Y—H0 ) under H0 and P (Y—H1 ) under H1
, and deﬁne the likelihood ratio ?(Y) = P (Y—H1 )/P (Y—H0 ). The Neyman-
Pearson lemma states that the likelihood ratio test ( 1 if ?(Y) ¿ ? ? if ?(Y) =
? , D(Y) = (1) 0 if ?(Y) ¡ ? for some ? ? (0, ?) and ? ? [0, 1], is a most

2

powerful test for its size: no other test has higher PD = Pr[D(Y) = 1—H1 ] for
the same bound on PF = Pr[D(Y) = 1—H0 ]. (When ?(Y) = ? , D = 1 with
probability ? and 0 otherwise.) Given a test size ?, we maximize PD subject
to PF ? ? by choosing ? and ? as follows. First we ﬁnd the smallest value ? ?
such that Pr[?(Y) ¿ ? ? —H0 ] ? ?. To maximize PD , which is monotonically
nondecreasing with PF , we choose the highest value ? ? that satisﬁes Pr[D(Y)
= 1—H0 ] = Pr[?(Y) ¿ ? ? —H0 ] + ? ? Pr[?(Y) = ? ? —H0 ] ? ?, ﬁnding ?
? = (? ? Pr[?(Y) ¿ ? ? —H0 ])/ Pr[?(Y) = ? ? —H0 ].

3
The optimal ROC curve for a combination of classiﬁers
We characterize the optimal ROC curve for a decision based on a combi-
nation of arbitrary classiﬁers?for any given bound ? on PF , we maximize PD
. We frame this problem as a NeymanPearson hypothesis test parameterized
by the choice of ?. We assume nothing about the classiﬁers except that each
produces an output in {0, 1}. In particular, we do not assume the classiﬁers are
independent or related in any way. Before introducing our method we analyze
the one-classiﬁer case (n = 1). Lemma 1 Let f1 be a classiﬁer with performance
probabilities PD1 and PF 1 . Its optimal ROC curve is a piecewise linear func-
tion parameterized by a free parameter ? bounding PF : for ? ¡ PF 1 , PD (?)
= (PD1 /PF 1 )?, and for ? ¿ PF 1 , PD (?) = [(1 ? PD1 )/(1 ? PF 1 )](? ?
PF 1 ) + PD1 . Proof. When ? ¡ PF 1 , we can obtain a likelihood ratio test
by setting ? ? = ?(1) and ? ? = ?/PF 1 , and for ? ¿ PF 1 , we set ? ? = ?(0)
and ? ? = (? ? PF 1 )/(1 ? PF 1 ). 2 2

The intuitive interpretation of this result is that to decrease or increase the
false alarm rate of the classiﬁer, we randomize between using its predictions and
always choosing 1 or 0. In ROC space, this forms lines interpolating between
(PF 1 , PD1 ) and (1, 1) or (0, 0), respectively. To generalize this result for
the combination of n classiﬁers, we require the distributions P (Y—H0 ) and P
(Y—H1 ). With this information we then compute and sort the likelihood ratios
?(y) for all outcomes y ? {0, 1}n . Let L be the list of likelihood ratios ranked
from low to high. Lemma 2 Given any 0 ? ? ? 1, the ordering L determines
parameters ? ? and ? ? for a likelihood ratio test of size ?. Lemma 2 sets up
a classiﬁcation rule for each interval between likelihoods in L and interpolates
between them to create a test with size exactly ?. Our meta-classiﬁer does this
for any given bound on its false positive rate, then makes predictions according
to Equation 1. To ﬁnd the ROC curve for our meta-classiﬁer, we plot PD
In particular, for each y ? {0, 1}n we can
against PF for all 0 ? ? ? 1.
compute Pr[?(Y) ¿ ?(y)—H0 ], which gives us one value for ? ? and a point
in ROC space (PF and PD follow directly from L and P ). Each ? ? will turn
out to be the slope of a line segment between adjacent vertices, and varying ?
? interpolates between the vertices. We call the ROC curve obtained in this
way the LR-ROC. Theorem 1 The LR-ROC weakly dominates the ROC curve
of any possible combination of Boolean functions g : {0, 1}n ? {0, 1} over the
outputs of n classiﬁers. Proof. Let ?? be the probability of false alarm PF for
g. Let ? ? and ? ? be chosen for a test of size ?? . Then our meta-classiﬁer?s
decision rule is a likelihood ratio test. By the Neyman-Pearson lemma, no other

3

test has higher power for any given size. Since ROC space plots power on the
y-axis and size on the x-axis, this means that the PD for g at PF = ?? cannot
be higher than that of the LR-ROC. Since this is true at any ?? , the LR-ROC
weakly dominates the ROC curve for g. 2 3.1

Practical considerations
To compute all likelihood ratios for the classiﬁer outcomes we need to know
the probability distributions P (Y—H0 ) and P (Y—H1 ).
In practice these
distributions need to be estimated. The simplest method is to run the base
classiﬁers on a training set and count occurrences of each outcome. It is likely
that some outcomes will not occur in the training, or will occur only a small
number of times. Our initial approach to deal with small or zero counts when
estimating was to use add-one smoothing. In our experiments, however, sim-
ple special-case treatment of zero counts always produced better results than
smoothing, both on the training set and on the test set. See Section 5 for de-
tails. Furthermore, the optimal ROC curve may have a diﬀerent likelihood ratio
for each possible outcome from the n classiﬁers, and therefore a diﬀerent point
in ROC space, so optimal ROC curves in general have up to 2n points. This
implies an exponential (in the number of classiﬁers) lower bound on the running
time of any algorithm to compute the optimal ROC curve for a combination of
classiﬁers. For a handful of classiﬁers, such a bound is not problematic, but
it is impractical to compute the optimal ROC curve for dozensnor hundreds of
classiﬁers. (However, by computing and sorting the likelihood ratios we avoid a
22 -time search over all possible classiﬁcation functions.)

4 4.1
Analysis The independent case
In this section we take an in-depth look at the case of two binary classiﬁers
f1 and f2 that are conditionally independent given the input?s class, so that P
(Y1 , Y2 —Hc ) = P (Y1 —Hc )P (Y2 —Hc ) for c ? {0, 1} (this section is
the only part of the paper in which we make any independence assumptions).
Since Y1 and Y2 are conditionally independent, we do not need the full joint
distribution; we need only the probabilities PD1 , PF 1 , PD2 , and PF 2 to
ﬁnd the combined PD and PF . For example, ?(01) = ((1 ? PD1 )PD2 )/((1 ?
PF 1 )PF 2 ). The assumption that f1 and f2 are conditionally independent and
proper deﬁnes a partial ordering on the likelihood ratio: ?(00) ¡ ?(10) ¡ ?(11)
and ?(00) ¡ ?(01) ¡ ?(11). Without loss of 3

Table 1: Two probability distributions. Class 1 (H1 ) Y1 Y2 0 1 0 0.2 0.375

1 0.1 0.325

Class 0 (H0 ) Y1 Y2 0 1 0 0.5 0.1 1 0.3 0.1
Class 1 (H1 ) Y1 Y2 0 1 0 0.2 0.1 1 0.2 0.5
(a)
Class 0 (H0 ) Y1 Y2 0 1 0 0.1 0.3 1 0.5 0.1 (b)
generality, we assume ?(00) ¡ ?(01) ¡ ?(10) ¡ ?(11). This ordering breaks
the likelihood ratio?s range (0, ?) into ﬁve regions; choosing ? in each region
deﬁnes a diﬀerent decision rule. The trivial cases 0 ? ? ¡ ?(00) and ?(11) ¡ ?
¡ ? correspond to always classifying as 1 and 0, respectively. PD and PF are
therefore both equal to 1 and both equal to 0, respectively. For the case ?(00)

4

? ? ¡ ?(01), Pr [?(Y) ¿ ? ] = Pr [Y = 01 ? Y = 10 ? Y = 11] = Pr [Y1 = 1
? Y2 = 1] . Thresholds in this range deﬁne an OR rule for the classiﬁers, with
PD = PD1 + PD2 ? PD1 PD2 and PF = PF 1 + PF 2 ? PF 1 PF 2 . For
the case ?(01) ? ? ¡ ?(10), we have Pr [?(Y) ¿ ? ] = Pr [Y = 10 ? Y = 11] =
Pr [Y1 = 1] . Therefore the performance probabilities are simply PD = PD1
and PF = PF 1 . Finally, the case ?(10) ? ? ¡ ?(11) implies that Pr [?(Y) ¿ ?
] = Pr [Y = 11] , and therefore thresholds in this range deﬁne an AND rule,
with PD = PD1 PD2 and PF = PF 1 PF 2 . Figure 1a illustrates this analysis
with an example. The assumption of conditional independence is a suﬃcient
condition for ensuring that the AND and OR rules improve on the ROCCH for
n classiﬁers, as the following result shows. Theorem 2 If the distributions of
the outputs of n proper binary classiﬁers Y1 , Y2 , . . . , Yn are conditionally
independent given the instance class, then the points in ROC space for the rules
AND (Y1 ? Y2 ? ? ? ? ? Yn ) and OR (Y1 ? Y2 ? ? ? ? ? Yn ) are strictly
above the convex hull of the ROC curves of the base classiﬁers f1 , . . . , fn .
Furthermore, these Boolean rules belong to the LR-ROC. Proof. The likelihood
ratio of the case when AND outputs 1 is given by ?(11 ? ? ? 1) = (PD1 PD2 ?
? ? PDn )/(PF 1 PF 2 ? ? ? PF n ). The likelihood ratio of the case when OR
does not output 1 is given by ?(00 ? ? ? 0) = [(1 ? PD1 )(1 ? PD2 ) ? ? ? (1 ?
PDn )]/[(1 ? PF 1 )(1 ? PF 2 ) ? ? ? (1 ? PF n )]. Now recall that for proper
classiﬁers ﬁ , PDi ¿ PF i and thus (1 ? PDi )/(1 ? PF i ) ¡ 1 ¡ PDi /PF i . It is
now clear that ?(00 ? ? ? 0) is the smallest likelihood ratio and ?(11 ? ? ? 1) is
the largest likelihood ratio, since others are obtained only by swapping P(F,D)i
and (1 ? P(F,D)i ), and therefore the OR and AND rules will always be part
of the optimal set of decisions for conditionally independent classiﬁers. These
rules are strictly above the ROCCH: because ?(11 ? ? ? 1) ¿ PD1 /PD2 , and
PD1 /PD2 is the slope of the line from (0, 0) to the ﬁrst point in the ROCCH
(f1 ), the AND point must be above the ROCCH. A similar argument holds for
OR since ?(00 ? ? ? 0) ¡ (1 ? PDn )/(1 ? PF n ). 2 4.2

Two examples
We return now to the general case with no independence assumptions. We
present two example distributions for the two-classiﬁer case that demonstrate
interesting results. The ﬁrst distribution appears in Table 1a. The likelihood
ratio values are ?(00) = 0.4, ?(10) = 3.75, ?(01) = 1/3, and ?(11) = 3.25, giving
us ?(01) ¡ ?(00) ¡ ?(11) ¡ ?(10). The three non-trivial rules correspond to the
Boolean functions Y1 ? ?Y2 , Y1 , and Y1 ? ?Y2 . Note that Y2 appears only
negatively despite being a proper classiﬁer, and both the AND and OR rules
are sub-optimal. The distribution for the second example appears in Table 1b.
The likelihood ratios of the outcomes are ?(00) = 2.0, ?(10) = 1/3, ?(01) = 0.4,
and ?(11) = 5, so ?(10) ¡ ?(01) ¡ ?(00) ¡ ?(11) and the three points deﬁning the
optimal ROC curve are ?Y1 ? Y2 , ?(Y1 ? Y2 ), and Y1 ? Y2 (see Figure 1b).
In this case, an XOR rule emerges from the likelihood ratio analysis. These
examples show that for true optimal results it is not suﬃcient to use weighted
voting rules w1 Y1 + w2 Y2 + ? ? ? + wn Yn ? ? , where w ? (0, ?) (like
some ensemble methods). Weighted voting always has AND and OR rules in
its ROC curve, so it cannot always express optimal rules. 4

5

1
Y1 ? Y2 Y2
0.8
Y1 ? Y2 Y1
0.4
0.8
Y1 ? Y2
PD
0.6
PD
0.6
Y2
0.4
PF 0.6
f1
f2
f3?
0.4
0.2
0.2
ROC of f2
LR?ROC 0.2
f3
ROC of f1
ROC of f2
0 0
f2?
0.6
Y1
0.4 ROC of f1
0.2
1
?Y1 ? Y2 ?(Y1 ? Y2 )
PD
1
0.8
Original ROC LR?ROC
f1?
LR?ROC
0.8
1
(a)
0 0
0.2
0.4 P F
0.6

6

0.8
(b)
1
0 0
0.2
0.4 P 0.6 F
0.8
1
(c)
Figure 1: (a) ROC for two conditionally independent classiﬁers. (b) ROC
curve for the distributions in Table 1b. (c) Original ROC curve and optimal
ROC curve for example in Section 4.4. 4.3

.

.

Optimality of the ROCCH
We have seen that in some cases, rules exist with points strictly above the
ROCCH. As the following result shows, however, there are conditions under
which the ROCCH is optimal. Theorem 3 Consider n classiﬁers f1 , .
, fn
. The convex hull of points (PF i , PDi ) with (0, 0) and (1, 1) (the ROCCH)
is an optimal ROC curve for the combination if (Yi = 1) ? (Yj = 1) for i ¡ j
and the following ordering holds: ?(00 ? ? ? 0) ¡ ?(00 ? ? ? 01) ¡ ?(00 ? ? ?
011) ¡ ? ? ? ¡ ?(1 ? ? ? 1). Proof. The condition (Yi = 1) ? (Yj = 1) for i ¡ j
implies that we only need to consider n + 2 points in the ROC space (the two
extra points are (0, 0) and (1, 1)) rather than 2n . It also implies the following
conditions on the joint distribution: Pr[Y1 = 0 ? ? ? ? ? Yi = 0 ? Yi+1 = 1
? ? ? ? ? Yn = 1—H0 ] = PF i+1 ? PF i , and Pr[Y1 = 1 ? ? ? ? ? Yn
= 1—H0 ] = PF 1 . With these conditions and the ordering condition on the
likelihood ratios, we have Pr[?(Y) ¿ ?(1 ? ? ? 1)—H0 ] = 0, and Pr[?(Y) ¿ ?(0
? ? 0} 1 ? ? ? 1)—H0 ] = PF i . Therefore, ﬁnding the optimal threshold of
the likelihood — ?{z i
ratio test for PF i?1 ? ? ¡ PF i , we get ? ? = ?(0 ? ? 0} 1 ? ? ? 1), and
for PF i ? ? ¡ PF i+1 , — ?{z i?1
? ? = ?(0 ? ? 0} 1 ? ? ? 1). This change in ? ? implies that the point PF
i is part of the LR-ROC. Setting — ?{z i
? = PF i (thus ? ? = ?(0 ? ? 0} 1 ? ? ? 1) and ? ? =0) implies Pr[?(Y) ¿
? ? —H1 ] = PDi . — ?{z

2
i
The condition Yi = 1 ? Yj = 1 for i ¡ j is the same inclusion condition
Flach and Wu use for repairing an ROC curve [2]. It intuitively represents the
performance in ROC space of a single classiﬁer with diﬀerent operating points.
The next section explores this relationship further. 4.4

Repairing an ROC curve
Flach and Wu give a voting technique to repair concavities in an ROC curve
that generates operating points above the ROCCH [2]. Their intuition is that
points underneath the convex hull can be mirrored to appear above the convex
hull in much the same way as an improper classiﬁer can be negated to obtain a
proper classiﬁer. Although their algorithm produces better ROC curves, their

7

solution will often yield curves with new concavities (see for example Flach
and Wu?s Figure 4 [2]). Their algorithm has a similar purpose to ours, but
theirs is a local greedy optimization technique, while our method performs a
global search in order to ﬁnd the best ROC curve. Figure 1c shows an example
comparing their method to ours. Consider the following probability distribution
on a random variable Y ? {0, 1}2 : P ((00, 10, 01, 11)—H1 ) = (0.1, 0.3, 0.0,
0.6), P ((00, 10, 01, 11)—H0 ) = (0.5, 0.001, 0.4, 0.099). Flach and Wu?s
method assumes the original ROC curve to be repaired has three models, or
operating points: f1 predicts 1 when Y ? {11}, f2 predicts 1 when Y ? {11, 01},
and f3 predicts 1 when Y ? {11, 01, 10}. If we apply Flach and Wu?s repair
algorithm, the point f2 is corrected to the point f2? ; however, the operating
points of f1 and f3 remain the same. 5

1.0 0.2
0.4
Pd
0.6
0.8
1.0 0.8 0.6 Pd 0.4 0.2 0.00
0.05
0.10
0.15
Meta (train) Base (train) Meta (test) Base (test) PART
0.0
0.0
Meta (train) Base (train) Meta (test) Base (test) PART 0.20
0.000
0.005
Pfa
0.010
0.015
Pfa
0.8 0.6 Pd 0.4 0.2
0.2
0.4
Pd
0.6
0.8
1.0
(b) hypothyroid
1.0
(a) adult
0.00
0.05
0.10
Meta (train) Base (train) Meta (test) Base (test) PART
0.0

8

0.0
Meta (train) Base (train) Meta (test) Base (test) PART 0.15
0.00
Pfa
0.02
0.04
0.06
0.08
0.10
Pfa
(c) sick-euthyroid
(d) sick
Figure 2: Empirical ROC curves for experimental results on four UCI datasets.
Our method improves on this result by ordering the likelihood ratios ?(01)
¡ ?(00) ¡ ?(11) ¡ ?(10) and using that ordering to make three diﬀerent rules: f1?
predicts 1 when Y ? {10}, f2? predicts 1 when Y ? {10, 11}, and f3? predicts 1
when Y ? {10, 11, 00}.

5
Experiments
We ran experiments to test the performance of our combining method on
the adult, hypothyroid, sick-euthyroid, and sick datasets from the UCI machine
learning repository [6]. We chose ﬁve base classiﬁers from the YALE machine
learning platform [7]: PART (a decision list algorithm), SMO (Sequential Min-
imal Optimization), SimpleLogistic, VotedPerceptron, and Y-NaiveBayes. We
used default settings for all classiﬁers. The adult dataset has around 30,000
training points and 15,000 test points and the sick dataset has around 2000
training points and 700 test points. The others each have around 2000 points
that we split randomly into 1000 training and 1000 test. For each experiment,
we estimate the joint distribution by training the base classiﬁers on a training
set and counting the outcomes. We compute likelihood ratios for all outcomes
and order them. When outcomes have no examples, we treat ?/0 as near-inﬁnite
and 0/? as near-zero and deﬁne 0/0 = 1. 6

We derive a sequence of decision rules from the likelihood ratios computed
on the training set. We can compute an optimal ROC curve for the combination
by counting the number of true positives and false positives each rule achieves.
In the test set we use the rules learned on the training set. 5.1

Results
The ROC graphs for our four experiments appear in Figure 2. The ROC
curves in these experiments all rise very quickly and then ﬂatten out, so we
show only the range of PF 1 for which the values are interesting. We can draw
some general conclusions from these graphs. First, PART clearly outperforms
the other base classiﬁers in three out of four experiments, though it seems to
overﬁt on the hypothyroid dataset. The LR-ROC dominates the ROC curves
of the base classiﬁers on both training and test sets. The ROC curves for
the base classiﬁers are all strictly below the LR-ROC in results on the test
sets. The results on training sets seem to imply that the LR-ROC is primarily

9

classifying like PART with a small boost from the other classiﬁers; however,
the test set results (in particular, Figure 2b) demonstrate that the LR-ROC
generalizes better than the base classiﬁers. The robustness of our method to
estimation errors is uncertain. In our experiments we found that smoothing did
not improve generalization, but undoubtedly our method would beneﬁt from
better estimation of the outcome distribution and increased robustness. We ran
separate experiments to test how many classiﬁers our method could support
in practice. Estimation of the joint distribution and computation of the ROC
curve ﬁnished within one minute for 20 classiﬁers (not including time to train
the individual classiﬁers). Unfortunately, the inherent exponential structure of
the optimal ROC curve means we cannot expect to do signiﬁcantly better (at
the same rate, 30 classiﬁers would take over 12 hours and 40 classiﬁers almost
a year and a half).

6
Related work
Our work is loosely related to ensemble methods such as bagging [8] and
boosting [9] because it ﬁnds meta-classiﬁcation rules over a set of base classi-
ﬁers. However, bagging and boosting each take one base classiﬁer and train
many times, resampling or reweighting the training data to generate classiﬁer
diversity [10] or increase the classiﬁcation margin [11]. The decision rules ap-
plied to the generated classiﬁers are (weighted) majority voting. In contrast, our
method takes any binary classiﬁers and ﬁnds optimal combination rules from
the more general space of all binary functions. Ranking algorithms, such as
RankBoost [12], approach the problem of ranking points by score or preference.
Although we present our methods in a diﬀerent light, our decision rule can be
interpreted as a ranking algorithm. RankBoost, however, is a boosting algo-
rithm and therefore fundamentally diﬀerent from our approach. Ranking can
be used for classiﬁcation by choosing a cutoﬀ or threshold, and in fact ranking
algorithms tend to optimize the common Area Under the ROC Curve (AUC)
metric. Although our method may have the side eﬀect of maximizing the AUC,
its formulation is diﬀerent in that instead of optimizing a single global metric,
it is a constrained optimization problem, maximizing PD for each PF . Another
more similar method for combining classiﬁers is stacking [13]. Stacking trains
a metalearner to combine the predictions of several base classiﬁers; in fact, our
method might be considered a stacking method with a particular meta-classiﬁer.
It can be diﬃcult to show the improvement of stacking in general over selecting
the best base-level classiﬁer [14]; however, stacking has a useful interpretation
as generalized cross-validation that makes it practical. Our analysis shows that
our combination method is the optimal meta-learner in the Neyman-Pearson
sense, but incorporating the model validation aspect of stacking would make an
interesting extension to our work.

7
Conclusion
In this paper we introduce a new way to analyze a combination of classiﬁers
and their ROC curves. We give a method for combining classiﬁers and prove that
it is optimal in the Neyman-Pearson sense. This work raises several interesting

10

questions. Although the algorithm presented in this paper avoids checking the
whole doubly exponential number of rules, the exponential factor in running
time limits the number of classiﬁers that can be 7

combined in practice. Can a good approximation algorithm approach op-
timality while having lower time complexity? Though in general we make no
assumptions about independence, Theorem 2 shows that certain simple rules
are optimal when we do know that the classiﬁers are independent. Theorem 3
proves that the ROCCH can be optimal when only n output combinations are
possible. Perhaps other restrictions on the distribution of outcomes can lead to
useful special cases.

Acknowledgments This work was supported in part by TRUST (Team for
Research in Ubiquitous Secure Technology), which receives support from the
National Science Foundation (NSF award number CCF-0424422) and the fol-
lowing organizations: AFOSR (#FA9550-06-1-0244), Cisco, British Telecom,
ESCHER, HP, IBM, iCAST, Intel, Microsoft, ORNL, Pirelli, Qualcomm, Sun,
Symantec, Telecom Italia, and United Technologies; and in part by the UC
Berkeley-Taiwan International Collaboration in Advanced Security Technolo-
gies (iCAST) program. The opinions expressed in this paper are solely those of
the authors and do not necessarily reﬂect the opinions of any funding agency or
the U.S. or Taiwanese governments.

2 References

[1] Foster Provost and Tom Fawcett. Robust classiﬁcation for imprecise envi-
ronments. Machine Learning Journal, 42(3):203?231, March 2001. [2] Peter A.
Flach and Shaomin Wu. Repairing concavities in ROC curves. In Proceedings
of the 19th International Joint Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence (IJCAI?05),
pages 702?707, August 2005. [3] Tom Fawcett. ROC graphs: Notes and prac-
tical considerations for data mining researchers. Technical Report HPL-2003-4,
HP Laboratories, Palo Alto, CA, January 2003. Updated March 2004.
[4]
J. Neyman and E. S. Pearson. On the problem of the most eﬃcient tests of
statistical hypotheses. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of Lon-
don, Series A, Containing Papers of a Mathematical or Physical Character,
231:289?337, 1933.
[5] Vincent H. Poor. An Introduction to Signal Detection
and Estimation. Springer-Verlag, second edition, 1988.
[6] D. J. Newman,
S. Hettich, C. L. Blake, and C. J. Merz. UCI repository of machine learning
databases, 1998. http://www.ics.uci.edu/?mlearn/MLRepository.html.
[7] I.
Mierswa, M. Wurst, R. Klinkenberg, M. Scholz, and T. Euler. YALE: Rapid pro-
totyping for complex data mining tasks. In Proceedings of the ACM SIGKDD
International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD),
[8] L. Breiman. Bagging predictors. Machine Learning, 24(2):123?140,
2006.
1996.
[9] Y. Freund and R. E. Schapire. Experiments with a new boosting
algorithm. In Thirteenth International Conference on Machine Learning, pages
148?156, Bari, Italy, 1996. Morgan Kaufmann.
[10] Thomas G. Dietterich.
Ensemble methods in machine learning. Lecture Notes in Computer Science,

11

[11] Robert E. Schapire, Yoav Freund, Peter Bartlett, and
1857:1?15, 2000.
Wee Sun Lee. Boosting the margin: A new explanation for the eﬀectiveness
of voting methods. The Annals of Statistics, 26(5):1651?1686, October 1998.
[12] Yoav Freund, Raj Iyer, Robert E. Schapire, and Yoram Singer. An eﬃcient
boosting algorithm for combining preferences. Journal of Machine Learning Re-
search (JMLR), 4:933?969, 2003.
[13] D. H. Wolpert. Stacked generalization.
Neural Networks, 5:241?259, 1992. ? [14] Saso D?zeroski and Bernard Zenko. Is
combining classiﬁers with stacking better than selecting the best one? Machine
Learning, 54:255?273, 2004.

8

12

