Automatic Generation of Social Tags for Music

Recommendation

Authored by:

Douglas Eck
Paul Lamere

Thierry Bertin-mahieux

Stephen Green

Abstract

Social tags are user-generated keywords associated with some resource
on the Web. In the case of music, social tags have become an important
component of Web2.0” recommender systems, allowing users to gener-
ate playlists based on use-dependent terms such as ”chill” or ”jogging”
that have been applied to particular songs. In this paper, we propose a
method for predicting these social tags directly from MP3 ﬁles. Using a
set of boosted classiﬁers, we map audio features onto social tags collected
from the Web. The resulting automatic tags (or ”autotags”) furnish infor-
mation about music that is otherwise untagged or poorly tagged, allowing
for insertion of previously unheard music into a social recommender. This
avoids the ”cold-start problem” common in such systems. Autotags can
also be used to smooth the tag space from which similarities and recom-
mendations are made by providing a set of comparable baseline tags for
all tracks in a recommender system.”

1 Paper Body

Social tags are a key part of ?Web 2.0? technologies and have become an im-
portant source of information for recommendation.
In the domain of music,
Web sites such as Last.fm use social tags as a basis for recommending mu-
sic to listeners. In this paper we propose a method for predicting social tags
using audio feature extraction and supervised learning. These automatically-
generated tags (or ?autotags?) can furnish information about music for which
good, descriptive social tags are lacking. Using traditional information retrieval
techniques a music recommender can use these autotags (combined with any
available listener-applied tags) to predict artist or song similarity. The tags can
also serve to smooth the tag space from which similarities and recommendations
are made by providing a set of comparable baseline tags for all artists or songs

1

in a recommender. This is not the ﬁrst attempt to predict something about
textual data using music audio as input. Whitman & Rifkin [10], for example,
provide an audio-driven model for predicting words found near artists in web
queries . One main contribution of the work in this paper lies in the scale of our
experiments. As is described in Section 4 we work with a social tag database of
millions of tags applied to ? 100, 000 artists and an audio database of ? 90, 000
songs spanning many of the more popular of these artists. This compares favor-
ably with previous attempts which by and large treat only very small datasets
(e.g. [10] used 255 songs drawn from 51 artists.) ?

Eck and Bertin-Mahieux currently at Dept. of Computer Science, Univ. of

Montreal, Montreal , Canada

1
This paper is organized as follows:

in Section 2 we describe social tags in
more depth, including a description of how social tags can be used to avoid
problems found in traditional collaborative ﬁltering systems, as well as a de-
scription of the tag set we built for these experiments. In Section 3 we present
an algorithm for autotagging songs based on labeled data collected from the
Internet. In Section 4 we present experimental results and also discuss the abil-
ity to use model results for visualization. Finally, in Section 5 we describe our
conclusions and future work.

2
Using social tags for recommendation
As the amount of online music grows, automatic music recommendation be-
comes an increasingly important tool for music listeners to ﬁnd music that they
will like. Automatic music recommenders commonly use collaborative ﬁltering
(CF) techniques to recommend music based on the listening behaviors of other
music listeners. These CF recommenders (CFRs) harness the ?wisdom of the
crowds? to recommend music. Even though CFRs generate good recommenda-
tions there are still some problems with this approach. A signiﬁcant issue for
CFRs recommenders is the cold-start problem. A recommender needs a signif-
icant amount of data before it can generate good recommendations. For new
music, music by an unknown artist with few listeners, a CFR cannot generate
good recommendations. Another issue is the lack of transparency in recom-
mendations [7]. A CFR cannot tell a listener why an artist was recommended
beyond the description: ?people who listen to X also listen to Y?. Also, a CFR
is relatively insensitive to multimodal uses of the same album or song. For
example songs from an album (a single purchase in a standard CFR system)
may be used in the context of dining, jogging and working. In each context,
the reason the song was selected changes. An alternative style of recommen-
dation that addresses many of the shortcomings of a CFR is to recommend
music based upon the similarity of ?social tags? that have been applied to
the music. Social tags are free text labels that music listeners apply to songs,
albums or artists. Typically, users are motivated to tag as a way to organize
their own personal music collection. The real strength of a tagging system is
seen when the tags of many users are aggregated. When the tags created by
thousands of diﬀerent listeners are combined, a rich and complex view of the

2

song or artist emerges. Table 1 show the top 21 tags and frequencies of tags
applied to the band ?The Shins?. Users have applied tags associated with the
genre (Indie, Pop, etc.), with the mood (mellow, chill), opinion (favorite, love),
style (singer-songwriter) and context (Garden State). From these tags and their
frequencies we learn much more about ?The Shins? than we would from a tradi-
tional single genre assignment of ?Indie Rock?. In this paper, we investigate the
automatic generation of tags with properties similar to those generated by social
taggers. Speciﬁcally, we introduce a machine learning algorithm that takes as
input acoustic features and predicts social tags mined from the web (in our case,
Last.fm). The model can then be used to tag new or otherwise untagged music,
thus providing a partial solution to the cold-start problem. For this research,
we extracted tags and tag frequencies for nearly 100,000 artists from the social
music website Last.fm using the Audioscrobbler web service [1]. The majority of
tags describe audio content. Genre, mood and instrumentation account for 77%
of the tags. See ?extra material? for a breakdown of tag types. Overcoming
the cold-start problem is the primary motivation for this area of research. For
new music or sparsely tagged music, we predict social tags directly from the
audio and apply these automatically generated tags (called autotags) in lieu of
traditionally applied social tags. By automatically tagging new music in this
fashion, we can reduce or eliminate much of the cold-start problem.

3
An autotagging algorithm
We now describe a machine learning model which uses the meta-learning
algorithm AdaBoost [5] to predict tags from acoustic features. This model is an
extension of a previous model [3] which won the Genre Prediction Contest and
was the 2nd place performer in the Artist Identiﬁcation Contest at MIREX 2005
(ISMIR conference, London, 2005). The model has two principal advantages.
First it selects features based on a feature?s ability to minimize empirical error.
We can therefore use the 2

Tag Indie Indie rock Indie pop Alternative Rock Seen Live Pop
Freq 2375 1138 841 653 512 298 231
Tag The Shins Favorites Emo Mellow Folk Alternative rock Acoustic
Freq 190 138 113 85 85 83 54
Tag Punk Chill Singer-songwriter Garden State Favorite Electronic Love
Freq 49 45 41 39 37 36 35
Table 1: Top 21 tags applied to The Shins
Artist A cool
PREDICTION
LEARNING ?80s? TAG
SONG TAGGING
80s
SET OF BOOSTERS
Song 1
rock
new song training audio features Song 1 cool
80s rock

3

?80s? booster target: ?80s? none/some/a lot
predicted tags
Figure 1: Overview of our model model to eliminate useless feature sets
by looking at the order in which those features are selected. We used this
property of the model to discard many candidate features such as chromagrams
(which map spectral energy onto the 12 notes of the Western musical scale)
because the weak learners associated with those features were selected very
late by AdaBoost. Second, though AdaBoost may need relatively more weak
learners to achieve the same performance on a large dataset than a small one,
the computation time for a single weak learner scales linearly with the number
of training examples. Thus AdaBoost has the potential to scale well to very
large datasets. Both of these properties are general to AdaBoost and are not
explored further in this short paper. See [5, 9] for more. 3.1

Acoustic feature extraction
The features we use include 20 Mel-Frequency Cepstral Coeﬃcients, 176 au-
tocorrelation coeﬃcients computed for lags spanning from 250msec to 2000msec
at 10ms intervals, and 85 spectrogram coeﬃcients sampled by constant-Q (or
log-scaled) frequency (see [6] for descriptions of these standard acoustic fea-
tures.) The audio features described above are calculated over short windows
of audio ( 100ms with 25ms overlap). This yields too many features per song
for our purposes. To address this, we create ?aggregate? features by comput-
ing individual means and standard deviations (i.e., independent Gaussians) of
these features over 5s windows of feature data. When ﬁxing hyperparameters
for these experiments, we also tried a combination of 5s and 10s features, but
saw no real improvement in results. For reasons of computational eﬃciency we
used random sampling to retain a maximum of 12 aggregate features per song,
corresponding to 1 minute of audio data. 3.2

Labels as a classiﬁcation problem
Intuitively, automatic labeling would be a regression task where a learner
would try to predict tag frequencies for artists or songs. However, because tags
are sparse (many artist are not tagged at all; others like Radiohead are heavily
tagged) this proves to be too diﬃcult using our current Last.fm 3

dataset. Instead, we chose to treat the task as a classiﬁcation one. Specif-
ically, for each tag we try to predict if a particular artist has ?none?, ?some?
or ?a lot? of a particular tag relative to other tags. We normalize the tag
frequencies for each artist so that artists having many tags can be compared
to artists having few tags. Then for each tag, an individual artist is placed
into a single class ?none?, ?some? or ?a lot? depending on the proportion of
times the tag was assigned to that artist relative to other tags assigned to that
artist. Thus if an artist received only 50 rock tags and nothing else, it would
be treated as having ?a lot? of rock. Conversely, if an artist received 5000 rock
tags but 10,000 jazz tags it would be treated as having ?some? rock and ?a lot?
of jazz. The speciﬁc boundaries between ?none?, ?some? and ?a lot? were de-
cided by summing the normalized tag counts or all artists, generating a 100-bin
histogram for each tag and moving the category boundaries such that an equal
number of artists fall into each of the categories. In Figure 2 the histogram for

4

?rock? is shown (with only 30 bins to make the plot easier to read). Note that
most artists fall into the lowest bin (no or very few instances of the ?rock? tag)
and that otherwise most of the mass is in high bins. This was the trend for
most tags and one of our motivations for using only 3 bins. As described in the
paper we do not directly use the predictions of the ?some? bin. Rather it serves
as a class for holding those artists for which we cannot conﬁdently say ?none?
or ?a lot?. See Figure 2 for an example.

Figure 2: A 30-bin histogram of the proportion of ?rock? tags to other tags

for all songs in the dataset. 3.3

Tag prediction with AdaBoost
AdaBoost [5] is a meta-learning method that constructs a strong classiﬁer
from a set of simpler classiﬁers, called weak learners in an iterative way. Orig-
inally intended for binary classiﬁcation, there exist several ways to extend it
to multiclass classiﬁcation. We use AdaBoost.MH [9] which treats multiclass
classiﬁcation as a set of one-versus-all binary classiﬁcation problems. In each
iteration t, the algorithm selects the best classiﬁer, called h(t) from a pool of
weak learners, based on its performance on the training set, and assigns it a
coeﬃcient ?(t) . The input to the weak learner is a d-dimensional observation
vector x ? ¡d containing audio features for one segment of aggregated data (5
seconds in our experiments). The output of h(t) is a binary vector y ? {?1,
1}k (t) over the k classes. hl = 1 means a vote for class l by a weak learner
while h(t) , ?1 is a vote against. After T iterations, the algorithm output is a
vector-valued discriminant function: g(x) =

T X
?(t) h(y) (x)
(1)
t=1
As weak learners we used single stumps, e.g. a binary threshold on one of the
features. In previous work we also tried decision trees without any signiﬁcant
improvement. Usually we obtain a single label by taking the class with the most
votes i.e f (x) = arg maxl gl (x), but in our model, we use the output value for
each class rather than the argmax. 3.4

Generating autotags
For each aggregate segment, a booster yields a prediction over the classes
?none?, ?some?, and ?a lot?. A booster?s raw output for a single segment might
be (none:?3.56) (some:0.14) (a lot:2.6). 4

These segment predictions can then be combined to yield artist-level predic-
tions. This can be achieved in two ways: a winning class can be chosen for each
segment (in this example the class ?a lot? would win with 2.6) and the mean
over winners can be tallied for all segments belonging to an artist. Alternately
we can skip choosing a winner and simply take the mean of the raw outputs
for an artist?s segments. Because we wanted to estimate tag frequencies using
booster magnitude we used the latter strategy. The next step is to transform
these class for our individual social tag boosters into a bag of words to be asso-
ciated with an artist. The most naive way to obtain a single value for rock is to
look solely at the prediction for the ?a lot? class. However this discards valu-

5

able information such as when a booster votes strongly ?none?. A better way to
obtain a measure for rock-ness is to take the center of mass of the three values.
However, because the values are not scaled well with respect to one another, we
ended up with poorly scaled results. Another intuitive idea is simply to subtract
the value of the ?none? bin from the value of the ?a lot? bin, the reasoning
being that ?none? is truly the opposite of ?a lot?. In our example, this would
yield a rock strength of 7.16. In experiments for setting hyperparameters, this
was shown to work better than other methods. Thus to generate our ﬁnal mea-
sure of rock-ness, we ignore the middle bin (?some?). However this should not
be taken to mean that the middle ?some? bin is useless: the booster needed
to learn to predict ?some? during training thus forcing it to be more selective
in predicting ?none? and ?a lot?. As a largemargin classiﬁer, AdaBoost tries
to separate the classes as much as possible, so the magnitude of the values for
each bin are not easily comparable. To remedy this, we normalize by taking
the minimum and maximum prediction for each booster, which seems to work
for ﬁnding similar artists. This normalization would not be necessary if we had
good tagging data for all artists and could perform regression on the frequency
of tag occurrence across artists.

4
Experiments
To test our model we selected the 60 most popular tags from the Last.fm
crawl data described in Section 2. These tags included genres such as ?Rock?,
?Electronica?, and ?Post Punk?, moodrelated terms such as ?Chillout?. The full
list of tags and frequencies are available in the ?extra materials?. We collected
MP3s for a subset of the artists obtained in our Audioscrobbler crawl. From
those MP3s we extracted several popular acoustic features. In total our training
and testing data included 89924 songs for 1277 artists and yielded more than 1
million 5s aggregate features. 4.1

Booster Errors
As described above, a classiﬁer was trained to map audio features onto aggre-
gate feature segments for each of the 60 tags. A third of the data was withheld
for testing. Because each of the 60 boosters needed roughly 1 day to process,
we did not perform cross-validation. However each booster was trained on a
large amount of data relative to the number of decision stumps learned, mak-
ing overﬁtting a remote possibility. Classiﬁcation errors are shown in Table 2.
These errors are broken down by tag in the annex for this paper. Using 3 bins
and balanced classes, the random error is about 67%.

Segment Song
Mean 40.93 37.61
Median 43.1 39.69
Min 21.3 17.8
Max 49.6 46.6
Table 2: Summary of test error (%) on predicting bins for songs and seg-

ments.
4.2
Evaluation measures

6

We use three measures to evaluate the performance of the model. The
ﬁrst TopN compares two ranked lists, a target ?ground truth? list A and our
predicted list B. This measure is introduced in [2], and is intended to place
emphasis on how well our list predicts the top few items of the target list. Let
kj be the position in list B of the jth element from list A. ?r = 0.51/3 , and ?c
= 0.52/3 , 5

as in [2]. The result is a value between 0 (dissimilar) and 1 (identical top N

), PN j kj j=1 ?r ?c si = PN l l=1 (?r ? ?c )

(2)
For the results produced below, we look at the top N = 10 elements in the
lists. Our second measure is Kendall?s T au, a classic measure in collaborative
ﬁltering which measures the number of discordant pairs in 2 lists. Let RA (i)
be the rank of the element i in list A, if i is not explicitly present, RA (i) =
length(A) + 1. Let C be the number of concordant pairs of elements (i, j), e.g.
RA (i) ¿ RA (j) and RB (i) ¡ RB (j).
In a similar way, D is the number of
discordant pairs. We use ? ?s approximation in [8]. We also deﬁne TA and TB
the number of ties in list A and B. In our case, it?s the number of pairs of artists
that are in A but not in B, because they end up having the same position RB
= length(B) + 1, and reciprocally. Kendall?s tau value is deﬁned as: ?=

C ?D sqrt((C + D + TA )(C + D + TB ))
(3)
Unless otherwise noted, we analyzed the top 50 predicted values for the
target and predicted lists. Finally, we compute what we call the TopBucket,
which is simply the percentage of common elements in the top N of 2 ranked
lists. Here as in Kendall we compare the top 50 predicted values unless otherwise
noted. 4.3

Constructing ground truth
As has long been acknowledged [4] one of the biggest challenges in addressing
this task is to ﬁnd a reasonable ?ground truth? against which to compare our
results. We seek a similarity matrix among artists which is not overly biased by
current popularity, and which is not built directly from the social tags we are
using for learning targets. Furthermore we want to derive our measure using
data that is freely available data on the web, thus ruling out commercial services
such as AllMusic (www.allmusic.com). Our solution is to construct our ground
truth similarity matrix using correlations from the listening habits of Last.fm
users. If a signiﬁcant number of users listen to artists A and B (regardless of the
tags they may assign to that artist) we consider those two artists similar. One
challenge, of course, is that some users listen to more music than others and
that some artists are more popular than others. Text search engines must deal
with a similar problem: they want to ensure that frequently used words (e.g.,
system) do not outweigh infrequently used words (e.g., prestidigitation) and
that long documents do not always outweigh short documents. Search engines
assign a weight to each word in a document. The weight is meant to represent
how important that word is for that document. Although many such weighting
schemes have been described (see [11] for a comprehensive review), the most
popular is the term frequency-inverse document frequency (or TF?IDF) weight-

7

ing scheme. TF?IDF assigns high weights to words that occur frequently in a
given document and infrequently in the rest of the collection. The fundamental
idea is that words that are assigned high weights for a given document are good
discriminators for that document from the rest of the collection. Typically, the
weights associated with a document are treated as a vector that has its length
normalized to one. In the case of LastFM, we can consider an artist to be a
?document?, where the ?words? of the document are the users that have lis-
tened to that artist. The TF?IDF weight for a given user for a given artist takes
into account the global popularity of a given artist and ensures that users who
have listened to more artists do not automatically dominate users who have
listened to fewer artists. The resulting similarity measure seems to us to do a
reasonable enough job of capturing artist similarity. Furthermore it does not
seem to be overly biased towards popular bands. See ?extra material? for some
examples. 4.4

Similarity Results
One intuitive way to compare autotags and social tags is to look at how well
the autotags reproduce the rank order of the social tags. We used the measures
in Section 4.2 to measure this on 100 artists not used for training (Table 3).
The results were well above random. For example, the top 5 autotags were in
agreement with the top 5 social tags 61% of the time. 6

autotags random
TopN 10 0.636 0.111
Kendall (N=5) -0.099 -0.645
TopBucket (N=5) 61.0% 8.1%
Table 3: Results for all three measures on tag order for 100 out-of-sample

artists.

A more realistic way to compare autotags and social tags is via their artist
similarity predictions. We construct similarity matrices from our autotag results
and from the Last.fm social tags used for training and testing. The similarity
measure we used wascosine similarity scos (A1 , A2 ) = A1 ? A2 /(——A1 ——
——A2 ——) where A1 and A2 are tag magnitudes for an artist. In keeping
with our interest in developing a commercial system, we used all available data
for generating the similarity matrices, including data used for training. (The
chance of overﬁtting aside, it would be unwise to remove The Beatles from
your recommender simply because you trained on some of their songs). The
similarity matrix is then used to generate a ranked list of similar artists for each
artist in the matrix. These lists are used to compute the measures describe in
Section 4.2. Results are found at the top in Table 4. One potential ﬂaw in this
experiment is that the ground truth comes from the same data source as the
training data. Though the ground truth is based on user listening counts and our
learning data comes from aggregate tagging counts, there is still a clear chance of
contamination. To investigate this, we selected the autotags and social tags for
95 of the artists from the USPOP database [2]. We constructed a ground truth
matrix based on the 2002 MusicSeer web survey eliciting similarity rankings
between artists from appro 1000 listeners [2]. These results show much closer
correspondence between our autotag results and the social tags from Last.fm

8

than the previous test. See bottom, Table 4. Groundtruth Last.FM MusicSeer

Model social tags autotags random social tags autotags random
TopN 10 0.26 0.118 0.005 0.237 0.184 0.051
Kendall 50 -0.23 -0.406 -0.635 -0.182 -0.161 -0.224
TopBucket 20 34.6% 22.5% 3.9% 29.7% 28.2% 21.5%
Table 4: Performance against Last.Fm (top) and MusicSeer (bottom) ground

truth.

It is clear from these previous two experiments that our autotag results do
not outperform the social tags on which they were trained. Thus we asked
whether combining the predictions of the autotags with the social tags would
yield better performance than either of them alone. To test this we blended
the autotag similarity matrix Sa with the social tag matrix Ss using ?Sa + (1
? ?)Ss . The results shown in Figure 3 show a consistent performance increase
when blending the two similarity sources. It seems clear from these results that
the autotags are of value. Though they do not outperform the social tags on
which they were trained, they do yield improved performance when combined
with social tags. At the same time they are driven entirely by audio and so can
be applied to new, untagged music. With only 60 tags the model makes some
reasonable predictions. When more boosters are trained, it is safe to assume
that the model will perform better.

5
Conclusion and future work
The work presented here is preliminary, but we believe that a supervised
learning approach to autotagging has substantial merit. Our next step is to
compare the performance of our boosted model to other approaches such as
SVMs and neural networks. The dataset used for these experiments is already
larger than those used for published results for genre and artist classiﬁcation.
However, a dataset another order of magnitude larger is necessary to approxi-
mate even a small commercial database of music. A further next step is com-
paring the performance of our audio features with other sets of audio features.
7

Figure 3: Similarity performance results when autotag similarities are blended
with social tag similarities. The horizontal line is the performance of the social
tags against ground truth. We plan to extend our system to predict many more
tags than the current set of 60 tags. We expect the accuracy of our system to
improve as we extend our tag set, especially as we add tags such as Classical
and Folk that are associated with whole genres of music. We will also continue
exploring ways in which the autotag results can drive music visualization. See
?extra examples? for some preliminary work. Our current method of evaluating
our system is biased to favor popular artists. In the future, we plan to extend
our evaluation to include comparisons with music similarity derived from hu-
man analysis of music. This type of evaluation should be free of popularity bias.
Most importantly, the machine-generated autotags need to be tested in a social
recommender. It is only in such a context that we can explore whether autotags,
when blended with real social tags, will in fact yield improved recommendations.

9

2 References

[1] Audioscrobbler. Web Services described at http://www.audioscrobbler.net/data/webservices/.
[2] A. Berenzweig, B. Logan, D. Ellis, and B. Whitman. A large-scale evaluation
of acoustic and subjective music similarity measures. In Proceedings of the 4th
International Conference on Music Information Retrieval (ISMIR 2003), 2003.
[3] J. Bergstra, N. Casagrande, D. Erhan, D. Eck, and B. K?egl. Aggregate fea-
tures and AdaBoost for music classiﬁcation. Machine Learning, 65(2-3):473?484,
2006.
[4] D. Ellis, B. Whitman, A. Berenzweig, and S. Lawrence. The quest
for ground truth in musical artist similarity. In Proceedings of the 3th Interna-
tional Conference on Music Information Retrieval (ISMIR 2002), 2002.
[5] Y.
Freund and R.E. Shapire. Experiments with a new boosting algorithm. In Ma-
chine Learning: Proceedings of the Thirteenth International Conference, pages
148?156, 1996. [6] B. Gold and N. Morgan. Speech and Audio Signal Process-
ing: Processing and Perception of Speech and Music. Wiley, Berkeley, Cali-
[7] Jonathan L. Herlocker, Joseph A. Konstan, and John Riedl.
fornia., 2000.
Explaining collaborative ﬁltering recommendations.
In Computer Supported
Cooperative Work, pages 241?250, 2000. [8] Jonathan L. Herlocker, Joseph A.
Konstan, Loren G. Terveen, and John T. Riedl. Evaluating collaborative ﬁlter-
ing recommender systems. ACM Trans. Inf. Syst., 22(1):5?53, 2004. [9] R. E.
Schapire and Y. Singer. Improved boosting algorithms using conﬁdence-rated
predictions. Machine Learning, 37(3):297?336, 1999. [10] Brian Whitman and
Ryan M. Rifkin. Musical query-by-description as a multiclass learning problem.
In IEEE Workshop on Multimedia Signal Processing, pages 153?156. IEEE Sig-
nal Processing Society, 2002. [11] Justin Zobel and Alistair Moﬀat. Exploring
the similarity space. SIGIR Forum, 32(1):18?34, 1998.

8

10

