An Empirical Analysis of Domain Adaptation

Algorithms for Genomic Sequence Analysis

Authored by:

Bernhard Sch?lkopf

Gunnar R?tsch

Gabriele Schweikert
Christian Widmer

Abstract

We study the problem of domain transfer for a supervised classiﬁca-
tion task in mRNA splicing. We consider a number of recent domain
transfer methods from machine learning, including some that are novel,
and evaluate them on genomic sequence data from model organisms of
varying evolutionary distance. We ﬁnd that in cases where the organisms
are not closely related, the use of domain adaptation methods can help
improve classiﬁcation performance.

1 Paper Body

Ten years ago, an eight-year lasting collaborative eﬀort resulted in the ﬁrst
completely sequenced genome of a multi-cellular organism, the free-living ne-
matode Caenorhabditis elegans. Today, a decade after the accomplishment of
this landmark, 23 eukaryotic genomes have been completed and more than 400
are underway. The genomic sequence builds the basis for a large body of research
on understanding the biochemical processes in these organisms. Typically, the
more closely related the organisms are, the more similar the biochemical pro-
cesses. It is the hope of biological research that by analyzing a wide spectrum of
model organisms, one can approach an understanding of the full biological com-
plexity. For some organisms, certain biochemical experiments can be performed
more readily than for others, facilitating the analysis of particular processes.
This understanding can then be transferred to other organisms, for instance by
verifying or reﬁning models of the processes?at a fraction of the original cost.
This is but one example of a situation where transfer of knowledge across do-
mains is fruitful. In machine learning, the above information transfer is called
domain adaptation, where one aims to use data or a model of a well-analyzed
source domain to obtain or reﬁne a model for a less analyzed target domain.
For supervised classiﬁcation, this corresponds to the case where there are ample

1

labeled examples (xi , yi ), i = 1, . . . , m for the source domain, but only few
such examples (xi , yi ), i = m + 1, . . . , m + n for the target domain (n ? m).
The examples are assumed to be drawn independently from the joint probability
distributions PS (X, Y ) and PT (X, Y ), respectively. The distributions PS (X,
Y ) = PS (Y —X) ? PS (X) and PT (X, Y ) = PT (Y —X) ? PT (X) can diﬀer
in several ways: (1) In the classical covariate shift case, it is assumed that only
the distributions of the input features P (X) varies between the two domains:
PS (X) 6= PT (X). The conditional, however, remains 1

These authors contributed equally.
invariant, PS (Y —X) = PT (Y —X). For a given feature vector x the label
y is thus independent of the domain from which the example stems. An example
thereof would be if a function of some biological material is conserved between
two organisms, but its composition has changed (e.g. a part of a chromosome
has been duplicated).
(2) In a more diﬃcult scenario the conditionals diﬀer
between domains, PS (Y —X) 6= PT (Y —X), while P (X) may or may not
vary. This is the more common case in biology. Here, two organisms may have
evolved from a common ancestor and a certain biological function may have
changed due to evolutionary pressures. The evolutionary distance may be a
good indicator for how well the function is conserved. If this distance is small,
we have reason to believe that the conditionals may not be completely diﬀerent,
and knowledge of one of them should then provide us with some information also
about the other one. While such knowledge transfer is crucial for biology, and
performed by biologists on a daily basis, surprisingly little work has been done to
exploit it using machine learning methods on biological databases. The present
paper attempts to ﬁll this gap by studying a realistic biological domain transfer
problem, taking into account several of the relevant dimensions in a common
experimental framework: ? methods ? over the last years, the ﬁeld of machine
learning has seen a strong increase in interest in the domain adaptation problem,
reﬂected for instance by a recent NIPS workshop ? domain distance ? ranging
from close organisms, where simply combining training sets does the job, to
distant organisms where more sophisticated methods can potentially show their
strengths ? data set sizes ? whether or not it is worth transferring knowledge
from a distant organism is expected to depend on the amount of data available
for the target system With the above in mind, we selected the problem of mRNA
splicing (see Figure A1 in the Appendix for more details) to assay the above
dimensions of domain adaptation on a task which is relevant to modern biology.
The paper is organized as follows: In Section 2, we will describe the experimental
design including the datasets, the underlying classiﬁcation model, and the model
selection and evaluation procedure. In Section 3 we will brieﬂy review a number
of known algorithms for domain adaptation, and propose certain variations. In
Section 4 we show the results of our comparison with a brief discussion.

2
Experimental Design
2.1 A Family of Classiﬁcation Problems We consider the task of identifying
so-called acceptor splice sites within a large set of potential splice sites based
on a sequence window around a site. The idea is to consider the recognition of

2

splice sites in diﬀerent organisms: In all cases, we used the very well studied
model organism C. elegans as the source domain. As target organisms we chose
two additional nematodes, namely, the close relative C. remanei, which diverged
from C. elegans 100 million years ago [10], and the more distantly related P.
paciﬁcus, a lineage which has diverged from C. elegans more than 200 million
years ago [7]. As a third target organism we used D. melanogaster, which is sep-
arated from C. elegans by 990 million years [11]. Finally, we consider the plant
A. thaliana, which has diverged from the other organisms more than 1,600 mil-
lion years ago. It is assumed that a larger evolutionary distance will likely also
have led to an accumulation of functional diﬀerences in the molecular splicing
machinery. We therefore expect that the diﬀerences of classiﬁcation functions
for recognizing splice sites in these organisms will increase with increasing evo-
lutionary distance. 2.2 The Classiﬁcation Model It has been demonstrated that
Support Vector Machines (SVMs) [1] are well suited for the task of splice site
predictions across a wide range of organisms [9].
In this work, the so-called
Weighted Degree kernel has been used to measure the similarity between two
example sequences x and x? of

ﬁxed length L by counting co-occurring substrings in both sequences at the

same position: L?l+1 ?

1 X X k?wd (x, x? ) = ?d I x[l:l+d] = x?[l:l+d] L l=1
(1)
d=1
where x[l:l+d] is the substring of length d of x at position l and ?d = 2
??d+1 ?2 +? is the weighting of the substring lengths. In our previous study
we have used sequences of length L = 140 and substrings of length ? = 22
for splice site detection [9]. With the four-letter DNA sequence alphabet {A,
C, G, T } this leads to a very high dimensional feature space (¿ 1013 dimen-
sions). Moreover, to archive the best classiﬁcation performance, a large number
of training examples is very helpful ([9] used up to 10 million examples). For
the designed experimental comparison we had to run all algorithms many times
for diﬀerent training set sizes, organisms and model parameters. We chose the
source and target training set as large as possible?in our case at most 100,000
examples per domain. Moreover, not for all algorithms we had eﬃcient imple-
mentations available that can make use of kernels. Hence, in order to perform
this study and to obtain comparable results, we had to restrict ourselves to a
case were we can explicitly work in the feature space, if necessary (i.e. ? not
much larger than two). We chose ? = 1. Note, that this choice does not limit
the generality of this study, as there is no strong reason, why eﬃcient imple-
mentations that employ kernels could not be developed for all methods. The
development of large scale methods, however, was not the main focus of this
study. Note that the above choices required an equivalent of about 1500 days
of computing time on state-ofthe-art CPU cores. We therefore refrained from
including more methods, examples or dimensions. 2.3 Splits and Model Selec-
tion In the ﬁrst set of experiments we randomly selected a source dataset of
100,000 examples from C. elegans, while data sets of sizes 2,500, 6,500, 16,000,
40,000 and 100,000 were selected for each target organism. Subsequently we

3

performed a second set of experiments where we combined several sources. For
our comparison we used 25,000 labeled examples from each of four remaining
organisms to predict on a target organism. We ensured that the positives to
negatives ratio is at 1/100 for all datasets. Two thirds of each target set were
used for training, while one third was used for evaluation in the course of hyper-
parameter tuning.1 Additionally, test sets of 60,000 examples were set aside for
each target organism. All experiments were repeated three times with diﬀerent
training splits (source and target), except the last one which always used the
full data set. Reported will be the average area under the precision-recall-curve
(auPRC) and its standard deviation, which is considered a sensible measure for
imbalanced classiﬁcation problems. The data and additional information will
be made available for download on a supplementary website.2

3 Methods for Domain Adaptation Regarding the distributional view that
was presented in Section 1, the problem of splice site prediction can be aﬀected
by both evils simultaneously, namely PS (X) 6= PT (X) and PS (Y —X) 6= PT
(Y —X), which is also the most realistic scenario in the case of modeling most
biological processes. In this paper, we will therefore drop the classical covariate
shift assumption, and allow for diﬀerent predictive functions PS (Y —X) 6=
PT (Y —X). 3.1 Baseline Methods (SVMS and SVMT ) As baseline methods
for the comparison we consider two methods: (a) training on the source data
only (SVMS ) and (b) training on the target data only (SVMT ). For SVMS we
use the source data for training however we tune the hyper-parameter on the
available target data. For SVMT we use the available target data for training
(67%) and model selection (33%). The resulting functions are fS (x) = h?(x),
wS i + bS and fT (x) = h?(x), wT i + bT . 1 2

Details on the hyper-parameter settings and tuning are shown in Table A2 in

the appendix. http://www.fml.mpg.de/raetsch/projects/genomedomainadaptation

3.2 Convex Combination (SVMS +SVMT ) The most straightforward idea
for domain adaptation is to reuse the two optimal functions fT and fS as gener-
ated by the base line methods SVMS and SVMT and combine them in a convex
manner: F (x) = ?fT (x) + (1 ? ?)fS (x). Here, ? ? [0, 1] is the convex combina-
tion parameter that is tuned on the evaluation set (33%) of the target domain.
A great beneﬁt of this approach is its eﬃciency. 3.3 Weighted Combination
(SVMS+T ) Another simple idea is to train the method on the union of source
and target data. The relative importance of each domain is integrated into the
loss term of the SVM and can be adjusted by setting domain-dependent cost
parameters CS and CT for the m and n training examples from the source and
target domain, respectively: min w,?

s.t.
m m+n X X 1 2 kwk + CS ?i + CT ?i 2 i=1 i=m+1
yi (hw, ?(xi )i + b) ? 1 ? ?i ?i ? 0 ?i ? [1, m + n]
(2)
?i ? [1, m + n]
This method has two model parameters and requires training on the union
of the training sets. Since the computation time of most classiﬁcation meth-
ods increases super-linearly and full model selection may require to train many

4

parameter combinations, this approach is computationally quite demanding.
Dual-task Learning (SVMS,T )

3.4
One way of extending the weighted combination approach is a variant of
multi-task learning [2]. The idea is to solve the source and target classiﬁcation
problems simultaneously and couple the two solutions via a regularization term.
This idea can be realized by the following optimization problem: min

wS ,wT ,?
s.t.
m+n X 1 ?i kwS ? wT k2 + C 2 i=1
yi (hwS , ?(xi )i + b) ? 1 ? ?i yi (hwT , ?(xi )i + b) ? 1 ? ?i ?i ? 0
(3) ?i ? 1, . . . , m ?i ? m + 1, . . . , m + n ?i ? 1, . . . , m + n
Please note that now wS and wT are optimized. The above optimization
problem can be solved using a standard QP-solver. In a preliminary experiment
we used the optimization package CPLEX to solve this problem, which took
too long as the number of variables is relatively large. Hence, we decided to ap-
proximate the soft-margin loss using the logistic loss l(f (x), y) = log(1+exp(?yf
(x))) and to use a conjugate gradient method3 to minimize the resulting objec-
tive function in terms of wS and wT . 3.5 Kernel Mean Matching (SVMS?T )
Kernel methods map the data into a reproducing kernel Hilbert space (RKHS)
by means of a mapping ? : X ? H related to a positive deﬁnite kernel via k(x, x?
) = h?(x), ?(x? )i. Depending on the choice of kernel, the space of H may be
spanned by a large number of higher order features of the data. In such cases,
higher order statistics for a set of input points can be computed in H by simply
taking the mean (i.e., the ﬁrst order statistics). In fact, it turns out that for a
certain class of kernels, the mapping n 1X ? : (x1 , . . . , xn ) 7? ?(xi ) n i=1 3

We used Carl Rasmussen?s minimize function.
is injective [5] ? in other words, given knowledge of (only) the mean (the
right hand side), we can completely reconstruct the set of points. For a charac-
terization of this class of kernels, see for instance [4]. It is often not necessary to
retain all information (indeed, it may be useful to specify which information we
want to retain and which one we want to disregard, see [8]). Generally speaking,
the higher dimensional H, the more information is contained in the mean. In [6]
it was proposed that one could use this for covariate shift adaptation, moving
the mean of a source distribution (over the inputs only) towards the mean of a
target distribution by re-weighting the source training points. We have applied
this to our problem, but found that a variant of this approach performed better.
In this variant, we do not re-weight the source points, but rather we translate
each point towards the mean of the target inputs: ! m m+n X X 1 1 ? j ) =
?(xj ) ? ? ?(x ?(xi ) ? ?(xi ) ?j = 1, . . . , m. m i=1 n i=m+1

This also leads to a modiﬁed source input distribution which is statistically
more similar to the target distribution and which can thus be used to improve
performance when training the target task. Unlike [6], we do have a certain
amount of labels also for the target distribution. We make use of them by
performing the shift separately for each class y ? {?1}: ! m m+n X X 1 1 ? j )
= ?(xj ) ? ? ?(x [[yi = y]]?(xi ) ? [[yi = y]]?(xi ) my i=1 ny i=m+1

5

.

.

for all j = m + 1, .

, m + n with yj = y, where my and ny are the
number of source and target examples with label y, respectively. The shifted
examples can now be used in diﬀerent ways to obtain a ﬁnal classiﬁer. We
decided to use the weighted combination with CS = CT for comparison. 3.6
Feature Augmentation (SVMS?T )

In [3] a method was proposed that augments the features of source and target
examples in a domainspeciﬁc way: ? ?(x) = (?(x), ?(x), 0)? for i = 1, . . . , m
? ?(x) = (?(x), 0, ?(x))? for i = m + 1, . . . , m + n. The intuition behind this
idea is that there exist one set of parameters that models the properties common
to both sets and two additional sets of parameters that model the speciﬁcs of
the two domains. It can easily be seen that the kernel for the augmented feature
space can be computed as:

2h?(xi ), ?(xj )i if [[i ? m]] = [[j ? m]] kAU G (xi , xi ) = h?(xi ), ?(xj )i
otherwise This means that the ?similarity? between two examples is two times
as high, if the examples were drawn from the same domain, as if they were drawn
from diﬀerent domains. Instead of the factor 2, we used a hyper-parameter B in
the following. 3.7 Combination of Several Sources Most of the above algorithms
can be extended in one way or another to integrate several source domains. In
this work we consider only three possible algorithms: (a) convex combinations of
several domains, (b) KMM on several domains and (c) an extension of the dual-
task learning approach to multi-task learning. We brieﬂy describe these methods
below: Multiple Convex Combinations (M-SVMS +SVMT ) The most general
version would be to optimize all convex combination coeﬃcients independently.
If done in a grid-search-like manner, it becomes prohibitive for more than say
three source domains. In principle, one can optimize these coeﬃcients also by
solving a linear program. In preliminary experiments we tried both approaches
and they typically did not lead to better results than the following combination:
1 X F (x) = ?fT (x) + (1 ? ?) fS (x), —S— S?S

where S is the set of all considered source domains. We therefore only

considered this way of combining the predictions.

Multiple KMM (M-SVMS?T ) Here, we shift the source examples of each
domain independently towards the target examples, but by the same relative
distance (?). Then we train one classiﬁer on the shifted source examples as well
as the target examples. Multi-task Learning (M-SVMS,T ) We consider the
following version of multi-task learning: min

{wD }D?D ,?
s.t.
X 1 X X ?D1 ,D2 kwD1 ? wD2 k2 + ?i 2 i
(4)
D1 ?D D2 ?D
yi (hwDj , ?(xi )i + b) ? 1 ? ?i ?i ? 0
(5)
for all examples (xi , yi ) in domain Dj ? D, where D is the set of all consid-
ered domains. ? is a set of regularization parameters, which we parametrized
by two parameters CS and CT in the following way: ?D1 ,D2 = CS if D1 and
D2 are source domains and CT otherwise.

6

4
Experimental Results
We considered two diﬀerent settings for the comparison. For the ﬁrst exper-
iment we assume that there is one source domain with enough data that should
be used to improve the performance in the target domain. In the second setting
we analyze whether one can beneﬁt from several source domains. 4.1 Single
Source Domain Due to space constraints, we restrict ourselves to presenting a
summary of our results with a focus on best and worst performing methods.
The detailed results are given in Figure A2 in the appendix, where we show
the median auPRC of the methods SVMT , SVMS , SVMS?T , SVMS+T ,
SVMS +SVMT , SVMS?T and SVMS,T for the considered tasks. The sum-
mary is given in Figure 1, where we ? illustrate which method performed best
(green), similarly well (within a conﬁdence interval of ?/ n) as the best (light
green), considerably worse than the best (yellow), not signiﬁcantly better than
the worst (light red) or worst (red). From these results we can make the fol-
lowing observations: 1. Independent of the task, if there is very little target
data available, the training on source data performs much better than train-
ing on the target data. Conversely, if there is much target data available then
training on it easily outperforms training the source data. 2. For a larger
evolutionary distance of the target organisms to source organism C. elegans, a
relatively small number of target training examples for the SVMT approach is
suﬃcient to achieve similar performance to the SVMS approach, which is al-
ways trained on 100,000 examples. We call the number of target examples with
equal source and target performance the break-even point. For instance, for the
closely related organism C. remanei one needs nearly as many target data as
source data to achieve the same performance. For the most distantly related
organism A. thaliana, less than 10% target data is suﬃcient to outperform the
source model. 3. In almost all cases, the performance of domain adaption algo-
rithms is considerably higher than source (SVMS ) and target only (SVMT ).
This is most pronounced near the break-even point, e.g. 3% improvement for
C. remanei and 14% for D. melanogaster. 4. Among the domain adaptation
algorithms, the dual-task learning approach (SVMS,T ) performed most often
best (12/20 cases). Second most often best (5/20) performed the convex com-
bination approach (SVMS +SVMT ). From our observations we can conclude
that the simple convex combination approach works surprisingly well. It is only
outperformed by the dual-task learning algorithm which performs consistently
well for all organisms and target training set sizes.

2 References

NA

7

