Sparse Signal Recovery Using Markov Random

Fields

Authored by:

Marco F. Duarte
Chinmay Hegde
Richard Baraniuk

Volkan Cevher

Abstract

Compressive Sensing (CS) combines sampling and compression into a
single sub-Nyquist linear measurement process for sparse and compress-
ible signals. In this paper, we extend the theory of CS to include signals
that are concisely represented in terms of a graphical model. In partic-
ular, we use Markov Random Fields (MRFs) to represent sparse signals
whose nonzero coeﬃcients are clustered. Our new model-based recon-
struction algorithm, dubbed Lattice Matching Pursuit (LaMP), stably
recovers MRF-modeled signals using many fewer measurements and com-
putations than the current state-of-the-art algorithms.

1 Paper Body

The Shannon/Nyquist sampling theorem tells us that in order to preserve in-
formation when uniformly sampling a signal we must sample at least two times
faster than its bandwidth. In many important and emerging applications, the
resulting Nyquist rate can be so high that we end up with too many samples
and must compress in order to store or transmit them. In other applications, in-
cluding imaging systems and high-speed analog-to-digital converters, increasing
the sampling rate or density beyond the current state-of-the-art is very expen-
sive. A transform compression system reduces the eﬀective dimensionality of
an N -dimensional signal by re-representing it in terms of a sparse expansion
in some basis (for example, the discrete cosine transform for JPEG). By sparse
we mean that only K ? N of the basis coeﬃcients are nonzero. The new theory
of compressive sensing (CS) combines sampling and compression into a single
subNyquist linear measurement process for sparse signals [1, 2]. In CS, we mea-
sure not periodic signal samples but rather inner products with M ¡ N known
measurement vectors; random measurement vectors play a starring role. We
then recover the signal by searching for the sparsest signal that agrees with

1

the measurements. Research in CS to date has focused on reducing both the
number of measurements M (as a function of N and K) and on reducing the
computational complexity of the recovery algorithm. Today?s state-of-the-art
CS systems can recover K-sparse and more general compressible signals using M
= O(K log(N/K)) measurements using polynomial-time linear programming or
greedy algorithms. While such sub-Nyquist measurement rates are impressive,
our contention in this paper is that for CS to truly live up its name it must more
fully leverage concepts from state-of-the-art compression algorithms. In virtu-
ally all such algorithms, the key ingredient is a signal model that goes beyond
simple sparsity by providing a model for the basis coeﬃcient structure. For
instance, JPEG does not only use the fact that most of the DCT of a natural
image are small. Rather, it also exploits the fact that the values and locations
of the large coeﬃcients have a particular structure that is characteristic of nat-
ural images. Coding this structure using an appropriate model enables JPEG
and other similar algorithms to compress images close to the maximum amount
possible, and signiﬁcantly better than a naive coder that just assigns bits to
each large coeﬃcient independently. 1

In this paper, we extend the theory of CS to include signals that are con-
cisely represented in terms of a graphical model [3]. We use Markov Random
Fields (MRFs) to represent sparse signals whose nonzero coeﬃcients also clus-
ter together. Our new model-based recovery algorithm, dubbed Lattice Match-
ing Pursuit (LaMP), performs rapid and numerically stable recovery of MRF-
modeled signals using far fewer measurements than standard algorithms. The
organization of the paper is as follows. In Sections 2 and 3, we brieﬂy review the
CS and MRF theories. We develop LaMP in Section 4 and present experimental
results in Section 5 using both simulated and real world data. We conclude by
oﬀering our perspective on the future directions of model-based CS research in
Section 6.
2 Compressive sensing: From sparsity to structured sparsity Sparse signal
recovery. Any signal x ? RN can be represented in terms of N coeﬃcients {?i
} in a basis {? i }N i=1 ; stacking the ? i as columns into the matrix ?N ?N ,
we can write succinctly that x = ??. We say that x has a sparse representation
if only K ? N entries of ? are nonzero, N and we denote by ?K the set of K
possible supports for such K-sparse signals. We say that x is compressible if
the sorted magnitudes of the entries of ? decay rapidly enough that it can be
well approximated as K-sparse. In Compressive Sensing (CS), the signal is not
acquired by measuring x or ? directly. Rather, we measure the M ¡ N linear
projections y = ?x = ??? using the M ? N matrix ?. In the sequel, without loss
of generality, we focus on two-dimensional image data and assume that ? = I
(the N ? N identity matrix) so that x = ?. The most commonly used criterion
for evaluating the quality of a CS measurement matrix is the restricted isometry
property (RIP). A matrix ? satisﬁes the K-RIP if there exists a constant ?K ¿
0 such that for all K-sparse vectors x, (1 ? ?K )kxk2 ? k?xk2 ? (1 + ?K )kxk2 .

(1)
The recovery of the set of signiﬁcant coeﬃcients ?i is achieved using optimiza-
tion: we search for the sparsest ? that agrees with the measurements y. While

2

in principle recovery is possible using a matrix that has the 2K-RIP with ?2K ¡
1, such an optimization is combinatorially complex (NPcomplete) and numeri-
cally unstable. If we instead use a matrix that has the 3K-RIP with ?3K ¡ 1/2,
then numerically stable recovery is possible in polynomial time using either a
linear program [1, 2] or a greedy algorithm [4]. Intriguingly, a random Gaussian
or Bernoulli matrix works with high probability, leading to a randomized acqui-
sition protocol instead of uniform sampling. Structured sparsity. While many
natural and manmade signals and images can be described to the ﬁrst-order
as sparse or compressible, their sparse supports (set of nonzero coeﬃcients) of-
ten have an underlying order. This order plays a central role in the transform
compression literature, but it has barely been explored in the CS context [5, 6].
The theme of this paper is that by exploiting a priori information on coeﬃcient
structure in addition to signal sparsity, we can make CS better, stronger, and
faster. Figure 1 illustrates a real-world example of structured sparse support
in a computer vision application. Figure 1(b) is a background subtracted im-
age computed from a video sequence of a parking lot with two moving people
(one image frame is shown in Figure 1(a)). The moving people form the fore-
ground (white in (b)), while the rest of the scene forms the background (black
in (b)). The background subtraction was computed from CS measurements of
the video sequence. Background subtracted images play a fundamental role in
making inferences about objects and activities in a scene and, by nature, they
have structured spatial sparsity corresponding to the foreground innovations. In
other words, compared to the scale of the scene, the foreground innovations are
usually not only sparse but also clustered in a distinct way, e.g., corresponding
to the silhouettes of humans and vehicles. Nevertheless, this clustering prop-
erty is not exploited by current CS recovery algorithms. Probabilistic RIP. The
RIP treats all possible K-sparse supports equally. However, if we incorporate a
probabilistic model on our signal supports and consider only the signal supports
with the highest likelihoods, then we can potentially do much better in terms
of the required number of measurements required for stable recovery. We say
that ? satisﬁes the (K, ?)-probabilistic RIP (PRIP) if there exists a constant
?K ¿ 0 such that for a K-sparse signal x generated by a speciﬁed probabilistic
signal model, (1) holds with probability at least 1 ? ? over the signal probability
space. We propose a preliminary result on the 2

PSfrag
(a)
(b)
(c)
Figure 1: A camera surveillance image (b) with the background subtracted
image (b) recovered using compressive measurements of the scene. The back-
ground subtracted image has resolution N = 240 ? 320 and sparsity K = 390.
(c) A random K = 390 sparse image in N = 240 ? 320 dimensions. The proba-
bility of image (b) under the Ising model is approximately 10856 times greater
than the probability of image (c).

number of random measurements needed under this new criterion; this is
a direct consequence of Theorem 5.2 of [8]. (See also [9] for related results.)

3

Lemma 1. Suppose that M , N , and ? ? [0, 1] are given and that the signal x is
generated by a known probabilistic model. Let ?K,? ? ?K denote the smallest
set of supports for which the probability that a K-sparse signal x has supp(x)
? / ?K,? is less than ?, and denote D = —?K,? —. If ? is a matrix with
normalized i.i.d. Gaussian or Bernoulli/Rademacher (?1) random entries, then
? has the (K, ?)-PRIP with probability at least 1 ? e?c2 M if M ? c1 (K +
log(D)), where c1 , c2 ¿ 0 depend only on the PRIP constant ?K . To illustrate
the signiﬁcance of the above lemma, consider the following probabilistic model
for an N -dimensional, K-sparse signal. We assume that the locations of the
non-zeros follow a homogeneous Poisson process with rate ? = ? log(?/K)N ??
, where ? ? 1. Thus, a particular non-zero coeﬃcient occurs within a distance
of N ? of its predecessor with probability 1 ? ?/K. We determine the size of the
likely K-sparse support set ?K under this particular signal model using a simple
counting argument. The location of the ﬁrst non-zero coeﬃcients is among the
ﬁrst N ? indices with probability 1 ? ?/K. After ﬁxing the location of the ﬁrst
coeﬃcient, the location of the second coeﬃcient is among the next N ? indices
immediately following the ﬁrst location with probability 1 ? ?/K. Proceeding
this way, after the locations of the ﬁrst j ? 1 coeﬃcients, have been ﬁxed, we
have that the j th non-zero coeﬃcient is among N ? candidate locations with
probability 1 ? ?/K. In this way, we obtain a set of supports ?K,? of size N ?K
that will occur with probability (1 ? ?/K)K ¿ 1 ? ?. Thus for the (K, ?)-PRIP
to hold for a random matrix, the matrix must have M = cK(1 + ? log N )
rows, as compared to the cK log(N/K) rows required for the standard K-RIP
to hold. When ? is on the order of (log N )?1 , the number of measurements
required and the complexity of the solution method grow essentially linearly
in K, which is a considerable improvement over the best possible M = O(K
log(N/K)) measurements required without such a priori information.

3 Graphical models for compressive sensing Clustering of the nonzero co-
eﬃcients in a sparse signal representation can be realistically captured by a
probabilistic graphical model such as a Markov random ﬁeld (MRF); in this
paper we will focus for concreteness on the classical Ising model [10]. Support
model. We begin with an Ising model for the signal support. Suppose we have
a K-sparse signal x ? RN whose support is represented by s ? {?1, 1}N such
that si = ?1 when xi = 0 and si = 1 when xi 6= 0. The probability density
function (PDF) of the signal support can be modeled using a graph Gs = (Vs ,
Es ), where Vs = {1, . . . , N } denotes a set of N vertices ? one for each of the
support indices ? and Es denotes the set of edges connecting support indices
that are spatial neighbors (see Figure 2(a)). The contribution of the interaction
between two elements {si , sj } in the support of x is controlled by the coeﬃcient
?ij ¿ 0. The contribution of each element si is controlled by a coeﬃcient ?i ,
resulting in the following PDF for the sparse support s: ? ? ? X ? X p(s; ?) =
exp ?ij si sj + ?i si ? Zs (?) , (2) ? ? i?Vs

(i,j)?Es
where Zs (?) is a strictly convex partition function with respect to ? that
normalizes the distribution so that it integrates to one. The parameter vector
? quantiﬁes our prior knowledge regarding the 3

4

y1 xi
xi sj si
yM
xj
xj
sj si
sj si (a)
(b)
(c)
Figure 2: Example graphical models: (a) Ising model for the support, (b)
Markov random ﬁeld model for the resulting coeﬃcients, (c) Markov random
ﬁeld with CS measurements.

signal support s and consists of the edge interaction parameters ?ij and the
vertex bias parameters ?i . These parameters can be learned from data using ?1
-minimization techniques [11]. The Ising model enforces coeﬃcient clustering.
For example, compare the clustered sparsity of the real background subtracted
image in Figure 1(b) with the dispersed ?independent? sparsity of the random
image in Figure 1(c). While both images (b) and (c) are equally sparse, under a
trained Ising model (?ij = 0.45 and ?i = 0), the image (b) is approximately 10856
times more likely than the image (c). Signal model. Without loss of generality,
we focus on 2D images that are sparse in the space domain, as in Figure 1(b).
Leveraging the Ising support model from above, we apply the MRF graphical
model in Figure 2(b) for the pixel coeﬃcient values. Under this model, the
support is controlled by an Ising model, and the signal values are independent
given the support. We now develop a joint PDF for the image pixel values x,
the support labels s, and the CS measurements y. We begin with the support
PDF p(s) from (2) and assume that we are equipped with a sparsitypromoting
PDF p(x—s) for x given s. The most commonly used PDF is the Laplacian
density (which is related to the ?1 -norm of x); however, other reference priors,
such as generalized Gaussians that are related to the ?p -norm of x, p ¡ 1, can
be more eﬀective [12]. We assume that the measurements

y are corrupted by i.i.d. Gaussian noise, i.e., p(y—x) = N y—?x, ? 2 I ,
where ? 2 is the unknown noise variance. From Figure 2(c), it is easy to show
that, given the signal x, the signal support s and the compressive measurements
y are independent using the D-separation property of graphs [13]. Hence, the
joint distribution of the vertices in the graph in Figure 2(b) can be written as
p(z) = p(s, x, y) = p(s, x)p(y—s, x) = p(s)p(x—s)p(y—x), T

T
(3)
T T
where z = [s , x , y ] . Then, (3) can be explicitly written as p(z) ? exp
? ? X ?
?ij si sj +
(i,j)?Es
X
[?i si + log(p(xi —si ))] ?

5

i?Vs
? ?
1 ——y ? ?x——22 . ? 2? 2
(4)
4 Lattice matching pursuit Using the coeﬃcient graphical model from Sec-
tion 3, we are now equipped to develop a new modelbased CS signal recovery
algorithm. Lattice Matching Pursuit (LaMP) is a greedy algorithm for signals
on 2D lattices (images) in which the likelihood of the signal support is itera-
tively evaluated and optimized under an Ising model. By enforcing a graphical
model, (i) partial knowledge of the sparse signal support greatly decreases the
ambiguity and thus size of the search space for the remaining unknown part,
accelerating the speed of the algorithm; and (ii) signal supports of the same size
but diﬀerent structures result in diﬀerent likelihoods (recall Figure 1(b) and
(c)), decreasing the required number of CS measurements and increasing the
numerical stability. Algorithm. The LaMP pseudocode is given in Algorithm
1. Similar to other greedy recovery algorithms such as matching pursuit and
CoSaMP [4], each iteration of LaMP starts by estimating a data residual r {k}
given the current estimate of the signal x{k?1} (Step 1). After calculating the
{k} residual, LaMP calculates a temporary signal estimate (Step 2) denoted by
xt . This signal esti? mate is the sum of the previous estimate x{k?1} and ? r
{k} , accounting for the current residual. Using this temporary signal estimate
as a starting point, LaMP then maximizes the likelihood (4) over the support
via optimization (Step 3). This can be eﬃciently solved using graph cuts with
4
Algorithm 1: LaMP ? Lattice Matching Pursuit e (desired sparsity). Input:
y, ?, x{0} = 0, s{0} = ?1, and K e Output: A K-sparse approximation x of
the acquired signal. Algorithm: repeat {Matching Pursuit Iterations} Step 1.
Calculate data residual: r{k} = y ? ?x{k?1} ; Step 2. Propose a temporary
target signal estimate: {k} xt = ?? r {k} + x{k?1} ; Step 3. Determine MAP
estimate of the support using graph cuts: h i P P {k} {k} s = maxs?{?1,+1}N
(i,j)?Es ?ij si sj + i?Vs ?i si + log(p([xt ]i —si )) ; Step 4. Estimate target
signal: e t = 0; t[s{k} = 1] = ?? [:, s{k} = 1]y; x{k} = Prune{t; K}; Step 5.
Iterate: k = k + 1;

until Maximum iterations or r{k} ¡ threshold; Return x = x{k} . 1 ?1
p(xi —si = ?1)
?2 ?3
L p(xi —si = +1)
?1
? log ?1
? log p(xi —si = ?1)
?
log p(xi —si =?1) ? log ?1
1
log ?2 log ?3
??
? log p(xi —si = +1)

6

?
log ?1
?
log p(xi —si =+1) log ?1
?1
U?1 (xi ; ? ) ? ?1 0 U+1 (xi ; ? )
Figure 3: Geometrical approximations of p(xi —si = ?1) and log p(xi —si

O(N ) complexity [14].

= +1).
In particular, for planar Ising models, the global
minimum of the problem can be obtained. Once a likely signal support s{k} is
obtained in Step 3, LaMP obtains an updated signal estimate x{k} using least
squares with the selected columns of the measurement matrix e signal coeﬃcients
(Step 4). Hence, the parameter ?[:, s{k} = 1] and pruning back to the largest
K e controls the sparsity of the approximation. In Step 4, a conjugate gradient
method is used for K eﬃciently performing the product by a pseudoinverse. If
the graphical model includes dependencies between the signal values xi , we then
replace the pseudoinverse product by a belief propagation algorithm to eﬃciently
solve for the signal values x{k} within Step 4. Signal log-likelihood log p(x—s).
The correct signal PDF to use given the support p(x—s) is problem-dependent.
Here, we provide one approximation that mimics the ?0 minimization for CS
recovery for the signal graphical model in Figure 2(c); we also use this in our
experiments in Section 5. The state si = 1 represents a nonzero coeﬃcient;
thus, all nonzero values of xi should have equal probability, and the value xi =
0 should have zero probability. Similarly, the state si = ?1 represents a zero-
valued coeﬃcient; thus, the mass of its probability function is concentrated at
zero. Hence, we use the approximations for xi ? [?L, L], a restricted dynamic
range: p(xi —si = ?1) = ?(xi ) and p(xi —si = 1) = (1 ? ?(xi ))/2L. However,
the optimization over the joint PDF in (4) requires a ?smoothing? of these PDFs
for two reasons: (i) to obtain robustness against noise and numerical issues; and
(ii) to extend the usage of the algorithm from sparse to compressible signals. We
approximate log p(xi —si = ?1) using the parametric form illustrated in Figure
3. Here, the constant ? is a slack parameter to separate large and small signal
coeﬃcients, and ?1 , ?2 , and ?3 are chosen according to ? and L to normalize
each PDF. We also denote a = ?3 L, with a ? 1. Using the normalization
constraints, it is possible to show that as the dynamic range increases, lim ?

L??
1 log ?2 ? and log ?1 ?a 5
lim ?
L??
log ?3 ? 0. log ?1
Hence, we approximate the likelihoods using the utility functions Usi (x; ?
) that follow this form. The optimization problem used by Step 3 of LaMP to
determine the support is then approximately equivalent to the following problem
i X Xh eij si sj + ei si + Us ([x{k+1} ]i ; ? ) , s{k+1} = max ? ? (5) i t
s?{?1,+1}N i?V (i,j)?Es

e = where ?

7

s
? log ?1 .
If the signal values are known to be positive, then the deﬁnitions of Usi can eij
is related to the desired be changed to enforce the positivity during estimation.
The choice of ? sparseness on the lattice structure. e on the lattice structure,
we apply statistical mechanics results on To enforce a desired sparsity K eij =
0.5 arcsin((1 ? m8 )? 14 ), where m is called the average the 2D Ising model and
choose ? magnetization. In our recovery problem, the average magnetization h
i and the desired signal sparsity ei = 0 unless there e e has a simple relationship:
m = (+1) ? K + (?1) ? (N ? K) /N . We set ? is prior information on the signal
support. The threshold ? is chosen at each iteration adaptively by e sorting the
magnitudes of the temporary target signal estimate coeﬃcients and determining
the 5K e threshold; this gives preference to the largest 5K coeﬃcients that attain
states si = 1, unless the cost incurred by enforcing the lattice structure is too
large. The pruning operation in Step 4 of LaMP e then enforces the desired
sparsity K.

5 Experiments
We now use several numerical simulations to demonstrate that for spatially
clustered sparse signals, which have high likelihood under our MRF model,
LaMP requires far fewer measurements and fewer computations for robust signal
recovery than state-of-the-art greedy and optimization techniques.1 Experiment
1: Shepp-Logan phantom. Figure 4 (top left) shows the classical N = 100 ? 100
Shepp-Logan phantom image. Its sparsity in the space domain is K = 1740. We
obtained compressive measurements of this image, which were then immersed
in additive white Gaussian noise to an SNR of 10dB. The top row of Figure 4
illustrates the iterative image estimates obtained using LaMP from just M =
2K = 3480 random Gaussian measurements of the noisy target. Within 3 itera-
tions, the support of the image is accurately determined; convergence occurs at
the 5th iteration. Figure 4 (bottom) compares LaMP to CoSaMP [4], a state-
of-the-art greedy recovery algorithm, and ﬁxed-point continuation (FPC) [17],
a state-of-the-art ?1 -norm minimization recovery algorithm using the same set
of measurements. Despite the presence of high noise (10dB SNR), LaMP per-
fectly recovers the signal support from only a small number of measurements.
It also outperforms both CoSaMP and FPC in terms of speed. Experiment 2:
Numerical stability. We demonstrate LaMP?s stability in the face of substantial
measurement noise. We tested both LaMP and FPC with a number of measure-
ments that gave close to perfect recovery of the Shepp-Logan phantom in the
presence of a small amount of noise; for LaMP, setting M = 1.7K suﬃces, while
FPC requires M = 4K. We then studied the degradation of the recovery quality
as a function of the noise level for both algorithms. For reference, a value of ?
= 20 corresponds to a measurement-to-noise ratio of just 6dB. The results in
Figure 5(a) demonstrate that LaMP is stable for a wide range of measurement
noise levels. Indeed, the rate of increase of the LaMP recovery error as a func-
tion of the noise variance ? (a measure of the stability to noise) is comparable to
that of FPC, while using far fewer measurements. Experiment 3: Performance
on real background subtracted images. We test the recovery algorithms over a

8

set of background subtraction images. The images were obtained from a test
video sequence, one image frame of which is shown in Figure 1, by choosing at
random two frames from the video and subtracting them in a pixel-wise fashion.
The large-valued pixels in the resulting images are spatially clustered and thus
are well-modeled by the MRF enforced by LaMP. We created 100 diﬀerent test
images; for each image, we deﬁne the sparsity K as the number of coeﬃcients
1 We use the GCOptimization package [14?16] to solve the support recovery
problem in Step 3 in Algorithm 1 in our implementation of LaMP.

6
Noise-free target
LaMP Iter. #1
LaMP Iter. #2
LaMP Iter. #3
LaMP Iter. #4
LaMP Iter. #5, 0.9s CoSaMP, 6.2s FPC, 6.5s Figure 4: Top: LaMP recovery

of the Shepp-Logan phantom (N = 100 ? 100, K = 1740, SNR = 10dB)

Maximum reconstruction error
3000 2500
Average normalized error magnitude
from M = 2K = 3480 noisy measurements. Bottom: Recoveries from LaMP,
CoSaMP, and FPC, including running times on the same computer. LaMP, M
= 1.7K FPC, M = 5K FPC, M = 4K

2000 1500 1000 500 0 0
5
10 ?
15
20
(a)
LaMP CoSaMP FPC
1.5
1
0.5
0 0
1
2
3 M/K
4
5
(b)
Figure 5: Performance of LaMP. (a) Maximum recovery error over 1000
noise iterations as a function of the input noise variance. LaMP has the same
robustness to noise as the FPC algorithm. (b) Performance over background
subtraction dataset of 100 images. LaMP achieves the best performance at M
? 2.5K , while both FPC and CoSaMP require M ¿ 5K to achieve the same
performance.

9

that contain 97% of the image energy. We then performed recovery of the
image using the LaMP, CoSaMP, and FPC algorithms under varying number
of measurements M , from 0.5K to 5K. An example recovery is shown in Figure
6. For each test and algorithm, we measured the magnitude of the estimation
error normalized by the magnitude of the original image. Figure 5(b) shows the
mean and standard deviations for the normalized error magnitudes of the three
algorithms. LaMP?s graphical model reduces the number of measurements nec-
essary for acceptable recovery quality to M ? 2.5K, while the standard algorithms
require M ? 5K measurements to achieve the same quality.

6 Conclusions We have presented an initial study of model-based CS signal
recovery using an MRF model to capture the structure of the signal?s sparse
coeﬃcients. As demonstrated in our numerical simulations, for signals conform-
ing to our model, the resulting LaMP algorithm requires signiﬁcantly fewer CS
measurements, has lower computational complexity, and has equivalent numer-
ical stability to the current state-of-the-art algorithms. We view this as an
initial step toward harnessing the power of modern compression and data mod-
eling methods for CS reconstruction. Much work needs to be done, however.
We are working to precisely quantify the reduction in the required number of
measurements (our numerical experiments suggest that M = O(K) is suﬃcient
for stable recovery) and computations. We also assert that probabilistic sig-
nal models hold the key to formulating inference problems in the compressive
measurement domain since in many signal processing applications, signals are
acquired merely for the purpose of making an inference such as a detection or
classiﬁcation decision. 7

Target
LaMP
CoSaMP
FPC
Figure 6: Example recoveries for background subtraction images, using M =
3K for each image. Acknowledgements. We thank Wotao Yin for helpful discus-
sions, and Aswin Sankaranarayanan for data used in Experiment 3. This work
was supported by grants NSF CCF-0431150 and CCF0728867, DARPA/ONR
N66001-08-1-2065, ONR N00014-07-1-0936 and N00014-08-1-1112, AFOSR FA9550-
07-1-0301, ARO MURI W311NF-07-1-0185, and the TI Leadership Program.

2 References

[1] D. L. Donoho. Compressed sensing. IEEE Trans. Info. Theory, 52(4):1289?1306,
Sept. 2006.
[2] E. J. Cand‘es. Compressive sampling. In Proc. International
Congress of Mathematicians, volume 3, pages 1433?1452, Madrid, Spain, 2006.
[3] S. L. Lauritzen. Graphical Models. Oxford University Press, 1996.
[4] D.
Needell and J. Tropp. CoSaMP: Iterative signal recovery from incomplete and
inaccurate samples. Applied and Computational Harmonic Analysis, June 2008.
To appear. [5] C. La and M. N. Do. Tree-based orthogonal matching pursuit al-
gorithm for signal reconstruction. In IEEE Int. Conf. Image Processing (ICIP),

10

pages 1277?1280, Atlanta, GA, Oct. 2006. [6] M. F. Duarte, M. B. Wakin, and
R. G. Baraniuk. Wavelet-domain compressive signal reconstruction using a hid-
den Markov tree model. In ICASSP, pages 5137?5140, Las Vegas, NV, April
2008.
[7] V. Cevher, A. Sankaranarayanan, M. F. Duarte, D. Reddy, R. G.
Baraniuk, and R. Chellappa. Compressive sensing for background subtraction.
In ECCV, Marseille, France, Oct. 2008. [8] R. G. Baraniuk, M. Davenport, R.
A. DeVore, and M. B. Wakin. A simple proof of the restricted isometry property
for random matrices. 2006. To appear in Const. Approx.
[9] T. Blumensath
and M. E. Davies. Sampling theorems for signals from the union of linear sub-
spaces. 2007. Preprint. [10] B. M. McCoy and T. T. Wu. The two-dimensional
Ising model. Harvard Univ. Press, 1973.
[11] M. J. Wainwright, P. Raviku-
mar, and J. D. Laﬀerty. High-dimensional graphical model selection using ?1
-regularized logistic regression. In Proc. of Advances in NIPS, 2006. [12] D. P.
Wipf and B. D. Rao. Sparse bayesian learning for basis selection. IEEE Trans.
Sig. Proc., 52(8):2153?2164, August 2004. [13] J. Pearl. Probabilistic Reason-
ing in Intelligent Systems: Networks of Plausible Inference. Morgan Kaufmann
Publishers, 1988.
[14] V. Kolmogorov and R. Zabin. What energy functions
can be minimized via graph cuts? IEEE Trans. on Pattern Anal. and Mach.
[15] Y. Boykov, O. Veksler, and R. Zabih. Eﬃcient
Int., 26(2):147?159, 2004.
IEEE Trans. on Pattern
approximate energy minimization via graph cuts.
Anal. and Mach. Int., 20(12):1222?1239, Nov. 2001.
[16] Y. Boykov and V.
Kolmogorov. An experimental comparison of min-cut/max-ﬂow algorithms for
energy minimization in vision. IEEE Trans. on Pattern Anal. and Mach. Int.,
26(9):1124?1137, Sept. 2004. [17] E. T. Hale, W Yin, and Y. Zhang. A ﬁxed-
point continuation method for ?1 -regularized minimization with applications to
compressed sensing. Technical Report TR07-07, Rice University, CAM Dept.,
2007.
8

11

