Multi-Level Active Prediction of Useful Image

Annotations for Recognition

Authored by:

Kristen Grauman

Sudheendra Vijayanarasimhan

Abstract

We introduce a framework for actively learning visual categories from
a mixture of weakly and strongly labeled image examples. We propose
to allow the category-learner to strategically choose what annotations it
receives—based on both the expected reduction in uncertainty as well as
the relative costs of obtaining each annotation. We construct a multiple-
instance discriminative classiﬁer based on the initial training data. Then
all remaining unlabeled and weakly labeled examples are surveyed to ac-
tively determine which annotation ought to be requested next. After each
request, the current classiﬁer is incrementally updated. Unlike previous
work, our approach accounts for the fact that the optimal use of manual
annotation may call for a combination of labels at multiple levels of gran-
ularity (e.g., a full segmentation on some images and a present/absent
ﬂag on others). As a result, it is possible to learn more accurate category
models with a lower total expenditure of manual annotation eﬀort.

1 Paper Body

Visual category recognition is a vital thread in computer vision research. The
recognition problem remains challenging because of the wide variation in ap-
pearance a single class typically exhibits, as well as diﬀerences in viewpoint,
illumination, and clutter. Methods are usually most reliable when good train-
ing sets are available, i.e., when labeled image examples are provided for each
class, and where those training examples are adequately representative of the
distribution to be encountered at test time. The extent of an image labeling
can range from a ﬂag telling whether the object of interest is present or absent,
to a full segmentation specifying the object boundary. In practice, accuracy of-
ten improves with larger quantities of training examples and/or more elaborate
annotations. Unfortunately, substantial human eﬀort is required to gather such
training sets, making it unclear how the traditional protocol for visual category
learning can truly scale. Recent work has begun to explore ways to mitigate the

1

burden of supervision [1?8]. While the results are encouraging, existing tech-
niques fail to address two key insights about low-supervision recognition: 1) the
division of labor between the machine learner and the human labelers ought to
respect any cues regarding which annotations would be easy (or hard) for either
party to provide, and 2) to use a ﬁxed amount of manual eﬀort most eﬀectively
may call for a combination of annotations at multiple levels (e.g., a full segmen-
tation on some images and a present/absent ﬂag on others). Humans ought to
be responsible for answering the hardest questions, while pattern recognition
techniques ought to absorb and propagate that information and answer the eas-
ier ones. Meanwhile, the learning algorithm must be able to accommodate the
multiple levels of granularity that may occur in provided image annotations,
and to compute which item at which of those levels appears to be most fruitful
to have labeled next (see Figure 1).

Coarser labels, less expensive
Coarser labels, less expensive
Finer labels, more expensive
Finer labels, more expensive
Fig. 1. Useful image annotations can occur at multiple levels of granularity.
Left: For example, a learner may only know whether the image contains a
particular object or not (top row, dotted boxes denote object is present), or
it may also have segmented foregrounds (middle row), or it may have detailed
outlines of object parts (bottom row). Right: In another scenario, groups of
images for a given class are collected with keyword-based Web search. The
learner may only be given the noisy groups and told that each includes at least
one instance of the speciﬁed class (top), or, for some groups, the individual
example images may be labeled as positive or negative (bottom). We propose
an active learning paradigm that directs manual annotation eﬀort to the most
informative examples and levels.

To address this challenge, we propose a method that actively targets the
learner?s requests for supervision so as to maximize the expected beneﬁt to
the category models. Our method constructs an initial classiﬁer from limited
labeled data, and then considers all remaining unlabeled and weakly labeled ex-
amples to determine what annotation seems most informative to obtain. Since
the varying levels of annotation demand varying degrees of manual eﬀort, our
active selection process weighs the value of the information gain against the cost
of actually obtaining any given annotation. After each request, the current clas-
siﬁer is incrementally updated, and the process repeats. Our approach accounts
for the fact that image annotations can exist at multiple levels of granularity:
both the classiﬁer and active selection objectives are formulated to accommo-
date dual-layer labels. To achieve this duality for the classiﬁer, we express the
problem in the multiple instance learning (MIL) setting [9], where training ex-
amples are speciﬁed as bags of the ﬁner granularity instances, and positive bags
may contain an arbitrary number of negatives. To achieve the duality for the ac-
tive selection, we design a decision-theoretic criterion that balances the variable
costs associated with each type of annotation with the expected gain in infor-
mation. Essentially this allows the learner to automatically predict when the

2

extra eﬀort of a more precise annotation is warranted. The main contribution
of this work is a uniﬁed framework to actively learn categories from a mixture of
weakly and strongly labeled examples. We are the ﬁrst to identify and address
the problem of active visual category learning with multi-level annotations. In
our experiments we demonstrate two applications of the framework for visual
learning (as highlighted in Figure 1). Not only does our active strategy learn
more quickly than a random selection baseline, but for a ﬁxed amount of manual
resources, it yields more accurate models than conventional single-layer active
selection strategies.

2
Related Work
The recognition community is well-aware of the expense of requiring well-
annotated image datasets. Recent methods have shown the possibility of learn-
ing visual patterns from unlabeled [3, 2] image collections, while other techniques
aim to share or re-use knowledge across categories [10, 4]. Several authors have
successfully leveraged the free but noisy images on the Web [5, 6, 11]. Using
weakly labeled images to learn categories was proposed in [1], and several re-
searchers have shown that MIL can accommodate the weak or noisy supervision
often available for image data [11?14]. Working in the other direction, some re-
search seeks to facilitate the manual labor of image annotation, tempting users
with games or nice datasets [7, 8]. However, when faced with a distribution
of unlabeled images, almost all existing methods for visual category learning
are essentially passive, selecting points at random to label. Active learning
strategies introduced in the machine learning literature generally select points
so as to minimize the model entropy or reduce classiﬁcation error (e.g., [15,
16]). Decision-theoretic measures for traditional (single-instance) learning have
been explored in [17, 18], where they were applied to classify synthetic data and
voicemail. Our active selection procedure is in part inspired by this work, as it
also seeks to balance the cost and utility tradeoﬀ. Recent work has con-
sidered active learning with Gaussian Process classiﬁers [19], and relevance
feedback for video annotations [20].
In contrast, we show how to form ac-
tive multiple-instance learners, where constraints or labels must be sought at
multiple levels of granularity. Further, we introduce the notion of predicting
when to ?invest? the labor of more expensive image annotations so as to ul-
timately yield bigger beneﬁts to the classiﬁer. Unlike any previous work, our
method continually guides the annotation process to the appropriate level of
supervision. While an active criterion for instance-level queries is suggested in
[21] and applied within an MI learner, it cannot actively select positive bags
or unlabeled bags, and does not consider the cost of obtaining the labels re-
quested. In contrast, we formulate a general selection function that handles the
full MIL paradigm and adapts according to the label costs. Experiments show
this functionality to be critical for eﬃcient learning from few images.

3
Approach
The goal of this work is to learn to recognize an object or category with
minimal human intervention. The key idea is to actively determine which anno-

3

tations a user should be asked to provide, and in what order. We consider image
collections consisting of a variety of supervisory information: some images are
labeled as containing the category of interest (or not), some have both a class
label and a foreground segmentation, while others have no annotations at all.
We derive an active learning criterion function that predicts how informative
further annotation on any particular unlabeled image or region would be, while
accounting for the variable expense associated with diﬀerent annotation types.
As long as the information expected from further annotations outweighs the cost
of obtaining them, our algorithm will request the next valuable label, re-train
the classiﬁer, and repeat. In the following we outline the MIL paradigm and dis-
cuss its applicability for two important image classiﬁcation scenarios. Then, we
describe our decision-theoretic approach to actively request useful annotations.
Finally, we discuss how to attribute costs and risks for multi-level annotations.
3.1 Multiple-Instance Visual Category Learning Traditional binary supervised
classiﬁcation assumes the learner is provided a collection of labeled data pat-
terns, and must learn a function to predict labels on new instances. However, the
fact that image annotations can exist at multiple levels of granularity demands
a learning algorithm that can encode any known labels at the levels they occur,
and so MIL [9] is more applicable. In MIL, the learner is instead provided with
sets (bags) of patterns rather than individual patterns, and is only told that at
least one member of any positive bag is truly positive, while every member of
any negative bag is guaranteed to be negative. The goal of MIL is to induce the
function that will accurately label individual instances such as the ones within
the training bags. MIL is well-suited for the following two image classiﬁcation
scenarios: ? Training images are labeled as to whether they contain the category
of interest, but they also contain other objects and background clutter. Every
image is represented by a bag of regions, each of which is characterized by its
color, texture, shape, etc. [12, 13]. For positive bags, at least one of the regions
contains the object of interest. The goal is to predict when new image regions
contain the object?that is, to learn to label regions as foreground or background.
? The keyword associated with a category is used to download groups of images
from multiple search engines in multiple languages. Each downloaded group is
a bag, and the images within it are instances [11]. For each positive bag, at
least one image actually contains the object of interest, while many others may
be irrelevant. The goal is to predict the presence or absence of the category in
new images.

In both cases, an instance-level decision is desirable, but bag-level labels
are easier to obtain. While it has been established that MIL is valuable in
such cases, previous methods do not consider how to determine what labels
would be most beneﬁcial to obtain. We integrate our active selection method
with the SVM-based MIL approach given in [22], which uses a Normalized Set
Kernel (NSK) to describe bags based on the average representation of instances
within them. Following [23], we use the NSK mapping for positive bags only; all
instances in a negative bag are treated individually as negative. We chose this
classiﬁer since it performs well in practice [24] and allows incremental updates
[25]; further, by virtue of being a kernel-based algorithm, it gives us ﬂexibility

4

in our choices of features and kernels. However, alternative MIL techniques that
provide probabilitistic outputs could easily be swapped in (e.g. [26, 24, 23]).

3.2 Multi-Level Active Selection of Image Annotations Given the current
MIL classiﬁer, our objective is to select what annotation should be requested
next. Whereas active selection criteria for traditional supervised classiﬁers need
only identify the best instance to label next, in the MIL domain we have a more
complex choice. There are three possible types of request: the system can ask
for a label on an instance, a label on an unlabeled bag, or for a joint labeling
of all instances within a positive bag. So, we must design a selection criterion
that simultaneously determines which type of annotation to request, and for
which example to request it. Adding to the challenge, the selection process
must also account for the variable costs associated with each level of annotation
(e.g., it will take the annotator less time to detect whether the class of interest
is present or not, while a full segmentation will be more expensive). We extend
the value of information (VOI) strategy proposed in [18] to enable active MIL
selection, and derive a generalized value function that can accept both instances
and bags. This allows us to predict the information gain in a joint labeling of
multiple instances at once, and thereby actively choose when it is worthwhile
to expend more or less manual eﬀort in the training process. Our method
continually re-evaluates the expected signiﬁcance of knowing more about any
unlabeled or partially labeled example, as quantiﬁed by the predicted reduction
in misclassiﬁcation risk plus the cost of obtaining the label. We consider a
collection of unlabeled data XU , and labeled data XL composed of a set of
positive bags Xp and a set of negative instances X?n . Recall that positively
labeled bags contain instances whose labels are unknown, since they contain
an unknown mix of positive and negative instances. Let rp denote the user-
speciﬁed risk associated with misclassifying a positive example as negative, and
rn denote the risk of misclassifying a negative. The risk associated with the
labeled data is: X X Risk(XL ) = rp (1 ? p(Xi )) + rn p(xi ), (1) Xi ?Xp

xi ?X?n
where xi denotes an instance and Xi denotes a bag. Here p(x) denotes the
probability that a given input is classiﬁed as positive: p(x) = Pr(sgn(w?(x) +
b) = +1—x) for the SVM hyperplane parameters w and b. We compute these
values using the mapping suggested in [27], which essentially ﬁts a sigmoid to
map the SVM outputs to posterior probabilities. Note that here a positive bag
Xi is ﬁrst transformed according to the NSK before computing its probability.
The corresponding risk for unlabeled data is: X Risk(XU ) = rp (1 ? p(xi ))
Pr(yi = +1—xi ) + rn p(xi )(1 ? Pr(yi = +1—xi )), (2) xi ?XU

where yi is the true label for unlabeled example xi . The value of Pr(y
= +1—x) is not directly computable for unlabeled data; following [18], we
approximate it as Pr(y = +1—x) ? p(x). This P simpliﬁes the risk for the
unlabeled data to: Risk(XU ) = xi ?XU (rp + rn )(1 ? p(xi ))p(xi ), where
again we transform unlabeled bags according to the NSK before computing the
posterior. The total cost T (XL , XU ) associated with the data is the total
misclassiﬁcation risk, plus the cost of obtaining all labeled data thus far: X X
T (XL , XU ) = Risk(XL ) + Risk(XU ) + C(Xi ) + C(xi ), (3) Xi ?Xp

5

xi ?X?n
where the function C(?) returns the cost of obtaining an annotation for its
input, and will be deﬁned in more detail below. To measure the expected utility
of obtaining any particular new annotation, we want to predict the change in
total cost that would result from its addition to XL . Thus, the value of obtaining
an annotation for input z is:

V OI(z) = T (XL , XU ) ? T XL ? z(t) , XU r z (4)
= Risk(XL ) + Risk(XU ) ? Risk XL ? z(t) + Risk (XU r z) ? C(z), where
z(t) denotes that the input z has been merged into the labeled set with its true
label t, and XU r z denotes that it has been removed from the set of unlabeled
data. If the VOI is high for a

given input, then the total cost would be decreased by adding its annota-
tion; similarly, low values indicate minor gains, and negative values indicate
an annotation that costs more to obtain than it is worth. Thus at each iter-
ation, the active learner surveys all remaining unlabeled and weakly labeled
examples, computes their VOI, and requests the label for the example with the
maximal value. However, there are two important remaining technical issues.
First, for this to be useful we must be able to estimate the empirical risk for
inputs before their labels are known. Secondly, for active selection to proceed
at multiple levels, the VOI must act as an overloaded function: we need to be
able to evaluate the VOI when z is an unlabeled instance or an unlabeled bag
or a weakly labeled example, i.e., a positive bag containing an unknown number
of negative instances. To estimate the total risk induced by incorporating a
newly annotated example z into XL before actually obtaining its true label t,
we estimate the updated risk term with its expected value: Risk(XL ? z(t) ) +
Risk(XU r z) ? E[Risk(XL ? z(t) ) + Risk(XU r z)] = E, where E is shorthand
for the expected value expression preceding it. If z is an unlabeled instance,
then computing the expectation is straightforward:

X E= Risk(XL ? z(l) ) + Risk(XU r z) Pr(sgn(w?(z) + b) = l—z), (5) l?L
where L = {+1, ?1} is the set of all possible label assignments for z. The
value Pr(sgn(w?(z) + b) = l—z) is obtained by evaluating the current classiﬁer
on z and mapping the output to the associated posterior, and risk is computed
based on the (temporarily) modiﬁed classiﬁer with z(l) inserted into the labeled
set. Similarly, if z is an unlabeled bag, the label assignment can only be pos-
itive or negative, and we compute the probability of either label via the NSK
mapping. If z is a positive bag containing M = —z— instances, however, there
are 2M possible labelings: L = {+1, ?1}M . For even moderately sized bags,
this makes a direct computation of the expectation impractical. Instead, we use
Gibbs sampling to draw samples of the label assignment from the joint distribu-
tion overnthe M instances? descriptors. Let z = {z1 , . . . , zM } be the positive
bag?s instances, o (a1 ) (aM ) (a) and let z = (z1 ), . . . , (zM ) denote the label
assignment we wish to sample, with aj ? {+1, ?1}. To sample from the con-
ditional distribution of one instance?s label given the rest?the basic procedure
required by Gibbs sampling?we re-train the MIL classiﬁer with the given labels
added, and then draw the remaining label according to aj ? Pr(sgn(w?(zj ) +
b) = +1—zj ), where zj denotes the one instance currently under consideration.

6

For positive bag z, the expected total risk is then the average risk computed
over all S generated samples: S
1 X (a ) (a ) E= Risk({XL r z} ? {z1 1 k , . . . , zMM k }) + Risk(XU r
{z1 , z2 , ..., zM }) , S

(6)
k=1
where k indexes the S samples. To compute the risk on XL for each ﬁxed
sample we simply remove the weakly labeled positive bag z, and insert its in-
stances as labeled positives and negatives, as dictated by the sample?s label
assignment. Computing the VOI values for all unlabeled data, especially for
the positive bags, requires repeatedly solving the classiﬁer objective function
with slightly diﬀerent inputs; to make this manageable we employ incremental
SVM updates [25]. To complete our active selection function, we must deﬁne
the cost function C(z), which maps an input to the amount of eﬀort required to
annotate it. This function is problem-dependent. In the visual categorization
scenarios we have set forth, we deﬁne the cost function in terms of the type of
annotation required for the input z; we charge equal cost to label an instance
or an unlabeled bag, and proportionally greater cost to label all instances in a
positive bag, as determined empirically with labeling experiments with human
users. This reﬂects that outlining an object contour is more expensive than
naming an object, or sorting through an entire page of Web search returns is
more work than labeling just one. We can now actively select which examples
and what type of annotation to request, so as to maximize the expected beneﬁt
to the category model relative to the manual eﬀort expended. After each an-
notation is added and the classiﬁer is revised accordingly, the VOI is evaluated
on the remaining unlabeled and weakly labeled data in order to choose the next
annotation. This process repeats either until the available amount of manual
resources is exhausted, or, alternatively, until the maximum VOI is negative,
indicating further annotations are not worth the eﬀort.

4
Results
In this section we demonstrate our approach to actively learn visual cate-
gories. We test with two distinct publicly available datasets that illustrate the
two learning scenarios above: (1) the SIVAL dataset1 of 25 objects in cluttered
backgrounds, and (2) a Google dataset ([5]) of seven categories downloaded from
the Web. In both, the classiﬁcation task is to say whether each unseen image
contains the object of interest or not. We provide comparisons with single-level
active learning (with both the method of [21], and where the same VOI function
is used but is restricted to actively label only instances), as well as passive learn-
ing. For the passive baseline, we consider random selections from amongst both
single-level and multi-level annotations, in order to verify that our approach
does not simply beneﬁt from having access to more informative possible labels.
2 To determine how much more labeling a positive bag costs relative to labeling
an instance, we performed user studies for both of the scenarios evaluated. For
the ﬁrst scenario, users were shown oversegmented images and had to click on
all the segments belonging to the object of interest. In the second, users were

7

shown a page of downloaded Web images and had to click on only those images
containing the object of interest. For both datasets, their baseline task was to
provide a present/absent ﬂag on the images. For segmentation, obtaining labels
on all positive segments took users on average four times as much time as setting
a ﬂag. For the Web images, it took 6.3 times as long to identify all positives
within bags of 25 noisy images. Thus we set the cost of labeling a positive bag
to 4 and 6.3 for the SIVAL and Google data, respectively. These values agree
with the average sparsity of the two datasets: the Google set contains about
30% true positive images while the SIVAL set contains 10% positive segments
per image. The users who took part in the experiment were untrained but still
produced consistent results. 4.1 Actively Learning Visual Objects and their
Foreground Regions from Cluttered Images The SIVAL dataset [21] contains
1500 images, each labeled with one of 25 class labels. The cluttered images
contain objects in a variety of positions, orientations, locations, and lighting
conditions. The images have been oversegmented into about 30 regions (in-
stances) each, each of which is represented by a 30-d feature describing its color
and texture. Thus each image is a bag containing both positive and negative
instances (segments). Labels on the training data specify whether the object of
interest is present or not, but the segments themselves are unlabeled (though
the dataset does provide ground truth segment labels for evaluation purposes).
The initial training set is comprised of 10 positive and 10 negative images per
class, selected at random. Our active learning method must choose its queries
from among 10 positive bags (complete segmentations), 300 unlabeled instances
(individual segments), and about 150 unlabeled bags (present/absent ﬂag on
the image). We use a quadratic kernel with a coeﬃcient of 10?6 , and average
results over ﬁve random training partitions. Figure 2(a) shows representative
(best and worst) learning curves for our method and the three baselines, all of
which use the same MIL classiﬁer (NSK-SVM). Note that the curves are plot-
ted against the cumulative cost of obtaining labels?as opposed to the number of
queried instances? since our algorithm may choose a sequence of queries with
non-uniform cost. All methods are given a ﬁxed amount of manual eﬀort (40
cost units) and are allowed to make a sequence of choices until that cost is used
up. Recall that a cost of 40 could correspond, for example, to obtaining labels
on 40 40 1 = 40 instances or 4 = 10 positive bags, or some mixture thereof.
Figure 2(b) summarizes the learning curves for all categories, in terms of the av-
erage improvement at a ﬁxed point midway through the active learning phase.
All four methods steadily improve upon the initial classiﬁer, but at diﬀerent
rates with respect to the cost. (All methods fail to do better than chance on the
?dirty glove? class, which we attribute to the lack of distinctive texture or color
on that object.) In general, a steeper learning curve indicates that a method
is learning most eﬀectively from the supplied labels. Our multi-level approach
shows the most signiﬁcant gains at a lower cost, meaning that it is best suited
for building accurate classiﬁers with minimal manual eﬀort on this dataset. As
we would expect, single-level active selections are better than random, but still
fall short of our multi-level approach. This is because single-level active selec-
tion can only make a sequence of greedy choices while our approach can jointly

8

select bags of instances to query. Interestingly, multi- and single-level random
selections perform quite similarly 1 2

http://www.cs.wustl.edu/accio/ See [28] for further implementation details,

image examples, and learning curves on all classes.

96 94 92 90
75 70 65 60
49
Multi?level active Single?level active Multi?level random Single?level ran-

dom

48
Area under ROC
98
Category ? dirtyworkgloves
Multi?level active Single?level active Multi?level random Single?level ran-

dom

80
Area under ROC
100
47 46 45 44 43 42
88 0
10
20
Cost
30
40
55 0
10
20
30
Cost
40
41 0
10
20
30
40
Cost
12 10 8 6 4 2 0 ?2
Multi?level Single?level Multi?level Single?level active active random ran-

dom

(b) Summary: all classes
(a) Example learning curves per class Fig. 2. Results on the SIVAL dataset.
(a) Sample learning curves per class, each averaged over ﬁve trials. First two
are best examples, last is worst. (b) Summary of the average improvement over
all categories after half of the annotation cost is used. For the same amount

9

of annotation cost, our multi-level approach learns more quickly than both tra-
ditional single-level active selection as well as both forms of random selection.
SIVAL dataset 8

Our Approach Random Multi-level Gain over Active Random % 10 +0.0051

+0.0241 372 20 +0.0130 +0.0360 176 50 +0.0274 +0.0495 81

Cost
MI Logistic Regression [21] Random MIU Gain over Active Random% +0.023

+0.050 117 +0.033 +0.070 112 +0.057 +0.087 52

Cumulative number of labels acquired per type
Area under ROC
85
Multi?level active Single?level active Multi?level random Single?level ran-

dom

Improvement in AUROC at cost = 20
Category ? apple
Category ? ajaxorange 102
7 6
unlabeled instances unlabeled bags positive bags (all instances)
5 4 3 2 1 0 0
2
4
6
8
10
Timeline
Fig. 3. Left: Comparison with [21] on the SIVAL data, as measured by the
average improvement in the AUROC over the initial model for increasing label-
ing cost values. Right: The cumulative number of labels acquired for each type
with increasing number of queries. Our method tends to request complete seg-
mentations or image labels early on, followed by queries on unlabeled segments
later on.

on this dataset (see boxplots in (b)), which indicates that having more in-
formative labels alone does not directly lead to better classiﬁers unless the right
instances are queried. The table in Figure 3 compares our results to those
reported in [21], in which the authors train an initial classiﬁer with multiple-
instance logistic regression, and then use the MI Uncertainty (MIU) to actively
choose instances to label. Following [21], we report the average gains in the AU-
ROC over all categories at ﬁxed points on the learning curve, averaging results
over 20 trials and with the same initial training set of 20 positive and nega-
tive images. Since the accuracy of the base classiﬁers used by the two methods
varies, it is diﬃcult to directly compare the gains in the AUROC. The NSKSVM
we use consistently outperforms the logistic regression approach using only the
initial training set; even before active learning our average accuracy is 68.84,
compared to 52.21 in [21]. Therefore, to aid in comparison, we also report the
percentage gain relative to random selection, for both classiﬁers. The results

10

show that our approach yields much stronger relative improvements, again illus-
trating the value of allowing active choices at multiple levels. For both methods,
the percent gains decrease with increasing cost; this makes sense, since even-
tually (for enough manual eﬀort) a passive learner can begin to catch up to
an active learner. 4.2 Actively Learning Visual Categories from Web Images
Next we evaluate the scenario where each positive bag is a collection of images,
among which only a portion are actually positive instances for the class of inter-
est. Bags are formed from the Googledownloaded images provided in [5]. This
set contains on average 600 examples for each of the seven categories. Naturally,
the number of true positives for each class are sparse: on average 30% contain
a ?good? view of the class of interest, 20% are of ?ok? quality (occlusions,
noise, cartoons, etc.), and 50% are ?junk?. Previous methods have shown how
to learn from noisy Web images, with results rivaling state-of-the-art supervised
techniques [11, 5, 6]. We show how to boost accuracy with these types of learn-
ers while leveraging minimal manual annotation eﬀort. To re-use the publicly
available dataset from [5], we randomly group Google images into bags of size
25 to simulate multiple searches as in [11], yielding about 30 bags per category.
We randomly select 10 positive and 10 negative bags (from all other categories)
to serve as the initial training data for each class. The rest of the positive bags
of a class are used to construct the test sets. All results are averaged over ﬁve
random partitions. We represent each image as a bag of ?visual words?, and
compare examples with a linear kernel. Our method makes active queries among
10 positive bags (complete labels) and about 250 unlabeled instances (images).
There are no unlabeled bags in this scenario, since every downloaded batch is
associated with a keyword.

60
55 0
60
55
50
Multi?level active Single?level active Multi?level random Single?level ran-

dom

72 70 68 66 64 62 60
10
20
Cost
30
40
0
10
20
Cost
30
40
0
10

11

20
Cost
30
40
Improvment in AUROC at cost 20
65
Category ? motorbike
Multi?level active Single?level active Multi?level random Single?level ran-

dom

Area under ROC
Area under ROC
Category ? guitar
Multi?level active Single?level active Multi?level random Single?level ran-

dom

Area under ROC
Category ? cars rear 70
12 10 8 6 4 2 0 ?2
Multi?level Single?level Multi?level Single?level random active random ac-

tive

(a) Example learning curves per class (b) Summary: all classes Fig. 4.
Results on the Google dataset, in the same format as Figure 2. Our multi-level
active approach outperforms both random selection strategies and traditional
single-level active selection.

Figure 4 shows the learning curves and a summary of our active learner?s
performance. Our multilevel approach again shows more signiﬁcant gains at a
lower cost relative to all baselines, improving accuracy with as few as ten la-
beled instances. On this dataset, random selection with multi-level annotations
actually outperforms random selection on single-level annotations (see the box-
plots). We attribute this to the distribution of bags/instances: on average more
positive bags were randomly chosen, and each addition led to a larger increase
in the AUROC.

5
Conclusions and Future Work
Our approach addresses a new problem: how to actively choose not only
which instance to label, but also what type of image annotation to acquire in
a cost-eﬀective way. Our method is general enough to accept other types of
annotations or classiﬁers, as long as the cost and risk functions can be appro-
priately deﬁned. Comparisons with passive learning methods and single-level
active learning show that our multi-level method is better-suited for building
classiﬁers with minimal human intervention. In future work, we will consider
look-ahead scenarios with more far-sighted choices. We are also pursuing ways
to alleviate the VOI computation cost, which as implemented involves processing
all unlabeled data prior to making a decision. Finally, we hope to incorporate
our approach within an existing system with many real users, like Labelme [8].

12

2 References

[1] Weber, M., Welling, M., Perona, P.: Unsupervised Learning of Models for
Recognition.
In: ECCV. (2000) [2] Sivic, J., Russell, B., Efros, A., Zisser-
man, A., Freeman, W.: Discovering Object Categories in Image Collections.
In: ICCV. (2005) [3] Quelhas, P., Monay, F., Odobez, J.M., Gatica-Perez, D.,
Tuytelaars, T., VanGool, L.: Modeling Scenes with Local Descriptors and La-
tent Aspects. In: ICCV. (2005) [4] Bart, E., Ullman, S.: Cross-Generalization:
Learning Novel Classes from a Single Example by Feature Replacement.
In:
CVPR. (2005) [5] Fergus, R., Fei-Fei, L., Perona, P., Zisserman, A.: Learning
Object Categories from Google?s Image Search. In: ICCV. (2005) [6] Li, L.,
Wang, G., Fei-Fei, L.: Optimol: Automatic Online Picture Collection via In-
cremental Model Learning.
In: CVPR. (2007) [7] von Ahn, L., Dabbish, L.:
Labeling Images with a Computer Game. In: CHI. (2004) [8] Russell, B., Tor-
ralba, A., Murphy, K., Freeman, W.: Labelme: a Database and Web-Based
Tool for Image Annotation. TR, MIT (2005) [9] Dietterich, T., Lathrop, R.,
Lozano-Perez, T.: Solving the Multiple Instance Problem with Axis-Parallel
Rectangles. Artiﬁcial Intelligence 89 (1997) 31?71 [10] Murphy, K., Torralba,
A., Freeman, W.: Using the Forest to See the Trees:a Graphical Model Re-
lating Features, Objects and Scenes. In: NIPS. (2003) [11] Vijayanarasimhan,
S., Grauman, K.: Keywords to Visual Categories: Multiple-Instance Learning
for Weakly Supervised Object Categorization. In: CVPR. (2008) [12] Maron,
O., Ratan, A.: Multiple-Instance Learning for Natural Scene Classiﬁcation. In:
ICML. (1998) [13] Yang, C., Lozano-Perez, T.: Image Database Retrieval with
Multiple-Instance Learning Techniques. In: ICDE. (2000) [14] Viola, P., Platt,
J., Zhang, C.: Multiple Instance Boosting for Object Detection.
In: NIPS.
(2005) [15] Freund, Y., Seung, H., Shamir, E., Tishby: Selective Sampling Us-
ing the Query by Committee Algorithm. Machine Learning 28 (1997) [16] Tong,
S., Koller, D.: Support Vector Machine Active Learning with Applications to
Text Classiﬁcation.
In: ICML. (2000) [17] Lindenbaum, M., Markovitch, S.,
Rusakov, D.: Selective Sampling for Nearest Neighbor Classiﬁers. Machine
Learning 54 (2004) [18] Kapoor, A., Horvitz, E., Basu, S.: Selective Supervi-
sion: Guiding Supervised Learning with Decision-Theoretic Active Learning.
In: IJCAI. (2007) [19] Kapoor, A., Grauman, K., Urtasun, R., Darrell, T.: Ac-
tive Learning with Gaussian Processes for Object Categorization. In: ICCV.
(2007) [20] Yan, R., Yang, J., Hauptmann, A.: Automatically Labeling Video
Data using Multi-Class Active Learning.
In: ICCV. (2003) [21] Settles, B.,
Craven, M., Ray, S.: Multiple-Instance Active Learning. In: NIPS. (2008) [22]
Gartner, T., Flach, P., Kowalczyk, A., Smola, A.: Multi-Instance Kernels. In:
ICML. (2002) [23] Bunescu, R., Mooney, R.: Multiple Instance Learning for
Sparse Positive Bags. In: ICML. (2007) [24] Ray, S., Craven, M.: Supervised v.
Multiple Instance Learning: An Empirical Comparison. In: ICML. (2005) [25]
Cauwenberghs, G., Poggio, T.: Incremental and Decremental Support Vector
Machine Learning. In: NIPS. (2000) [26] Andrews, S., Tsochantaridis, I., Hof-
mann, T.: Support Vector Machines for Multiple-Instance Learning. In: NIPS.
(2002) [27] Platt, J.: Probabilistic Outputs for Support Vector Machines and

13

Comparisons to Regularized Likelihood Methods. In: Advances in Large Margin
Classiﬁers. MIT Press (1999) [28] Vijayanarasimhan, S., Grauman, K.: Multi-
level Active Prediction of Useful Image Annotations for Recognition. Technical
Report UT-AI-TR-08-2, University of Texas at Austin (2008)

14

