Adaptive Forward-Backward Greedy Algorithm

for Sparse Learning with Linear Models

Authored by:

Tong Zhang

Abstract

Consider linear prediction models where the target function is a sparse
linear combination of a set of basis functions. We are interested in the
problem of identifying those basis functions with non-zero coeﬃcients and
reconstructing the target function from noisy observations. Two heuris-
tics that are widely used in practice are forward and backward greedy
algorithms. First, we show that neither idea is adequate. Second, we
propose a novel combination that is based on the forward greedy algo-
rithm but takes backward steps adaptively whenever beneﬁcial. We prove
strong theoretical results showing that this procedure is eﬀective in learn-
ing sparse representations. Experimental results support our theory.

1 Paper Body

.

.

.

.

, xn ? Rd , with corresponding
Consider a set of input vectors x1 , .
desired output variables y1 , .
, yn . The task of supervised learning
is to estimate the functional relationship y ? f (x) between the input x and
the output variable y from the training examples {(x1 , y1 ), .
, (xn
, yn )}. The quality of prediction is often measured through a loss function
?(f (x), y). In this paper, we consider linear prediction model f (x) = wT x.
As in boosting or kernel methods, nonlinearity can be introduced by including
nonlinear features in x. We are interested in the scenario that d n. That is,
there are many more features than the number of samples.
In this case, an
unconstrained empirical risk minimization is inadequate because the solution
overﬁts the data. The standard remedy for this problem is to impose a constraint
on w to obtain a regularized problem. An important target constraint is sparsity,
which corresponds to the (non-convex) L0 regularization, where we deﬁne kwk0
= —{j : wj 6= 0}— = k. If we know the sparsity parameter k, a good learning
method is L0 regularization: n

.

.

? = arg min w
w?Rd
1X ?(wT xi , yi ) subject to kwk0 ? k. n i=1
(1)

1

If k is not known, then one may regard k as a tuning parameter, which can
be selected through crossvalidation. This method is often referred to as subset
selection in the literature. Sparse learning is an essential topic in machine learn-
ing, which has attracted considerable interests recently. Generally speaking, one
is interested in two closely related themes: feature selection, or identifying the
basis functions with non-zero coeﬃcients; estimation accuracy, or reconstructing
the target function from noisy observations. It can be shown that the solution
of the L0 regularization problem in (1) achieves ? It can also good prediction
accuracy if the target function can be approximated by a sparse w. solve the
feature selection problem under extra identiﬁability assumptions. However, a
fundamental diﬃculty with this method is the computational cost, because the
number of subsets of {1, . . . , d} of cardinality k (corresponding to the nonzero
components of w) is exponential in k. There are no eﬃcient algorithms to solve
the subset selection formulation (1). 1

Due to the computational diﬃcult, in practice, there are three standard
methods for learning sparse representations by solving approximations of (1).
The ﬁrst approach is L1 -regularization (Lasso). The idea is to replace the L0
regularization in (1) by L1 regularization. It is the closest convex approximation
to (1). It is known that L1 regularization often leads to sparse solutions. Its
performance has been theoretically analyzed recently. For example, if the target
is truly sparse, then it was shown in [10] that under some restrictive conditions
referred to as irrepresentable conditions, L1 regularization solves the feature
selection problem. The prediction performance of this method has been consid-
ered in [6, 2, 1, 9]. Despite its popularity, there are several problems with L1
regularization: ﬁrst, the sparsity is not explicitly controlled, and good feature
selection property requires strong assumptions; second, in order to obtain very
sparse solution, one has to use a large regularization parameter that leads to
suboptimal prediction accuracy because the L1 penalty not only shrinks irrele-
vant features to zero, but also shrinks relevant features to zero. A sub-optimal
remedy is to threshold the resulting coeﬃcients; however this requires additional
tuning parameters, making the resulting procedures more complex and less ro-
bust. The second approach to approximately solve the subset selection problem
is forward greedy algorithm, which we will describe in details in Section 2. The
method has been widely used by practitioners. The third approach is backward
greedy algorithm. Although this method is widely used by practitioners, there
isn?t any theoretical analysis when n d (which is the case we are interested in
here). The reason will be discussed later.
In this paper, we are particularly
interested in greedy algorithms because they have been widely used but the
eﬀectiveness has not been well analyzed. As we shall explain later, neither the
standard forward greedy idea nor th standard backward greedy idea is adequate
for our purpose. However, the ﬂaws of these methods can be ﬁxed by a simple
combination of the two ideas. This leads to a novel adaptive forward-backward
greedy algorithm which we present in Section 3. The general idea works for all
loss functions. For least squares loss, we obtain strong theoretical results show-
ing that the method can solve the feature selection problem under moderate
conditions. For clarity, this paper only considers the ﬁxed design formulation.

2

.

.

.

.

To simplify notations in our description, we will replace the optimization prob-
lem in (1) with a more general formulation. Instead of working with n input
data vectors xi ? Rd , we work with d feature vectors fj ? Rn (j = 1, .
,
d), and y ? Rn . Each fj corresponds to the j-th feature component of xi for i
= 1, . . . , n. That is, fj,i = xi,j . Using this notation, we can generally rewrite
(1) with in the ? = arg minw?Rd R(w) subject to kwk0 ? k, where weight w
= [w1 , .
, wd ] ? Rd , form w and R(w) is a real-valued cost function P
which we are interested in optimization. For least squares regression, we have
R(w) = n?1 k j wj fj ? yk22 . In the following, we also let ej ? Rd be the
vector of zeros, except for the j-component which is one. For convenience, we
also introduce the following notations. Deﬁnition 1.1 Deﬁne supp(w) = {j : wj
6= 0} as the set of nonzero coeﬃcients of a vector w = [w1 , . . . , wd ] ? Rd
. For a weight vector w ? Rd , we deﬁne mapping f : Rd ? Rn as: Pd d ? f
(w) = f ) = minw?Rd kf (w) ? j=1 wj fj . Given f ? R and F ? {1, . . . , d},
let w(F, 2 ? ) = w(F, ? f k2 subject to supp(w) ? F , and let w(F y) be the
solution of the least squares problem using features F .

2
Forward and Backward Greedy Algorithms
Forward greedy algorithms have been widely used in applications. The basic
algorithm is presented in Figure 1. Although a number of variations exist, they
all share the basic form of greedily picking an additional feature at every step to
aggressively reduce the cost function. The intention is to make most signiﬁcant
progress at each step in order to achieve sparsity. In this regard, the method
can be considered as an approximation algorithm for solving (1). A major ﬂaw
of this method is that it can never correct mistakes made in earlier steps. As
an illustration, we consider the situation plotted in Figure 2 with least squares
regression. In the ﬁgure, y can be expressed as a linear combination of f1 and f2
but f3 is closer to y. Therefore using the forward greedy algorithm, we will ﬁnd
f3 ﬁrst, then f1 and f2 . At this point, we have already found all good features
as y can be expressed by f1 and f2 , but we are not able to remove f3 selected
in the ﬁrst step. The above argument implies that forward greedy method is
inadequate for feature selection. The method only works when small subsets of
the basis functions {fj } are near orthogonal 2

Input: f1 , . . . , fd , y ? Rn and ¿ 0 Output: F (k) and w(k) let F (0) = ?
and w(0) = 0 for k = 1, 2, . . . let i(k) = arg mini min? R(w(k?1) + ?ei ) let
F (k) = {i(k) } ? F (k?1) ? (k) ) let w(k) = w(F (k?1) if (R(w ) ? R(w(k) ) ?
) break end Figure 1: Forward Greedy Algorithm f1

f5
f4
f3
y
f2
Figure 2: Failure of Forward Greedy Algorithm
[7]. In general, Figure 2 (which is the case we are interested in in this paper)
shows that forward greedy algorithm will make errors that are not corrected later
on. In order to remedy the problem, the so-called backward greedy algorithm

3

has been widely used by practitioners. The idea is to train a full model with
all the features, and greedily remove one feature (with the smallest increase of
cost function) at a time. Although at the ﬁrst sight, backward greedy method
appears to be a reasonable idea that addresses the problem of forward greedy
algorithm, it is computationally very costly because it starts with a full model
with all features. Moreover, there are no theoretical results showing that this
procedure is eﬀective. In fact, under our setting, the method may only work
when d n (see, for example, [3]), which is not the case we are interested in. In the
case d n, during the ﬁrst step, we start with a model with all features, which can
immediately overﬁt the data with perfect prediction. In this case, the method
has no ability to tell which feature is irrelevant and which feature is relevant
because removing any feature still completely overﬁts the data. Therefore the
method will completely fail when d n, which explains why there is no theoretical
result for this method.

3
Adaptive Forward-Backward Greedy Algorithm
The main strength of forward greedy algorithm is that it always works with a
sparse solution explicitly, and thus computationally eﬃcient. Moreover, it does
not signiﬁcantly overﬁt the data due to the explicit sparsity. However, a major
problem is its inability to correct any error made by the algorithm. On the other
hand, backward greedy steps can potentially correct such an error, but need to
start with a good model that does not completely overﬁt the data ? it can only
correct errors with a small amount of overﬁtting. Therefore a combination of
the two can solve the fundamental ﬂaws of both methods. However, a key design
issue is how to implement a backward greedy strategy that is provably eﬀective.
Some heuristics exist in the literature, although without any eﬀectiveness proof.
For example, the standard heuristics, described in [5] and implemented in SAS,
includes another threshold 0 in addition to : a feature is deleted if the cost-
function increase by performing the deletion is no more than 0 . Unfortunately
we cannot provide an eﬀectiveness proof for this heuristics: if the threshold 0 is
too small, then it cannot delete any spurious features introduced in the forward
steps; if it is too large, then one cannot make progress because good features
are also deleted. In practice it can be hard to pick a good 0 , and even the best
choice may be ineﬀective. 3

This paper takes a more principled approach, where we speciﬁcally design
a forward-backward greedy procedure with adaptive backward steps that are
carried out automatically. The procedure has provably good performance and
ﬁxes the drawbacks of forward greedy algorithm illustrated in Figure 2. There
are two main considerations in our approach: we want to take reasonably ag-
gressive backward steps to remove any errors caused by earlier forward steps,
and to avoid maintaining a large number of basis functions; we want to take
backward step adaptively and make sure that any backward greedy step does
not erase the gain made in the forward steps. Our algorithm, which we refer to
as FoBa, is listed in Figure 3. It is designed to balance the above two aspects.
Note that we only take a backward step when the increase of cost function is
no more than half of the decrease of cost function in earlier forward steps. This

4

implies that if we take ‘ forward steps, then no matter how many backward
steps are performed, the cost function is decreased by at least an amount of ‘/2.
It follows that if R(w) ? 0 for all w ? Rd , then the algorithm terminates after
no more than 2R(0)/ steps. This means that the procedure is computationally
eﬃcient. Input: f1 , . . . , fd , y ? Rn and ¿ 0 Output: F (k) and w(k) let F (0)
= ? and w(0) = 0 let k = 0 while true let k = k + 1 // forward step let i(k) =
arg mini min? R(w(k?1) + ?ei ) let F (k) = {i(k) } ? F (k?1) ? (k) ) let w(k)
= w(F (k) let ? = R(w(k?1) ) ? R(w(k) ) if (? (k) ? ) k =k?1 break endif //
backward step (can be performed after each few forward steps) while true (k) let
j (k) = arg minj?F (k) R(w(k) ? wj ej ) (k) let ? 0 = R(w(k) ? wj (k) ej (k) ) ?
R(w(k) ) if (? 0 ¿ 0.5? (k) ) break let k = k ? 1 let F (k) = F (k+1) ? {j (k+1)
} ? (k) ) let w(k) = w(F end end Figure 3: FoBa: Forward-Backward Greedy
Algorithm Now, consider an application of FoBa to the example in Figure 2.
Again, in the ﬁrst three forward steps, we will be able to pick f3 , followed by f1
and f2 . After the third step, since we are able to express y using f1 and f2 only,
by removing f3 in the backward step, we do not increase the cost. Therefore at
this stage, we are able to successfully remove the incorrect basis f3 while keeping
the good features f1 and f2 . This simple illustration demonstrates the eﬀective-
ness of FoBa. In the following, we formally characterize this intuitive example,
and prove the eﬀectiveness of FoBa for feature selection as well as parameter
estimation. Our analysis assumes the least squares loss. However, it is possible
to handle more general loss functions with a more complicated derivation. We
introduce the following deﬁnition, which characterizes how linearly independent
small subsets of {fj } of size k are. For k n, the number ?(k) can be bounded
away from zero even when d n. For example, for random basis functions fj ,
we may take ln d = O(n/k) and still have ?(k) to be bounded away from zero.
This quantity is the smallest eigenvalue of the k ? k diagonal blocks of the d
? d design matrix [ﬁT fj ]i,j=1,...,d , and has appeared in recent analysis of L1
regularization 4

methods such as in [2, 8], etc. We shall refer it to as the sparse eigenvalue
condition. This condition is the least restrictive condition when compared to
other conditions in the literature [1].

.

.

Deﬁnition 3.1 Deﬁne for all 1 ? k ? d: ?(k) = inf n1 kf (w)k22 /kwk22 :
kwk0 ? k . Assumption 3.1 Consider least squares loss R(w) = n1 kf (w(k) ) ?
yk22 . Assume that the basis functions are normalized such that n1 kfj k22 =
, d, and assume that {yi }i=1,...,n are independent (but
1 for all j = 1, .
not necessarily identically distributed) sub-Gaussians: there exists ? ? 0 such 2
2 that ?i and ?t ? R, Eyi et(yi ?Eyi ) ? e? t /2 . Both Gaussian and bounded
random variables are sub-Gaussian using the above deﬁnition. For example, we
have the following Hoeﬀding?s inequality. If a random variable ? ? [a, b], then
2 2 2 2 E? et(??E?) ? e(b?a) t /8 . If a random variable is Gaussian: ? ? N (0, ?
2 ), then E? et? ? e? t /2 . The following theorem is stated with an explicit for
convenience. In applications, one can always run the algorithm with a smaller
and use cross-validation to determine the optimal stopping point. Theorem 3.1
Consider the FoBa algorithm in Figure 3, where Assumption 3.1 holds. Assume
also ? ? Rd such that w ? T xi = Eyi for i = 1, . . . , n, and that the target

5

is sparse: there exists w ? Let k? = —F? —, and ¿ 0 be the stopping criterion
in Figure 3. Let s ? d be an F? = supp(w). ? j —2 ? integer which either
equals d or satisﬁes the condition 8k? ? s?(s)2 . If minj?supp(w) ? —w 64 ?2
, and for some ? ? (0, 1/3), ? 64?(s)?2 ? 2 ln(2d/?)/n, then with probability
25 ?(s) ? 2 ? larger than 1 ? when the algorithm terminates, we have F (k)
= F? and kw(k) ? wk h 3?,p i p ? ? ? k/(n?(k)) 1 + 20 ln(1/?) . ? j are
The result shows that one can identify the correct set of features F? as long
as the weights w not close to zero when j ? F? . This condition is necessary
for all feature selection algorithms including previous analysis of Lasso. The
theorem can be applied as long as eigenvalues of small s ? s diagonal blocks
of the design matrix [ﬁT fj ]i,j=1,...,d are bounded away from zero (i.e., sparse
eigenvalue condition). This is the situation under which the forward greedy step
can make mistakes, but such mistakes can be corrected using FoBa. Because the
conditions of the theorem do not prevent forward steps from making errors, the
example described in Figure 2 indicates that it is not possible to prove a similar
result for the forward greedy algorithm. The result we proved is also better
than that of Lasso, which can successfully select features under irrepresentable
conditions of [10]. It is known that the sparse eigenvalue condition considered
here is generally weaker [8, 1]. p ? j — (j ? F? ) is larger than the noise level O(?
ln d/n) in Our result relies on the assumption that —w order to select features
eﬀectively. If any nonzero weight is below the noise level, then no algorithm
can distinguish it from zero with large probability. That is, in this case, one
cannot reliably perform feature selection due to the noise. Therefore FoBa is
near optimal in term of its ability to perform reliable feature selection, except
for the constant hiding in O(?). For target that is not truly sparse, similar
results can be obtained. In this case, it is not possible to correctly identify all
the features with large probability. However, we can show that FoBa can still
select part of the features reliably, with good parameter estimation accuracy.
Such results can be found in the full version of the paper, available from the
author?s website.

4
Experiments
We compare FoBa described in Section 3) to forward-greedy and L1 -regularization

on artiﬁcial and real data. They show that in practice, FoBa is closer to subset
selection than the other two approaches, in the sense that FoBa achieves smaller
training error given any sparsity level. In oder to compare with Lasso, we use
the LARS [4] package in R, which generates a path of actions for adding and
deleting features, along the L1 solution path. For example, a path of {1, 3, 5,
?3, . . .} means that in the ﬁst three steps, feature 1, 3, 5 are added; and the
next step removes feature 3. Using such a solution path, we can compare Lasso
to Forward-greedy and FoBa under the same framework. Similar to the Lasso
path, FoBa also generates a path with both addition and deletion operations,
while forward-greedy algorithm only adds features without deletion. 5

Our experiments compare the performance of the three algorithms using the
corresponding feature addition/deletion paths. We are interested in features
selected by the three algorithms at any sparsity level k, where k is the desired

6

number of features presented in the ﬁnal solution. Given a path, we can keep an
active feature set by adding or deleting features along the path. For example,
for path {1, 3, 5, ?3}, we have two potential active feature sets of size k = 2:
{1, 3} (after two steps) and {1, 5} (after four steps). We then deﬁne the k
best features as the active feature set of size k with the smallest least squares
error because this is the best approximation to subset selection (along the path
generated by the algorithm). From the above discussion, we do not have to
set explicitly in the FoBa procedure. Instead, we just generate a solution path
which is ﬁve times as long as the maximum desired sparsity k, and then generate
the best k features for any sparsity level using the above described procedure.
4.1

Simulation Data
Since for real data, we do not know the true feature set F? , simulation is
needed to compare feature selection performance. We generate n = 100 data
points of dimension d = 500. The target vector ? is truly sparse with k? = 5
nonzero coeﬃcients generated uniformly from 0 to 10. The noise w level is ? 2 =
0.1. The basis functions fj are randomly generated with moderate correlation:
that is, some basis functions are correlated to the basis functions spanning
the true target. Note that if there is no correlation (i.e., fj are independent
random vectors), then both forward-greedy and L1 -regularization work well
because the basis functions are near orthogonal (this is the well-known case
considered in the compressed sensing literature). Therefore in this experiment,
we generate moderate correlation so that the performance of the three methods
can be diﬀerentiated. Such moderate correlation does not violate the sparse
eigenvalue condition in our analysis, but violates the more restrictive conditions
for forward-greedy method and Lasso.

least squares training error parameter estimation error feature selection error
FoBa 0.093 ? 0.02 0.057 ? 0.2 0.76 ? 0.98
Forward-greedy 0.16 ? 0.089 0.52 ? 0.82 1.8 ? 1.1
L1 0.25 ? 0.14 1.1 ? 1 3.2 ? 0.77
Table 1: Performance comparison on simulation data at sparsity level k =
5 Table 1 shows the performance of the three methods (including two versions
of FoBa), where we repeat the experiments 50 times, and report the average
? standard-deviation. We use the three methods to select ﬁve best features,
using the procedure described above. We report three metrics. Training error
is the squared error of the least squares solution with the selected ﬁve features.
Parameter estimation error is the 2-norm of the estimated parameter (with the
ﬁve features) minus the true parameter. Feature selection error is the number
of incorrectly selected features.
It is clear from the table that for this data,
FoBa achieves signiﬁcantly smaller training error than the other two methods,
which implies that it is closest to subset selection. Moreover, the parameter
estimation performance and feature selection performance are also better. The
two versions of FoBa perform very similarly for this data. 4.2

Real Data
Instead of listing results for many datasets without gaining much insights,
we present a more detailed study on a typical dataset, which reﬂect typical

7

behaviors of the algorithms. Our study shows that FoBa does what it is de-
signed to do well: that is, it gives a better approximation to subset selection
than either forward-greedy or L1 regularization. Moreover, the diﬀerence be-
tween aggressive FoBa and conservative FoBa become more signiﬁcant. In this
study, we use the standard Boston Housing data, which is the housing data
for 506 census tracts of Boston from the 1970 census, available from the UCI
Machine Learning Database Repository: http://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/. Each
census tract is a data-point, with 13 features (we add a constant oﬀset one as
the 14th feature), and the desired output is the housing price. In the experi-
ment, we randomly partition the data into 50 training plus 456 test points. We
perform the experiments 50 times, and for each sparsity level from 1 to 10, we
report the average training and test squared error. The results are plotted in
Figure 4. From the results, we can see that FoBa achieves 6

?
FoBa forward?greedy L1
?
?
50
test error
55
?
45
30
training error
40
60
50
FoBa forward?greedy L1
65
60
? ?
70
better training error for any given sparsity, which is consistent with the
theory and the design goal of FoBa. Moreover, it achieves better test accuracy
with small sparsity level (corresponding to a more sparse solution). With large
sparsity level (corresponding to a less sparse solution), the test error increase
more quickly with FoBa. This is because it searches a larger space by more
aggressively mimic subset selection, which makes it more prone to overﬁtting.
However, at the best sparsity level of 2 or 3 (for aggressive and conservative
FoBa, respectively), FoBa achieves signiﬁcantly better test error. Moreover, we
can observe with small sparsity level (a more sparse solution), L1 regularization
performs poorly, due to the bias caused by using a large L1 -penalty.

? ?
?
?
?

8

40
20
? ?
?
?
?
? ?
2
4
6
8
?
35
?
10
2
sparsity
?
4
?
6
8
10
sparsity
Figure 4: Performance of the algorithms on Boston Housing data Left: av-
erage training squared error versus sparsity; Right: average test squared error
versus sparsity For completeness, we also compare FoBa to the backward-greedy
algorithm and the classical heuristic forward-backward greedy algorithm as im-
plemented in SAS (see its description at the beginning of Section 3). We still
use the Boston Housing data, but plot the results separately, in order to avoid
cluttering. As we have pointed out, there is no theory for the SAS version
of forward-backward greedy algorithm. It is diﬃcult to select an appropriate
backward threshold 0 : a too small value leads to few backward steps, and a
too large value leads to overly aggressive deletion, and the procedure terminates
very early. In this experiment, we pick a value of 10, because it is a reasonably
large quantity that does not lead to an extremely quick termination of the pro-
cedure. The performance of the algorithms are reported in Figure 5. From the
results, we can see that backward greedy algorithm performs reasonably well on
this problem. Note that for this data, d n, which is the scenario that backward
does not start with a completely overﬁtted full model. Still, it is inferior to
FoBa at small sparsity level, which means that some degree of overﬁtting still
occurs. Note that backward-greedy algorithm cannot be applied in our simu-
lation data experiment, because d n which causes immediate overﬁtting. From
the graph, we also see that FoBa is more eﬀective than the SAS implementation
of forward-backward greedy algorithm. The latter does not perform signiﬁcant
better than the forward-greedy algorithm with our choice of 0 . Unfortunately,

9

using a larger backward threshold 0 will lead to an undesirable early termina-
tion of the algorithm. This is why the provably eﬀective adaptive backward
strategies introduced in this paper are superior.

5
Discussion
This paper investigates the problem of learning sparse representations using
greedy algorithms. We showed that neither forward greedy nor backward greedy
algorithms are adequate by themselves. However, through a novel combination
of the two ideas, we showed that an adaptive forward-back greedy algorithm,
referred to as FoBa, can eﬀectively solve the problem under reasonable condi-
tions. FoBa is designed to be a better approximation to subset selection. Under
the sparse eigenvalue condition, we obtained strong performance bounds for
FoBa for feature selection and parameter estimation. In fact, to the author?s
knowledge, in terms of sparsity, the bounds developed for FoBa in this paper
are superior to all earlier results in the literature for other methods. 7
FoBa Forward?Backward (SAS) forward?greedy backward?greedy
50
?
60
40
?
FoBa Forward?Backward (SAS) forward?greedy backward?greedy
?
70
?
?
?
? ?
50
test error
30
training error
?
?
?
?
? ?
?
? ? ? ?
?
?
? ?
?
?
? ?
?

10

?
40
20
? ?
? ?
? ?
? ?
? ?
? ?
2
4
6
8
10
2
sparsity
4
6
8
10
sparsity
Figure 5: Performance of greedy algorithms on Boston Housing data. Left:
average training squared error versus sparsity; Right: average test squared er-
ror versus sparsity Our experiments also showed that FoBa achieves its design
goal: that is, it gives smaller training error than either forward-greedy or L1
regularization for any given level of sparsity. Therefore the experiments are con-
sistent with our theory. In real data, better sparsity helps on some data such as
Boston Housing. However, we shall point out that while FoBa always achieves
better training error for a given sparsity in our experiments on other datasets
(thus it achieves our design goal), L1 regularization some times achieves better
test performance. This is not surprising because sparsity is not always the best
complexity measure for all problems. In particular, the prior knowledge of using
small weights, which is encoded in the L1 regularization formulation but not in
greedy algorithms, can lead to better generalization performance on some data
(when such a prior is appropriate).

2 References

[1] Peter Bickel, Yaacov Ritov, and Alexandre Tsybakov. Simultaneous analysis
of Lasso and Dantzig selector. Annals of Statistics, 2008. to appear.
[2] Flo-
rentina Bunea, Alexandre Tsybakov, and Marten H. Wegkamp. Sparsity oracle
inequalities for the Lasso. Electronic Journal of Statistics, 1:169?194, 2007. [3]
Christophe Couvreur and Yoram Bresler. On the optimality of the backward
greedy algorithm for the subset selection problem. SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl.,
21(3):797?808, 2000.
[4] Bradley Efron, Trevor Hastie, Iain Johnstone, and

11

Info. Theory, 50(10):2231?2242, 2004.

Robert Tibshirani. Least angle regression. Annals of Statistics, 32(2):407?499,
2004. [5] T. Hastie, R. Tibshirani, and J. Friedman. The Elements of Statistical
Learning. Springer, 2001. [6] Vladimir Koltchinskii. Sparsity in penalized em-
pirical risk minimization. Annales de l?Institut Henri Poincar?, 2008. [7] Joel
A. Tropp. Greed is good: Algorithmic results for sparse approximation. IEEE
Trans.
[8] Cun-Hui Zhang and Jian
Huang. Model-selection consistency of the Lasso in high-dimensional linear re-
gression. Technical report, Rutgers University, 2006.
[9] Tong Zhang. Some
sharp performance bounds for least squares regression with L1 regularization.
The Annals of Statistics, 2009. to appear.
[10] Peng Zhao and Bin Yu. On
model selection consistency of Lasso. Journal of Machine Learning Research,
7:2541?2567, 2006.

8

12

