Regularized Distance Metric Learning:Theory

and Algorithm

Authored by:

Rong Jin

Shijun Wang
Yang Zhou

Abstract

In this paper, we examine the generalization error of regularized dis-
tance metric learning. We show that with appropriate constraints, the
generalization error of regularized distance metric learning could be in-
dependent from the dimensionality, making it suitable for handling high
dimensional data. In addition, we present an eﬃcient online learning al-
gorithm for regularized distance metric learning. Our empirical studies
with data classiﬁcation and face recognition show that the proposed al-
gorithm is (i) eﬀective for distance metric learning when compared to the
state-of-the-art methods, and (ii) eﬃcient and robust for high dimensional
data.

1 Paper Body

Distance metric learning is a fundamental problem in machine learning and
pattern recognition. It is critical to many real-world applications, such as in-
formation retrieval, classiﬁcation, and clustering [6, 7]. Numerous algorithms
have been proposed and examined for distance metric learning. They are usu-
ally classiﬁed into two categories: unsupervised metric learning and supervised
metric learning. Unsupervised distance metric learning, or sometimes referred
to as manifold learning, aims to learn a underlying low-dimensional manifold
where the distance between most pairs of data points are preserved. Example
algorithms in this category include ISOMAP [13] and Local Linear Embedding
(LLE) [8]. Supervised metric learning attempts to learn distance metrics from
side information such as labeled instances and pairwise constraints. It searches
for the optimal distance metric that (a) keeps data points of the same classes
close, and (b) keeps data points from diﬀerent classes far apart. Example algo-
rithms in this category include [17, 10, 15, 5, 14, 19, 4, 12, 16]. In this work,
we focus on supervised distance metric learning. Although a large number of
studies were devoted to supervised distance metric learning (see the survey in

1

[18] and references therein), few studies address the generalization error of dis-
tance metric learning. In this paper, we examine the generalization error for
regularized distance metric learning. Following the idea of stability analysis [1],
we show that with appropriate constraints, the generalization error of regular-
ized distance metric learning is independent from the dimensionality of data,
making it suitable for handling high dimensional data. In addition, we present
an online learning algorithm for regularized distance metric learning, and show
its regret bound. Note that although online metric learning was studied in [9],
our approach is advantageous in that (a) it is computationally more eﬃcient
in handling the constraint of SDP cone, and (b) it has a proved regret bound
while [9] only shows a mistake bound for the datasets that can be separated by
a Mahalanobis distance. To verify the eﬃcacy and eﬃciency of the proposed al-
gorithm for regularized distance metric learning, we conduct experiments with
data classiﬁcation and face recognition. Our empirical results show that the
proposed online algorithm is (1) eﬀective for metric learning compared to the
state-of-the-art methods, and (2) robust and eﬃcient for high dimensional data.
1
2 Regularized Distance Metric Learning Let D = {zi = (xi , yi ), i = 1, . .
. , n} denote the labeled examples, where xk = (x1k , . . . , xdk ) ? Rd is a
vector of d dimension and yi ? {1, 2, . . . , m} is class label. In our study, we
assume that the norm of any example is upper bounded by R, i.e., supx —x—2
? R. Let A ? Sd?d be the + distance metric to be learned, where the distance
between two data points x and x? is calculated as —x ? x? —2A = (x ? x?
)? A(x ? x? ). Following the idea of maximum margin classiﬁers, we have the
following framework for regularized distance metric learning: ? ? ?1 ? X

2C min —A—2F + g yi,j 1 ? —xi ? xj —2A : A 0, tr(A) ? ?(d) (1) A ?2 ?

n(n ? 1) i¡j

where
? yi,j is derived from class labels yi and yj , i.e., yi,j = 1 if yi = yj and ?1
otherwise. ? g(z) is the loss function. It outputs a small value when z is a large
positive value, and a large value when z is large negative. We assume g(z) to be
convex and Lipschitz continuous with Lipschitz constant L. ? —A—2F is the
regularizer that measures the complexity of the distance metric A. ? tr(A) ?
?(d) is introduced to ensure a bounded domain for A. As will be revealed later,
this constraint will become active only when the constraint constant ?(d) is
sublinear in d, i.e., ? ? O(dp ) with p ¡ 1. We will also show how this constraint
could aﬀect the generalization error of distance metric learning.

3 Generalization Error Let AD be the distance metric learned by the algo-
rithm in (1) from the training examples D. Let ID (A) denote the empirical loss
, i.e., X

2 ID (A) = g yi,j 1 ? —xi ? xj —2A (2) n(n ? 1) i¡j
For the convenience of presentation, we also write g yi,j (1 ? —xi ? xj —2A
) = V (A, zi , zj ) to highlight its dependence on A and two examples zi and zj
. We denote by I(A) the loss of A over the true distribution, i.e., I(A) = E(zi
,zj ) [V (A, zi , zj )]

(3)

2

Given the empirical loss ID (A) and the loss over the true distribution I(A),

we deﬁne the estimation error as DD

=
I(AD ) ? ID (AD )
(4)
In order to show the behavior of estimation error, we follow the analysis
based on the stability of the algorithm [1]. The uniform stability of an algorithm
determines the stability of the algorithm when one of the training examples is
replaced with another. More speciﬁcally, an algorithm A has uniform stability
? if ?(D, z), ?i, sup —V (AD , u, v) ? V (ADz,i , u, v)— ? ?

(5)
u,v
where Dz,i stands for the new training set that is obtained by replacing
zj ? D with a new example z. We further deﬁne ? = ?/n as the uniform
stability ? behaves like O(1/n). The advantage of using stability analysis for the
generalization error of regularized distance metric learning. This is because the
example pair (zi , zj ) used for training distance metrics are not I.I.D. although
zi is, making it diﬃcult to directly utilize the results from statistical learning
theory. In the analysis below, we ﬁrst show how to derive the generalization
error bound for regularized distance metric learning given the uniform stability
? (or ?). We then derive the uniform stability constant for the regularized
distance metric learning framework in (1). 2

3.1 Generalization Error Bound for Given Uniform Stability Analysis in this
section follows closely [1], and we therefore omit the detailed proofs. Our anal-
ysis utilizes the McDiarmid inequality that is stated as follows. Theorem 1.
(McDiarmid Inequality) Given random variables {vi }li=1 , vi? , and a func-
tion F : v l ? R satisfying ? ? ? sup

? v1 ,...,vl ,vi
? ? ?F (v1 , . . . , vl ) ? F (v1 , . . . , vi?1 , vi , vi+1 , . . . , vl )? ? ci ,
the following statement holds
2?
Pr (—F (v1 , . . . , vl ) ? E(F (v1 , . . . , vl ))— ¿ ?) ? 2 exp ? Pl
2 i=1 ci
!
To use the McDiarmid inequality, we ﬁrst compute E(DD ).
Lemma 1. Given a distance metric learning algorithm A has uniform stability
?/n, we have the following inequality for E(DD ) ? E(DD ) ? 2 (6) n where n
is the number of training examples in D. The result in the following lemma
shows that the condition in McDiarmid inequality holds. Lemma 2. Let D be a
collection of n randomly selected training examples, and Di,z be the collection
of examples that replaces zi in D with example z. We have —DD ? DDi,z —
bounded as follows —DD ? DDi,z — ?

2? + 8L?(d) + 2g0 n
(7)
where g0 = supz,z? —V (0, z, z ? )— measures the largest loss when distance
metric A is 0. Combining the results in Lemma 1 and 2, we can now derive

3

the the bound for the generalization error by using the McDiarmid inequality.
Theorem 2. Let D denote a collection of n randomly selected training examples,
and AD be the distance metric learned by the algorithm in (1) whose uniform
stability is ?/n. With probability 1 ? ?, we have the following bound for I(AD
) r ln(2/?) 2? + (2? + 4L?(d) + 2g0 ) (8) I(AD ) ? ID (AD ) ? n 2n 3.2
Generalization Error for Regularized Distance Metric Learning First, we show
that the superium of tr(AD ) is O(d1/2 ), which veriﬁes that ?(d) should behave
sublinear in d. This is summarized by the following proposition. Proposition 1.
The trace constraint in (1) will be activated only when p ?(d) ? 2dg0 C

(9)
where g0 = supz,z? —V (0, z, z ? )—.
Proof. It follows directly from [tr(AD )/d]2 ? —AD —2F ? 2C sup —V (0,

z, z ?)— ? Cg0 . z,z ?

To bound the uniform stability, we need the following proposition Proposi-
tion 2. For any two distance metrics A and A? , we have the following inequality
hold for any examples zu and zv —V (A, zu , zv ) ? V (A? , zu , zv )— ? 4LR2
—A ? A? —F 3

(10)
The above proposition follows directly from the fact that (a) V (A, z, z ? )
is Lipschitz continuous and (b) —x—2 ? R for any example x. The following
lemma bounds —AD ? AD? —F .

Lemma 3. Let D denote a collection of n randomly selected training exam-
ples, and by z = (x, y) a randomly selected example. Let AD be the distance
metric learned by the algorithm in (1). We have —AD ? ADi,z —F ?

8CLR2 n
(11)
The proof of the above lemma can be found in Appendix A. By putting the
results in Lemma 3 and Proposition 2, we have the following theorem for the
stability of the Frobenius norm based regularizer. Theorem 3. The uniform
stability for the algorithm in (1) using the Frobenius norm regularizer, denoted
by ?, is bounded as follows ?=

? 32CL2 R4 ? n n
(12)
where ? = 32CL2 R4 Combing Theorem 3 and 2, we have the following
theorem for the generalization error of distance metric learning algorithm in
(1) using the Frobenius norm regularizer Theorem 4. Let D be a collection of
n randomly selected examples, and AD be the distance metric learned by the
algorithm in (1) with h(A) = —A—2F . With probability 1 ? ?, we have the
following bound for the true loss function I(AD ) where AD is learned from (1)
using the Frobenius norm regularizer r ln(2/?) 32CL2 R4 2 4 I(AD ) ? ID (AD
) ? + 32CL R + 4Ls(d) + 2g0 (13) n 2n

? where s(d) = min 2dg0 C, ?(d) . Remark? The most important feature in
the estimation error is that it converges in the order of O(s(d)/ n). By choosing
?(d) to have a low dependence of d (i.e., ?(d) ? dp with p ? 1), the proposed
framework for regularized distance metric learning will be robust to the high

4

dimensional data. In the extreme case, by setting ?(d) to be a constant, the
estimation error will be independent from the dimensionality of data.

4 Algorithm In this section, we discuss an eﬃcient algorithm for solving (1).
We assume a hinge loss for g(z), i.e., g(z) = max(0, b ? z), where b is the
classiﬁcation margin. To design an online learning algorithm for regularized
distance metric learning, we follow the theory of gradient based online learning
[2] by deﬁning potential function ?(A) = —A—2F /2. Algorithm 1 shows the
online learning algorithm. The theorem below shows the regret bound for the
online learning algorithm in Figure 1. Theorem 5. Let the online learning
algorithm 1 run with learning rate ? ¿ 0 on a sequence (xt , x?t ), yt , t = 1, . .
. , n. Assume —x—2 ? R for all the training examples. Then, for all distance
d?d metric M ? S+ , we have

1 1 2 bn ? L L (M ) + —M — n F 1 ? 8R4 ?/b 2? where
?n (M ) =
n X t=1
n
X
bn = max 0, b ? yt (1 ? —xt ? x?t —2M ) , L max 0, b ? yt (1 ? —xt ?

x?t —2At?1 ) t=1

4
Algorithm 1 Online Learning Algorithm for Regularized Distance Metric
Learning 1: INPUT: predeﬁned learning rate ? 2: Initialize A0 = 0 3: for t =
1, . . . , T do 4: Receive a pair of training examples {(x1t , yt1 ), (x2t , yt2 )}
5: Compute the class label yt : yt = +1 if yt1 = yt2 , and yt = ?1 otherwise.
6: if the training pair (x1t , x2t ), yt is classiﬁed correctly, i.e., yt 1 ? —x1t
? x2t —2At?1 ¿ 0 then 7: At = At?1 . 8: else 9: At = ?S+ (At?1 ? ?yt (xt ?
x?t )(xt ? x?t )? ), where ?S+ (M ) projects matrix M into the SDP cone. 10:
end if 11: end for

The proof of this theorem can be found in Appendix B. Note that the above
online learning algorithm require computing ?S+ (M ), i.e., projecting matrix
M onto the SDP cone, which is expensive for high dimensional data. To address
this challenge, ﬁrst notice that M ? = ?S+ (M ) is equivalent to the optimization
problem M ? = arg minM ? 0 —M ? ? M —F . We thus approximate At = ?S+
(At?1 ? ?yt (xt ? x?t )(xt ? x?t )? ) with At = At?1 ? ?t yt (xt ? x?t )(xt ?
x?t )? where ?t is computed as follows

?t = arg min —?t ? ?— : ?t ? [0, ?], At?1 ? ?t yt (xt ? x?t )(xt ? x?t )? 0

(14) ?t

The following theorem shows the solution to the above optimization problem.

Theorem 6. The optimal solution ?t to the problem in (14) is expressed as

? yt = ?1 ?t = ? ?1 min ?, [(xt ? x?t )? A?1 (x ? x )] yt = +1 t t?1
t Proof of this theorem can be found in the supplementary materials. Finally,
the quantity (xt ? ?1 x?t )At?1 (xt ? x?t ) can be computed by solving the
following optimization problem max 2u? (xt ? x?t ) ? u? Au u

whose optimal value can be computed eﬃciently using the conjugate gradient
method [11]. Note that compared to the online metric learning algorithm in [9],
the proposed online learning algorithm for metric learning is advantageous in

5

that (i) it is computationally more eﬃcient by avoiding projecting a matrix into
a SDP cone, and (ii) it has a provable regret bound while [9] only presents the
mistake bound for the separable datasets.

5 Experiments We conducted an extensive study to verify both the eﬃciency
and the eﬃcacy of the proposed algorithms for metric learning. For the con-
venience of discussion, we refer to the propoesd online distance metric learning
algorithm as online-reg. To examine the eﬃcacy of the learned distance metric,
we employed the k Nearest Neighbor (k-NN) classiﬁer. Our hypothesis is that
the better the distance metric is, the higher the classiﬁcation accuracy of k-NN
will be. We set k = 3 for k-NN for all the experiments according to our experi-
ence. We compare our algorithm to the following six state-of-the-art algorithms
for distance metric learning as baselines: (1) Euclidean distance metric; (2) Ma-
halanobisP distance metric, which is comn puted as the inverse of covariance
matrix of training samples, i.e., ( i=1 xi xi )?1 ; (3) Xing?s algorithm proposed
in [17]; (4) LMNN, a distance metric learning algorithm based on the large mar-
gin nearest neighbor classiﬁer [15]; (5) ITML, an Information-theoretic metric
learning based on [4]; and (6) Relevance Component Analysis (RCA) [10]. We
set the maximum number of iterations for Xing?s method to be 10, 000. The
number of target neighbors in LMNN and parameter ? in ITML 5

Table 1: Classiﬁcation error (%) of a k-NN (k = 3) classiﬁer on the ten UCI
data sets using seven diﬀerent metrics. Standard deviation is included. Dataset
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9

Eclidean 19.5 ? 2.2 39.9 ? 2.3 36.0 ? 2.0 4.0 ? 1.7 30.6 ? 1.9 25.4 ? 4.2 31.9

? 2.8 18.9 ? 0.5 2.0 ? 0.4

Mahala 18.8 ? 2.5 6.7 ? 0.6 42.1 ? 4.0 10.4 ? 2.7 29.1 ? 2.1 18.4 ? 3.4 10.0

? 2.8 37.3 ? 0.5 6.1 ? 0.5

Xing 29.3 ? 17.2 40.1 ? 2.6 43.5 ? 12.5 3.1 ? 2.0 30.6 ? 1.9 23.3 ? 3.4 24.6

? 7.5 16.1 ? 0.6 12.4 ? 0.8

LMNN 13.8 ? 2.5 3.6 ? 1.1 33.1 ? 0.6 3.9 ? 1.6 29.6 ? 1.8 15.2 ? 3.1 4.5 ?

2.4 18.4 ? 0.4 1.6 ? 0.3

ITML 8.6 ? 1.7 40.0 ? 2.3 39.8 ? 3.3 3.2 ? 1.6 28.8 ? 2.1 17.1 ? 4.1 28.7 ?

3.7 23.3 ? 1.3 2.5 ? 0.4

RCA 17.4 ? 1.5 3.8 ? 0.4 41.6 ? 0.7 2.9 ? 1.5 28.6 ? 2.3 13.9 ? 2.2 1.8 ? 1.5

30.6 ? 0.7 2.8 ? 0.4

Online-reg 13.2 ? 2.2 3.7 ? 1.2 37.3 ? 4.1 3.2 ? 1.3 27.7 ? 1.3 12.9 ? 2.2 1.8

? 1.1 19.8 ? 0.6 2.9 ? 0.4

Table 2: p-values of the Wilcoxon signed-rank test of the 7 methods on
the 9 datasets. Methods Eclidean Mahala Xing LMNN ITML RCA Online-reg
Euclidean 1.000 0.734 0.641 0.004 0.496 0.301 0.129 Mahala 0.734 1.000 0.301
0.008 0.570 0.004 0.004 Xing 0.641 0.301 1.000 0.027 0.359 0.074 0.027 LMNN
0.004 0.008 0.027 1.000 0.129 0.496 0.734 ITML 0.496 0.570 0.359 0.129 1.000
0.820 0.164 RCA 0.301 0.004 0.074 0.496 0.820 1.000 0.074 Online-reg 0.129
0.004 0.027 0.734 0.164 0.074 1.000

were tuned by cross validation over the range from 10?4 to 104 . All the
algorithms are implemented and run using Matlab. All the experiment are run

6

on a AMD Processor 2.8G machine, with 8GMB RAM and Linux operation
system.

5.1 Experiment (I): Comparison to State-of-the-art Algorithms We con-
ducted experiments of data classiﬁcation over the following nine datasets from
UCI repository: (1) balance-scale, with 3 classes, 4 features, and 625 instances;
(2) breast-cancer, with 2 classes, 10 features, and 683 instance; (3) glass, with 6
classes, 9 features, and 214 instances; (4) iris, with 3 classes, 4 features, and 150
instances; (5) pima, with 2 classes, 8 features, and 768 instances; (6) segmenta-
tion, with 7 classes, 19 features, and 210 instances; (7)wine, with 3 classes, 13
features, and 178 instances; (8) waveform, with 3 classes, 21 features, and 5000
instances; (9) optdigits, with 10 classes, 64 features, 3823 instances. For all the
datasets, we randomly select 50% samples for training, and use the remaining
samples for testing. Table 1 shows the classiﬁcation errors of all the metric
learning methods over 9 datasets averaged over 10 runs, together with the stan-
dard deviation. We observe that the proposed metric learning algorithm deliver
performance that comparable to the state-of-the-art methods.
In particular,
for almost all datasets, the classiﬁcation accuracy of the proposed algorithm is
close to that of LMNN, which has yielded overall the best performance among
six baseline algorithms. This is consistent with the results of the other studies,
which show LMNN is among the most eﬀective algorithms for distance metric
learning. To further verify if the proposed method performs statistically bet-
ter than the baseline methods, we conduct statistical test by using Wilcoxon
signed-rank test [3]. The Wilcoxon signed-rank test is a non-parametric statisti-
cal hypothesis test for the comparisons of two related samples. It is known to be
safer than the Student?s t-test because it does not assume normal distributions.
From table 2, we ﬁnd that the regularized distance metric learning improves the
classiﬁcation accuracy signiﬁcantly compared to Mahalanobis distance, Xing?s
method and RCA at signiﬁcant level 0.1. It performs slightly better than ITML
and is comparable to LMNN. 6

att?face
att?face
1
7000 LMNN 6000
Running time (seconds)
Classiﬁcation accuracy
0.9 0.8 0.7 0.6 0.5 Euclidean Mahalanobis LMNN ITML RCA Online reg
0.4 0.3 0.2 0.1 0.1
0.12
0.14
0.16
0.18
ITML RCA
5000
Online reg
4000
3000

7

2000
1000
0 0.1
0.2
Image resize ratio
0.12
0.14
0.16
0.18
0.2
Image resize ratio
(a)
(b)
Figure 1: (a) Face recognition accuracy of kNN and (b) running time of
LMNN, ITML, RCA and online reg algorithms on the ?att-face? dataset with
varying image sizes.

5.2 Experiment (II): Results for High Dimensional Data To evaluate the de-
pendence of the regularized metric learning algorithms on data dimensions, we
tested it by the task of face recognition. The AT&T face database 1 is used
in our study. It consists of grey images of faces from 40 distinct subjects, with
ten pictures for each subject. For every subject, the images were taken at dif-
ferent times, with varied the lighting condition and diﬀerent facial expressions
(open/closed-eyes, smiling/not-smiling) and facial details (glasses/no-glasses).
The original size of each image is 112 ? 92 pixels, with 256 grey levels per pixel.
To examine the sensitivity to data dimensionality, we vary the data dimension
(i.e., the size of images) by compressing the original images into size diﬀerent
sizes with the image aspect ratio preserved. The image compression is achieved
by bicubic interpolation (the output pixel value is a weighted average of pixels
in the nearest 4-by-4 neighborhood). For each subject, we randomly spit its
face images into training set and test set with ratio 4 : 6. A distance metric
is learned from the collection of training face images, and is used by the kNN
classiﬁer (k = 3) to predict the subject ID of the test images. We conduct each
experiment 10 times, and report the classiﬁcation accuracy by averaging over
40 subjects and 10 runs. Figure 1 (a) shows the average classiﬁcation accuracy
of the kNN classiﬁer using diﬀerent distance metric learning algorithms. The
running times of diﬀerent metric learning algorithms for the same dataset is
shown in Figure 1 (b). Note that we exclude Xing?s method in comparison
because its extremely long computational time. We observed that with increas-
ing image size (dimensions), the regularized distance metric learning algorithm
yields stable performance, indicating that the it is resilient to high dimensional
data. In contrast, for almost all the baseline methods except ITML, their per-
formance varied signiﬁcantly as the size of the input image changed. Although
ITML yields stable performance with respect to diﬀerent size of images, its high
computational cost (Figure 1), arising from solving a Bregman optimization
problem in each iteration, makes it unsuitable for high-dimensional data.

8

6 Conclusion In this paper, we analyze the generalization error of regular-
ized distance metric learning. We show that with appropriate constraint, the
regularized distance metric learning could be robust to high dimensional data.
We also present eﬃcient learning algorithms for solving the related optimization
problems. Empirical studies with face recognition and data classiﬁcation show
the proposed approach is (i) robust and eﬃcient for high dimensional data, and
(ii) comparable to the state-of-theart approaches for distance learning. In the
future, we plan to investigate diﬀerent regularizers and their eﬀect for distance
metric learning.

1
http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/research/dtg/attarchive/facedatabase.html
7
ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS The work was supported in part by the National
Science Foundation (IIS-0643494) and the U. S. Army Research Laboratory and
the U. S. Army Research Oﬃce (W911NF-09-1-0421). Any opinions, ﬁndings,
and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the
authors and do not necessarily reﬂect the views of NSF and ARO.

Appendix A: Proof of Lemma 3 Proof. We introduce the Bregmen diver-
gence for the proof of this lemma. Given a convex function of matrix ?(X), the
Bregmen divergence between two matrices A and B is computed as follows:

d? (A, B) = ?(B) ? ?(A) ? tr ??(A)? (B ? A) We deﬁne convex function N

(X) and VD (X) as follows: N (X) = kXk2F ,

VD (X) =
X 2 V (X, zi , zj ) n(n ? 1) i¡j
and furthermore convex function TD (X) = N (X) + CVD (X). We thus
have dN (AD , ADi,z ) + dN (ADi,z , AD ) ? dTD (AD , ADi,z ) + dTDi,z
(ADi,z , AD ) X C = [V (ADi,z , zi , zj ) ? V (ADi,z , z, zj ) + V (AD , z, zj )
? V (AD , zi , zj )] n(n ? 1) j6=i

8CLR2 ? —AD ? ADi,z —F n The ﬁrst inequality follows from the fact
that both N (X) and VD (X) are convex in X. The second step holds because
matrix AD and ADi,z minimize the objective function TD (X) and TDi,z (X),
respectively, and therefore ?

(ADi,z ? AD ) ?TD (AD ) ? 0,
?
(AD ? ADi,z ) ?TDi,z (ADi,z ) ? 0
Since dN (A, B) = kA ? Bk2F , we therefore have —AD ? ADi,z —2F ?
8CLR2 —AD ? ADi,z —F , n
which leads to the result in the lemma.
Appendix B: Proof of Theorem 7 Proof. We denote by A?t = At?1 ? ?y(xt ?
x?t )(xt ? x?t )? and At = ?S+ (A?t ). Following Theorem 11.1 and Theorem
11.4 [2], we have n 1 1X b ? Ln ? Ln (M ) ? D? (M, A0 ) + D?? (At?1 , A?t )
? ? t=1 where

1 1 —A ? B—2F , ?(A) = ?? (A) = —A—2F 2 2 Using the relation A?t =
At?1 ? ?y(xt ? x?t )(xt ? x?t )? and A0 = 0, we have n i 1 X h 1 2 b Ln ? Ln
(M ) ? —M —F + I yt (1 ? —xt ? x?t —2At?1 ) ¡ 0 —xt ? x?t —4 2? 2? t=1
D?? (A, B) =

9

By assuming —x—2 ? R for any training example, we have —xt ? x?t —42
? 16R4 . Since n n h i X X 16R4 16R4 b ? 2 ? 4 I yt (1 ? —xt ? xt —At?1 ) ¡
0 —xt ? xt — ? max(0, b ? yt (1 ? —xt ? x?t —2At?1 )) = Ln b b t=1 t=1
we thus have the result in the theorem

8

2 References

[1] Bousquet, Olivier, and Andr?e Elisseeﬀ. Stability and generalization. Jour-
nal of Machine Learning Research, 2:499?526, March 2002.
[2] Nicolo Cesa-
Bianchi and Gabor Lugosi. Prediction, Learning, and Games. Cambridge
University Press, New York, NY, USA, 2006.
[3] G.W. Corder and D.I. Fore-
man. Nonparametric Statistics for Non-Statisticians: A Step-by-Step Approach.
New Jersey: Wiley, 2009.
[4] J.V. Davis, B. Kulis, P. Jain, S. Sra, and I.S.
Dhillon. Information-theoretic metric learning. In Proceedings of the 24th in-
ternational conference on Machine Learning, 2007.
[5] A. Globerson and S.
In Advances in Neural Infor-
Roweis. Metric learning by collapsing classes.
mation Processing Systems, 2005.
[6] Steven C.H. Hoi, Wei Liu, and Shih-Fu
Chang. Semi-supervised distance metric learning for collaborative image re-
trieval. In Proceedings of IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern
Recognition (CVPR), 2008. [7] Steven C.H. Hoi, Wei Liu, Michael R. Lyu, and
Wei-Ying Ma. Learning distance metrics with contextual constraints for image
retrieval. In Proceedings of IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern
Recognition (CVPR), 2006.
[8] L. K. Saul and S. T. Roweis. Think globally,
ﬁt locally: Unsupervised learning of low dimensional manifolds. Journal of Ma-
chine Learning Research, 4, 2003. [9] Shai Shalev-Shwartz, Yoram Singer, and
Andrew Y. Ng. Online and batch learning of pseudometrics. In Proceedings
of the twenty-ﬁrst international conference on Machine learning, pages 94?101,
2004. [10] N. Shental, T. Hertz, D. Weinshall, and M. Pavel. Adjustment learn-
ing and relevant component analysis. In Proceedings of the Seventh European
Conference on Computer Vision, volume 4, pages 776?792, 2002. [11] Jonathan
R Shewchuk. An introduction to the conjugate gradient method without the
agonizing pain. Technical report, Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA,
USA, 1994. [12] Luo Si, Rong Jin, Steven C. H. Hoi, and Michael R. Lyu. Col-
laborative image retrieval via regularized metric learning. In ACM Multimedia
Systems Journal (MMSJ), 2006.
[13] J.B. Tenenbaum, V. de Silva, and J. C.
Langford. A global geometric framework for nonlinear dimensionality reduction.
Science, 290, 2000. [14] I.W. Tsang, P.M. Cheung, and J.T. Kwok. Kernel rel-
evant component analysis for distance metric learning. In IEEE International
Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN), 2005.
[15] K. Weinberger, J.
Blitzer, and L. Saul. Distance metric learning for large margin nearest neighbor
classiﬁcation.
In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 2005.
[16] Lei Wu, Steven C.H. Hoi, Rong Jin, Jianke Zhu, and Nenghai Yu. Distance
metric learning from uncertain side information with application to automated
photo tagging. In Proceedings of ACM International Conference on Multimedia

10

[17] E.P. Xing, A.Y. Ng, M.I. Jordan, and S. Russell. Distance
(MM), 2009.
In Ad-
metric learning, with application to clustering with side-information.
vances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 2002.
[18] L. Yang and R.
Jin. Distance metric learning: A comprehensive survey. Michigan State Uni-
versity, Tech. Rep., 2006.
[19] L. Yang, R. Jin, R. Sukthankar, and Y. Liu.
An eﬃcient algorithm for local distance metric learning.
In the Proceedings
of the Twenty-First National Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence Proceedings
(AAAI), 2006.

9

11

