Accelerated Gradient Methods for Stochastic

Optimization and Online Learning

Authored by:

James T. Kwok

Chonghai Hu

Weike Pan

Abstract

Regularized risk minimization often involves non-smooth optimization,
either because of the loss function (e.g., hinge loss) or the regularizer (e.g.,
$ell 1$-regularizer). Gradient descent methods, though highly scalable
and easy to implement, are known to converge slowly on these problems.
In this paper, we develop novel accelerated gradient methods for stochas-
tic optimization while still preserving their computational simplicity and
scalability. The proposed algorithm, called SAGE (Stochastic Acceler-
ated GradiEnt), exhibits fast convergence rates on stochastic optimization
with both convex and strongly convex objectives. Experimental results
show that SAGE is faster than recent (sub)gradient methods including
FOLOS, SMIDAS and SCD. Moreover, SAGE can also be extended for
online learning, resulting in a simple but powerful algorithm.

1 Paper Body

Risk minimization is at the heart of many machine learning algorithms. Given
a class of models parameterized by w and a loss function ?(?, ?), the goal is to
minimize EXY [?(w; X, Y )] w.r.t. w, where the expectation is over the joint
distribution of input X and output Y . However, since the joint distribution is
typically unknown in practice, a surrogate problem is to replace the expectation
by its empirical average on a training sample {(x1 , y1 ), . . . , (xm , ym )}.
Moreover, a regularizer ?(?) is often added for well-posedness. This leads to the
minimization of the regularized risk m

min w
1 X ?(w; xi , yi ) + ??(w), m i=1
(1)
where ? is a regularization parameter.

In optimization terminology, the
deterministic optimization problem in (1) can be considered as a sample average
approximation (SAA) of the corresponding stochastic optimization problem:
min EXY [?(w; X, Y )] + ??(w). w

1

(2)
Since both ?(?, ?) and ?(?) are typically convex, (1) is a convex optimiza-
tion problem which can be conveniently solved even with standard oﬀ-the-shelf
optimization packages. However, with the proliferation of data-intensive ap-
plications in the text and web domains, data sets with millions or trillions of
samples are nowadays not uncommon. Hence, oﬀ-the-shelf optimization solvers
are too slow to be used. Indeed, even tailor-made softwares for speciﬁc models,
such as the sequential minimization optimization (SMO) method for the SVM,
have superlinear computational 1

complexities and thus are not feasible for large data sets. In light of this, the
use of stochastic methods have recently drawn a lot of interest and many of these
are highly successful. Most are based on (variants of) the stochastic gradient
descent (SGD). Examples include Pegasos [1], SGD-QN [2], FOLOS [3], and
stochastic coordinate descent (SCD) [4]. The main advantages of these methods
are that they are simple to implement, have low per-iteration complexity, and
can scale up to large data sets. Their runtime is independent of, or even decrease
with, the number of training samples [5, 6]. On the other hand, because of
their simplicity, these methods have a slow convergence rate, and thus may
require a large number of iterations. While standard gradient schemes have a
slow convergence rate, they can often be ?accelerated?. This stems from the
pioneering work of Nesterov in 1983 [7], which is a deterministic algorithm for
smooth optimization. Recently, it is also extended for composite optimization,
where the objective has a smooth component and a non-smooth component
[8, 9]. This is particularly relevant to machine learning since the loss ? and
regularizer ? in (2) may be non-smooth. Examples include loss functions such
as the commonly-used hinge loss used in the SVM, and regularizers such as the
popular ?1 penalty in Lasso [10], and basis pursuit. These accelerated gradient
methods have also been successfully applied in the optimization problems of
multiple kernel learning [11] and trace norm minimization [12]. Very recently,
Lan [13] made an initial attempt to further extend this for stochastic composite
optimization, and obtained the convergence rate of

? O L/N 2 + (M + ?)/ N . (3)
Here, N is the number of iterations performed by the algorithm, L is the
Lipschitz parameter of the gradient of the smooth term in the objective, M is
the Lipschitz parameter of the nonsmooth term, and ? is the variance of the
stochastic subgradient. Moreover, note that the ﬁrst term of (3) is related to
the smooth component in the objective while the second term is related to the
nonsmooth component. Complexity results [14, 13] show that (3) is the optimal
convergence rate for any iterative algorithm solving stochastic (general) convex
composite optimization.

However, as pointed out in [15], a very useful property that can improve the
convergence rates in machine learning optimization problems is strong convexity.
For example, (2) can be strongly convex either because of the strong convexity
of ? (e.g., log loss, square loss) or ? (e.g., ?2 regularization). On the other hand,
[13] is more interested in general convex optimization problems and so strong
convexity is not utilized. Moreover, though theoretically interesting, [13] may

2

be of limited practical use as (1) the stepsize in its update rule depends on the
often unknown ?; and (2) the number of iterations performed by the algorithm
has to be ﬁxed in advance.
Inspired by the successes of Nesterov?s method,
we develop in this paper a novel accelerated subgradient stochastic composite
optimization. It achieves the optimal convergence rate scheme for ?

2 of O L/N + ?/ N for general convex objectives, and O (L + ?)/N 2 +
???1 /N for ?strongly convex objectives. Moreover, its per-iteration complexity
is almost as low as that for standard (sub)gradient? methods. Finally, we also
extend the accelerated gradient scheme to online learning. We obtain O( N
) regret for general convex problems and O(log N ) regret for strongly convex
problems, which are the best regret bounds currently known for these problems.

2
Setting and Mathematical Background
First, we recapitulate a few notions in convex analysis. (Lipschitz continuity)
A function f (x) is L-Lipschitz if kf (x) ? f (y)k ? Lkx ? yk. Lemma 1. [14] The
gradient of a diﬀerentiable function f (x) is Lipschitz continuous with Lipschitz
parameter L if, for any x and y, L (4) f (y) ? f (x) + h?f (x), y ? xi + kx ? yk2 .
2 (Strong convexity) A function ?(x) is ?-strongly convex if ?(y) ? ?(x)+hg(x),
y?xi+ ?2 ky?xk2 for any x, y and subgradient g(x) ? ??(x). Lemma 2. [14] Let
?(x) be ?-strongly convex and x? = arg minx ?(x). Then, for any x, ? ?(x) ?
?(x? ) + kx ? x? k2 . (5) 2 2
with a composite objective function min{?(x) ? E[F (x, ?)] + ?(x)}, (6) x

We consider the following stochastic convex stochastic optimization problem,

where ? is a random vector, f (x) ? E[F (x, ?)] is convex and diﬀerentiable,
and ?(x) is convex but non-smooth. Clearly, this includes the optimization
problem (2). Moreover, we assume that the gradient of f (x) is L-Lipschitz and
?(x) is ?-strongly convex (with ? ? 0). Note that when ?(x) is smooth (?(x) =
0), ? lower bounds the smallest eigenvalue of its Hessian. Recall that in smooth
optimization, the gradient update xt+1 = xt ? ??f (xt ) on a function f (x) can
be seen as proximal regularization of the linearized f at the current iterate xt
[16]. In other 1 words, xt+1 = arg minx (h?f (xt ), x ? xt i + 2? kx ? xt k2
). With the presence of a non-smooth component, we have the following more
general notion. (Gradient mapping) [8] In minimizing f (x) + ?(x), where f is
convex and diﬀerentiable and ? is convex and non-smooth,

1 kx ? xt k2 + ?(x) (7) xt+1 = arg min h?f (x), x ? xt i + x 2?
is called the generalized gradient update, and ? = ?1 (xt ? xt+1 ) is the
(generalized) gradient mapping. Note that the quadratic approximation is made
to the smooth component only. It can be shown that the gradient mapping is
analogous to the gradient in smooth convex optimization [14, 8]. This is also a
common construct used in recent stochastic subgradient methods [3, 17].

3
Accelerated Gradient Method for Stochastic Learning
Let G(xt , ?t ) ? ?x F (x, ?t )—x=xt be the stochastic gradient of F (x, ?t ).
We assume that it is an unbiased estimator of the gradient ?f (x), i.e., E? [G(x,
?)] = ?f (x). Algorithm 1 shows the proposed algorithm, which will be called
SAGE (Stochastic Accelerated GradiEnt).
It involves the updating of three

3

sequences {xt }, {yt } and {zt }. Note that yt is the generalized gradient update,
and xt+1 is a convex combination of yt and zt . The algorithm also maintains
two parameter sequences {?t } and {Lt }. We will see in Section 3.1 that
diﬀerent settings of these parameters lead to diﬀerent convergence rates. Note
that the only expensive step of Algorithm 1 is the computation of the generalized
gradient update yt , which is analogous to the subgradient computation in other
subgradient-based methods. In general, its computational complexity depends
on the structure of ?(x). As will be seen in Section 3.3, this can often be
eﬃciently obtained in many regularized risk minimization problems. Algorithm
1 SAGE (Stochastic Accelerated GradiEnt). Input: Sequences {Lt } and {?t }.
Initialize: y?1 = z?1 = 0, ?0 = ?0 = 1. L0 = L + ?. for t = 0 to N do xt = (1
? ?t )yt?1 + ?t zt?1 .

yt = arg minx hG(xt , ?t ), x ? xt i + L2t kx ? xt k2 + ?(x) . zt = zt?1 ?

(Lt ?t + ?)?1 [Lt (xt ? yt ) + ?(zt?1 ? xt )]. end for Output yN . 3.1

Convergence Analysis
Deﬁne ?t ? G(xt , ?t ) ? ?f (xt ). Because of the unbiasedness of G(xt , ?t
), E?t [?t ] = 0. In the following, we will show that the value of ?(yt ) ? ?(x)
can be related to that of ?(yt?1 ) ? ?(x) for any x. Let ?t ? Lt (xt ? yt ) be the
gradient mapping involved in updating yt . First, we introduce the following
lemma. Lemma 3. For t ? 0, ?(x) is quadratically bounded from below as 2Lt
? L ? k?t k2 . ?(x) ? ?(yt ) + h?t , x ? xt i + kx ? xt k2 + h?t , yt ? xi + 2
2L2t 3

Proposition 1. Assume that for each t ? 0, k?t k? ? ? and Lt ¿ L, then
Lt ?t2 + ??t kx ? zt k2 2 ?2 Lt ?t2 kx ? zt?1 k2 + + ?t h?t , x ? zt?1 i. ?

(1 ? ?t )[?(yt?1 ) ? ?(x)] + 2 2(Lt ? L)

?(yt ) ? ?(x) +
(8)
Proof. Deﬁne Vt (x) = h?t , x ? xt i + ?2 kx ? xt k2 + Lt2?t kx ? zt?1 k2
. It is easy to see that zt = arg minx?Rd Vt (x). Moreover, notice that Vt (x)
is (Lt ?t + ?)-strongly convex. Hence on applying Lemmas 2 and 3, we obtain
that for any x, Lt ?t + ? kx ? zt k2 Vt (zt ) ? Vt (x) ? 2 ? Lt ?t Lt ?t + ? =
h?t , x ? xt i + kx ? xt k2 + kx ? zt?1 k2 ? kx ? zt k2 2 2 2 2Lt ?L Lt ?t Lt
?t +? ? ?(x)??(yt )? k?t k2 + kx?zt?1 k2 ? kx?zt k2 +h?t , x?yt i. 2L2t 2 2
Then, ?(yt ) can be bounded from above, as: Lt ?t 2Lt ? L k?t k2 ? kzt ? zt?1
k2 ?(yt ) ??(x) + h?t , xt ? zt i ? 2 2Lt 2 (9) Lt ?t Lt ?t + ? 2 2 + kx ? zt?1
k ? kx ? zt k + h?t , x ? yt i, 2 2 where the non-positive term ? ?2 kzt ? xt
k2 has been dropped from its right-hand-side. On the other hand, by applying
Lemma 3 with x = yt?1 , we get 2Lt ? L k?t k2 , (10) ?(yt ) ? ?(yt?1 ) ? h?t ,
xt ? yt?1 i + h?t , yt?1 ? yt i ? 2L2t where the non-positive term ? ?2 kyt?1
? xt k2 has also been dropped from the right-hand-side. On multiplying (9) by
?t and (10) by 1 ? ?t , and then adding them together, we obtain

2Lt ? L Lt ?t2 k?t k2 + A + B + C ? kzt ? zt?1 k2 , (11) 2 2Lt 2 where A
= h?t , ?t (xt ? zt ) + (1 ? ?t )(xt ? yt?1 )i, B = ?t h?t , x ? yt i + (1 ? ?t
)h?t , yt?1 ? yt i, L ?2 +?? L ?2 and C = t2 t kx ? zt?1 k2 ? t t2 t kx ? zt
k2 . In the following, we consider to upper bound A and B. First, by using the
update rule of xt in Algorithm 1 and the Young?s inequality1 , we have ?(yt )

4

? ?(x) ? (1 ? ?t )[?(yt?1 ) ? ?(x)] ?

A = h?t , ?t (xt ? zt?1 ) + (1 ? ?t )(xt ? yt?1 )i + ?t h?t , zt?1 ? zt i = ?t

h?t , zt?1 ? zt i ?

Lt ?t2 k?t k2 . kzt ? zt?1 k2 + 2 2Lt
On the other hand, B can be bounded as B = h?t , ?t x + (1 ? ?t )yt?1 ?

xt i + h?t , xt ? yt i = ?t h?t , x ? zt?1 i +

(12) h?t , ?t i Lt
?k?t k , (13) Lt where the second equality is due to the update rule of xt ,
and the last step is from the CauchySchwartz inequality and the boundedness
of ?t . Hence, plugging (12) and (13) into (11), ? ?t h?t , x ? zt?1 i +

(Lt ?L)k?t k2 ?k?t k + + ?t h?t , x?zt?1 i + C 2L2t Lt ?2 ? (1 ? ?t )[?(yt?1

) ? ?(x)] + + ?t h?t , x ? zt?1 i + C, 2(Lt ? L)

?(yt ) ? ?(x) ? (1??t )[?(yt?1 )??(x)]?
where the last step is due to the fact that ?ax2 + bx ? obtain (8). 1
The Young?s inequality states that hx, yi ?
kxk2 2a
+
4
b2 4a
akyk2 2
with a, b ¿ 0. On re-arranging terms, we
for any a ¿ 0.
Let the optimal solution in problem (6) be x? . From the update rules
in Algorithm 1, we observe that the triplet (xt , yt?1 , zt?1 ) depends on the
random process ?[t?1] ? {?0 , . . . , ?t?1 } and hence is also random. Clearly,
zt?1 and x? are independent of ?t . Thus, E?[t] h?t , x? ? zt?1 i

= E?[t?1] E?[t] [h?t , x? ? zt?1 i—?[t?1] ] = E?[t?1] E?t [h?t , x? ? zt?1 i]
= E?[t?1] hx? ? zt?1 , E?t [?t ]i = 0,
where the ﬁrst equality uses Ex [h(x)] = Ey Ex [h(x)—y], and the last
equality is from our assumption that the stochastic gradient G(x, ?) is unbiased.
Taking expectations on both sides of (8) with x = x? , we obtain the following
corollary, which will be useful in proving the subsequent theorems. Corollary
1. Lt ?t2 + ??t E[kx? ? zt k2 ] 2 ?2 Lt ?t2 E[kx? ? zt?1 k2 ] + . ? (1 ? ?t
)(E[?(yt?1 )] ? ?(x? )) + 2 2(Lt ? L)

E[?(yt )] ? ?(x? ) +
So far, the choice of Lt and ?t in Algorithm 1 has been left unspeciﬁed. In the
following, we will show that with a good choice of Lt and ?t , (the expectation
of) ?(yt ) converges rapidly to ?(x? ). Theorem 1. Assume that E[kx? ? zt k2
] ? D2 for some D. Set 3
Lt = b(t + 1) 2 + L,
?t =
2 , t+2
where b ¿ 0 is a constant. Then the expected error of Algorithm 1 can be

bounded as

3D2 L 1 5? 2 ? 2 ? . E[?(yN )] ? ?(x ) ? + 3D b + N2 3b N If ? were

known, we can set b to the optimal choice of ? 2 ?5?D . N

5

?
5? 3D ,
and the bound in (15) becomes
(14)
(15) 3D 2 L N2
+
Note that so far ?(x) is only assumed to be convex. As is shown in the
following theorem, the convergence rate can be further improved by assuming
strong convexity. This also requires another setting of ?t and Lt which is diﬀer-
ent from that in (14). Theorem 2. Assume the same conditions as in Theorem
1, except that ?(x) is ?-strongly convex. Set s ?2 ?t?1 , for t ? 1, (16) Lt = L +
???1 ?t = ?t?1 + t?1 ? t?1 , for t ? 1; 4 2 where ?t ? ?tk=1 (1 ? ?t ) for t ? 1
and ?0 = 1. Then, the expected error of Algorithm 1 can be bounded as 2(L +
?)D2 6? 2 E[?(yN )] ? ?(x? ) ? + . (17) 2 N N? In comparison, FOLOS only
converges as O(log(N )/N ) for strongly convex objectives. 3.2

Remarks
As in recent studies on stochastic composite optimization [13], the error
bounds in (15) and (17) consist of two terms: a faster term which is related to
the smooth component and a slower term related to the non-smooth component.
SAGE beneﬁts from using the structure of the problem and accelerates the
convergence of the smooth component. On the other hand, many stochastic
(sub)gradient-based algorithms like FOLOS do not separate the smooth from
the non-smooth part, but simply treat the whole objective ?as non-smooth.
Consequently, convergence of the smooth component is also slowed down to
O(1/ N ). As can be seen from (15) and (17), the convergence of SAGE is
essentially encumbered by the variance of the stochastic subgradient. Recall
that the variance of the average of p i.i.d. random 5

variables is equal to 1/p of the original variance. Hence, as in Pegasos [1],
? can be reduced by estimating the subgradient from a data subset. Unlike
the AC-SA algorithm in [13], the settings of Lt and ?t in (14) do not require
knowledge of ? and the number of iterations, both of which can be diﬃcult
to estimate in practice. Moreover, with the use of a sparsity-promoting ?(x),
SAGE can produce a sparse solution (as will be experimentally demonstrated
in Section 5) while AC-SA cannot. This is because in SAGE, the output yt is
obtained from a generalized gradient update. With a sparsity-promoting ?(x),
this reduces to a (soft) thresholding step, and thus ensures a sparse solution. On
the other hand, in each iteration of AC-SA, its output is a convex combination
of two other variables. Unfortunately, adding two vectors is unlikely to produce
a sparse vector. 3.3

Eﬃcient Computation of yt
The computational eﬃciency of Algorithm 1 hinges on the eﬃcient compu-
tation of yt . Recall that yt is just the generalized gradient update, and so is not
signiﬁcantly more expensive than the gradient update in traditional algorithms.
Indeed, the generalized gradient update is often a central component in various
optimization and machine learning algorithms. In particular, Duchi and Singer
[3] showed how this can be eﬃciently computed with the various smooth and

6

non-smooth regularizers, including the ?1 , ?2 , ?22 , ?? , Berhu and matrix
norms. Interested readers are referred to [3] for details.

4
Accelerated Gradient Method for Online Learning
In this section, we extend the proposed accelerated gradient scheme for online
learning of (2). The algorithm, shown in Algorithm 2, is similar to the stochastic
version in Algorithm 1. Algorithm 2 SAGE-based Online Learning Algorithm.
Inputs: Sequences {Lt } and {?t }, where Lt ¿ L and 0 ¡ ?t ¡ 1. Initialize: z1 =
y1 . loop xt = (1 ? ?t )yt?1 + ?t zt?1 .

Output yt = arg minx h?ft?1 (xt ), x ? xt i + L2t kx ? xt k2 + ?(x) .
zt = zt?1 ? ?t (Lt + ??t )?1 [Lt (xt ? yt ) + ?(zt?1 ? xt )]. end loop First,
we introduce the following lemma, which plays a similar role as its stochastic
counterpart of Lemma 3. Moreover, let ?t ? Lt (xt ? yt ) be the gradient
mapping related to the updating of yt . Lemma 4. For t ¿ 1, ?t (x) can be
quadratically bounded from below as ?t?1 (x) ? ?t?1 (yt ) + h?t , x ? xt i +

? 2Lt ? L kx ? xt k2 + k?t k2 . 2 2L2t
Proposition 2. For any x and t ? 1, assume that there exists a subgradient
g?(x) ? ??(x) such that k?ft (x) + g?(x)k? ? Q. Then for Algorithm 2, ?t?1
(yt?1 ) ? ?t?1 (x) ?

Q2 Lt Lt + ??t + kx ? zt?1 k2 ? kx ? zt k2 2(1 ? ?t )(Lt ? L) 2?t 2?t (18)

Lt (1 ? ?t2 )Lt ? ?t (1 ? ?t )L 2 2 kyt?1 ? zt?1 k ? kzt ? yt k . + 2 2

Proof Sketch. Deﬁne ?t = Lt ?t?1 . From the update rule of zt , one can
check that ? ?t zt = arg min Vt (x) ? h?t , x ? xt i + kx ? xt k2 + kx ? zt?1
k2 . x 2 2 Similar to the analysis in obtaining (9), we can obtain 2Lt ?L ?t ?t
?t +? ?t?1 (yt )??t?1 (x) ? h?t , xt?zt i? k?t k2? kzt?zt?1 k2+ kx?zt?1 k2?
kx?zt k2 . (19) 2 2Lt 2 2 2 6

On the other hand, h?t , xt ? zt i ?
Lt k?t k2 = (kzt ? xt k2 ? kzt ? yt k2 ) 2Lt 2 Lt (1 ? ?t ) Lt Lt kzt ? zt?1

k2 + kzt?1 ? yt?1 k2 ? kzt ? yt k2 , (20) ? 2?t 2 2

on using the convexity of k ? k2 . Using (20), the inequality (19) becomes

?t?1 (yt ) ? ?t?1 (x) ?

Lt (1 ? ?t ) Lt kzt?1 ? yt?1 k2 ? kzt ? yt k2 2 2 ?t ?t + ? Lt ? L 2 k?t k

+ kx ? zt?1 k2 ? kx ? zt k2 . ? 2 2Lt 2 2

(21)
On the other hand, by the convexity of ?t?1 (x) and the Young?s inequality,
we have ?t?1 (yt?1 ) ? ?t?1 (yt ) ? h?ft?1 (yt?1 ) + g?t?1 (yt?1 ), yt?1 ? yt i ?

Q2 (1 ? ?t )(Lt ? L) + kyt?1 ? yt k2 . 2(1 ? ?t )(Lt ? L) 2
(22)
Moreover, by using the update rule of xt and the convexity of k ? k2 , we

have

kyt?1 ? yt k2 = k(yt?1 ? xt ) + (xt ? yt )k2 = k?t (yt?1 ? zt?1 ) + (xt ?

yt )k2 ? ?t kyt?1 ? zt?1 k2 + (1 ? ?t )?1 kxt ? yt k2 = ?t kyt?1 ? zt?1 k2 +

k?t k2 . (1 ? ?t )L2t
(23)
On using (23), it follows from (22) that ?t?1 (yt?1 ) ? ?t?1 (yt ) ?

7

Q2 ?t (1??t )(Lt ?L) Lt ?L k?t k2 . + kyt?1 ?zt?1 k2 + 2(1??t )(Lt ?L) 2

2L2t

Inequality (18) then follows immediately by adding this to (21). ? Theorem
3. Assume that ? = 0, and kx? ?zt k ? D for t ? 1. Set ?t = a and Lt = aL t
? 1+L, where a ? (0, 1) is a constant. Then the regret of Algorithm 2 can be
bounded as

N X ? Q2 LD2 LD2 ? + + [?t (yt ) ? ?t (x )] ? N. 2a 2 a(1 ? a)L t=1
Theorem 4. Assume that ? ¿ 0, and kx? ? zt k ? D for t ? 1. Set ?t = a,
and Lt = a?t + L + a?1 (? ? L)+ , where a ? (0, 1) is a constant. Then the
regret of Algorithm 2 can be bounded as

N X Q2 (2a + a?1 )? + L D2 + log(N + 1). [?t (yt ) ? ?t (x? )] ? 2a 2a(1

? a)? t=1 In particular, with a = 12 , the regret bound reduces to

5
Experiments
3? 2
+ L D2 +
2Q2 ?
log(N + 1).
In this section, we perform experiments on the stochastic optimization of
(2). Two data sets are used2 (Table 1). The ﬁrst one is the pcmac data set,
which is a subset of the 20-newsgroup data set from [18], while the second one
is the RCV1 data set, which is a ﬁltered collection of the Reuters RCV1 from
[19]. We choose the square loss for ?(?, ?) and the ?1 regularizer for ?(?) in
(2). As discussed in Section 3.3 and [3], the generalized gradient update can be
eﬃciently computed by soft thresholding in this case. Moreover, we do not use
strong convexity and so ? = 0. We compare the proposed SAGE algorithm (with
Lt and ?t in (14)) with three recent algorithms: (1) FOLOS [3]; (2) SMIDAS
[4]; and (3) SCD [4]. For fair comparison, we compare their convergence 2

Downloaded from http://people.cs.uchicago.edu/?vikass/svmlin.html and http://www.cs.ucsb.edu/?wychen/sc.html.
7
behavior w.r.t. both the number of iterations and the number of data access
operations, the latter of which has been advocated in [4] as an implementation-
independent measure of time. Moreover, the eﬃciency tricks for sparse data
described in [4] are also implemented. Following [4], we set the regularization
parameter ? in (2) to 10?6 . The ? parameter in SMIDAS is searched over the
range of {10?6 , 10?5 , 10?4 , 10?3 , 10?2 , 10?1 }, and the one with the lowest
?1 -regularized loss is used. As in Pegasos [1], the (sub)gradient is computed
from small sample subsets. The subset size p is set to min(0.01m, 500), where
m is the data set size. This is used on all the algorithms except SCD, since SCD
is based on coordinate descent and is quite diﬀerent from the other stochastic
subgradient algorithms.3 All the algorithms are trained with the same maximum
amount of ?time? (i.e., number of data access operations). Table 1: Summary
of the data sets. data set pcmac RCV1

#features 7,511 47,236
#instances 1,946 193,844
sparsity 0.73% 0.12%

8

Results are shown in Figure 1. As can be seen, SAGE requires much fewer
iterations for convergence than the others (Figures 1(a) and 1(e)). Moreover,
the additional costs on maintaining xt and zt are small, and the most expensive
step in each SAGE iteration is in computing the generalized gradient update.
Hence, its per-iteration complexity is comparable with the other (sub)gradient
schemes, and its convergence in terms of the number of data access operations
is still the fastest (Figures 1(b), 1(c), 1(f) and 1(g)). Moreover, the sparsity of
the SAGE solution is comparable with those of the other algorithms (Figures
1(d) and 1(h)). 100

0.8 0.6 0.4 0.2 0 0
1000
2000
3000
Number of Iterations
80 SAGE FOLOS SMIDAS SCD
0.6 0.4
40
2
4
6
8
0 0
10
Number of Data Accessesx 106
(a)
SAGE FOLOS SMIDAS SCD
60
20
0.2 0 0
4000
8000
1 0.8
Density of w
SAGE FOLOS SMIDAS
Error (%)
L1 regularized loss
L1 regularized loss
1
2
4
6
8
4000 2000 0 0
10
Number of Data Accessesx 106
(b)

9

SAGE FOLOS SMIDAS SCD
6000
(c)
2
4
6
8
10
Number of Data Accesses x 106
(d)
4
0.6 0.4 0.2 0 0
1000
2000
3000
4000
Number of Iterations
(e)
SAGE FOLOS SMIDAS SCD
0.8 0.6
80
0.4
60 40 20
0.2 0 0
SAGE FOLOS SMIDAS SCD
Density of w
SAGE FOLOS SMIDAS
0.8
4
1
Error (%)
L1 regularized loss
L1 regularized loss
100 1
0.5
1
1.5
2
0 0
2.5
Number of Data Accessesx 108
0.5
1
1.5
2
Number of Data Accesses

10

(f)
(g)
2.5 8 x 10
x 10
3 2
SAGE FOLOS SMIDAS SCD
1 0 0
0.5
1
1.5
2
2.5
Number of Data Accessesx 108
(h)
Figure 1: Performance of the various algorithms on the pcmac (upper) and

RCV1 (below) data sets.

6
Conclusion
In this paper, we developed a novel accelerated gradient method (SAGE)
for stochastic convex composite optimization. It enjoys the computational sim-
plicity and scalability of traditional (sub)gradient methods but are much faster,
both theoretically and empirically. Experimental results show that SAGE out-
performs recent (sub)gradient descent methods. Moreover, SAGE can also be
extended to online learning, obtaining the best regret bounds currently known.
Acknowledgment This research has been partially supported by the Research
Grants Council of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region under grant
615209. 3 For the same reason, an SCD iteration is also very diﬀerent from an
iteration in the other algorithms. Hence, SCD is not shown in the plots on the
regularized loss versus number of iterations.

8

2 References

[1] S. Shalev-Shwartz, Y. Singer, and N. Srebro. Pegasos: Primal estimated
sub-gradient solver for SVM. In Proceedings of the 24th International Confer-
ence on Machine Learning, pages 807?814, Corvalis, Oregon, USA, 2007. [2] A.
Bordes, L. Bottou, and P. Gallinari. SGD-QN: Careful Quasi-Newton Stochas-
tic Gradient Descent. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 10:1737?1754,
[3] J. Duchi and Y. Singer. Online and batch learning using forward
2009.
looking subgradients. Technical report, 2009.
[4] S. Shalev-Shwartz and A.
Tewari. Stochastic methods for ?1 regularized loss minimization. In Proceed-
ings of the 26th International Conference on Machine Learning, pages 929?936,
Montreal, Quebec, Canada, 2009. [5] L. Bottou and O. Bousquet. The tradeoﬀs
of large scale learning. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems
20. 2008.
[6] S. Shalev-Shwartz and N. Srebro. SVM optimization: Inverse

11

dependence on training set size. In Proceedings of the 25th International Con-
ference on Machine Learning, pages 928?935, Helsinki, Finland, 2008.
[7] Y.
Nesterov. A method for unconstrained convex minimization problem with the
rate of convergence o( k12 ). Doklady AN SSSR (translated as Soviet. Math.
Docl.), 269:543?547, 1983.
[8] Y. Nesterov. Gradient methods for minimiz-
ing composite objective function. CORE Discussion Paper 2007/76, Catholic
University of Louvain, September 2007.
[9] A. Beck and M. Teboulle. A fast
iterative shrinkage-thresholding algorithm for linear inverse problems. SIAM
Journal on Imaging Sciences, 2:183?202, 2009.
[10] R. Tibshirani. Regression
shrinkage and selection via the Lasso. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society:
Series B, 58:267?288, 1996.
[11] S. Ji, L. Sun, R. Jin, and J. Ye. Multi-label
multiple kernel learning.
In Advances in Neural Information Processing Sys-
tems 21. 2009. [12] S. Ji and J. Ye. An accelerated gradient method for trace
In Proceedings of the International Conference on Ma-
norm minimization.
chine Learning. Montreal, Canada, 2009.
[13] G. Lan. An optimal method
for stochastic composite optimization. Technical report, School of Industrial
and Systems Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, 2009.
[14] Y. Nes-
terov and I.U.E. Nesterov. Introductory Lectures on Convex Optimization: A
Basic Course. Kluwer, 2003.
[15] S.M. Kakade and S. Shalev-Shwartz. Mind
the duality gap: Logarithmic regret algorithms for online optimization. In Ad-
vances in Neural Information Processing Systems 21. 2009. [16] A. Beck and M.
Teboulle. Mirror descent and nonlinear projected subgradient methods for con-
vex optimization. Operations Research Letters, 31(3):167?175, 2003.
[17] S.J.
Wright, R.D. Nowak, and M.A.T. Figueiredo. Sparse reconstruction by separa-
ble approximation. In Proceedings of the International Conference on Acoustics,
Speech, and Signal Processing, Las Vegas, Nevada, USA, March 2008. [18] V.
Sindhwani and S.S. Keerthi. Large scale semi-supervised linear SVMs. In Pro-
ceedings of the SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information
Retrieval, pages 477?484, Seattle, WA, USA, 2006.
[19] Y. Song, W.Y. Chen,
H. Bai, C.J. Lin, and E.Y. Chang. Parallel spectral clustering. In Proceedings
of the European Conference on Machine Learning, pages 374?389, Antwerp,
Belgium, 2008.

9

12

