Evaluating neuronal codes for inference using

Fisher information

Authored by:

Matthias Bethge

Haefner Ralf

Abstract

Many studies have explored the impact of response variability on the
quality of sensory codes. The source of this variability is almost always
assumed to be intrinsic to the brain. However, when inferring a particu-
lar stimulus property, variability associated with other stimulus attributes
also eﬀectively act as noise. Here we study the impact of such stimulus-
induced response variability for the case of binocular disparity inference.
We characterize the response distribution for the binocular energy model
in response to random dot stereograms and ﬁnd it to be very diﬀerent
from the Poisson-like noise usually assumed. We then compute the Fisher
information with respect to binocular disparity, present in the monocular
inputs to the standard model of early binocular processing, and thereby
obtain an upper bound on how much information a model could theoret-
ically extract from them. Then we analyze the information loss incurred
by the diﬀerent ways of combining those inputs to produce a scalar single-
neuron response. We ﬁnd that in the case of depth inference, monocular
stimulus variability places a greater limit on the extractable information
than intrinsic neuronal noise for typical spike counts. Furthermore, the
largest loss of information is incurred by the standard model for posi-
tion disparity neurons (tuned-excitatory), that are the most ubiquitous in
monkey primary visual cortex, while more information from the inputs is
preserved in phase-disparity neurons (tuned-near or tuned-far) primarily
found in higher cortical regions.

1 Paper Body

Understanding how the brain performs statistical inference is one of the main
problems of theoretical neuroscience. In this paper, we propose to apply the
tools developed to evaluate the information content of neuronal codes corrupted
by noise to address the question of how well they support statistical inference. At
the core of our approach lies the interpretation of neuronal response variability
due to nuisance stimulus variability as noise. Many theoretical and experimental

1

studies have probed the impact of intrinsic response variability on the quality
of sensory codes ([1, 12] and references therein). However, most neurons are
responsive to more than one stimulus attribute. So when trying to infer a
particular stimulus property, the brain needs to be able to ignore the eﬀect of
confounding attributes that also inﬂuence the neuron?s response. We propose
to evaluate the usefulness of a population code for inference over a particular
parameter by treating the neuronal response variability due to nuisance stimulus
attributes as noise equivalent to intrinsic noise (e.g. Poisson spiking). We
explore the implications of this new approach for the model system of stereo
vision where the inference task is to extract depth from binocular images. We
compute the Fisher information present ?

Corresponding author (ralf.haefner@gmail.com)
1
Right image
Left RF Right RF
Tuning curve response
Left image
response
disparity
disparity
Figure 1: Left: Example random dot stereogram (RDS). Right: Illustration

of bincular energy model without (top) and with (bottom) phase disparity.

in the monocular inputs to the standard model of early binocular processing
and thereby obtain an upper bound on how precisely a model could theoretically
extract depth. We compare this with the amount of information that remains
after early visual processing. We distinguish the two principal model ﬂavors that
have been proposed to explain the physiological ﬁndings. We ﬁnd that one of
the two models appears superior to the other one for inferring depth. We start
by giving a brief introduction to the two principal ﬂavors of the binocular energy
model. We then retrace the processing steps and compute the Fisher information
with respect to depth inference that is present: ﬁrst in the monocular inputs,
then after binocular combination, and ﬁnally for the resulting tuning curves.

2
Binocular disparity as a model system
Stereo vision has the advantage of a clear separation between the relevant
stimulus dimension ? binocular disparity ? and the confounding or nuisance
stimulus attributes ? monocular image structure ([9]). The challenge in infer-
ring disparity in image pairs consists in distinguishing true from false matches,
regardless of the monocular structures in the two images. The stimulus that
tests this system in the most general way are random dot stereograms (RDS)
that consist of nearly identical dot patterns in either eye (see Figure 1). The fact
that parts of the images are displaced horizontally with respect to each other
has been shown to be suﬃcient to give rise to a sensation of depth in humans
and monkeys ([5, 4]). Since RDS do not contain any monocular depth cues (e.g.
size or perspective) the brain needs to correctly match the monocular image
features across eyes to compute disparity. The standard model for binocular

2

processing in primary visual cortex (V1) is the binocular energy model ([5, 10]).
It explains the response of disparity-selective V1 neurons by linearly combining
the output of monocular simple cells and passing the sum through a squaring
nonlinearity (illustrated in Figure 1). e2 o2 e o e 2 o 2 reven = (?Le + ?R )
+ (?Lo + ?R ) = ?Le 2 + ?Lo 2 + ?R + ?R + 2(?Le ?R + ?Lo ?R ). (1) e o
where ?L is the output of an even-symmetric receptive ﬁeld (RF) applied to the
left image, ?R is the output of an odd-symmetric receptive ﬁeld (RF) applied
to the right image, etc. By pairing an even and an odd-symmetric RF in each
eye1 , the monocular part of the response of the cell e2 o2 ?Le 2 + ?Lo 2 +
?R + ?R becomes invariant to the monocular phase of a grating stimulus (since
2 2 sin + cos = 1) and the binocular part is modulated only by the diﬀerence
(or disparity) between the phases in left and right grating ? as observed for
complex cells in V1. The disparity tuning curve resulting from the combination
in equation (1) is even-symmetric (illustrated in Figure 1 in blue) and is one of
two primary types of tuning curves found in cortex ([5]). In order to model the
other, odd-symmetric type of tuning curves (Figure 1 in red), the ﬁlter outputs
are combined such that the output of an even-symmetric ﬁlter is always com-
bined with that of an odd-symmetric one in the other eye: o 2 e 2 e2 o2 o e
rodd = (?Le + ?R ) + (?Lo + ?R ) = ?Le 2 + ?Lo 2 + ?R + ?R + 2(?Le ?R
+ ?Lo ?R ). 1

WLOG we assume the quadrature pair to consist of a purely even and a

purely odd RF.

2
(2)
Note that the two models are identical in their monocular inputs and the
monocular part of their output (the ﬁrst four terms in equations 1 and 2) and
only vary in their binocular interaction terms (in brackets). The only way in
which the ﬁrst model can implement preferred disparities other than zero is
by a positional displacement of the RFs in the two eyes with respect to each
other (the disparity tuning curve achieves its maximum when the disparity in
the image matches the disparity between the RFs). The second model, on the
other hand achieves non-zero preferred disparities by employing a phase shift
between the left and right RF (90 deg in our case). It is therefore considered to
be phase-disparity model, while the ﬁrst one is called a position disparity one.2

3
Results
How much information the response of a neuron carries about a particular
stimulus attribute depends both on the sensitivity of the response to changes in
that attribute and to the variability (or uncertainty) in the response across all
stimuli while keeping that attribute ﬁxed. Fisher information is the standard
way to quantify this intuition in the context of intrinsic noise ([6], but also
see [2]) and we will use it to evaluate the binocular energy model mechanisms
with regard to their ability to extract the disparity information contained in the
monocular inputs arriving at the eyes. 3.1

Response variability
response Figure 2 shows the mean of the binocular response of the two

3

models. The variation of the response around the mean due to the variation
in monocular image structure in the RDS is shown in Figure 3 (top row) for
four exemplary disparities: ?1, 0, 1 and uncorrelated (??), indicated in Figure
2. Unlike in the commonly assumed case of intrinsic noise, pbinoc (r—d) ? the
stimulus-conditioned response distribution ? d is far from Poisson or Gaussian.
Interestingly, its mode is always at zero ? the average response to uncorrelated
stimuli ? and the fact that the mean depends on the stimulus disparity is
primarily due to the -1 0 1 disparity-dependence of the skew of the response
distribution (Figure 3).3 The skew in turn depends on the disparity through the
disparity- Figure 2: Binocular redependent correlation between the RF outputs
as illustrated in Figure sponses for even (blue) and 3 (bottom row). Of particular
interest are the response distributions odd (red) model. at the zero disparity 4
, the disparities at which rodd takes its minimum and maximum, respectively,
and the uncorrelated case (inﬁnite disparity). In the case of inﬁnite disparity,
the images in the two eyes are completely independent of each other and hence
the outputs of the left and right RFs are independent Gaussians. Therefore, ?L
?R ? pbinoc (r—d = ?) is symmetric around 0. In the case of zero disparity
(identical images in left and right eye), the correlation is 1 between the outputs
of left and right RFs (both even, or both odd).
It follows that ?L ?R ? ?21
and hence has a mean of 1. What is also apparent is that the binocular energy
model with phase disparity (where each even-symmetric RF is paired with an
odd-symmetric one) never achieves perfect correlation between the left and right
eye and only covers smaller values.

3.2
Fisher information
3.2.1
Fisher information contained in monocular inputs
First, we quantify the information contained in the inputs to the energy
model by using Fisher information. Consider the 4D space spanned by the
outputs of the four RFs in left and right eye: e o (?Le , ?Lo , ?R , ?R ). Since
the ? are drawn from identical Gaussians5 , the mean responses of the 2

We use position disparity model and even-symmetric tuning interchangeably,
as well as phase disparity model and odd-symmetric tuning. Unfortunately, the
term disparity is used for both disparities between the RFs, and for disparities
between left and right images (in the stimulus).
If not indicated otherwise,
we will always refer to stimulus disparity for the rest of the paper. 3 The RF
outputs are Normally distributed in the limit of inﬁnitely many dots (RFs act
as linear ﬁlters + central limit theorem). Therefore the disparity-conditioned
responses p(r—d) correspond to the oﬀ-diagonal terms in a Wishart distribu-
tion, marginalized over all the other matrix elements. 4 WLOG we assume the
displacement between the RF centers in the left and right eye to be zero. 5 The
model RFs have been normalized by their variance, such that var[?] = 1 and ?
? N (0, 1).

3
1
1

4

0
?1
0
1
1
0
?1
0
0
1
1
?1
0
1
0
1
1
1
1
0
0
0
0
?1
?1
?1
?1
?1
0
1
?1
0
1
?1
0
1
?1
0
1
?1
0
1
Figure 3: Response distributions p(r—d) for varying d. Top row: histograms
for values of interaction o e (red). Bottom row: distribution of corresponding
RF outputs ?L vs (blue) and ?Le ?R terms ?Le ?R o e ) colors refer ) and red
(?Le vs ?R ?R . 1? curves are shown to indicate correlations. Blue (?Le vs

5

?R to the model with even-symmetric tuning curve and odd-symmetric tuning
curve, respectively. The disparity value for each column is ??, ?1, 0 and 1
corresponding to those highlighted in Figure 2.

monocular inputs do not depend on the stimulus and hence, the Fisher
information is given by o e ): , ?R I(d) = 12 tr(C ?1 C 0 C ?1 C 0 ) where C is
the covariance matrix belonging to (?Le , ?Lo , ?R ? ? 1 0 a(d) c(d) 1 c(?d) a(d)
? ? 0 C=? a(d) c(?d) 1 0 ? c(d) a(d) 0 1 o o e i as Gabor i and c(d) := h?Le ?R
i = h?Lo ?R where we model the interaction terms a(d) := h?Le ?R functions6
since Gabors functions have been shown to provide a good ﬁt to the range of
RF shapes and disparity tuning curves that are empirically observed in early
sensory cortex ([5]).7 a(d) and c(d) are illustrated by the blue and red curves in
Figure 2, respectively. Because the binocular part of the energy model response,
or disparity tuning curve, is the convolution of the left and right RFs, the phase
of the Gabor describing the disparity tuning curve is given by the diﬀerence
between the phases of the corresponding RFs. Therefore c(d) is odd-symmetric
and c(?d) = ?c(d). We obtain

Iinputs (d) =
2 (1 ?
a2
?
c2 ) 2
(1 + a2 ? c2 )a02 + (1 + c2 ? a2 )c02 + 4aca0 c0
(3)
where we omitted the stimulus dependence of a(d) and c(d) for clarity of
exposition and where 0 denotes the 1st derivative with respect to the stimulus
d. The denominator of equation (3)) is given by det C and corresponds to the
Gaussian envelope of the Gabor functions for a(d) and c(d): det C = 1 ? a2 ?
c2 = 1 ? exp(?

s2 ). ?2
In Figure 4B (black) we plot the Fisher information as a function of disparity.
We ﬁnd that the Fisher information available in the inputs diverges at zero
disparity (at the diﬀerence between the centers of the left and right RFs in
general). This means that the ability to discriminate zero disparity from 2

0) A Gabor function is deﬁned as cos(2?f d ? ?) exp[? (d?d ] were f is spatial
frequency, d is disparity, 2? 2 ? is the Gabor phase, do is the envelope center (set
to zero here, WLOG) and ? the envelope bandwidth. 7 The assumption that
the binocular interaction can be modeled by a Gabor is not important for the
principal results of this paper. In fact, the formulas for the Fisher information
in the monocular inputs and in the disparity tuning curves derived below hold
for other (reasonable) choices for a(d) and c(d) as well.

6
4
2
B
A
1.5 1

6

C
100
100
50
50
0.4 0.3 0.2
0.5 0 ?4
D
0.1 ?2
0
2
disparity d
4
0 ?4
?2
0
2
0 ?4
4
disparity d
?2
0
2
disparity d
4
0 ?4
?2
0
2
disparity d
4
Figure 4: A: Disparity tuning curves for the model using position disparity
(even) and phase disparity (odd) in blue and red, respectively. B: Black: Fisher
information contained in the monocular inputs. Blue: Fisher information left
after combining inputs from left and right eye according to position disparity
model. Red: Fisher information after combining inputs using phase disparity
model. Note that the black and red curves diverge at zero disparity. C: Fisher
information for the ﬁnal model output/neuronal response. Same color code as
previously. Solid lines correspond to complex, dashed lines to simple cells. D:
Same as C but with added Gaussian noise in the monocular inputs.

nearby disparities is arbitrarily good. In reality, intrinsic neuronal variability

will limit the Fisher information at zero.8 3.2.2

Combination of left and right inputs
Next we analyze the information that remains after linearly combining the
monocular inputs in the energy model. It follows that the 4-dimensional monoc-
ular input space is reduced to a 2-dimensional e o o e ), respectively. , ?Lo + ?R

7

) and (?Le + ?R , ?Lo + ?R binocular one for each model, sampled by (?Le +
?R Again, the marginal distributions are Gaussians with zero mean independent
of stimulus disparity. This means that we can compute the Fisher information
for the position disparity model from the covariance matrix C as above:

e 2 e o h(?Le + ?R ) i h(?Le + ?R )(?Lo + ?R )i Ceven = o 2 o e ) i )i h(?Lo

+ ?R )(?Lo + ?R h(?Le + ?R

2 + 2a 0 = 0 2 + 2a e o Here we exploited that h?Le ?Lo i = h?R ?R i = 0
since the even and odd RFs are orthogonal and that e o o e h?L ?R i = ?h?R
?L i. The Fisher information follows as

Ieven (d) =
a0 (d)2 . [1 + a(d)]2
(4)
The dependence of Fisher information on d is shown in Figure 4B (blue).
The total information (as measured by integrating Fisher information over all
disparities) communicated by the positiondisparity model is greatly reduced
compared to the total Fisher information present in the inputs. a(d) is an even-
symmetric Gabor (illustrated in Figure 2) and hence the Fisher information is
greatest on either side of the maximum where the slopes of a(d) are steepest,
and zero at the center where a(d) has its peak. We note here that the Fisher
information for the ﬁnal tuning curve for the position-disparity model is the
same as in equation (4) and therefore we will postpone a more detailed discussion
of it until section 3.2.3. 2

E.g. additive Gaussian noise with variance ? N on the monocular ﬁlter

outputs eliminates the singularity: 2 2 det C = 1 + ? N ? a2 ? c2 ? ? N . 8

5
On the other hand, when combining the monocular inputs according to the

phase disparity model, we ﬁnd:

o 2 o e h(?Le + ?R ) i h(?Le + ?R )(?Lo + ?R )i Codd = o e e 2 h(?Le +

?R )(?Lo + ?R )i h(?Lo + ?R ) i

2 + 2c 2a = 2a 2 ? 2c e o o o e since again h?Le ?Lo i = h?R ?R i = 0 and

h?Le ?R i = ?h?R ?L i = c. The Fisher information in this case follows as

1 Iodd (d) = (1 + a2 ? c2 )a02 + (1 + c2 ? a2 )c02 + 4aca0 c0 (1 ? a2
? c2 )2 1 = Iinputs (d) 2 Iodd (d) is shown in Figure 4B (red). While loosing
50% of the Fisher information present in the inputs, the Fisher information
after combining left and right RF outputs is much larger in this case than for
the position disparity model explored above. How can that be? Why are the
two ways of combining the monocular outputs not symmetric? Insight into this
question can be gained by looking at the binocular interaction terms in the
quadratic expansion of the feature space for the two models.9 e o o e For the
position disparity model we obtain the 3-dimensional space (?Le ?R , ?Lo ?R ,
?Le ?R + ?Lo ?R ) of o e which the third dimension cannot contribute to the
Fisher information since ?Le ?R + ?Lo ?R = 0. In o e e o the phase-disparity
model, however, the quadratic expansion yields (?Le ?R , ?Lo ?R , ?Le ?R + ?Lo
?R ). Here, all three dimensions are linearly independent (although correlated),
each contributing to the Fisher information. This can also explain why Iodd
(d) is symmetric around zero, and independent of the Gabor phase of c(d).

8

While this is not a rigorous analysis yet of the diﬀerences between the models
at the stage of binocular combination, it serves as a starting point for a future
investigation.

3.2.3
Disparity tuning curves
In order to collapse the 2-dimensional binocular inputs into a scalar output
that can be coded in the spike rate of a neuron, the energy model postulates
a squaring output nonlinearity after each linear combination and summing the
results. Since the (?L + ?R )2 are not Normally distributed and their means
depend on the stimulus disparity, we cannot employ the above approach to
calculate Fisher information but instead use the more general ” 2 # Z ?

2 ? ? ln p(r; d) = p(r; d) ln p(r; d) dr (5) I(d) = E ?d ?d 0 where p(r; d)
is the response distribution for stimulus disparity d. Because the ? are drawn
from a o e are drawn from N [0, 2(1 + a(d))] since we deﬁned and ?Lo + ?R
Gaussian with variance 1, ?Le + ?R e 2 o 2 o o e e ) are independent and it
) and (?Lo + ?R a(d) = h?L ?R i = h?L ?R i. Conditioned on d, (?Le + ?R
follows for the model with an even-symmetric tuning function that e

1 e 2 o 2 (?L + ?R ) + (?Lo + ?R ) ? ?22 and 2[1 + a(d)]
1 r H(r) (6) peven (r; d) = exp ? 4[1 + a(d)] 4[1 + a(d)] where H(r) is the
Heaviside step function.10 Substituting equation (6) into equation (5) we ﬁnd11

2
Z ? a0 (d)2 r r complex Ieven (d) = ? 1 exp ? dr 4[1 + a(d)]3 0 4[1 + a(d)]

4[1 + a(d)] 0 2 a (d) = (7) [1 + a(d)]2 9

By quadratic expansion of the feature space we refer to expanding a 2-
dimensional feature space (f1 , f2 ) to a 3-dimensional one (f12 , f22 , f1 f2 ) by
considering the binocular interaction terms in all quadratic forms. 10 We see
that hripeven (r;d) = 4[1 + a(d)] and hence we recover the Gabor-shaped tuning
function that we introduced in section 3.2.1 to model the empirically observed
relationship between disparity d and mean spike rate r. R 11 ? dx (x/? ? 1)2
exp(?x/?) = ? for ? ¿ 0. 0

6
Remarkably, this is exactly the same amount of information that is available
after summing left and right RFs (see equation 4), so none is lost after squaring
and combining the quadrature pair. We show Ieven (d) in Figure 4C (blue). It is
also interesting to note that the general form for Ieven (d) diﬀers from the Fisher
information based on the Poisson noise model (and ignoring stimulus variability
as considered here) only by the exponent of 2 in the denominator. Since 1 +
a(d) ? 0 this means that the qualitative dependence of I on d is the same, the
main diﬀerence being that the Fisher information favors small over large spike
rates even more. Conversely, it follows that when Fisher information only takes
the neuronal noise into consideration, it greatly overestimates the information
that the neuron carries with respect to the to-be-inferred stimulus parameter for
realistic spike counts (of greater than two). Furthermore, unlike in the Poisson
case, a scaling up of the tuning function 1 + a(d) does not translate into greater
Fisher information. Fisher information with respect to stimulus variability as
considered here is invariant to the absolute height of the tuning curve.12 o 2

9

e 2 Considering the phase-disparity model, (?Le +?R ) and (?Lo +?R ) are
drawn from N [0, 2(1+c(d))] e o e o and N [0, 2(1 + c(d))], respectively, since
c(d) = h?L ?R i = ?h?Lo ?R i. Unfortunately, since ?Le + ?R o e and ?L +
?R have diﬀerent variances depending on d, and are usually not independent
of each other, the sum cannot be modeled by a ?2 ?distribution. However, we
can compute the Fisher information for the two implied binocular simple cells
instead.13 It follows that e

1 o 2 (?L + ?R ) ? ?21 and 2[1 + c(d)] psimple odd (r; d)
=
1 r 1 p ? exp ? H(r). 4[1 + c(d)] 2?(1/2) 1 + c(d) r
and14 simple Iodd (d)
=
1 c0 (d)2 p 2?(1/2) 1 + c(d)5 0
=
Z 0
?
2
1 r r 1 ? exp ? dr ? 4[1 + c(d)] r 4[1 + c(d)] 2
2
1 c (d) 2 [1 + c(d)]2
simple The dependence of Iodd on disparity is shown in Figure 4C (red
dashed). Most of the Fisher information is located in the primary slope (com-
pare Figure 4A) followed by secondary slope to its left. The reason for this is
the strong boost Fisher information gets when responses are lowest. We also
see that the total Fisher information carried by a phase-disparity simple cell is
signiﬁcantly higher than that carried by a position-disparity simple cell (com-
pare dashed red and blue lines) raising the question of what other advantages
or trade-oﬀs there are that make it beneﬁcial for the primate brain to employ so
many position-disparity ones. Intrinsic neuronal variability may provide part of
the answer since the diﬀerence in Fisher information between both models de-
creases as intrinsic variability increases. Figure 4D shows the Fisher information
after Gaussian noise has been added to the monocular inputs. However, even
in this high intrinsic noise regime (noise variance of the same order as tuning
curve amplitude) the model with phase disparity carries signiﬁcantly more total
Fisher information. 15

12
What is outside of the scope of this paper but obvious from equation (7)
is that Fisher information is maximized when the denominator, or the tuning
function is minimal. Within the context of the energy model, this occurs for
neither the position-disparity model, nor the classic phase-disparity one, but for
a model where the left and right RFs that are linearly combined, are inverted
with respect to each other (i.e. phase-shifted by ?). In that case a(d) is a Gabor
function with phase ? and becomes zero at zero disparity such that the Fisher
information diverges. Such neurons, called tuned-inhibitory (TI, [11]) make up
a small minority of neurons in monkey V1. 13 The energy model as presented
thus far models the responses of binocular complex cells. Disparityo 2 selective

10

simple cells are typically modeled by just one combination of left and right RFs
(?Le + ?R ) or e 2 (?Lo + ? ) , and not the entire quadrature pair. R R ?
? ? ?1 14 ? dx x (x/? ? 1/2)2 exp(?x/?) = ? ?/2 for ? ¿ 0. 0 15 This
derivation equally applies to the Fisher information of simple cells with position
disparity by suba0 (d)2 simple stituting a(d) for c(d) and we obtain Ieven (d)
= 12 [1+a(d)] 2 . This function is shown in Figure 4C (blue dashed).

7
4
Discussion
The central idea of our paper is to evaluate the quality of a sensory code
with respect to an inference task by taking stimulus variability into account, in
particular that induced by irrelevant stimulus attributes. By framing stimulus-
induced nuisance variability as noise, we were able to employ the existing frame-
work of Fisher information for evaluating the standard model of early binocular
processing with respect to inferring disparity from random dot stereograms. We
started by investigating the disparity-conditioned variability of the binocular re-
sponse in the absence of intrinsic neuronal noise. We found that the response
distributions are far from Poisson or Gaussian and ? independent of stimu-
lus disparity ? are always peaked at zero (the mean response to uncorrelated
images). The information contained in the correlations between left and right
RF outputs are translated into a modulation of the neuron?s mean ﬁring rate
primarily by altering the skew of the response distribution. This is quite diﬀer-
ent from the case of intrinsic noise and has implications for comparing diﬀerent
codes. It is noteworthy that these response distributions are entirely imposed
by the sensory system ? the combination of the structure of the external world
with the internal processing model. Unlike the case of intrinsic noise which is
usually added ad-hoc after the neuronal computation has been performed, in
our case the computational model impacts the usefulness of the code beyond
the traditionally reported tuning functions. This property extends to the case
of population codes, the next step for future work. Of great importance for
the performance of population codes are interneuronal correlations. Again, the
noise correlations due to nuisance stimulus parameters are a direct consequence
of the processing model and the structure of the external input. Next we com-
pared the Fisher information available for our inference task at various stages
of binocular processing. We computed the Fisher information available in the
monocular inputs to binocular neurons in V1, after binocular combination and
after the squaring nonlinearity required to translate binocular correlations into
mean ﬁring rate modulation. We ﬁnd that despite the great stimulus variabil-
ity, the total Fisher information available in the inputs diverges and is only
bounded by intrinsic neuronal variability. The same is still true after binocular
combination for one ﬂavor of the model considered here ? that employing phase
disparity (or pairing unlike RFs in either eye), not the other one (position dis-
parity), which has lost most information after the initial combination. At this
point, our new approach allows us to ask a normative question: In what way
should the monocular inputs be combined so as to lose a minimal amount of in-
formation about the relevant stimulus dimension? Is the combination proposed

11

by the standard model to obtain even-symmetric tuning curves the only one to
do so or are they others that produce a diﬀerent tuning curve, with a diﬀerent
response distribution that is more suited to inferring depth? Conversely, we can
compare our results for the model stages leading from simple to complex cells
and compare them with the corresponding Fisher information computed from
empirically observed distributions, to test our model assumptions. Recently,
Fisher information has been criticized as a tool for comparing population codes
([3, 2]). We note that our approach can be readily adapted to other measures
like mutual information or their framework of neurometric function analysis to
compare the performance of diﬀerent codes in a disparity discrimination task.
Another potentially promising avenue of future research would to investigate the
eﬀect of thresholding on inference performance. One reason that odd-symmetric
tuning curves had higher Fisher information in the case we investigated was that
odd-symmetric cells produce near-zero responses more often in the context of
the energy model. However, it is known from empirical observations that ﬁt-
ting even-symmetric disparity tuning curves requires an additional thresholding
output nonlinearity. It is unclear at this point to what extend such a change
to the response distribution helps or hinders inference. And ﬁnally, we suggest
that considering the diﬀerent shapes of response distributions induced by the
speciﬁcs of the sensory modality might have an impact on the discussion about
probabilistic population codes ([7, 8] and references therein). Cue-integration,
for instance, has usually been studied under the assumption of Poisson-like re-
sponse distributions, assumptions that do not appear to hold in the case of
combining disparity cues from diﬀerent parts of the visual ﬁeld. Acknowledg-
ments This work has been supported by the Bernstein award to MB (BMBF;
FKZ: 01GQ0601). 8

2 References

[1] LF Abbott and P Dayan. The eﬀect of correlated variability on the accu-
racy of a population code. Neural Comput, 11(1):91?101, 1999.
[2] P Berens,
S Gerwinn, A Ecker, and M Bethge. Neurometric function analysis of popula-
tion codes. In Y. Bengio, D. Schuurmans, J. Laﬀerty, C. K. I. Williams, and
A. Culotta, editors, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 22,
pages 90?98. 2009.
[3] M Bethge, D Rotermund, and K Pawelzik. Optimal
short-term population coding: when ﬁsher information fails. Neural Comput,
14(10):2317?2351, 2002. [4] C Blakemore and B Julesz. Stereoscopic depth af-
tereﬀect produced without monocular cues. Science, 171(968):286?288, 1971. [5]
BG Cumming and GC DeAngelis. The physiology of stereopsis. Annu Rev Neu-
rosci, 24:203?238, 2001. [6] P Dayan and LF Abbott. Theoretical neuroscience:
Computational and mathematical modeling of neural systems. MIT Press, 2001.
[7] J Fiser, P Berkes, G Orban, and M Lengyel. Statistically optimal percep-
tion and learning: from behavior to neural representations. Trends Cogn Sci,
14(3):119?130, 2010. [8] WJ Ma, JM Beck, PE Latham, and A Pouget. Bayesian
inference with probabilistic population codes. Nat Neurosci, 9(11):1432?1438,

12

2006. [9] David Marr. Vision: A Computational Investigation into the Human
Representation and Processing of Visual Information. Henry Holt and Co., Inc.,
New York, NY, USA, 1982.
[10] I Ohzawa, GC DeAngelis, and RD Freeman.
Stereoscopic depth discrimination in the visual cortex: neurons ideally suited
as disparity detectors. Science, 249(4972):1037?1041, 1990. [11] GF Poggio and
B Fischer. Binocular interaction and depth sensitivity in striate and prestriate
cortex of behaving rhesus monkey. J Neurophysiol, 40(6):1392?1405, 1977. [12]
F. Rieke, D. Warland, R.R. van, Steveninck, and W. Bialek. Spikes: exploring
the neural code. MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 1997.

9

13

