Parametric Bandits: The Generalized Linear Case

Authored by:

Csaba Szepesv?ri

Sarah Filippi
Olivier Cappe

Aur?lien Garivier

Abstract

We consider structured multi-armed bandit tasks in which the agent is
guided by prior structural knowledge that can be exploited to eﬃciently
select the optimal arm(s) in situations where the number of arms is large,
or even inﬁnite. We pro- pose a new optimistic, UCB-like, algorithm for
non-linearly parameterized bandit problems using the Generalized Lin-
ear Model (GLM) framework. We analyze the regret of the proposed
algorithm, termed GLM-UCB, obtaining results similar to those recently
proved in the literature for the linear regression case. The analysis also
highlights a key diﬃculty of the non-linear case which is solved in GLM-
UCB by focusing on the reward space rather than on the parameter space.
Moreover, as the actual eﬃciency of current parameterized bandit algo-
rithms is often deceiving in practice, we provide an asymptotic argument
leading to signiﬁcantly faster convergence. Simulation studies on real data
sets illustrate the performance and the robustness of the proposed GLM-
UCB approach.

1 Paper Body

In the classical K-armed bandit problem, an agent selects at each time step one
of the K arms and receives a reward that depends on the chosen action. The aim
of the agent is to choose the sequence of arms to be played so as to maximize
the cumulated reward. There is a fundamental trade-oﬀ between gathering ex-
perimental data about the reward distribution (exploration) and exploiting the
arm which seems to be the most promising. In the basic multi-armed bandit
problem, also called the independent bandits problem, the rewards are assumed
to be random and distributed independently according to a probability distribu-
tion that is speciﬁc to each arm ?see [1, 2, 3, 4] and references therein. Recently,
structured bandit problems in which the distributions of the rewards pertain-
ing to each arm are connected by a common unknown parameter have received
much attention [5, 6, 7, 8, 9]. This model is motivated by the many practical

1

applications where the number of arms is large, but the payoﬀs are interrelated.
Up to know, two diﬀerent models were studied in the literature along these lines.
In one model, in each times step, a side-information, or context, is given to the
agent ﬁrst. The payoﬀs of the arms depend both on this side information and
the index of the arm. Thus the optimal arm changes with the context [5, 6,
9]. In the second, simpler model, that we are also interested in here, there is
no side-information, but the agent is given a model that describes the possible
relations 1

between the arms? payoﬀs. In particular, in ?linear bandits? [10, 8, 11, 12],
each arm a ? A is associated with some d-dimensional vector ma ? Rd known to
the agent. The expected payoﬀs of the arms are given by the inner product of
their associated vector and some ﬁxed, but initially unknown parameter vector
?? . Thus, the expected payoﬀ of arm a is m?a ?? , which is linear in ?? .1
In this article, we study a richer generalized linear model (GLM) in which the
expectation of the reward conditionally to the action a is given by ?(m?a ?? ),
where ? is a real-valued, non-linear function called the (inverse) link function.
This generalization allows to consider a wider class of problems, and in partic-
ular cases where the rewards are counts or binary variables using, respectively,
Poisson or logistic regression. Obviously, this situation is very common in the
ﬁelds of marketing, social networking, web-mining (see example of Section 5.2
below) or clinical studies. Our ﬁrst contribution is an ?optimistic? algorithm,
termed GLM-UCB, inspired by the Upper Conﬁdence Bound (UCB) approach
[2]. GLM-UCB generalizes the algorithms studied by [10, 8, 12]. Our next con-
tribution are ﬁnite-time bounds on the statistical performance of this algorithm.
In particular, we show that the performance depends on the dimension of the
parameter but not on the number of arms, a result that was previously known
in the linear case. Interestingly, the GLM-UCB approach takes advantage of the
particular structure of the parameter estimate of generalized linear models and
operates only in the reward space. In contrast, the parameter-space conﬁdence
region approach adopted by [8, 12] appears to be harder to generalize to non-
linear regression models. Our second contribution is a tuning method based on
asymptotic arguments. This contribution addresses the poor empirical perfor-
mance of the current algorithms that we have observed for small or moderate
sample-sizes when these algorithms are tuned based on ﬁnite-sample bounds.
The paper is organized as follows. The generalized linear bandit model is pre-
sented in Section 2, together with a brief survey of needed statistical results.
Section 3 is devoted to the description of the GLM-UCB algorithm, which is
compared to related approaches. Section 4 presents our regret bounds, as well
as a discussion, based on asymptotic arguments, on the optimal tuning of the
method. Section 5 reports the results of two experiments on real data sets. 2

Generalized Linear Bandits, Generalized Linear Models
We consider a structured bandit model with a ﬁnite, but possibly very large,
number of arms. At each time t, the agent chooses an arm At from the set A (we
shall denote the cardinality of A by K). The prior knowledge available to the
agent consists of a collection of vectors {ma }a?A of features which are speciﬁc
to each arm and a so-called (inverse) link function ? : R ? R. The generalized

2

linear bandit model investigated in this work is based on the assumption that
the payoﬀ Rt received at time t is conditionally independent of the past payoﬀs
and choices and it satisﬁes (1) E [ Rt — At ] = ?(m?At ?? ) ,

for some unknown parameter vector ?? ? Rd . This framework generalizes
the linear bandit model considered by [10, 8, 12]. Just like the linear bandit
model builds on linear regression, our model capitalizes on the well-known sta-
tistical framework of Generalized Linear Models (GLMs). The advantage of this
framework is that it allows to address various, speciﬁc reward structures widely
found in applications. For example, when rewards are binary-valued, a suitable
choice of ? is ?(x) = exp(x)/(1 + exp(x)), leading to the logistic regression
model. For integer valued rewards, the choice ?(x) = exp(x) leads to the Pois-
son regression model. This can be easily extended to the case of multinomial
(or polytomic) logistic regression, which is appropriate to model situations in
which the rewards are associated with categorical variables. To keep this article
self-contained, we brieﬂy review the main properties of GLMs [13]. A univariate
probability distribution is said to belong to a canonical exponential family if its
density with respect to a reference measure is given by p? (r) = exp (r? ? b(?)
+ c(r)) ,

(2)
where ? is a real parameter, c(?) is a real function and the function b(?)
is assumed to be twice continuously diﬀerentiable. This family contains the
Gaussian and Gamma distributions when the reference measure is the Lebesgue
measure and the Poisson and Bernoulli distributions when the 1

Throughout the paper we use the prime to denote transposition.
2
reference measure is the counting measure on the integers. For a random
variable R with density ? deﬁned in (2), E(R) = b(?) and Var(R) = ?b(?),
where b? and ?b denote, respectively, the ﬁrst and second derivatives of b. In
addition, ?b(?) can also be shown to be equal to the Fisher information matrix
for the parameter ?. The function b is thus strictly convex. Now, assume that,
in addition to the response variable R, we have at hand a vector of covariates X
? Rd . The canonical GLM associated to (2) postulates that p? (r—x) = px?
? (r), where ? ? Rd is a vector of parameter. Denote by ? = b? the so-called
inverse link function. From the properties of b, we know that ? is continuously
diﬀerentiable, strictly increasing, and thus one-to-one. The maximum likelihood
estimator ??t , based on observations (R1 , X1 ), . . . (Rt?1 , Xt?1 ), is deﬁned
as the maximizer of the function t?1 X

k=1
log p? (Rk —Xk ) =
t?1 X
k=1
Rk Xk? ? ? b(Xk? ?) + c(Rk ) ,
a strictly concave function in ?. Upon diﬀerentiating, we obtain that ??t is

the unique solution of the following estimating equation 2

t?1 X
k=1

3

(Rk ? ?(Xk? ?)) Xk = 0 ,
(3)
? In practice, the solution of (3) may be found eﬃciently where we have used
the fact that ? = b. using, for instance, Newton?s algorithm. A semi-parametric
version of the above model is obtained by assuming only that E? [R—X] = ?(X
? ?) without (much) further assumptions on the conditional distribution of R
given X. In this case, the estimator obtained by solving (3) is referred to as the
maximum quasi-likelihood estimator. It is a remarkable fact that this estimator
is consistent under very general assumptions as long as the Pt?1 design matrix
k=1 Xk Xk? tends to inﬁnity [14]. As we will see, this matrix also plays a
crucial role in the algorithm that we propose for bandit optimization in the
generalized linear bandit model. 3

The GLM-UCB Algorithm
According to (1), the agent receives, upon playing arm a, a random reward
whose expected value is ?(m?a ?? ), where ?? ? ? is the unknown parameter.
The parameter set ? is an arbitrary closed subset of Rd . Any arm with largest
expected reward is called optimal. The aim of the agent is to quickly ﬁnd an
optimal arm in order to maximize the received rewards. The greedy action
argmaxa?A ?(m?a ??t ) may lead to an unreliable algorithm which does not
suﬃciently explore to guarantee the selection of an optimal arm. This issue can
be addressed by resorting to an ?optimistic approach?. As described by [8, 12]
in the linear case, an optimistic algorithm consists in selecting, at time t, the
arm At = argmax max E? [ Rt — At = a] s.t. k? ? ??t kMt ? ?(t) , a

?
(4)
where ? is an appropriate, ?slowly increasing? function, Mt =
t?1 X
mAk m?Ak
(5)
k=1
? is the design matrix corresponding to the ﬁrst t ? 1 timesteps and kvkM
= v ? M v denotes the matrix norm induced by the positive semideﬁnite matrix
M . The region k? ? ??t kMt ? ?(t) is a conﬁdence ellipsoid around the
estimated parameter ??t . Generalizing this approach beyond the case of linear
link functions looks challenging. In particular, in GLMs, the relevant conﬁdence
regions may have a more complicated geometry in the parameter space than
simple ellipsoids. As a consequence, the beneﬁts of this form of optimistic
algorithms appears dubious.3 2

Here, and in what follows log denotes the natural logarithm. Note that max-
imizing ?(m?a ?) over a convex conﬁdence region is equivalent to maximizing
m?a ? over the same region since ? is strictly increasing. Thus, computationally,
this approach is not more diﬃcult than it is for the linear case. 3

3
An alternative approach consists in directly determining an upper conﬁdence
bound for the expected reward of each arm, thus choosing the action a that
maximizes E??t [ Rt — At = a] + ?(t)kma kM ?1 . t

4

In the linear case the two approaches lead to the same solution [12]. Inter-
estingly, for non-linear bandits, the second approach looks more appropriate.
In the rest of this section, we apply this second approach to the GLM bandit
model deﬁned in (1). According to (3), the maximum quasi-likelihood estimator
of the parameter in the GLM is the unique solution of the estimating equation
t?1

X Rk ? ?(m?Ak ??t ) mAk = 0 ,
(6)
k=1
where A1 , .

.

.

, At?1 denote the arms played so far and R1 , .

,
Rt?1 are the corresponding rewards. Pt?1 Let gt (?) = k=1 ?(m?Ak ?)mAk
be the invertible function such that the estimated parameter ??t P ? satisﬁes gt
(??t ) = t?1 k=1 Rk mAk . Since ?t might be outside of the set of admissible
parameters ?, ? we ?project it? to ?, to obtain ?t :

.

.

??t = argmin gt (?) ? gt (??t ) ???
Mt?1
t?1
X
= argmin gt (?) ? Rk mAk ???
k=1
Mt?1
.
(7)
Note that if ??t ? ? (which is easy to check and which happened to hold
always in the examples we dealt with) then we can let ??t = ??t . This is impor-
tant since computing ??t is non-trivial and we can save this computation by this
simple check. The proposed algorithm, GLM-UCB, is as follows: Algorithm 1
GLM-UCB 1: Input: {ma }a?A 2: Play actions a1 , . . . , ad , receive R1 , . .
. , Rd . 3: for t ¿ d do 4: Estimate ??t according to (6) ? 5: if ??t ? ? let ??t
= ??t else compute o n ?t according to (7) 6: Play the action At = argmaxa
?(m?a ??t ) + ?(t)kma kM ?1 , receive Rt t 7: end for At time t, for each arm a,
an upper bound ?(m?a ??t ) + ?ta is computed, where the ?exploration bonus?
?ta = ?(t)kma kM ?1 is the product of two terms. The quantity ?(t) is a slowly
increasing t function; we prove in Section 4 that ?(t) can be set to guarantee
high-probability bounds on the expected regret (for the actual form used, see
(8)). Note that the leading term of ?ta is kma kM ?1 t which decreases to zero
as t increases. As we are mostly interested in the case when the number of arms
K is much larger than the dimension d, the algorithm is simply initialized by
playing actions a1 , .
, mad form a
basis of M = span(ma , a ? A). Without loss of generality, here and in what
follows we assume that the dimension of M is equal to d. Then, by playing a1
, . . . , ad in the ﬁrst d steps the agent ensures that Mt is invertible for all t.
An alternative strategy would be to initialize M0 = ?0 I, where I is the d ? d
identify matrix. 3.1 Discussion The purpose of this section is to discuss some
properties of Algorithm 1, and in particular the interpretation of the role played
by kma kM ?1 . t

, ad such that the vectors ma1 .

.

.

.

.

5

Generalizing UCB The standard UCB algorithm for K arms [2] can be seen
as a special case of GLM-UCB where the vectors of covariates associated with
the arms form an orthogonal system and ?(x) = x. Indeed, take d = K, A =
{1, . . . , K}, deﬁne the vectors {ma }a?A as the canonical basis {ea }a?A of
Rd , and take ? ? Rd the vector whose component ?a is the expected reward
for arm a. 4

Then, Mt is a diagonal matrix whose a-th diagonal element is the number
Nt (a) of times the a-th arm haspbeen played up to time t. Therefore, the
exploration bonus in GLM-UCB is given by ? a = ??t (a) ?ta = ?(t)/ Nt (a).
Moreover, the maximum quasi-likelihood estimator ??t satisﬁes R t P t?1 ?a =
1 I R is the empirical mean of the rewards received for all a ? A, where R k
{A =a} t t k=1 Nt (a) while playing arm a. Algorithm 1 then reduces to the
familiar UCB algorithm. In this case, it is known that the expected cumulated
regret can be controlled upon setting the slowly varying p function ? to ?(t) =
2 log(t), assuming that the range of the rewards is bounded by one [2].

Generalizing linear bandits Obviously, setting ?(x) = x, we obtain a linear
bandit model. In this case, assuming that ? = Rd , the algorithm will reduce
to those described in the papers [8, 12].
In particular, the maximum quasi-
likelihood estimator becomes the least-squares estimator and as noted earlier,
the algorithm behaves identically to one which chooses the parameter optimisti-
cally within the conﬁdence ellipsoid {? : k? ? ??t kMt ? ?(t)}.

Dependence in the Number of Arms In contrast to an algorithm such as UCB,
Algorithm 1 does not need that all arms be played even once.4 To understand
this phenomenon, observe that, 2 2 2 2 (1 + kmAt kM ?1 ) for as Mt+1 =
Mt + mAt m?At , kma kM ?1 = kma kM ?1 ? m?a Mt?1 mAt t t t+1 a
any arm a. Thus the exploration bonus ?t+1 decreases for all arms, except
those which are exactly orthogonal to mAt (in the Mt?1 metric). The decrease
is most signiﬁcant for arms that are colinear to mAt . This explains why the
regret bounds obtained in Theorems 1 and 2 below depend on d but not on K.
4

Theoretical analysis
In this section we ﬁrst give our ﬁnite sample regret bounds and then show
how the algorithm can be tuned based on asymptotic arguments. 4.1 Regret
Bounds To quantify the performance of the GLM-UCB algorithm, we consider
the cumulated (pseudo) regret deﬁned as the expected diﬀerence between the
optimal reward obtained by always playing an optimal arm and the reward
received following the algorithm: RegretT =

T X t=1
?(m?a? ?? ) ? ?(m?At ?? ) .
For the sake of the analysis, in this section we shall assume that the following
assumptions hold: Assumption 1. The link function ? : R ? R is continuously
diﬀerentiable, Lipschitz with constant k? and such that c? = inf ???,a?A ?(m
? ?a ?) ¿ 0. For the logistic function k? = 1/4, while the value of c? depends
on sup???,a?A —m?a ?—.
Assumption 2. The norm of covariates in {ma : a ? A} is bounded: there
exists cm ¡ ? such that for all a ? A, kma k2 ? cm . Finally, we make the

6

following assumption on the rewards: Assumption 3. There exists Rmax ¿ 0
such that for any t ? 1, 0 ? Rt ? Rmax holds a.s. Let ?t = Rt ? ?(m?At ??
). For all t ? 1, it holds that E [?t —mAt , ?t?1 , . . . , mA2 , ?1 , mA1 ] =
0 a.s. As for the standard UCB algorithm, the regret can be analyzed in terms
of the diﬀerence between the expected reward received playing an optimal arm
and that of the best sub-optimal arm: ?(?? ) =

min
a:?(m?a ?? )¡?(m?a? ?? )
?(m?a? ?? ) ? ?(m?a ?? ) .
Theorem 1 establishes a high probability bound on the regret underlying

using GLM-UCB with 2k? ?Rmax p ?(t) = 2d log(t) log(2 d T /?) , (8) c? 4

Of course, the linear bandit algorithms also share this property with our

algorithm.

5
p where T is the ﬁxed time horizon, ? = 3 + 2 log(1 + 2c2m /?0 ) and ?0
denotes the smallest Pd ? eigenvalue of i=1 mai mai , which by our previous
assumption is positive. Theorem 1 (Problem Dependent Upper Bound). Let s
= max(1, c2m /?0 ). Then, under Assumptions 1?3, for all T ? 1, the regret
satisﬁes:

2 32?2 Rmax k?2 C d2 2d T 2 P RegretT ? (d + 1)Rmax + ? 1 ? ? with C
= log [s T ] log . ?(?? ) ? c2? Note that the above regret bound depends on
the true value of ?? through ?(?? ). The following theorem provides an upper-
bound of the regret independently of the ?? . Theorem 2 (Problem Independent
Upper Bound). Let s = max(1, c2m /?0 ). Then, under Assumptions 1?3, for
all T ? 1, the regret satisﬁes s

! 2dT 8Rmax k? ? P RegretT ? (d + 1)Rmax + Cd log [s T ] T log ? 1 ? ?
with C = . ? c? The proofs of Theorems 1?2 can be found in the supplementary
material. The main idea is to use the explicit form of the estimator given by
(6) to show that t?1

X
k
? mAk ?k ?1 . kmAt kM ?1 ?(m?At ?? ) ? ?(m?At ??t ) ? t c? Mt k=1
Bounding the last term on the right-hand side is then carried out following

the lines of [12]. 4.2 Asymptotic Upper Conﬁdence Bound

Preliminary experiments carried out using the value of ?(t) deﬁned equa-
tion (8), including the case where ? is the identity function ?i.e., using the
algorithm described by [8, 12], revealed poor performance for moderate sample
sizes. A look into the proof of the regret bound easily explains this observation
as the mathematical involvement of the arguments is such that some approx-
imations seem unavoidable, in particular several applications of the Cauchy-
Schwarz inequality, leading to pessimistic conﬁdence bounds. We provide here
some asymptotic arguments that suggest to choose signiﬁcantly smaller explo-
ration bonuses, which will in turn be validated by the numerical experiments
presented in Section 5. Consider the canonical GLM associated with an inverse
link function ? and assume that the vectors of covariates X are drawn indepen-
dently under a ﬁxed distribution. This random design model would for instance

7

describe the situation when the arms are drawn randomly from a ﬁxed distribu-
tion. Standard statistical arguments show that the Fisher information matrix
pertaining to this model is given by J = E[?(X ? ? ?? )XX ? ] and that the
maximum likelihood estimate ??t is such D D that t?1/2 (??t ? ?? ) ?? N (0, J
?1 ), where ?? stands for convergence in distribution. Moreover, a.s. ? ?1 t Mt
?? ? where ? = E[XX ]. Hence, using the delta-method and Slutsky?s lemma
D kma k?1?1 (?(m? ??t ) ? ?(m? ?? )) ?? N (0, ?(m ? ? ?? )km? k?2?1 km?
k2 ?1 ) . Mt

a
a
a
a ?
a J
The right-hand variance is smaller than k? /c? as J c? ?. Hence, for any
sampling distribution such that J and ? are positive deﬁnite and suﬃciently
large t and small ?,

q ?1 ? ? ? P kma kM ?1 (?(ma ?t ) ? ?(ma ?? )) ¿ 2k? /c? log(1/?) t
is asymptotically bounded by ?. Based on the above asymptotic argument,
we ppostulate that using p ?(t) = 2k? /c? log(t), i.e., inﬂating the exploration
bonus by a factor of k? /c? compared to the usual UCB setting, is suﬃcient.
This is the setting used in the simulations below. 5

Experiments
To the best of our knowledge, there is currently no public benchmark avail-
able to test bandit methods on real world data. On simulated data, the proposed
method unsurprisingly outperforms its competitors when the data is indeed sim-
ulated from a well-speciﬁed generalized linear model. In order to evaluate the
potential of the method in more challenging scenarios, we thus carried out two
experiments using real world datasets. 6

5.1 Forest Cover Type Data In this ﬁrst experiment, we test the performance
of the proposed method on a toy problem using the ?Forest Cover Type dataset?
from the UCI repository. The dataset (centered and normalized with constant
covariate added, resulting in 11-dimensional vectors, ignoring all categorical
variables) has been partitioned into K = 32 clusters using unsupervised k-means.
The values of the response variable for the data points assigned to each cluster
are viewed as the outcomes of an arm while the centroid of the cluster is taken
as the 11-dimensional vector of covariates characteristic of the arm. To cast
the problem into the logistic regression framework, each response variable is
binarized by associating the ﬁrst class (?Spruce/Fir?) to a response R = 1 and
all other six classes to R = 0. The proportions of responses equal to 1 in each
cluster (or, in other word, the expected reward associated with each arm) ranges
from 0.354 to 0.992, while the proportion on the complete set of 581,012 data
points is equal to 0.367. In eﬀect, we try to locate as fast as possible the cluster
that contains the maximal proportion of trees from a given species. We are
faced with a 32-arm problem in a 11-dimensional space with binary rewards.
Obviously, the logistic regression model is not satisﬁed, although we do expect

8

some regularity with respect to the position of the cluster?s centroid as the
logistic regression trained on all data reaches a 0.293 misclassiﬁcation rate.

2000
Regrett
1500
UCB GLM?UCB ??greedy
1000 500 0 0
1000
2000
3000
4000
5000 t
6000
7000
8000
6000
9000 10000
GLM?UCB UCB
4000 2000 0
2
4
6
8
10 arm a
12
14
16
18
Figure 1: Top: Regret of the UCB, GLM-UCB and the ?-greedy algorithms.
Bottom: Frequencies of the 20 best arms draws using the UCB and GLM-UCB.
We compare the performance of three algorithms. First, the GLM-UCB algo-
rithm, with parameters tuned as indicated in Section 4.2. Second, the standard
UCB algorithm that ignores the covariates. Third, an ?-greedy algorithm that
performs logistic regression and plays the best estimated action, At = argmaxa
?(m?a ??t ), with probability 1 ? ? (with ? = 0.1). We observe in the top graph
of Figure 1 that the GLM-UCB algorithm achieves the smallest average regret
by a large margin. When the parameter is well estimated, the greedy algorithm
may ﬁnd the best arm in little time and then leads to small regrets. However,
the exploration/exploitation tradeoﬀ is not correctly handled by the ?-greedy
approach causing a large variability in the regret. The lower plot of Figure 1
shows the number of times each of the 20 best arms have been played by the
UCB and GLM-UCB algorithms. The arms are sorted in decreasing order of
expected reward. It can be observed that GML-UCB only plays a small subset
of all possible arms, concentrating on the bests. This behavior is made possible
by the predictive power of the covariates: by sharing information between arms,

9

it is possible to obtain suﬃciently accurate predictions of the expected rewards
of all actions, even for those that have never (or rarely) been played. 7

5.2 Internet Advertisement Data In this experiment, we used a large record of
the activity of internet users provided by a major ISP. The original dataset logs
the visits to a set of 1222 pages over a six days period corresponding to about
5.108 page visits. The dataset also contains a record of the users clicks on the
ads that were presented on these pages. We worked with a subset of 208 ads and
3.105 users. The pages (ads) were partitioned in 10 (respectively, 8) categories
using Latent Dirichlet Allocation [15] applied to their respective textual content
(in the case of ads, the textual content was that of the page pointed to by the
ad?s link). This second experiment is much more challenging, as the predictive
power of the sole textual information turns out to be quite limited (for instance,
Poisson regression trained on the entire data does not even correctly identify
the best arm). The action space is composed of the 80 pairs of pages and
ads categories: when a pair is chosen, it is presented to a group of 50 users,
randomly selected from the database, and the reward is the number of recorded
clicks. As the average reward is typically equal to 0.15, we use a logarithmic
link function corresponding to Poisson regression. The vector of covariates for
each pair is of dimension 19:
it is composed of an intercept followed by the
concatenation of two vectors of dimension 10 and 8 representing, respectively,
the categories of the pages and the ads. In this problem, the covariate vectors
do not span the entire space; to address this issue, it is suﬃcient to consider
the pseudo-inverse of Mt instead of the inverse. On this data, we compared the
GLM-UCB algorithm with the two alternatives described in Section 5.1. Figure
2 shows that GLM-UCB once again outperforms its competitors, even though
the margin over UCB is now less remarkable. Given the rather limited predictive
power of the covariates in this example, this is an encouraging illustration of the
potential of techniques which use vectors of covariates in real-life applications.

Regret
3000 2000
UCB GLM?UCB ??greedy
1000 0 0
1000
2000
3000
4000
5000
t
Figure 2: Comparison of the regret of the UCB, GLM-UCB and the ?-greedy

(? = 0.1) algorithm on the advertisement dataset. 6

Conclusions
We have introduced an approach that generalizes the linear regression model
studied by [10, 8, 12]. As in the original UCB algorithm, the proposed GLM-
UCB method operates directly in the reward space. We discussed how to tune
the parameters of the algorithm to avoid exaggerated optimism, which would
slow down learning. In the numerical simulations, the proposed algorithm was

10

shown to be competitive and suﬃciently robust to tackle real-world problems.
An interesting open problem (already challenging in the linear case) consists
in tightening the theoretical results obtained so far in order to bridge the gap
between the existing (pessimistic) conﬁdence bounds and those suggested by
the asymptotic arguments presented in Section 4.2, which have been shown to
perform satisfactorily in practice. Acknowledgments This work was supported
in part by AICML, AITF, NSERC, PASCAL2 under no 216886, the DARPA
GALE project under no HR0011-08-C-0110 and Orange Labs under contract no
289365. 8

2 References

[1] T.L. Lai and H. Robbins. Asymptotically eﬃcient adaptive allocation rules.
Advances in Applied Mathematics, 6(1):4?22, 1985.
[2] P. Auer, N. Cesa-
Bianchi, and P. Fischer. Finite-time analysis of the multiarmed bandit problem.
[3] N. Cesa-Bianchi and G. Lugosi.
Machine Learning, 47(2):235?256, 2002.
Prediction, learning, and games. Cambridge Univ Pr, 2006.
[4] J. Audibert,
R. Munos, and Cs. Szepesv?ari. Tuning bandit algorithms in stochastic envi-
ronments. Lecture Notes in Computer Science, 4754:150, 2007. [5] C.C. Wang,
S.R. Kulkarni, and H.V. Poor. Bandit problems with side observations. IEEE
Transactions on Automatic Control, 50(3):338?355, 2005.
[6] J. Langford and
T. Zhang. The epoch-greedy algorithm for multi-armed bandits with side infor-
mation. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 817?824,
2008.
[7] S. Pandey, D. Chakrabarti, and D. Agarwal. Multi-armed bandit
problems with dependent arms. International Conference on Machine learning,
pages 721?728, 2007. [8] V. Dani, T.P. Hayes, and S.M. Kakade. Stochastic lin-
ear optimization under bandit feedback. Conference on Learning Theory, 2008.
[9] S.M. Kakade, S. Shalev-Shwartz, and A. Tewari. Eﬃcient bandit algorithms
for online multiclass prediction. In Proceedings of the 25th International Con-
ference on Machine learning, pages 440?447. ACM, 2008. [10] P. Auer. Using
conﬁdence bounds for exploitation-exploration trade-oﬀs. Journal of Machine
Learning Research, 3:397?422, 2002. [11] Y. Abbasi-Yadkori, A. Antos, and Cs.
Szepesv?ari. Forced-exploration based algorithms for playing in stochastic linear
bandits. In COLT Workshop on On-line Learning with Limited Feedback, 2009.
[12] P. Rusmevichientong and J.N. Tsitsiklis. Linearly parameterized bandits.
[13] P. McCullagh
Mathematics of Operations Research, 35(2):395?411, 2010.
and J. A. Nelder. Generalized Linear Models. Chapman and Hall, 1989.
[14]
K. Chen, I. Hu, and Z. Ying. Strong consistency of maximum quasi-likelihood
estimators in generalized linear models with ﬁxed and adaptive designs. Annals
of Statistics, 27(4):1155?1163, 1999.
[15] David M. Blei, Andrew Y. Ng, and
Michael I. Jordan. Latent Dirichlet allocation. Advances in Neural Information
Processing Systems, 14:601?608, 2002. [16] V.H. De La Pena, M.J. Klass, and
T.L. Lai. Self-normalized processes: exponential inequalities, moment bounds
and iterated logarithm laws. Annals of Probability, 32(3):1902?1933, 2004. [17]
P. Rusmevichientong and J.N. Tsitsiklis. Linearly parameterized bandits. Arxiv

11

preprint arXiv:0812.3465v2, 2008.

9

12

