Decoding Ipsilateral Finger Movements from

ECoG Signals in Humans

Authored by:

Kilian Q. Weinberger

Yuzong Liu

Mohit Sharma
Charles Gaona

Jonathan Breshears

Jarod Roland

Zachary Freudenburg

Eric Leuthardt

Abstract

Several motor related Brain Computer Interfaces (BCIs) have been
developed over the years that use activity decoded from the contralateral
hemisphere to operate devices. Many recent studies have also talked about
the importance of ipsilateral activity in planning of motor movements. For
successful upper limb BCIs, it is important to decode ﬁnger movements
from brain activity. This study uses ipsilateral cortical signals from hu-
mans (using ECoG) to decode ﬁnger movements. We demonstrate, for
the ﬁrst time, successful ﬁnger movement detection using machine learn-
ing algorithms. Our results show high decoding accuracies in all cases
which are always above chance. We also show that signiﬁcant accuracies
can be achieved with the use of only a fraction of all the features recorded
and that these core features also make sense physiologically. The results
of this study have a great potential in the emerging world of motor neu-
roprosthetics and other BCIs.

1 Paper Body

Several motor related Brain Computer Interfaces (BCIs) have been developed
over the years that use activity decoded from the contralateral hemisphere to
operate devices. Contralateral primary motor cortex is also the region most
severely aﬀected by hemispheric stroke. Recent studies have identiﬁed ipsilat-
eral cortical activity in planning of motor movements and its potential impli-
cations for a stroke relevant BCI. The most fundamental functional loss after a
hemispheric stroke is the loss of ﬁne motor control of the hand. Thus, whether

1

ipsilateral cortex encodes ﬁnger movements is critical to the potential feasibil-
ity of BCI approaches in the future. This study uses ipsilateral cortical signals
from humans (using ECoG) to decode ﬁnger movements. We demonstrate, for
the ﬁrst time, successful ﬁnger movement detection using machine learning al-
gorithms. Our results show high decoding accuracies in all cases which are
always above chance. We also show that signiﬁcant accuracies can be achieved
with the use of only a fraction of all the features recorded and that these core
features are consistent with previous physiological ﬁndings. The results of this
study have substantial implications for advancing neuroprosthetic approaches
to stroke populations not currently amenable to existing BCI techniques.

1
Introduction
Note by authors after publication: The results in Figure 3 could not be
reproduced in subsequent experiments and should be considered invalid. We
apologize for this mishap. Other results in this paper are not aﬀected. The
evolving understanding of motor function in the brain has led to novel Brain
Computer Interface (BCI) platforms that can potentially assist patients with
severe motor disabilities. A BCI is a device that can decode human intent from
brain activity alone in order to create an alternate communication and con-
trol channel for people with severe motor impairments [39]. This brain-derived
control is dependent on the emerging understanding of cortical physiology as
it pertains to motor function. Examples are seen in the seminal discoveries by
Georgopoulus and Schwartz that neurons in motor cortex show directional tun-
ing and, when taken as a population, can predict direction and speed of arm
movements in monkey models [12, 19]. In the subsequent two decades, these
ﬁndings were translated to substantial levels of brain-derived control in mon-
key models and preliminary human clinical trials [14, 34]. Another example
is seen in Pfurtschellers work in analyzing electroencephalography (EEG). His
group was one of the ﬁrst to describe the changes in amplitudes in sensorimotor
rhythms associated with motor movement [24]. As a result, both Pfurtscheller
and Wolpaw have used these signals to achieve basic levels of control in humans
with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and spinal cord injury [25, 40]. All
these methods are based on a functioning motor cortex capable of controlling
the contralateral limb. This is the 1

exact situation that does not exist in unilateral stroke. Hence, these systems
to date oﬀer little hope for patients suﬀering from hemispheric stroke. For a
BCI to assist a hemiparetic patient, the implant will likely need to utilize un-
aﬀected cortex ipsilateral to the aﬀected limb (opposite the side of the stroke).
To do so, an expanded understanding of how and to what degree of complexity
motor and motor associated cortex encodes ipsilateral hand movements is essen-
tial. Electrocorticography (ECoG), or signal recorded from the surface of the
brain, oﬀers an excellent opportunity to further deﬁne what level of motor infor-
mation can be deciphered from human ipsilateral cortex related to movements
(e.g. gross motor movements versus ﬁne motor kinematics of individual ﬁnger
movements). The ECoG signal is more robust compared to the EEG signal:
its magnitude is typically ﬁve times larger, its spatial resolution as it relates

2

to independent signals is much greater (0.125 versus 3.0 cm for EEG), and its
frequency bandwidth is signiﬁcantly higher (0-550 Hz versus 0- 40 Hz for EEG)
[11, 30]. When analyzed on a functional level, many studies have revealed that
diﬀerent frequency bandwidths carry highly speciﬁc and anatomically focal in-
formation about cortical processing. Thus far, however, no studies have utilized
these ECoG spectral features to deﬁnitively analyze and decode cortical process-
ing of the speciﬁc kinematics of ipsilateral ﬁnger movements. In the past year,
the ﬁrst demonstration of this concept of utilizing ipsilateral motor signals for
simple device control have been published both with ECoG (in healthy subjects)
and MEG (in stroke patients) [4, 38]. In this study we set out to further explore
the decoding of individual ﬁnger movements of the ipsilateral hand that could
potentially be utilized for more sophisticated BCIs in the future. We studied
3 subjects who required invasive monitoring for seizure localization. Each had
electrode arrays placed over the frontal lobe and a portion of sensorimotor cor-
tex for approximately a week. Each subject performed individual ﬁnger tasks
and the concurrent ECoG signal was recorded and analyzed. The principal
results show that individual ipsilateral ﬁnger movements can be decoded with
high accuracy. Through machine learning techniques, our group was able to
determine the intent to ﬂex and extend individual ﬁnger movements of the ip-
silateral hand. These results indicate that an ECoG based BCI platform could
potentially operate a hand orthotic based on ipsilateral motor signals. This
could provide a neuroprosthetic alternative to patients with hemispheric stroke
who have otherwise failed non-invasive and medical rehabilitative techniques.

2
Data Collection
The subjects in this study were three patients (females; 8, 36, 48 years of age)
with intractable epilepsy who underwent temporary placement of intracranial
electrode arrays to localize seizure foci prior to surgical resection. All had
normal levels of cognitive function and all were right-handed. Subject 1 had
a right hemispheric 8?8 grid while subjects 2 and 3 had left hemispheric 8?8
grids. All gave informed consent. The study was approved by the Washington
University Human Research Protection Oﬃce. Each subject sat in their hospital
bed 75 cm from a 17-inch LCD video screen. In this study, the subject wore a
data glove on the each hand to precisely monitor ﬁnger movements. Each hand
rested on a table in front of the screen. The screen randomly cued the patient
to ﬂex and extend a given ﬁnger (e.g., left index ﬁnger, right ring ﬁnger, etc.).
A cue came up on the monitor and as long as it was present, subjects would,
at a self-paced speed, move the indicated ﬁnger from the ﬂexed to the extended
position until the cue disappeared. They were instructed on the method prior
to participation. Each cued task period would last 2 seconds with a randomized
rest period between 1.5 and 2.5 seconds(i.e., a trial). There were on average 30
trials per ﬁnger for a given subject. For subject 1, the thumb data recording
was found to be noisy and hence was eliminated from any further analysis.
Visual cues were presented using the BCI2000 program [27]. All motor hand
kinematics were monitored by the patient wearing a USB linked 5DT Data
Glove 5 Ultras (Fifth Dimension, Irvine, CA) on each hand. These data gloves

3

are designed to measure ﬁnger ﬂexure with one sensor per ﬁnger at up to 8-bit
ﬂexure resolution. The implanted platinum electrode arrays were 8?8 electrode
arrays(Ad-Tech, Racine, WI and PMT, Chanhassen, MN). The grid and system
setup details are described elsewhere [38]. ECoG signals were acquired using
BCI2000, stored, and converted to MATLAB ﬁles for further processing and
analysis. All electrodes were referenced to an inactive intracranial electrode.
The sampling frequency was 1200 Hz and data acquisition is band-pass ﬁltered
from 0.15 to 500 Hz. 2

2.1
Data Preprocessing
Gabor Filter Analysis All ECoG data sets were visually inspected and re-
referenced with respect to the common average to account for any unwanted en-
vironmental noise. For these analyses, the timeseries ECoG data was converted
into the frequency domain using a Gabor ﬁlter bank [17]. Spectral amplitudes
between 0 and 550 Hz were analyzed on a logarithmic scale. The ﬁnger positions
from the data glove were converted into velocities. These frequency responses
and velocities were then used as an input to machine learning algorithms de-
scribed below. Inherent in this is the estimation of the lag between the ECoG
signal and the actual ﬁnger movement. As part of the modeling process, the
value of this variable which resulted in the best decoding accuracy was chosen
for further analysis. Average time lags were then used to align the ECoG signal
to the ﬁnger movement signal. Those features optimized for predicting indi-
vidual ﬁnger movement were then reviewed in light of anatomic location and
spectral association in each subject. Dimensionality Reduction Due to the high
dimensionality of the spectral data (#channels(N ) ? #f requencies(F )), it is
important to reduce the dimensions in order to build a more conducive ma-
chine learning algorithm. Principle component analysis, or PCA, is among the
most popular dimensionality reduction algorithm. PCA projects the original
high-dimensional feature space into a much lower principle subspace, such that
the variance of low-dimensional data is maximized. In the real-time decoding
task, we use PCA to reduce the input data. However, in the weight analysis,
we preserve all the N ? F features because we want to study the eﬀect of using
all the features. Electrode Co-Registration Radiographs were used to identify
the stereotactic coordinates of each grid electrode [10], and cortical areas were
deﬁned the GetLOC package for ECoG electrode localization [18]. Stereotac-
tically deﬁned electrodes were mapped to the standardized brain model. The
experimental results were then collated with these anatomical mapping data.

3
Algorithms
In this section, we describe the machine learning algorithms used for the
ﬁnger movement decoding tasks. We focus on three diﬀerent settings: 1. binary
classiﬁcation, 2. multiclass classiﬁcation and 3. multitask classiﬁcation. All the
data is split into a training and a testing dataset. We chose our parameters based
on a validation dataset split from the training dataset. Binary Classiﬁcation We
treat the ﬁnger movement detection problem as a binary classiﬁcation setting.
The data is presented as a time series with feature vector xt and velocity label

4

yt at time t. The goal is to predict if at time t, a ﬁnger is moving (yt = 1) or
not (yt = ?1). For this purpose, we adapted logistic regression (LR) [26] and
binary support vector machines (SVM) [7]. Both classiﬁers learn parameters
(w, b) ? Rd ? R. The prediction at time t is computed as y?t = sign(w¿ xt +
b). The vector w is learned with the following optimization problem min (w,b)

T X
L(w¿ xt + b, yt ) + ?—w—q .
(1)
t=1
Here, ? ? 0 is the regularization constant that trades oﬀ weight sparsity
with complexity. The norm of the regularization can be the ‘1 norm (q = 1)
or the ‘2 norm (q = 2). The ‘1 norm has the tendency to result in sparse
classiﬁers which assign non-zero weights to only a small subset of the available
features. This allows us to infer which brain regions and frequencies are most
important for accurate predictions. The ‘2 norm tends to yield slightly better
classiﬁcation results (and is easier to optimize) but is not as interpretable as
it typically assigns small weights to many features. The loss functions L diﬀer
for the two above mentioned algorithms. We will denote the loss function for
logistic regression as Llr and for SVMs as Lsvm . The exact deﬁnitions are: Llr
(z, y) = log(1 + exp(?yz))

Lsvm (z, y) = max(1 ? yz, 0)
(2)
Multiclass Classiﬁcation A second setting of interest is the diﬀerentiation of
ﬁngers. Here we do not want to predict if a ﬁnger is moving but which one.
Consequently, at any time point t we could have one of K possible labels, such as
?Index Finger? (yt = 1), ?Ring Finger? (yt = 2), etc. We adopt the Crammer
and Singer multi-class adaptation of support vector machines (MCSVM) [8].
For each class k ? {1, .
, K}, we learn class-speciﬁc parameters wk , bk .
.
The loss only focuses on 3

.

pairwise comparisons between the diﬀerent classes and ensures that wk¿ xt
+ bk ? wr¿ xt + br + 1 if yt = k for any r 6= k. For completeness, we re-state
the optimization problem: T X X

min (w1 ,b1 ),...,(wK ,bK )
max(1 +
wrT xt
+ br ?
t=1 r6=yt
(wyTt xyt
+ byt ), 0) + ?
K X
—wk —q .
(3)
k=1
Similar to the scenario of binary classiﬁcation, the constant ? ? 0 regulates
the trade-oﬀ between complexity and sparseness. Multitask Learning In the

5

movement detection setting, each ﬁnger is learned as an independent classiﬁ-
cation problem. In the ﬁnger discrimination setting, we actively discriminate
between the individual ﬁngers. Multitask learning (MTL) is a way to com-
bine the binary ﬁnger movement detection problems by learning them jointly
[5]. In the setting of brain decoding, it seems reasonable to assume that there
are certain features which are associated with the general cortical processing of
ﬁnger movements. This is analogous to the notion of language processing and
articulation in cortical areas. Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI)
studies have shown that although speech is represented in general cortical ar-
eas, individual features speciﬁc to diﬀerent kinds of words can be found [16, 23].
We adopt the MTL adaptation for SVMs of [9], and an analogous framework
for logistic regression, which leverages the commonalities across learning tasks
by modeling them explicitly with an additional shared weight vector w0 . The
prediction at time t for ﬁnger k is deﬁned as y?t = (w0 + wk )¿ xt . The
corresponding optimization problem becomes min

w0 ,w1 ,...,wK
?0 —w0 — +
K X T X
L((w0 + wk )¿ xt , yt ) + ?k —wk —q .
(4)
k=0 t=1
The parameter ?0 regulates how much of the learning is shared.

If ?0 ?
+?, then w0 = 0 and we reduce our setting to the original binary classiﬁcation
mentioned above. On the other hand, setting ?0 = 0 and ?k¿0 0 will result in
weight vectors wk¿0 = 0. As a result, one would learn only a single classiﬁer
with weight vector w0 for generic ﬁnger movement.

4
Results
In this section we evaluate our algorithms for ipsilateral decoding on three
subjects. First, we approximate the time-lag between ECoG signal and ﬁn-
ger movement, then we present decoding results on ﬁnger movement detection,
discrimination and also joint decoding of all ﬁngers in one hand.

Area Under the Curve
Time Lag We ﬁrst study the eﬀects of 1 decoding time lag between cortical
signal and movement using features. The decod0.8 ing accuracy is computed
by shifting the feature dataset xt and the target dataset yt 0.6 by a presumed
number of sample points (i.e. we are evaluating the performance of 0.4 decoder
h: h(xt ) = yt+?T , by increasing Index the value of ?T ). The best time lag is
Middle 0.2 Ring selected as the value of ?T which leads Little to best decoding
accuracy. Figure 1 Average 0 shows the decoding accuracy as a function 0 150
300 450 600 750 Time Lag (ms) of time-lag for four individual ﬁnger movements
in Subject 1. Oﬀsets between Figure 1: Decoding time lag for ipsilateral ﬁnger
move0 and 800 ms are tested for all ﬁngers and ment in Subject 1. The x-axis is
the presumed time lag an average oﬀset time is computed. The ?T (ms) between
input feature vectors and target labels, average time lag for the ipsilateral ﬁnger
and the y-axis is the area under the ROC curve commovement for Subject 1

6

is observed to be puted from L1-regularized logistic regression model. around
158 ms. This is in accordance with The bold black line is the average AUC,
and the best previous studies by our group which show decoding time-lag is
indicated by the black dotted line. similar time lags between cortical activity
and actual movements [38]. All further analysis is based on cortical activity
(features) shifted relative to movement by the average time-lag reported here.

4
1
0.8
0.8
0.8
0.6 Index Middle Ring Little
0.4 0.2 0 0
0.2
0.4 0.6 0.8 False Positive Rate
(a) Subject 1
1
True Positive Rate
1 True Positive Rate
True Positive Rate
1
0.6 Thumb Index Middle Ring Little
0.4 0.2 0 0
0.2
0.4 0.6 0.8 False Positive Rate
(b) Subject 2
1
0.6 Thumb Index Middle Ring Little
0.4 0.2 0 0
0.2
0.4 0.6 0.8 False Positive Rate
1
(c) Subject 3
Figure 2: ROC curve for the ipsilateral ﬁnger movement decoder. Horizontal
axis shows the false positive rate, and the vertical axis shows the true positive
rate. The dotted line is the accuracy of a random classiﬁer. Classiﬁers that
have higher area under the ROC curve, or AUC, indicate better classiﬁcation
performance. Detecting Finger Movement We characterize the movement de-
tection task as a binary classiﬁcation. We ﬁrst set a threshold thresh, and label
the targets yt as 1 if the velocity at time t vt ? thresh, and -1 otherwise. Then,
we use ‘1-regularized logistic regression for the binary classiﬁcation. We use re-
ceiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve to evaluate the performance of the
binary classiﬁcation. ROC curve is widely used in signal estimation and detec-
tion theory, and is a graphical plot of true positive rate versus the false positive
rate. ROC analysis allows user to pick the optimal discrimination threshold for
the binary classiﬁer. We pick regularizer ? from validation dataset. Figure 2

7

shows the result of ROC curve for three subjects. This demonstrates that ‘1-
regularized logistic regression is a powerful tool in detecting ﬁnger movement.
Finger Discrimination In this section, we study how to discriminate which ﬁn-
ger has made the movement. We ﬁrst extract the sample points of which the
ﬁnger is moving from the time-series. We then apply multiclass SVM to do the
classiﬁcation. The result is shown as the confusion matrices in Figure 3, and
the colorbar shows the accuracy. Each row of the matrix represents the ﬁnger
that actually moved and each column represents predicted ﬁnger. The elements
of the matrix shows the percentage of all movements of a particular ﬁnger that
has been classiﬁed as particular predicted ﬁnger. Note that the accuracy by a
random multiclass classiﬁer is 1/(number of ﬁngers). It can be concluded that
the ECoG signal contains useful information to discriminate individual ﬁnger
movement.

!”#$%&’()
!”#$%&’()
Predicted Movement
!”#$%&’()
Actual Movement
Figure 3: Note from authors after publication: Results in this ﬁgure are
invalid (see note in introduction).Confusion matrix of ﬁnger movement multi-
class classiﬁcation. The rows are the actual movement, and the columns are the
predicted movement.

4.1
Learning Commonality from the Brain Activity
In this section, we present how multitask learning improves the performance
of the classiﬁer. Although multitask learning has been employed in the context
of brain signal decoding [2], we are the ﬁrst to decode ECoG signals in humans.
We group all the individual ﬁnger movement together, such that each task has
similarity with others. First of all, we evaluate the performance of single-task 5
learning using SVM. Then, we study the SVM-based multitask learning. As
we show in Equation 4, we make trade-oﬀ between modeling joint component
and and modeling class-speciﬁc components by adjusting parameters ?0 and
?. We search a number of regularization constant (?0 , ?), and pick up the
parameters that lead to highest average AUC for all tasks. Table 1 shows the
comparison of SVM-based single task learning and multitask learning. Here we
evaluate the multitask learning algorithm based on the improvement of (1-AUC);
(1-AUC) stands for the area above the curve. The average improvement of the
decoder for three patients is 25.53%, 5.60%, and 18.57%, respectively. This
conﬁrms our assumption that there exists brain activity that controls the ﬁnger
movement, irrespective of any particular ﬁnger. By carefully searching the best
parameters that regulates the trade-oﬀ between learning commonality among
all ﬁnger movement and speciﬁcity of exact ﬁnger movement, the classiﬁcation
algorithm can be signiﬁcantly improved. We also compare the ‘1/‘2regularized
logistic regression-based multitask learning with SVM-based multitask learning.
There is an improvement on (1-AUC) for logistic regression-based multitask
learning. Again, it illustrates that multitask learning is particularly helpful

8

in learning similar tasks that are controlled by the brain. However, we prefer
SVM-based multitask learning because of the larger improvement.

AUC Thumb Index Middle Ring Little
Subject 1 STL MTL N/A N/A 0.8477 0.8494 0.8393 0.8569 0.8000 0.8561

0.7425 0.7865

Subject 2 STL MTL 0.7710 0.7845 0.9061 0.8948 0.9021 0.8990 0.8888 0.8894

0.7124 0.7586

Subject 3 STL MTL 0.7680 0.8611 0.7454 0.8242 0.9459 0.9481 0.7404 0.7479

0.7705 0.7801

Table 1: Comparison of SVM-based single-task learning (STL) and SVM-
based multi-task learning (MTL). The parameters are chosen from validation
dataset: ?0 = 10?2 and ? = 104 for Subject 1, ?0 = 1 and ? = 102 for Subject
2, and ?0 = 102 and ? = 10?2 for Subject 3. The best decoding performance is
indicated in bold.

5
Weight Analysis
An important part of decoding ﬁnger movements from cortical activity is to
map the features back to cortical domain. Physiologically, it is important to
understand the features which contribute most to the decoding algorithms i.e.
the features with the highest weights. As shown in Table 2 below, the decoding
accuracy, indicated by AUC, does not change much as we increase the number
of features used for classiﬁcation. This signiﬁes that from the large feature set
used for decoding, a few features form the core and are the most important. To
visualize these core features, we mapped the top 30 features back to the brain.
Figure 4 above shows the normalized weights from the features used to classify
ﬁnger movements from non-movements. It is apparent from the ﬁgure that the
features with the highest weights fall in the DLPFC and premotor areas. This
is what we would expect since these two areas are the one?s most involved in
the planning of motor movements. As previously reported, the frequency range
with the highest weights falls in the lower frequencies in ipsilateral movements
[38].
In our case, the frequencies fall in the delta-alpha range. As noted by
Tallon-Baudry, attention networks of the brain aﬀect the oscillatory synchrony
as low as theta-alpha range frequencies [31].

# features AUC
1 0.681
2 0.717
4 0.755
8 0.787
16 0.803
32 0.807
64 0.807
256 0.807
4096 0.808
Table 2: The area under the curve (AUC) as a function of the number of
features used for classiﬁcation. Features were selected in decreasing order of
their respective absolute weights from logistic regression with ‘1 regularization.

9

6
Subject 1
Subject 2
Subject 3
Figure 4: Brain map representing the weights of the top 30 features of the
three subjects. It represents the variability in cortical processing of ipsilateral
ﬁnger movements.
It can also be seen that cortical processing occurs as a
network involving dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, pre-motor and motor areas.
The frequency range for these features is in the delta and alpha range i.e. the
low frequency range.

6
Discussion
The notion that motor cortex plays a role in ipsilateral body movements
was ﬁrst asserted by NybergHansen et al. that 15% of corticospinal neurons
did not decussate in cats [22]. Originally this was felt to represent more axial
motor control. Further studies in single-neuron recordings in monkey models
extended this observation to include ipsilateral hand and ﬁnger function. Tanji
et al. demonstrated that a small percentage of primary motor cortical neurons
showed increased activity with ipsilateral hand movements [32]. This site was
found to be anatomically distinct from contralateral hand sites and, when stim-
ulated, produced ipsilateral hand movements [1]. Additionally, a larger subset of
premotor neurons was found to demonstrate more robust activations with cues
to initiate movement during both ipsilateral and contralateral movements than
with primary motor sites [3, 6]. These ﬁndings in animal models support the
conclusion that a small percent of motor and a larger percent of premotor cor-
tex participate in control of ipsilateral limb and hand movements. In humans,
there appears to be a dichotomy in how motor regions contribute depending
on whether the primary or non-primary motor cortex is examined. Using fMRI
Newton et al. demonstrated that there was a negative change from baseline
in fMRI bold sequence in M1 associated with ipsilateral movements and pos-
tulated this to represent increased inhibition [21]. Verstynen et al., however,
recently published contrasting results. Their group showed that anatomically
distinct primary motor sites demonstrated increased activation that became
more pronounced during the execution of complex movements [36]. The role
that premotor cortex plays appears to be distinct from that of primary motor
cortex.
In normal subjects, fMRI shows that there is more robust bilateral
activation of the dorsal premotor cortex with either contralateral or ipsilateral
hand movements [15]. The ﬁndings by Huang, et al.
(2004) demonstrated
that ipsilateral premotor areas have magnetoencephalography (MEG) dipole
peak latencies that signiﬁcantly precede contralateral M1 sensorimotor cortex in
performing unilateral ﬁnger movements. Using electroencephalography (EEG),
ipsilateral hand movements have been shown to induce alteration in cortical
potentials prior to movement; this is referred to as premotor positivity [33, 29].
Spectral analyses of EEG signals have shown bihemispheric low-frequency re-
sponses with various ﬁnger and hand movements. Utilizing electrocorticography
(ECoG), Wisneski et al more deﬁnitively demonstrated that the cortical phys-

10

iology associated with ipsilateral hand movements was associated with lower
frequency spectral changes, an earlier timing, and premotor predominant corti-
cal localization, when compared to cortical physiology that was associated with
contralateral hand movements [38]. Taken together, these ﬁndings support more
of a motor planning role, rather than execution role, in ipsilateral hand actions.
Decoding the information present in the ECoG signal with regard to ipsilateral
ﬁnger movements is important in deﬁning the potential use of BCI methodolo-
gies for patients with hemispheric dysfunction due to stroke or trauma. If high
resolution motor kinematics can be decoded from the ECoG signal (e.g. individ-
ual ﬁnger ﬂexion and extension), a BCI platform could potentially be created
to restore function to a stroke induced paretic hand. Since up to one-half of
hemispheric stroke 7

patients are chronically left with permanent loss of function in their aﬀected
hand, this could have substantial clinical impact [20]. Functional imaging has
shown these severely aﬀected patients to have increased activity in the premotor
regions of their unaﬀected hemispheres [28, 37]. The exact role this activity plays
is still unclear. It may simply be an indicator of a more severe outcome [35]
or an adapative mechanism to optimize an already poor situation [13]. Thus,
incomplete recovery and its association with heightened ipsilateral activation
may reﬂect the up-regulation of motor planning with an inability to execute
or actuate the selected motor choice. In this situation, a BCI may provide a
unique opportunity to aid in actuating the nascent premotor commands. By
decoding the brain signals associated with a given motor intention, the BCI
may then convert these signals into commands that could control a robotic
assist device that would allow for improved hand function (i.e., a robotic glove
that opens and closes the hand or a functional electrical simulator that operates
the nerves and muscles of the hand). The BCI would allow the ipsilateral
premotor cortex to bypass the physiological bottleneck determined by injured
and dysfunctional contralateral primary cortex (due to stroke) and the small
and variable percentage of uncrossed motor ﬁbers from ipsilateral M1. This new
methodology would allow for restoration of function in chronically and severely
aﬀected subjects for whom methods of rehabilitation have not accomplished a
suﬃciently recovery.

7
Conclusion
To our knowledge, this work describes the ﬁrst instance of successful de-
tection of individual ﬁnger movements from human ipsilateral ECoG signals.
In this paper, we present a general decoding framework using the following al-
gorithms: (1) ‘1-regularized logistic regression for detecting ﬁnger movement;
(2) Multiclass support vector machines to discriminate between ﬁngers; and
(3) First demonstration of multitask learning into the ECoG signal to improve
decoding accuracy. The results presented here suggest that there exists infor-
mation on the cortex ipsilateral to the moving ﬁngers which can be decoded
with high accuracy using machine learning algorithms. These results present a
great potential in the world of neuroprosthetics and BCI. For patients suﬀering
from stroke and hemiparesis, decoding ﬁnger movements from the unaﬀected

11

hemisphere can be of tremendous help. Our future goals involve simultaneous
decoding of ﬁnger and arm movements (using standard center out joystick task)
from both ipsilateral and contralateral hemispheres. Another important goal is
the real-time use of these decoding results and demonstrate their utility in the
world of BCI.

2 References

[1] H. Aizawa, H. Mushiake, M. Inase, and J. Tanji. An output zone of the mon-
key primary motor cortex specialized for bilateral hand movement. Experimen-
tal Brain Research, 82(1):219?221, 1990.
[2] M. Alamgir, M. Grosse-Wentrup,
and Y. Altun. Multitask learning for brain-computer interfaces. Proceedings of
the Thirteenth International Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence and Statistics,
9:17?24, 2010.
[3] C. Brinkman and R. Porter. Supplementary motor area in
the monkey: activity of neurons during performance of a learned motor task.
Journal of Neurophysiology, 42(3):681, 1979. [4] E. Buch, C. Weber, L. Cohen,
C. Braun, M. Dimyan, T. Ard, J. Mellinger, A. Caria, S. Soekadar, A. Fourkas,
et al. Think to move: a neuromagnetic brain-computer interface (BCI) sys-
tem for chronic stroke. Stroke, 39(3):910, 2008.
[5] R. Caruana. Multitask
learning. Machine learning, 28:41?75, 1997.
[6] P. Cisek, D. Crammond, and
J. Kalaska. Neural activity in primary motor and dorsal premotor cortex in
reaching tasks with the contralateral versus ipsilateral arm. Journal of neuro-
physiology, 89(2):922, 2003. [7] C. Cortes and V. Vapnik. Support-vector net-
works. Machine learning, 20(3):273?297, 1995. [8] K. Crammer and Y. Singer.
On the algorithmic implementation of multiclass kernel-based vector machines.
The Journal of Machine Learning Research, 2:265?292, 2002.
[9] T. Evgeniou
and M. Pontil. Regularized multi?task learning. In KDD, pages 109?117, 2004.
[10] P. Fox, J. Perlmutter, and M. Raichle. A stereotactic method of anatomical
localization for positron emission tomography. Journal of Computer Assisted
Tomography, 9(1):141, 1985.
[11] W. Freeman, M. Holmes, B. Burke, and S.
Vanhatalo. Spatial spectra of scalp eeg and emg from awake humans. Clini-
cal Neurophysiology, 114(6):1053?1068, 2003. [12] A. Georgopoulos, J. Kalaska,
R. Caminiti, and J. Massey. On the relations between the direction of two-
dimensional arm movements and cell discharge in primate motor cortex. Jour-
nal of Neuroscience, 2(11):1527, 1982.
[13] C. Gerloﬀ, K. Bushara, A. Sailer,
E. Wassermann, R. Chen, T. Matsuoka, D. Waldvogel, G. Wittenberg, K. Ishii,
L. Cohen, et al. Multimodal imaging of brain reorganization in motor areas of
the contralesional hemisphere of well recovered patients after capsular stroke.
Brain, 129(3):791, 2006. [14] L. Hochberg, M. Serruya, G. Friehs, J. Mukand, M.
Saleh, A. Caplan, A. Branner, D. Chen, R. Penn, and J. Donoghue. Neuronal
ensemble control of prosthetic devices by a human with tetraplegia. Nature,
442(7099):164?171, 2006.

8
[15] H. Johansen-Berg, M. Rushworth, M. Bogdanovic, U. Kischka, S. Wimalaratna,

and P. Matthews. The role of ipsilateral premotor cortex in hand movement

12

after stroke. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 99(22):14518,
2002. [16] M. Just, V. Cherkassky, S. Aryal, and T. Mitchell. A neurosemantic
theory of concrete noun representation based on the underlying brain codes.
2010. [17] E. Leuthardt, Z. Freudenberg, D. Bundy, and J. Roland. Microscale
recording from human motor cortex: implications for minimally invasive electro-
corticographic brain-computer interfaces. Journal of Neurosurgery: Pediatrics,
27(1), 2009.
[18] K. Miller, S. Makeig, A. Hebb, R. Rao, M. Dennijs, and J.
Ojemann. Cortical electrode localization from x-rays and simple mapping for
electrocorticographic research: The. Journal of neuroscience methods, 162(1-
2):303?308, 2007. [19] D. Moran and A. Schwartz. Motor cortical representation
of speed and direction during reaching. Journal of Neurophysiology, 82(5):2676,
1999.
[20] H. Nakayama, H. J?rgensen, H. Raaschou, and T. Olsen. Recovery
of upper extremity function in stroke patients: the copenhagen stroke study.
Archives of physical medicine and rehabilitation, 75(4):394, 1994. [21] J. New-
ton, A. Sunderland, and P. Gowland. fmri signal decreases in ipsilateral primary
motor cortex during unilateral hand movements are related to duration and side
of movement. Neuroimage, 24(4):1080?1087, 2005. [22] R. Nyberg-Hansen and
A. Brodal. Sites of termination of corticospinal ﬁbers in the cat. an experimen-
tal study with silver impregnation methods. The Journal of Comparative Neu-
rology, 120(3):369?391, 2004. [23] S. Petersen, P. Fox, M. Posner, M. Mintum,
and M. Raichle. Positron emission tomographic studies of the cortical anatomy
of single-word processing. Cognitive psychology: key readings, page 109, 2004.
[24] G. Pfurtscheller and A. Aranibar. Event-related cortical desynchronization
detected by power measurements of scalp EEG* 1. Electroencephalography and
Clinical Neurophysiology, 42(6):817?826, 1977. [25] G. Pfurtscheller, C. Guger,
G. Muller, G. Krausz, and C. Neuper. Brain oscillations control hand orthosis
in a tetraplegic. Neuroscience letters, 292(3):211?214, 2000. [26] S. Ryali and V.
Menon. Feature selection and classiﬁcation of fmri data using logistic regression
with l1 norm regularization. NeuroImage, 47:S57, 2009. [27] G. Schalk, D. Mc-
Farland, T. Hinterberger, N. Birbaumer, and J. Wolpaw. Bci2000: a general-
purpose brain-computer interface system.
IEEE Transactions on Biomedical
Engineering, 51(6):1034?1043, 2004.
[28] R. Seitz, P. Hoﬂich, F. Binkofski, L.
Tellmann, H. Herzog, and H. Freund. Role of the premotor cortex in recovery
from middle cerebral artery infarction. Archives of neurology, 55(8):1081, 1998.
[29] H. Shibasaki and M. Kato. Movement-associated cortical potentials with
unilateral and bilateral simultaneous hand movement. Journal of Neurology,
208(3):191?199, 1975. [30] R. Srinivasan, P. Nunez, R. Silberstein, E. Inc, and
O. Eugene. Spatial ﬁltering and neocortical dynamics: estimates of eeg coher-
ence. IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering, 45(7):814?826, 1998. [31]
C. Tallon-Baudry. Oscillatory synchrony and human visual cognition. Journal
of Physiology-Paris, 97(2-3):355?363, 2003.
[32] J. Tanji, K. Okano, and K.
Sato. Neuronal activity in cortical motor areas related to ipsilateral, contralat-
eral, and bilateral digit movements of the monkey. Journal of neurophysiology,
60(1):325, 1988. [33] I. Tarkka and M. Hallett. Cortical topography of premo-
tor and motor potentials preceding self-paced, voluntary movement of dominant
and non-dominant hands. Electroencephalography and Clinical Neurophysiol-

13

ogy, 75(1-2):36?43, 1990. [34] D. Taylor and A. Schwartz. Direct cortical control
of 3d neuroprosthetic devices. Aug. 17 2004. US Patent App. 10/495,207. [35]
A. Turton, S. Wroe, N. Trepte, C. Fraser, and R. Lemon. Contralateral and
ipsilateral emg responses to transcranial magnetic stimulation during recovery
of arm and hand function after stroke. Electroencephalography and Clinical
Neurophysiology/Electromyography and Motor Control, 101(4):316?328, 1996.
[36] T. Verstynen, J. Diedrichsen, N. Albert, P. Aparicio, and R. Ivry. Ipsilat-
eral motor cortex activity during unimanual hand movements relates to task
complexity. Journal of Neurophysiology, 93(3):1209, 2005.
[37] C. Weiller, F.
Chollet, K. Friston, R. Wise, and R. Frackowiak. Functional reorganization of
the brain in recovery from striatocapsular infarction in man. Annals of Neurol-
ogy, 31(5):463?472, 2004. [38] K. Wisneski, N. Anderson, G. Schalk, M. Smyth,
D. Moran, and E. Leuthardt. Unique cortical physiology associated with ipsi-
lateral hand movements and neuroprosthetic implications. Stroke, 39(12):3351,
2008.
[39] J. Wolpaw, N. Birbaumer, D. McFarland, G. Pfurtscheller, and T.
Vaughan. Brain-computer interfaces for communication and control. Clini-
cal neurophysiology, 113(6):767?791, 2002. [40] J. Wolpaw and D. McFarland.
Control of a two-dimensional movement signal by a noninvasive brain-computer
interface in humans. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the
United States of America, 101(51):17849, 2004.

9

14

