Spectral Methods for Learning Multivariate

Latent Tree Structure

Authored by:

Tong Zhang

Sham M. Kakade

Le Song

Daniel J. Hsu

Kamalika Chaudhuri

Animashree Anandkumar

Abstract

This work considers the problem of learning the structure of multi-
variate linear tree models, which include a variety of directed tree graph-
ical models with continuous, discrete, and mixed latent variables such as
linear-Gaussian models, hidden Markov models, Gaussian mixture mod-
els, and Markov evolutionary trees. The setting is one where we only
have samples from certain observed variables in the tree, and our goal is
to estimate the tree structure (i.e., the graph of how the underlying hid-
den variables are connected to each other and to the observed variables).
We propose the Spectral Recursive Grouping algorithm, an eﬃcient and
simple bottom-up procedure for recovering the tree structure from inde-
pendent samples of the observed variables. Our ﬁnite sample size bounds
for exact recovery of the tree structure reveal certain natural dependen-
cies on underlying statistical and structural properties of the underlying
joint distribution. Furthermore, our sample complexity guarantees have
no explicit dependence on the dimensionality of the observed variables,
making the algorithm applicable to many high-dimensional settings. At
the heart of our algorithm is a spectral quartet test for determining the
relative topology of a quartet of variables from second-order statistics.

1 Paper Body

Graphical models are a central tool in modern machine learning applications, as
they provide a natural methodology for succinctly representing high-dimensional
distributions. As such, they have enjoyed much success in various AI and ma-
chine learning applications such as natural language processing, speech recogni-
tion, robotics, computer vision, and bioinformatics. The main statistical chal-
lenges associated with graphical models include estimation and inference. While

1

the body of techniques for probabilistic inference in graphical models is rather
rich [1], current methods for tackling the more challenging problems of param-
eter and structure estimation are less developed and understood, especially in
the presence of latent (hidden) variables. The problem of parameter estimation
involves determining the model parameters from samples of certain observed
variables. Here, the predominant approach is the expectation maximization
(EM) algorithm, and only rather recently is the understanding of this algorithm
improving [2, 3]. The problem of structure learning is to estimate the under-
lying graph of the graphical model. In general, structure learning is NP-hard
and becomes even more challenging when some variables are unobserved [4].
The main approaches for structure estimation are either greedy or local search
approaches [5, 6] or, more recently, based on convex relaxation [7]. 1

z1 z2
z3 h g

z4{{z1 , z2 }, {z3 , z4 }} (a)

z1 z3
z2 h g
z1
z4

z4{{z1 , z3 }, {z2 , z4 }} (b)

z2 h g

z3{{z1 , z4 }, {z2 , z3 }} (c)

z1 z4
z2 h

z3{{z1 , z2 , z3 , z4 }} (d)
Figure 1: The four possible (undirected) tree topologies over leaves {z1 , z2 ,
z3 , z4 }. This work focuses on learning the structure of multivariate latent tree
graphical models. Here, the underlying graph is a directed tree (e.g., hidden
Markov model, binary evolutionary tree), and only samples from a set of (mul-
tivariate) observed variables (the leaves of the tree) are available for learning
the structure. Latent tree graphical models are relevant in many applications,
ranging from computer vision, where one may learn object/scene structure from
the co-occurrences of objects to aid image understanding [8]; to phylogenetics,
where the central task is to reconstruct the tree of life from the genetic material
of surviving species [9]. Generally speaking, methods for learning latent tree
structure exploit structural properties aﬀorded by the tree that are revealed
through certain statistical tests over every choice of four variables in the tree.
These quartet tests, which have origins in structural equation modeling [10, 11],
are hypothesis tests of the relative conﬁguration of four (possibly non-adjacent)
nodes/variables in the tree (see Figure 1); they are also related to the four
point condition associated with a corresponding additive tree metric induced
by the distribution [12]. Some early methods for learning tree structure are

2

based on the use of exact correlation statistics or distance measurements (e.g.,
[13, 14]). Unfortunately, these methods ignore the crucial aspect of estima-
tion error, which ultimately governs their sample complexity. Indeed, this (lack
of) robustness to estimation error has been quantiﬁed for various algorithms
(notably, for the popular Neighbor Joining algorithm [15, 16]), and therefore
serves as a basis for comparing diﬀerent methods. Subsequent work in the
area of mathematical phylogenetics has focused on the sample complexity of
evolutionary tree reconstruction [17, 15, 18, 19]. The basic model there cor-
responds to a directed tree over discrete random variables, and much of the
recent eﬀort deals exclusively in the regime for a certain model parameter (the
Kesten-Stigum regime [20]) that allows for a sample complexity that is polylog-
arithmic in the number of leaves, as opposed to polynomial [18, 19]. Finally,
recent work in machine learning has developed structure learning methods for
latent tree graphical models that extend beyond the discrete distributions of
evolutionary trees [21], thereby widening their applicability to other problem
domains. This work extends beyond previous studies, which have focused on
latent tree models with either discrete or scalar Gaussian variables, by directly
addressing the multivariate setting where hidden and observed nodes may be
random vectors rather than scalars. The generality of our techniques allows us
to handle a much wider class of distributions than before, both in terms of the
conditional independence properties imposed by the models (i.e., the random
vector associated with a node need not follow a distribution that corresponds
to a tree model), as well as other characteristics of the node distributions (e.g.,
some nodes in the tree could have discrete state spaces and others continuous,
as in a Gaussian mixture model). We propose the Spectral Recursive Grouping
algorithm for learning multivariate latent tree structure. The algorithm has at
its core a multivariate spectral quartet test, which extends the classical quar-
tet tests for scalar variables by applying spectral techniques from multivariate
statistics (speciﬁcally canonical correlation analysis [22, 23]). Spectral methods
have enjoyed recent success in the context of parameter estimation [24, 25, 26,
27]; our work shows that they are also useful for structure learning. We use
the spectral quartet test in a simple modiﬁcation of the recursive grouping al-
gorithm of [21] to perform the tree reconstruction. The algorithm is essentially
a robust method for reasoning about the results of quartet tests (viewed simply
as hypothesis tests); the tests either conﬁrm or reject hypotheses about the rel-
ative topology over quartets of variables. By carefully choosing which tests to
consider and properly interpreting their results, the algorithm is able to recover
the correct latent tree structure (with high probability) in a provably eﬃcient
manner, in terms of both computational and sample complexity. The recursive
grouping procedure is similar to the short quartet method from phylogenetics
[15], which also guarantees eﬃcient reconstruction in the context of evolutionary
trees. However, our method and analysis applies to considerably more general
high-dimensional settings; for instance, our sample complexity bound is given
in terms of natural correlation con2

ditions that generalize the more restrictive eﬀective depth conditions of pre-
vious works [15, 21]. Finally, we note that while we do not directly address the

3

question of parameter estimation, provable parameter estimation methods may
derived using the spectral techniques from [24, 25].

.

.

, xn } and internal nodes Vhid := {h1 , h2 , .

2 2.1
Preliminaries Latent variable tree models
Let T be a connected, directed tree graphical model with leaves Vobs :=
{x1 , x2 , .
, hm
} such that every node has at most one parent. The leaves are termed the
observed variables and the internal nodes hidden variables. Note that all nodes
in this work generally correspond to multivariate random vectors; we will abuse
terminology and still refer to these random vectors as random variables. For
any h ? Vhid , let ChildrenT (h) ? VT denote the children of h in T. Each
observed variable x ? Vobs is modeled as random vector in Rd , and each hidden
variable h ? Vhid as a random vector in Rk . The joint distribution over all
the variables VT := Vobs ? Vhid is assumed satisfy conditional independence
properties speciﬁed by the tree structure over the variables. Speciﬁcally, for any
disjoint subsets V1 , V2 , V3 ? VT such that V3 separates V1 from V2 in T,
the variables in V1 are conditionally independent of those in V2 given V3 . 2.2

.

.

Structural and distributional assumptions
The class of models considered are speciﬁed by the following structural and
distributional assumptions. Condition 1 (Linear conditional means). Fix any
hidden variable h ? Vhid . For each hidden child g ? ChildrenT (h) ? Vhid ,
there exists a matrix A(g—h) ? Rk?k such that E[g—h] = A(g—h) h; and for
each observed child x ? ChildrenT (h) ? Vobs , there exists a matrix C(x—h)
? Rd?k such that E[x—h] = C(x—h) h. We refer to the class of tree graphical
models satisfying Condition 1 as linear tree models. Such models include a vari-
ety of continuous and discrete tree distributions (as well as hybrid combinations
of the two, such as Gaussian mixture models) which are widely used in practice.
Continuous linear tree models include linear-Gaussian models and Kalman ﬁl-
ters. In the discrete case, suppose that the observed variables take on d values,
and hidden variables take k values. Then, each variable is represented by a
binary vector in {0, 1}s , where s = d for the observed variables and s = k for
the hidden variables (in particular, if the variable takes value i, then the corre-
sponding vector is the i-th coordinate vector), and any conditional distribution
between the variables is represented by a linear relationship. Thus, discrete
linear tree models include discrete hidden Markov models [25] and Markovian
evolutionary trees [24]. In addition to the linearity, the following conditions are
assumed in order to recover the hidden tree structure. For any matrix M , let
?t (M ) denote its t-th largest singular value. Condition 2 (Rank condition).
The variables in VT = Vhid ? Vobs obey the following rank conditions. 1. For
all h ? Vhid , E[hh? ] has rank k (i.e., ?k (E[hh? ]) ¿ 0). 2. For all h ? Vhid
and hidden child g ? ChildrenT (h) ? Vhid , A(g—h) has rank k. 3. For all
h ? Vhid and observed child x ? ChildrenT (h) ? Vobs , C(x—h) has rank
k. The rank condition is a generalization of parameter identiﬁability conditions
in latent variable models [28, 24, 25] which rules out various (provably) hard
instances in discrete variable settings [24]. 3

h4 h2

4

x3
h1 x1
T1
h3 x4
T2
x6
T3
x5
x2
Figure 2: Set of trees Fh4 = {T1 , T2 , T3 } obtained if h4 is removed.
Condition 3 (Non-redundancy condition). Each hidden variable has at least
three neighbors. Furthermore, there exists ?2max ¿ 0 such that for each pair of
distinct hidden variables h, g ? Vhid , det(E[hg ? ])2 ? ?2max ¡ 1. det(E[hh?
]) det(E[gg ? ]) The requirement for each hidden node to have three neighbors
is natural; otherwise, the hidden node can be eliminated. The quantity ?max
is a natural multivariate generalization of correlation. First, note that ?max
? 1, and that if ?max = 1 is achieved with some h and g, then h and g are
completely correlated, implying the existence of a deterministic map between
hidden nodes h and g; hence simply merging the two nodes into a single node h
(or g) resolves this issue. Therefore the non-redundancy condition simply means
that any two hidden nodes h and g cannot be further reduced to a single node.
Clearly, this condition is necessary for the goal of identifying the correct tree
structure, and it is satisﬁed as soon as h and g have limited correlation in just
a single direction. Previous works [13, 29] show that an analogous condition
ensures identiﬁability for general latent tree models (and in fact, the conditions
are identical in the Gaussian case). Condition 3 is therefore a generalization
of this condition suitable for the multivariate setting. Our learning guarantees
also require a correlation condition that generalize the explicit depth conditions
considered in the phylogenetics literature [15, 24]. To state this condition, ﬁrst
deﬁne Fh to be the set of subtrees of that remain after a hidden variable h ?
Vhid is removed from T (see Figure 2). Also, for any subtree T ? of T, let
Vobs [T ? ] ? Vobs be the observed variables in T ? . Condition 4 (Correlation
condition). There exists ?min ¿ 0 such that for all hidden variables h ? Vhid
and all triples of subtrees {T1 , T2 , T3 } ? Fh in the forest obtained if h is
removed from T, max

min
x1 ?Vobs [T1 ],x2 ?Vobs [T2 ],x3 ?Vobs [T3 ] {i,j}?{1,2,3}
?k (E[xi x? j ]) ? ?min .
The quantity ?min is related to the eﬀective depth of T, which is the maxi-
mum graph distance between a hidden variable and its closest observed variable
[15, 21]. The eﬀective depth is at most logarithmic in the number of variables
(as achieved by a complete binary tree), though it can also be a constant if every
hidden variable is close to an observed variable (e.g., in a hidden Markov model,
the eﬀective depth is 1, even though the true depth, or diameter, is m + 1). If
the matrices giving the (conditionally) linear relationship between neighboring
variables in T are all well-conditioned, then ?min is at worst exponentially small

5

in the eﬀective depth, and therefore at worst polynomially small in the number
of variables. Finally, also deﬁne ?max :=

max{x1 ,x2 }?Vobs
{?1 (E[x1 x? 2 ])}
to be the largest spectral norm of any second-moment matrix between ob-
served variables. Note ?max ? 1 in the discrete case, and, in the continuous
case, ?max ? 1 if each observed random vector is in isotropic position. In this
work, the Euclidean norm of a vector x is denoted by ?x?, and the (induced)
spectral norm of a matrix A is denoted by ?A?, i.e., ?A? := ?1 (A) = sup{?Ax?
: ?x? = 1}. 4
Algorithm 1 SpectralQuartetTest on observed variables {z1 , z2 , z3 , z4 }.
?i,j of the second-moment matrix Input: For each pair {i, j} ? {1, 2, 3, 4}, an
empirical estimate ? ? E[zi zj ] and a corresponding conﬁdence parameter ?i,j
¿ 0. Output: Either a pairing {{zi , zj }, {zi? , zj ? }} or ?. 1: if there exists a
partition of {z1 , z2 , z3 , z4 } = {zi , zj } ? {zi? , zj ? } such that k ?

s=1
?i,j ) ? ?i,j ]+ [?s (? ?i? ,j ? ) ? ?i? ,j ? ]+ ¿ [?s (?
then return the pairing {{zi , zj }, {zi? , zj ? }}.
k ?
?i? ,j ) + ?i? ,j )(?s (? ?i,j ? ) + ?i,j ? ) (?s (?
s=1
2: else return ?.
3
Spectral quartet tests
This section describes the core of our learning algorithm, a spectral quartet
test that determines topology of the subtree induced by four observed variables
{z1 , z2 , z3 , z4 }. There are four possibilities for the induced subtree, as
shown in Figure 1. Our quartet test either returns the correct induced subtree
among possibilities in Figure 1(a)?(c); or it outputs ? to indicate abstinence.
If the test returns ?, then no guarantees are provided on the induced subtree
topology. If it does return a subtree, then the output is guaranteed to be the
correct induced subtree (with high probability). The quartet test proposed is
described in Algorithm 1 (SpectralQuartetTest). The notation [a]+ denotes
max{0, a} and [t] (for an integer t) denotes the set {1, 2, . . . , t}.
The quartet test is deﬁned with respect to four observed variables Z := {z1
, z2 , z3 , z4 }. For each ?i,j of the second-moment matrix pair of variables zi
and zj , it takes as input an empirical estimate ? E[zi zj? ], and conﬁdence
bound parameters ?i,j which are functions of N , the number of samples ?i,j ?s,
a conﬁdence parameter ?, and of properties of the distributions of zi and used
to compute the ? zj . In practice, one uses a single threshold ? for all pairs,
which is tuned by the algorithm. Our theoretical analysis also applies to this
case. The output of the test is either ? or a pairing of the variables {{zi , zj },
{zi? , zj ? }}. For example, if the output is the pairing is {{z1 , z2 }, {z3 , z4
}}, then Figure 1(a) is the output topology. Even though the conﬁguration in
Figure 1(d) is a possibility, the spectral quartet test never returns {{z1 , z2 , z3

6

, z4 }}, as there is no correct pairing of Z. The topology {{z1 , z2 , z3 , z4 }}
can be viewed as a degenerate case of {{z1 , z2 }, {z3 , z4 }} (say) where the
hidden variables h and g are deterministically identical, and Condition 3 fails
to hold with respect to h and g. 3.1

Properties of the spectral quartet test
With exact second moments: The spectral quartet test is motivated by the
following lemma, which shows the relationship between the singular values of
second-moment matrices of the zi ?s and the ?k induced topology among them
in the latent tree. Let detk (M ) := s=1 ?s (M ) denote the product of the k
largest singular values of a matrix M . Lemma 1 (Perfect quartet test). Suppose
that the observed variables Z = {z1 , z2 , z3 , z4 } have the true induced tree
topology shown in Figure 1(a), and the tree model satisﬁes Condition 1 and
Condition 2. Then detk (E[z1 z3? ])detk (E[z2 z4? ]) detk (E[z1 z4? ])detk
(E[z2 z3? ]) det(E[hg ? ])2 = = ?1 det(E[hh? ]) det(E[gg ? ]) detk (E[z1
z2? ])detk (E[z3 z4? ]) detk (E[z1 z2? ])detk (E[z3 z4? ]) (1) and detk (E[z1
z3? ])detk (E[z2 z4? ]) = detk (E[z1 z4? ])detk (E[z2 z3? ]). This lemma
shows that given the true second-moment matrices and assuming Condition 3,
the inequality in (1) becomes strict and thus can be used to deduce the correct
topology: the correct pairing is {{zi , zj }, {zi? , zj ? }} if and only if detk (E[zi
zj? ])detk (E[zi? zj?? ]) ¿ detk (E[zi? zj? ])detk (E[zi zj?? ]). 5

Reliability: The next lemma shows that even if the singular values of E[zi
zj? ] are not known exactly, then with valid conﬁdence intervals (that contain
these singular values) a robust test can be constructed which is reliable in the
following sense: if it does not output ?, then the output topology is indeed the
correct topology. Lemma 2 (Reliability). Consider the setup of Lemma 1, and
suppose that Figure 1(a) is the ?i,j ) ? ?i,j ? correct topology. If for all pairs
{zi , zj } ? Z and all s ? [k], ?s (? ? ? ?s (E[zi zj ]) ? ?s (?i,j ) + ?i,j , and if
SpectralQuartetTest returns a pairing {{zi , zj }, {zi? , zj ? }}, then {{zi , zj
}, {zi? , zj ? }} = {{z1 , z2 }, {z3 , z4 }}. In other words, the spectral quartet
test never returns an incorrect pairing as long as the singular ?i,j . The lemma
values of E[zi zj? ] lie in an interval of length 2?i,j around the singular values
of ? below shows how to set the ?i,j s as a function of N , ? and properties of
the distributions of zi and zj so that this required event holds with probability
at least 1 ? ?. We remark that any valid conﬁdence intervals may be used;
the one described below is particularly suitable when the observed variables are
high-dimensional random vectors. Lemma 3 (Conﬁdence intervals). Let Z =
{z1 , z2 , z3 , z4 } be four random vectors. Let ?zi ? ? Mi ?i,j is computed using
almost surely, and let ? ? (0, 1/6). If each empirical second-moment matrix ?
N iid copies of zi and zj , and if E[?zi ?2 ?zj ?2 ] ? tr(E[zi zj? ]E[zi zj? ]? )
, ti,j := 1.55 ln(24d?i,j /?), max{?E[?zj ?2 zi zi? ]?, ?E[?zi ?2 zj zj? ]?} ? ?
? ?? ?? 2 max ?E[?zj ?2 zi zi? ]?, ?E[?zi ?2 zj zj? ]? ti,j Mi Mj ti,j ?i,j ? + , N
3N then with probability 1 ? ?, for all pairs {zi , zj } ? Z and all s ? [k], ?i,j )
? ?i,j ? ?s (E[zi z ? ]) ? ?s (? ?i,j ) + ?i,j . ?s ( ? d?i,j :=

j
(2)
Conditions for returning a correct pairing: The conditions under which Spec-

7

tralQuartetTest returns an induced topology (as opposed to ?) are now pro-
vided.

An important quantity in this analysis is the level of non-redundancy be-
tween the hidden variables h and g. Let det(E[hg ? ])2 ?2 := . (3) det(E[hh? ])
det(E[gg ? ]) If Figure 1(a) is the correct induced topology among {z1 , z2 , z3
, z4 }, then the smaller ? is, the greater the gap between detk (E[z1 z2? ])detk
(E[z3 z4? ]) and either of detk (E[z1 z3? ])detk (E[z2 z4? ]) and detk (E[z1 z4?
])detk (E[z2 z3? ]). Therefore, ? also governs how small the ?i,j need to be for
the quartet test to return a correct pairing; this is quantiﬁed in Lemma 4. Note
that Condition 3 implies ? ? ?max ¡ 1. Lemma 4 (Correct pairing). Suppose
that (i) the observed variables Z = {z1 , z2 , z3 , z4 } have the true induced
tree topology shown in Figure 1(a); (ii) the tree model satisﬁes Condition 1,
Condition 2, and ? ¡ 1 (where ? is deﬁned in (3)), and (iii) the conﬁdence
bounds in (2) hold for all {i, j} and all s ? [k]. If ? 1 ? 1 ?i,j ¡ ? min 1, ? 1
? min{?k (E[zi zj? ])} 8k ? {i,j} for each pair {i, j}, then SpectralQuartetTest
returns the correct pairing {{z1 , z2 }, {z3 , z4 }}.

4
The Spectral Recursive Grouping algorithm
The Spectral Recursive Grouping algorithm, presented as Algorithm 2, uses
the spectral quartet test discussed in the previous section to estimate the struc-
ture of a multivariate latent tree distribution from iid samples of the observed
leaf variables.1 The algorithm is a modiﬁcation of the recursive 1 ?x,y and
threshold parameTo simplify notation, we assume that the estimated second-
moment matrices ? ters ?x,y ? 0 for all pairs {x, y} ? Vobs are globally deﬁned.
In particular, we assume the spectral quartet tests use these quantities.

6
Algorithm 2 Spectral Recursive Grouping. ?x,y for all pairs {x, y} ? Vobs
computed from N iid Input: Empirical second-moment matrices ? samples from
the distribution over Vobs ; threshold parameters ?x,y for all pairs {x, y} ?
Vobs . ? or ?failure?. Output: Tree structure T 1: let R := Vobs , and for all
x ? R, T [x] := rooted single-node tree x and L[x] := {x}. 2: while —R— ¿ 1
do 3: let pair {u, v} ? {{? u, v?} ? R : Mergeable(R, L[?], u ?, v?) = true}
be such that ?x,y ) : (x, y) ? L[u] ? L[v]} is maximized. If no such pair exists,
then halt max{?k (? and return ?failure?. 4: let result := Relationship(R, L[?],
T [?], u, v). 5: if result = ?siblings? then 6: Create a new variable h, create
subtree T [h] rooted at h by joining T [u] and T [v] to h with edges {h, u}
and {h, v}, and set L[h] := L[u] ? L[v]. 7: Add h to R, and remove u and v
from R. 8: else if result = ?u is parent of v? then 9: Modify subtree T [u] by
joining T [v] to u with an edge {u, v}, and modify L[u] := L[u] ? L[v]. 10:
Remove v from R. 11: else if result = ?v is parent of u? then 12: {Analogous to
above case.} 13: end if 14: end while ? := T [h] where R = {h}. 15: Return T
grouping (RG) procedure proposed in [21]. RG builds the tree in a bottom-up
fashion, where the initial working set of variables are the observed variables.
The variables in the working set always correspond to roots of disjoint subtrees
of T discovered by the algorithm. (Note that because these subtrees are rooted,
they naturally induce parent/child relationships, but these may diﬀer from those

8

implied by the edge directions in T.) In each iteration, the algorithm determines
which variables in the working set to combine. If the variables are combined as
siblings, then a new hidden variable is introduced as their parent and is added
to the working set, and its children are removed. If the variables are combined
as neighbors (parent/child), then the child is removed from the working set.
The process repeats until the entire tree is constructed. Our modiﬁcation of
RG uses the spectral quartet tests from Section 3 to decide which subtree roots
in the current working set to combine. Note that because the test may return
? (a null result), our algorithm uses the tests to rule out possible siblings
or neighbors among variables in the working set?this is encapsulated in the
subroutine Mergeable (Algorithm 3), which tests quartets of observed variables
(leaves) in the subtrees rooted at working set variables. For any pair {u, v} ?
R submitted to the subroutine (along with the current working set R and leaf
sets L[?]): ? Mergeable returns false if there is evidence (provided by a quartet
test) that u and v should ﬁrst be joined with diﬀerent variables (u? and v ?
, respectively) before joining with each other; and ? Mergeable returns true
if no quartet test provides such evidence. The subroutine is also used by the
subroutine Relationship (Algorithm 4) which determines whether a candidate
pair of variables should be merged as neighbors (parent/child) or as siblings:
essentially, to check if u is a parent of v, it checks if v is a sibling of each child
of u. The use of unreliable estimates of long-range correlations is avoided by
only considering highly-correlated variables as candidate pairs to merge (where
correlation is measured using observed variables in their corresponding subtrees
as proxies). This leads to a sample-eﬃcient algorithm for recovering the hidden
tree structure. The Spectral Recursive Grouping algorithm enjoys the following
guarantee. Theorem 1. Let ? ? (0, 1). Assume the directed tree graphical model
T over variables (random vectors) VT = Vobs ? Vhid satisﬁes Conditions 1, 2,
3, and 4. Suppose the Spectral Recursive 7

Algorithm 3 Subroutine Mergeable(R, L[?], u, v). Input: Set of nodes R;
leaf sets L[v] for all v ? R; distinct u, v ? R. Output: true or false. 1: if there
exists distinct u? , v ? ? R {u, v} and (x, y, x? , y ? ) ? L[u] ? L[v] ?
L[u? ] ? L[v ? ] s.t. SpectralQuartetTest({x, y, x? , y ? }) returns {{x, x?
}, {y, y ? }} or {{x, y ? }, {x? , y}} then return false. 2: else return true.
Algorithm 4 Subroutine Relationship(R, L[?], T [?], u, v). Input: Set of nodes
R; leaf sets L[v] for all v ? R; rooted subtrees T [v] for all v ? R; distinct u,
v ? R. Output: ?siblings?, ?u is parent of v? (?u ? v?), or ?v is parent of u?
(?v ? u?). 1:
if v is a leaf then assert v
?? u. 3: let R[w] := (R {w}) ? {w ? : w ? is a child of w in T [w]} for each
w ? {u, v}. 4: if there exists child u1 of u in T [u] s.t. Mergeable(R[u], L[?],
u1 , v) = false then assert ?u ?? v?. 5:
if there exists child v1 of v in T [v]
s.t. Mergeable(R[v], L[?], u, v1 ) = false then assert ?v ?? u?. 6: if both ?u ??
v? and ?v ?? u? were asserted then return ?siblings?. 7: else if ?u ?? v? was
asserted then return ?v is parent of u? (?v ? u?). 8: else return ?u is parent
of v? (?u ? v?). Grouping algorithm (Algorithm 2) is provided N independent
samples from the distribution over Vobs , and uses parameters given by ? 2Bxi
,xj txi ,xj Mxi Mxj txi ,xj ?xi ,xj := + (4) N 3N where

if u is a leaf then assert u ?? v. 2:

9

? ? ?? ?? 2 ? ? ? ? Bxi ,xj := max ?E[?xi ?2 xj x? , j ] , E[?xj ? xi xi ]

d?xi ,xj :=

E[?xi ? ?xj ? ] ? tr(E[xi x? ]E[xj x? i ]) ? ? j ?? ?? ?, ?E[?xi ?2 xj x? ]? ,

max ?E[?xj ?2 xi x? ] i j 2

2
Mxi ? ?xi ?
almost surely,
txi ,xj := 4 ln(4d?xi ,xj n/?).
Let B := maxxi ,xj ?Vobs {Bxi ,xj }, M := maxxi ?Vobs {Mxi }, t := maxxi

,xj ?Vobs {txi ,xj }. If N¿?

200 ? k 2 ? B ? t
2 ?min ? (1 ? ?max ) ?max
?2 +
7 ? k ? M2 ? t
2 ?min ? (1 ? ?max ) ?max
,
? with then with probability at least 1 ? ?, the Spectral Recursive Grouping

algorithm returns a tree T the same undirected graph structure as T.

Consistency is implied by the above theorem with an appropriate scaling of
? with N . The theorem reveals that the sample complexity of the algorithm de-
pends solely on intrinsic spectral properties of the distribution. Note that there
is no explicit dependence on the dimensions of the observable variables, which
makes the result applicable to high-dimensional settings. Acknowledgements
Part of this work was completed while DH was at the Wharton School of the
University of Pennsylvania and at Rutgers University. AA was supported by in
part by the setup funds at UCI and the AFOSR Award FA9550-10-1-0310.

2 References

[1] M. J. Wainwright and M. I. Jordan. Graphical models, exponential families,
and variational inference. Foundations and Trends in Machine Learning, 1(1-
2):1?305, 2008.

8
[2] S. Dasgupta and L. Schulman. A probabilistic analysis of EM for mix-
tures of separated, spherical Gaussians. Journal of Machine Learning Research,
8(Feb):203?226, 2007. [3] K. Chaudhuri, S. Dasgupta, and A. Vattani. Learn-
ing mixtures of Gaussians using the k-means algorithm, 2009. arXiv:0912.0086.
[4] D. M. Chickering, D. Heckerman, and C. Meek. Large-sample learning of
Bayesian networks is NP-hard. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 5:1287?1330,
[5] C. Chow and C. Liu. Approximating discrete probability distri-
2004.
IEEE Transactions on Information Theory,
butions with dependence trees.
[6] N. Friedman, I. Nachman, and D. Pe?er. Learning
14(3):462?467, 1968.
Bayesian network structure from massive datasets: the ?sparse candidate? al-
gorithm. In Fifteenth Conference on Uncertainty in Artiﬁcial Intelligence, 1999.
[7] P. Ravikumar, M. J. Wainwright, and J. Laﬀerty. High-dimensional Ising

10

model selection using ?1 regularized logistic regression. Annals of Statistics,
38(3):1287?1319, 2010. [8] M. J. Choi, J. J. Lim, A. Torralba, and A. S. Will-
sky. Exploiting hierarchical context on a large database of object categories. In
IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, 2010.
[9] R.
Durbin, S. R. Eddy, A. Krogh, and G. Mitchison. Biological Sequence Analy-
sis: Probabilistic Models of Proteins and Nucleic Acids. Cambridge University
[10] J. Wishart. Sampling errors in the theory of two factors.
Press, 1999.
[11] K. Bollen. Structural
British Journal of Psychology, 19:180?187, 1928.
Equation Models with Latent Variables. John Wiley & Sons, 1989.
[12] P.
Buneman. The recovery of trees from measurements of dissimilarity. In F. R.
Hodson, D. G. Kendall, and P. Tautu, editors, Mathematics in the Archae-
[13] J. Pearl and M.
ological and Historical Sciences, pages 387?395. 1971.
Tarsi. Structuring causal trees. Journal of Complexity, 2(1):60?77, 1986.
[14]
N. Saitou and M. Nei. The neighbor-joining method: A new method for re-
constructing phylogenetic trees. Molecular Biology and Evolution, 4:406?425,
1987. [15] P. L. Erd?os, L. A. Sz?ekely, M. A. Steel, and T. J. Warnow. A few
logs suﬃce to build (almost) all trees: Part II. Theoretical Computer Science,
221:77?118, 1999. [16] M. R. Lacey and J. T. Chang. A signal-to-noise analysis
of phylogeny estimation by neighbor-joining: insuﬃciency of polynomial length
sequences. Mathematical Biosciences, 199(2):188?215, 2006. [17] P. L. Erd?os,
L. A. Sz?ekely, M. A. Steel, and T. J. Warnow. A few logs suﬃce to build (al-
most) all trees (I). Random Structures and Algorithms, 14:153?184, 1999. [18]
E. Mossel. Phase transitions in phylogeny. Transactions of the American Math-
ematical Society, 356(6):2379?2404, 2004. [19] C. Daskalakis, E. Mossel, and S.
Roch. Evolutionary trees and the Ising model on the Bethe lattice: A proof of
Steel?s conjecture. Probability Theory and Related Fields, 149(1?2):149?189,
2011.
[20] H. Kesten and B. P. Stigum. Additional limit theorems for inde-
composable multidimensional galtonwatson processes. Annals of Mathematical
Statistics, 37:1463?1481, 1966.
[21] M. J. Choi, V. Tan, A. Anandkumar, and
A. Willsky. Learning latent tree graphical models. Journal of Machine Learning
Research, 12:1771?1812, 2011. [22] M. S. Bartlett. Further aspects of the the-
ory of multiple regression. Mathematical Proceedings of the Cambridge Philo-
sophical Society, 34:33?40, 1938.
[23] R. J. Muirhead and C. M. Waternaux.
Asymptotic distributions in canonical correlation analysis and other multivari-
ate procedures for nonnormal populations. Biometrika, 67(1):31?43, 1980. [24]
E. Mossel and S. Roch. Learning nonsingular phylogenies and hidden Markov
models. Annals of Applied Probability, 16(2):583?614, 2006. [25] D. Hsu, S. M.
Kakade, and T. Zhang. A spectral algorithm for learning hidden Markov mod-
els. In Twenty-Second Annual Conference on Learning Theory, 2009.
[26] S.
M. Siddiqi, B. Boots, and G. J. Gordon. Reduced-rank hidden Markov models.
In Thirteenth International Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence and Statistics,
2010. [27] L. Song, S. M. Siddiqi, G. J. Gordon, and A. J. Smola. Hilbert space
embeddings of hidden Markov models. In International Conference on Machine
Learning, 2010.
Identiﬁa-
bility of parameters in latent structure models with many observed variables.
The Annals of Statistics, 37(6A):3099?3132, 2009.
[29] J. Pearl. Probabilis-

[28] E. S. Allman, C. Matias, and J. A. Rhodes.

11

tic Reasoning in Intelligent Systems?Networks of Plausible Inference. Morgan
Kaufmann, 1988.
[30] D. Hsu, S. M. Kakade, and T. Zhang. Dimension-free
tail inequalities for sums of random matrices, 2011. arXiv:1104.1672.

9

12

