Convergent Bounds on the Euclidean Distance

Authored by:

Yoonho Hwang
Hee-kap Ahn

Abstract

Given a set V of n vectors in d-dimensional space, we provide an
eﬃcient method for computing quality upper and lower bounds of the
Euclidean distances between a pair of the vectors in V . For this purpose,
we deﬁne a distance measure, called the MS-distance, by using the mean
and the standard deviation values of vectors in V . Once we compute
the mean and the standard deviation values of vectors in V in O(dn)
time, the MS-distance between them provides upper and lower bounds
of Euclidean distance between a pair of vectors in V in constant time.
Furthermore, these bounds can be reﬁned further such that they converge
monotonically to the exact Euclidean distance within d reﬁnement steps.
We also provide an analysis on a random sequence of reﬁnement steps
which can justify why MS-distance should be reﬁned to provide very tight
bounds in a few steps of a typical sequence. The MS-distance can be used
to various problems where the Euclidean distance is used to measure the
proximity or similarity between objects. We provide experimental results
on the nearest and the farthest neighbor searches.

1 Paper Body

The Euclidean distance between two vectors x and y in d-dimensional space is
a typical distance measure that reﬂects their proximity in the space. Measuring
the Euclidean distance is a fundamental operation in computer science, including
the areas of database, computational geometry, computer vision and computer
graphics. In machine learning, the Euclidean distance, denoted by dist(x, y),
or it?s variations(for example, e——x?y—— ) are widely used to measure data
similarity for clustering [1], classiﬁcation [2] and so on. A typical problem is
as follows. Given two sets X and Y of vectors in d-dimensional space, our
goal is to ﬁnd a pair (x, y), for x ? X and y ? Y , such that dist(x, y)
is the optimum (minimum or maximum) over all such pairs. For the nearest
or farthest neighbor searches, X is the set consisting of a single query point
while Y consists of all candidate data points. If the dimension is low, a brute-
force computation would be fast enough. However, data sets in areas such as
optimization, computer vision, machine learning or statistics often live in spaces

1

of dimensionality in the order of thousands or millions. In d dimensional space,
a single distance computation already takes O(d) time, thus the cost for ﬁnding
the nearest or farthest neighbor becomes O(dnm) time, where n and m are the
cardinalities of X and Y , respectively. Several techniques have been proposed
to reduce computation cost for computing distance. Probably PCA (principal
component analysis) is the most frequently used technique for this purpose [3],
in which we use an orthogonal transformation based on PCA to convert a set of
given data so that the dimensionality of the transformed data is reduced. Then
it computes distances between pairs of transformed data eﬃciently. However,
this transformation does not preserve the pairwise distances of data in general,
therefore there is no guarantee on the computation results. 1

If we restrict ourselves to the nearest neighbor search, some methods us-
ing space partitioning trees such as KD-tree [4], R-tree [5], or their variations
have been widely used. However, they become impractical for high dimensions
because of their poor performance in constructing data structures for queries.
Recently, cover tree [6] has been used for high dimensional nearest neighbor
search, but its construction time increases drastically as the dimension increases
[7]. Another approach that has attracted some attention is to compute a good
bound of the exact Euclidean distance eﬃciently such that it can be used to ﬁlter
oﬀ some unnecessary computation, for example, the distance computation be-
tween two vectors that are far apart from each other in nearest neighbor search.
One of such methods is to compute a distance bound using the inner product
approximation [8]. This method, however, requires the distribution of the input
data to be known in advance, and works only on data in some predetermined
distribution. Another method is to compute a distance bound using bitwise
operations [9]. But this method works well only on uniformly distributed vec-
tors, and requires O(2d ) bitwise operations in d dimension. A method using an
index structure [10] provides an eﬀective ﬁltering method based on the triangle
inequality. But this works well only when data are well clustered. In this paper,
we deﬁne a distance measure, called the MS-distance, by using the mean and
the standard deviation values of vectors in V . Once we compute the mean and
the standard deviation values of vectors in V in O(dn) time, the MS-distance
provides tight upper and lower bounds of Euclidean distance between any pair of
vectors in V in constant time. Furthermore, these bounds can be reﬁned further
in such a way to converge monotonically to the exact Euclidean distance within
d reﬁnement steps. Each reﬁnement step takes constant time. We provide an
analysis on a random sequence of k reﬁnement steps for 0 ? k ? d, which shows
a good expectation on the lower and upper bounds. This can justify that the
MS-distance provides very tight bounds in a few reﬁnement steps of a typical
sequence. We also show that the MS-distance can be used in fast ﬁltering. Note
that we do not use any assumption on data distribution. The MS-distance can
be used to various applications where the Euclidean distance is a measure for
proximity or similarity between objects. Among them, we provide experimental
results on the nearest and the farthest neighbor searches.

2
An Upper and A Lower Bounds of the Euclidean Distance

2

Pd For a d-dimensional vector x = [x1 , x2 , . . . , xd ], we denote its mean
by ?x = d1 i=1 xi and its P d variance by ?x2 = d1 i=1 (xi ? ?x )2 . For a pair
of vectors x and y, we can reformulate the squared Euclidean distance between
x and y as follows. Let a = [a1 , a2 , . . . , ad ] and b = [b1 , b2 , . . . , bd ]
such that ai = xi ? ?x and bi = yi ? ?y . dist(x, y)2 =

d X
(xi ? yi )2
i=1
=
d X
((?x + ai ) ? (?y + bi ))2
i=1
=
d X
(?2x + 2ai ?x + a2i + ?2y + 2bi ?y + b2i ? 2(?x ?y + ai ?y + bi ?x + ai

bi )) (1)

i=1
=
d X
(?2x ? 2?x ?y + ?2y + a2i + b2i ? 2ai bi )
(2)
i=1 d X
= d (?x ? ?y )2 + (?x + ?y )2 ? 2d?x ?y ? 2 ai bi
(3)
i=1 d X
= d (?x ? ?y )2 + (?x ? ?y )2 + 2d?x ?y ? 2 ai bi . i=1
2
(4)
Pd Pd Pd By the deﬁnitions of ai and bi , we have i=1 ai = i=1 bi = 0, and
d1 i=1 a2i = ?x2 . By the ﬁrst properties, equation (1) is simpliﬁed to (2), and
by the second property, equations (2) becomes (3) and (4). Note that equations
(3) and (4) are composed of the mean and variance values (their products and
squared values, multiplied by d) of x and y, except the last summations. Thus,
once we preprocess V of n vectors such that both ?x and ?x for all x ? V are
computed in O(dn) time and stored in a table of size O(n), this sum can be
computed in constant time for any pair of vectors, regardless of the dimension.
Pd The last summation, i ai bi , is the inner product ha, bi, and therefore by
applying the CauchySchwarz inequality we get v u d d d uX X X —ha, bi— =
— ai bi — ? t( (5) a2i )( b2i ) = d?x ?y . i=1

i=1
i=1
This gives us the following upper and lower bounds of the squared Euclidean
distance from equations (3) and (4). Lemma 1 For two d-dimensional vectors
x, y, the followings hold. dist(x, y)2 ? d (?x ? ?y )2 + (?x ? ?y )2 2

2
2

3

dist(x, y) ? d (?x ? ?y ) + (?x + ?y )
3
(6)
(7)
The MS-distance
The lower and upper bounds in inequalities (6) and (7) can be computed in
constant time once we compute the mean and standard variance values of each
vector in V in the preprocessing. However, in some applications these bounds
may not be tight enough. In this section, we introduce the MSdistance which
not only provides lower and upper bounds of the Euclidean distance in constant
time, but also could be reﬁned further in such a way to converge to the exact
Euclidean distance within d steps. To do this, we reformulate equations (3) and
(4), that is, the inner product ha, bi. If qP the last term ofq Pd Pd d 2 2 the
norms ——a—— = i=1 ai or ——b—— = i=1 bi are zero, then i=1 ai bi = 0,
thus the upper and lower bounds become the same. This implies that we can
compute the exact Euclidean distance in constant time. So from now on, we
assume that both ——a—— and ——b—— are non-zero. We reformulate the
inner product ha, bi. d X

ai bi = d?x ?y ? d?x ?y +
i=1
d X
ai bi
i=1
?x ?y = d?x ?y ? 2
! d X 2ai bi 2d ? ? ? i=1 x y ! 2 X 2 X d d d X ai bi 2ai bi + ? ?x ?y ? ?

i=1 i=1 i=1 x y

= d?x ?y ?
?x ?y 2
= d?x ?y ?
d ? x ? y X bi ai 2 ( ? ) 2 i=1 ?y ?x
d ?x ?y X bi ai 2 = ?d?x ?y + ( + ) 2 i=1 ?y ?x
(8)
(9)
(10)
Pd Pd Equation (8) is because of i=1 a2i = d?x2 and i=1 b2i = d?y2 . We
can also get equation (10) by switching the roles of the term ?d?x ?y and the
term d?x ?y in the above equations. 3

Deﬁnition. Now we deﬁne the MS-distance between x and y in its lower
bound form, denoted by MSL (x, y, k), by replacing the last term of equation
(3) with equation (9), and in its upper bound form, denoted by MSU(x, y, k)
by replacing the last term of equation (4) with equation (10). The MS-distance
makes use of the nonincreasing intermediate values for its upper bound and the
nondecreasing intermediate values for its lower bound. We let a0 = b0 = 0.
MSL (x, y, k)

2
2

4

= d (?x ? ?y ) + (?x ? ?y )
+ ?x ?y
k X bi i=0
MSU (x, y, k)
k X
= d (?x ? ?y )2 + (?x + ?y )2 ? ?x ?y i=0
ai ? ?y ?x
2
bi ai + ?y ?x
2
(11)
(12)
Properties. Note that equation (11) is nondecreasing and equation (12) is
nonincreasing while i increases from 0 to d, because d, ?x , and ?y are all
nonnegative, and ( ?byi ? ?axi )2 and ( ?byi + ?axi )2 are also nonnegative for
all i. This is very useful because, in equation (11), the ﬁrst term, MSL(x, y, 0), is
already a lower bound of dist(x, y)2 by inequality (6) , and the lower bound can
be reﬁned further nondecreasingly over the summation in the second term. If we
stop the summation at i = k, for k ¡ d, the intermediate result is also a reﬁned
lower bounds of dist(x, y)2 . Similarly, in equation (12), the ﬁrst term, MSU(x,
y, 0), is already an upper bound of dist(x, y)2 by inequality (7) , and the upper
bound can be reﬁned further nonincreasingly over the summation in the second
term. This means we can stop the summation as soon as we ﬁnd a bound good
enough for the application under consideration. If we need the exact Euclidean
distance, we can get it by continuing to the full summation. We summarize
the above properties in the following. Lemma 2 (Monotone Convergence) Let
MSL(x, y, k) and MSU(x, y, k) be the lower and upper bounds of MS-distance
as deﬁned above, respectively. Then the following properties hold. ? MSL(x, y,
0) ? MSL(x, y, 1) ? ? ? ? ? MSL(x, y, d ? 1) ? MSL(x, y, d) = dist(x, y)2
. ? MSU(x, y, 0) ? MSU(x, y, 1) ? ? ? ? ? MSU(x, y, d ? 1) ? MSU(x, y,
d) = dist(x, y)2 . ? MSL(x, y, k) = MSL(x, y, k + 1) if and only if bk+1 /?y
= ak+1 /?x . ? MSU(x, y, k) = MSU(x, y, k + 1) if and only if bk+1 /?y =
?ak+1 /?x . Lemma 3 For 0 ? k ¡ d, we can update MSL(x, y, k) to MSL(x, y,
k + 1), and MSU(x, y, k) to MSU (x, y, k + 1) in constant time. Fast Filtering.
We must emphasize that MSL(x, y, 0) and MSU(x, y, 0) can be used for fast
ﬁltering. Let ? denote a threshold for ﬁltering deﬁned in some proximity search
problem under consideration. If ? ¡ MSL(x, y, 0) in case of nearest search or ? ¿
MSL(x, y, 0) in case of farthest search, we do not need to consider this pair (x,
y) as a candidate, thus we can save time from computing their exact Euclidean
distance. Precisely speaking, we map each d-dimensional vector x = [x1 , x2 , .
. . , xd ] into a pair of points, ? + and x ? ? , in the 2-dimensional plane such
that x ? + = [?x , ?x ] and x ? ? = [?x , ??x ]. Then x ? + )2 = MSL(x, y,
0)/d dist(? x+ , y +

? 2
? ) = MSU(x, y, 0)/d. dist(? x ,y
(13) (14)

5

To see why it is useful in fast ﬁltering, consider the case of ﬁnding the nearest
vector. For ddimensional vectors in V of size n, we have n pairs of points in the
plane as in Figure 1. Since ?x ? + denote is nonnegative, exactly n points lie
on or below ?-axis. Let q be a query vector, and let q the point mapped in the
plane as deﬁned above. Among these n points lying on or below ?-axis, let ??
? + . Note that the closest point from the query can be computed x i be the
point that is nearest to q eﬃciently in 2-dimensional space, for example, after
constructing some space partitioning structures such as kd-trees or R-trees, each
query can be answered in poly-logarithmic search time. 4

? + lies outside the circle Then we can ignore all d-dimensional vectors x
whose mapped point x ? + and of radius dist(? ?? centered at q q+ , x ) in
the plane, because they are strictly farther than xi i from q.

?
X1+
Y+
X2+
? X1?
Y
?
X2?
Figure 1: Fast ﬁltering using MSL(x, y, 0) and MSU(x, y, 0). All d-
dimensional vectors x whose ? + lies outside the circle are strictly farther
than xi from q. mapped point x

4
Estimating the Expected Diﬀerence Between Two Bounds
We now turn to estimating the expected diﬀerence between MSL(x, y, k)
and MSU(x, y, k). Observe that MSL(x, y, k) is almost the same as MSL(x, y,
k ? 1) if bk /?y ? ak /?x . Hence, in the worst case, MSL(x, y, 0) = MSL(x, y,
d ? 1) ¡ MSL(x, y, d) = dist(x, y)2 when bk /?y = ak /?x for all k = 0, 1, . . .
, d ? 1, except k = d. Therefore, if we need a lower bound strictly better than
MSL (x, y, 0), then we need to go through all d reﬁnement steps, which takes
O(d) time. It is not diﬃcult to see that this also applies to the case of MSU(x,
y, k). However, this is unlikely to happen. Consider a random order for the
last term in equation MSL (x, y, k) and for the last term in equation MSU (x,
y, k). We show below that their expected values increase and decrease linearly,
respectively, as k increases from 0 to d. Formally, let (a?(i) , b?(i) ) denote the
ith pair in the random order. We measure the expected quality of the bounds
by the diﬀerence between the bounds, that is, MSU(x, y, k) ? MSL(x, y, k) as
follows.

! k X a?(i) 2 b?(i) 2 MSU (x, y, k) ? MSL (x, y, k) = 4d?x ?y ? 2?x ?y +
?x ?y i=0 2 2 ! d ai bi kX + = 4d?x ?y ? 2?x ?y d i=0 ?x ?y = 4d?x ?y ? 4k?x
?y = 4?x ?y (d ? k)

(15)
(16) (17) (18)
Let us explain how we get Equation (16) from (15). Let N denote the set of
all pairs, and let N k denote the set of ﬁrst k pairs in the random order. Since

6

each pair in N is treated equally, N k is a Pk random subset of N of size k.
Therefore, i=1 (a?(i) /?x )2 is equivalent to take the total sum of Pk (ai /?x )2
with i from 1 to d and divide it by d/k. We can also show this for i=1 (b?(i)
/?y )2 by a similar augment. Pd Pd Equations (17) and (18) are because i=1
a2i = d?x2 and i=1 b2i = d?y2 by deﬁnitions of ai and bi . Pd Pd By replacing
each squared sum with d, that is , by applying i=1 (ai /?x )2 = i=1 (bi /?y )2
= d, we have Equation (18). Lemma 4 The expected value of MSU(x, y, k) ?
MSL(x, y, k) is 4?x ?y (d ? k). 5

Because dist(x, y)2 always lies in between the two bounds, the following
also holds. Corollary 1 Both expected values of MSU(x, y, k) ? dist(x, y)2
and dist(x, y)2 ? MSL(x, y, k) are at most 4?x ?y (d ? k). This shows a
good theoretical expectation on the lower and upper bounds. This can justify
that the MS-distance provides very tight bounds in a few reﬁnement steps of a
typical sequence.

5
Applications : Proximity Searches
The MS-distance can be used to application problems where the Euclidean
distance is a measure for proximity or similarity of objects. As a case study,
we implemented the nearest neighbor search (NNS) and the farthest neighbor
search (FNS) using the MS-distance. Given a set X of d-dimensional vectors xi
, for i = 1, . . . , n, and a d-dimensional query vector q, we use the following
simple randomized algorithm for NNS. Initially, we set ? to the threshold given
from the application under consideration or computed from the fast ﬁltering in
2-dimension in Section 3. 1. Consider the vectors in X one at a time according
to this sequence. At the ith stage, we do the followings.
if MSL(q, xi , 0) ¡
if MSL(q, xi , j) ¿ ? : break; if j = d: ? = MSL(q,
? : for j = 1, 2, ..., d :
xi , d); NN = i; 2. return NN as the nearest neighbor of q with the squared
Euclidean distance ?. Note that the ﬁrst line of the pseudocodes ﬁlters out the
vectors whose distance to q is larger than ? as in the fast ﬁltering in Section 3.
In the for loop, we compute MSL(q, xi , j) from MSL(q, xi , j ?1) in constant
time. From the last two lines of the pseudocodes, we update ? to the exact
Euclidean distance between q and xi and store the index as the current nearest
neighbor (NN). The algorithm for the farthest neighbor search is similar to this
one, except that it uses MSU(xi , y, j) and maintains the maximum distance.
For empirical comparison, we implemented a linear search algorithm that simply
computes distances from q to every xi and chooses the one with the minimum
distance. We also used the implementation of the cover tree [6]. A cover tree is a
data structure that supports fast nearest neighbor queries given a ﬁxed intrinsic
dimensionality [7]. We tested these implementations on data sets from UCI
machine learning archive [11]. We selected data sets D from various dimensions
(from 10 to 100, 000), and randomly selected 30 queries points Q ? D, and
queried them on D Q. We labelled the data set on d-dimension as ?Dd?. The
data sets D500, D5000, D10000, D20000, D100000 were used in NIPS 2003
challenge on feature selection [12]. The test machine has one CPU, Intel Q6600
with 2.4GHz, 3GB memory, and 32bit Ubuntu 10 operating system running on
the machine. Figure 2 shows the percentage of data ﬁltered oﬀ. For the data sets

7

on relaxed dimensions, the MS-distance ﬁltered oﬀ over 95% of data without
lose of accuracy. For high dimensional data, MS-distance failed to ﬁlter oﬀ
many data. Probably this is because the distances from queries to their nearest
vectors tend to converge to the distances to their farthest vectors as described in
[13]. This makes it hard to decrease (or increase in FNS) the threshold ? for the
MS-distance enough to ﬁlter oﬀ many data. However, on such high dimensions,
both the linear search and the cover tree algorithm also show poor performance.
Figure 3 shows the preprocessing time of the MS-distance and the cover tree
for NNS. The time axis is log-scaled second. This shows that the preprocessing
time of the MS-distance is up to 1000 times 6

100 Time(Second)
Percent(%)
80 60 40 20
NNS
D10 D11 D16 D19 D22 D27 D37 D50 D55 D57 D61 D64 D86 D90 D167

D255 D500 D617 D5000 D10000 D20000 D105

D10 D11 D16 D19 D22 D27 D37 D50 D55 D57 D61 D64 D86 D90 D167

D255 D500 D617 D5000 D10000 D20000 D105

0
10000 1000 100 10 1 0.1 0.01 0.001
FNS
MS-dist
Figure 2: Data ﬁltered oﬀ in percentage.
Cover
Figure 3: Preprocessing time for nearest neighbor search in log-scaled second.
faster than the one in the cover tree. This is because for the MS-distance
it requires only O(dn) time to compute the mean and the standard deviation
values.
1.2
1
Relative Time
Relative Time
1.2 0.8 0.6 0.4 0.2
1 0.8 0.6 0.4 0.2 0
D10 D11 D16 D19 D22 D27 D37 D50 D55 D57 D61 D64 D86 D90 D167

D255 D500 D617 D5000 D10000 D20000 D105

D10 D11 D16 D19 D22 D27 D37 D50 D55 D57 D61 D64 D86 D90 D167

D255 D500 D617 D5000 D10000 D20000 D105

0
MS-dist
Cover
MS-dist
Linear
Figure 4: Relative running time for the nearest neighbor search queries,

normalized by linear search time.

Linear

8

Figure 5: Relative running time for the farthest neighbor search queries,

normalized by linear search time.

Figure 4 shows the time spent for NNS queries. The graph shows the query
time that is normalized by the linear search time. It is clear that the ﬁltering
algorithm based on the MS-distance beats the linear search algorithm, even on
high dimensional data in the results. The cover tree, which is designed exclu-
sively for NNS, shows slightly better query performance than ours. However,
the MS-distance is more general and ﬂexible: it supports addition of a new vec-
tor to the data set (our data structure) in O(d) time for computing the mean
and the standard deviation values of the vector. Deletion of a vector from the
data set can be done in constant time. Furthermore, the data structure for NNS
can also be used for FNS. Figure 5 shows the time spent for FNS queries. This
is outstanding compared to the linear search algorithm. We hardly know any
other previous work achieving better performance than this.

6
Conclusion
We introduce a fast distance bounding technique, called the MS-distance, by
using the mean and the standard deviation values. The MS-distance between
two vectors provides upper and lower bounds of Euclidean distance between
them in constant time, and these bounds converge monotonically to the exact
Euclidean distance over iteration. The MS-distance can be used to application
problems where the Euclidean distance is a measure for proximity or similarity
of objects. The experimental results show that our method is eﬃcient enough
even to replace the best known algorithms for proximity searches. 7

Table 1: Data sets
Data Label
Name
D10 D11 D16 D19 D22 D27 D37 D50 D55 D57 D61
Page Blocks Wine Quality Letter Recognition Image Segmentation Parkin-
sons Tel Steel Plates Faults Statlog Satellite MiniBooNE Covertype Spambase
IPUMS Census

# of vectors 5473 6497 20000 2310 5875 1941 6435 130064 581012 4601

233584

Data Label
Name
D64 D86 D90 D167 D255 D500 D617 D5000 D10000 D20000 D100000
Optical Recognition Insurance Company YearPredictionMSD Musk2 Se-

meion Madelon ISOLET Gisette Arcene Dexter Dorothea

# of vectors 5620 5822 515345 6597 1593 4400 7795 13500 900 2600 1950
Acknowledgments This work was supported by the National Research Foun-
dation of Korea Grant funded by the Korean Government (MEST) (NRF-2010-
0009857).

9

2 References

[1] J. B. MacQueen. Some methods for classiﬁcation and analysis of multivari-
ate observations.
In L. M. Le Cam and J. Neyman, editors, Proceedings of
the ﬁfth Berkeley Symposium on Mathematical Statistics and Probability, vol-
ume 1, pages 281?297. University of California Press, 1967. [2] V. N. Vapnik.
The Nature of Statistical Learning Theory. Springer, New York, NY, USA,
1995.
[3] K. Pearson. On lines and planes of closest ﬁt to systems of points
in space. Philosophical Magazine, 2:559?572, 1901. [4] J. L. Bentley. Multidi-
mensional binary search trees used for associative searching. Communications
of ACM, 18:509?517, September 1975.
[5] A. Guttman. R-trees: A dynamic
index structure for spatial searching. In Beatrice Yormark, editor, Proceedings
of the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data, SIG-
MOD ?84, pages 47?57. ACM, 1984.
[6] A. Beygelzimer, S. Kakade, and J.
Langford. Cover trees for nearest neighbor. In Proceedings of the 23rd interna-
tional conference on Machine learning, ICML ?06, pages 97?104, New York, NY,
USA, 2006. ACM. [7] D. R. Karger and M. Ruhl. Finding nearest neighbors in
growth-restricted metrics. In Proceedings of the 34th annual ACM symposium
on Theory of computing, STOC ?02, pages 741?750, New York, NY, USA, 2002.
ACM. ? E?gecio?glu and H. Ferhatosmano?glu. Dimensionality reduction and
similarity computation by inner [8] O. product approximations. In Proceedings
of the ninth international conference on Information and knowledge manage-
ment, CIKM ?00, pages 219?226, New York, NY, USA, 2000. ACM. [9] R.
Weber, H. J. Schek, and S. Blott. A quantitative analysis and performance
study for similarity-search methods in high-dimensional spaces. In Proceedings
of the 24rd International Conference on Very Large Data Bases, VLDB ?98,
pages 194?205, San Francisco, CA, USA, 1998. Morgan Kaufmann Publishers
Inc. [10] H. V. Jagadish, B. C. Ooi, K.L. Tan, C. Yu, and R. Zhang. idistance:
An adaptive b+-tree based indexing method for nearest neighbor search. ACM
Transactions on Database Systems, 30:364?397, June 2005.
[11] UCI machine
learning archive. http://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/.

8
[12] NIPS 2003 challenge on feature selection. http://clopinet.com/isabelle/projects/nips2003/.

[13] K. S. Beyer, J. Goldstein, R. Ramakrishnan, and U. Shaft. When is ?near-
est neighbor? meaningful? In Proceedings of the 7th International Conference
on Database Theory, ICDT ?99, pages 217?235, London, UK, 1999. Springer.

9

10

