A Reinforcement Learning Theory for

Homeostatic Regulation

Authored by:

Boris S. Gutkin
Mehdi Keramati

Abstract

Reinforcement learning models address animal’s behavioral adaptation
to its changing ”external” environment, and are based on the assumption
that Pavlovian, habitual and goal-directed responses seek to maximize re-
ward acquisition. Negative-feedback models of homeostatic regulation, on
the other hand, are concerned with behavioral adaptation in response to
the ”internal” state of the animal, and assume that animals’ behavioral
objective is to minimize deviations of some key physiological variables
from their hypothetical setpoints. Building upon the drive-reduction the-
ory of reward, we propose a new analytical framework that integrates
learning and regulatory systems, such that the two seemingly unrelated
objectives of reward maximization and physiological-stability prove to be
identical. The proposed theory shows behavioral adaptation to both in-
ternal and external states in a disciplined way. We further show that the
proposed framework allows for a uniﬁed explanation of some behavioral
phenomenon like motivational sensitivity of diﬀerent associative learning
mechanism, anticipatory responses, interaction among competing motiva-
tional systems, and risk aversion.

1 Paper Body

?Reinforcement learning? and ?negative-feedback models of homeostatic regu-
lation? are two control theory-based computational frameworks that have had
major contributions in learning and motivation literatures in behavioral psy-
chology, respectively. Proposing neurobiologically-plausible algorithms, compu-
tational theory of reinforcement learning (RL) explains how animals adapt their
behavior to varying contingencies in their ?external? environment, through per-
sistently updating their estimates of the rewarding value of feasible choices [1].
The teaching signal required for these updates is suggested to be carried by
phasic activity of midbrain dopamine neurons [2] projecting to the striatum,
where stimulus-response associations are supposed to be encoded. Critically,

1

this theory is built upon one hypothetical assumption: animals behavioral ob-
jective is to maximize reward acquisition. In this respect, without addressing the
question of how the brain constructs reward, the RL theory gives a normative
explanation for how the brains decision making circuitry shapes instrumental
responses as a function of external cues, so as the animal to satisfy its reward-
maximization objective. Negative-feedback models of homeostatic regulation
(HR), on the other hand, seek to explain regular variabilities in behavior as a
function of the internal state of the animal, when the external stimuli are ﬁxed
[3, 4]. Homeostasis means maintaining stable of some physiological variables.
Correspondingly, behavioral homeostasis refers to corrective responses that are
triggered by deviation of 1

a regulated variable from its hypothetical setpoint. In fact, regulatory sys-
tems operate ?as if? they aim at defending variables against perturbations. In
this sense, existence of an ?error signal? (also known as ?negative feedback?),
deﬁned by the discrepancy between the current and desired internal state, is
essential for any regulatory mechanism. Even though the presence of this nega-
tive feedback in controlling motivated behaviors is argued to be indisputable for
explaining some behavioral and physiological facts [3], three major diﬃculties
have raised criticism against negative-feedback models of behavioral homeosta-
sis [3, 5]: (1) Anticipatory eating and drinking can be elicited in the absence
of physiological depletion [6], supposedly in order to prevent anticipated devi-
ations in future. In more general terms, motivated behaviors are observed to
be elicited even when no negative feedback is detectable. (2) Intravenous (and
even intragastric, in some cases) injection of food is not motivating, even though
it alleviates deviation of the motivational state from its homeostatic setpoint.
For example, rats do not show motivation, after several learning trials, to run
down an alley for intragastric feeding by milk, whereas they quickly learn to run
for normal drinking of milk [7]. These behavioral patterns are used as evidence
to argue that maintaining homeostasis (reducing the negative feedback) is not
a behavioral objective.
In contrast, taste (and other sensory) information of
stimuli is argued to be the key factor for their reinforcing properties [5]. (3)
The traditional homeostatic regulation theory simply assumes that the animal
knows how to translate its various physiological deﬁcits into the appropriate
behaviors. In fact, without taking into account the contextual state of the ani-
mal, negative feedback models only address the question of whether or not the
animal should have motivation toward a certain outcome, without answering
how the outcome can be achieved through a series of instrumental actions. The
existence of these shortcomings calls for rethinking the traditional view toward
homeostatic regulation theory. We believe that these shortcomings, as well as
the weak spot of RL models in not taking into account the internal drive state
of the animal, all arise from lack of an integrated view toward learning and mo-
tivation. We show in this paper that a simple uniﬁed computational theory for
RL and HR allows for explaining a wide range of behavioral patterns including
those mentioned above, without decreasing the explanatory power of the two
original theories. We further show that such a uniﬁed theory can satisfy the
two objectives of reward maximization and deviation minimization at the same

2

time.
2
The model
The term ?reward? (with many equivalents like reinforcer, motivational
salience, utility, etc.) has been at the very heart of behavioral psychology since
its foundation. In purely behavioral terms, it refers to a stimulus delivered to
the animal after a response is made, that increases the probability of making
that response in the future. RL theory proposes algorithms for how diﬀerent
learning systems can adapt agent?s responses to varying external conditions in
order to maximize the acquisition of reward. For this purpose, RL algorithms
try to learn, via experiences, the sum of discounted rewards expected to be
received after taking a speciﬁc action (at ), in a speciﬁc state (st ), onward. [?
] ? [ ] 2 i?t V (st , at ) = E rt + ?rt+1 + ? rt+2 + . . . —st , at = E ? ri —st
, at (1) i=t

0 ? ? ? 1 discounts future rewards. rt denotes the rewarding value of the
outcome the animal receives at time t, which is a often set to a ?ﬁxed? value
that can be either positive or negative, depending on whether the corresponding
stimulus is appetitive or aversive, respectively. However, animals motivation for
outcomes is not ﬁxed, but a function of their internal state: a food pellet is more
rewarding to a hungry, than a sated rat. In fact, the internal state (also referred
to as drive, or motivational state) of the animal aﬀects the reinforcing value of a
constant external outcome. As an attempt to identify the nature of reward and
its relation to drive states, neo-behaviorists like Hull [8], Spence, and Mowrer
have proposed the ?drive reduction? theory of motivation. According to this
theory, one primary mechanism underlying reward is drive reduction. In terms
of homeostatic 2

regulation theory, reward is deﬁned as a stimulus that reduces the discrep-
ancy between the current and the desired drive state of the animal, i.e, food
pellet is rewarding to a hungry rat because it fulﬁlls a physiological need. To
capture this idea formally, let?s Ht = {h1,t , h2,t , .., hN,t } denote the phys-
iological state of the animal at time t, and H ? = {h?1 , h?2 , .., h?N } as the
homeostatic setpoint. As a special case, ﬁgure 1 shows a simpliﬁed system where
food and water constitute all the physiological needs. This model can obviously
be extended, without loss of generality, to cover other homeostatically regulated
drives, as well as more detailed aspects of feeding like diﬀerential drives for car-
bohydrate, sodium, calcium, etc. A drive function can then be deﬁned on this
space as a mapping from physio-

Figure 1: An examplary homeostatic space, with food and water as regulated

physiological needs logical state to motivation:

v uN u? m —h?i ? hi,t —n d(Ht ) = t
(2)
i=1
This drive function is in fact a distance function (Euclidian distance when
m = n = 2) that creates some quasi-circle iso-drive curves centred around the
homeostatic setpoint. The homeostatic space, as a multidimensional metric
space, is a hypothetical construct that allow us to explain a wide range of

3

behavioral and physiological evidence in a uniﬁed framework. Since animals
physiological states are most often below the setpoint, our focus in this paper
is mostly on the quarter of the homeostatic space that is below the homeostatic
setpoint. Having deﬁned drive, we can now provide a formal deﬁnition for
reward, based on the drive reduction theory. Assume that as the result of some
actions, the animal receives an outcome at time t that contains ki,t units of
the constituent hi , for each i ? {1, 2, .., N }. Kt can be deﬁned as a row
i ? {1, 2, .., N }). Consumption of that outcome
vector with entries (ki,t :
will result in a transition of the physiological state from Ht to Ht+1 = Ht +
Kt , and consequently, a transition of the drive state from d(Ht ) to d(Ht + Kt
). For example, ﬁgure 1 shows the transition resulted from taking k1 units of
food. Accordingly, the rewarding value of that outcome can be deﬁned as the
consequent reduction in the drive function: r(Ht , Kt ) = d(Ht ) ? d(Ht+1 ) =
d(Ht ) ? d(Ht + Kt )

(3)
This drive-reduction deﬁnition of reward is the central element in our pro-
posed framework that will bridge the gap between regulatory and reward learn-
ing systems.

3
Behavioral plausibility of the reward function
Before discussing how the reward deﬁned in equation 3 can be used by as-
sociative learning mechanisms (RL theory), we are interested in this section
to show that the functional form proposed for the reward function allows for
several behavioral phenomena to be explained in a uniﬁed framework. 3

For all m ¿ n ¿ 2, the rewarding value of an outcome consisting of only one
constituent, Kt = (0, 0, .., kj,t , .., 0) ,when the animal is in the motivational
state Ht , will have the four below properties. Even though these properties are
written for the cases that the need state remains below the setpoint, as the drive
function is symmetric in respect to the setpoint, similar result can be derived
for other three quarters. 3.1

Reward value increases with the dose of outcome
The reward function is an increasing function of the magnitude of the out-
come (e.g., number of food pellets); i.e. the bigger the outcome is, the more
rewarding value it will have. It is straightforward to show that: dr(Ht , Kt )
¿ 0 : for kj,t ¿ 0 (4) dkj,t Supporting this property of the drive function, it is
shown in progressive ratio schedules that rats maintain higher breakpoints when
reinforced with bigger appetitive outcomes, reﬂecting higher motivation toward
them [9, 10]. 3.2

Excitatory eﬀect of deprivation level
Increasing the deprivation level of the animal will increase the reinforcing
strength of a constant dose of a corresponding outcome, i.e. a single pellet of
food is more rewarding to a hungry, than a sated rate. dr(Ht , Kt ) ¿ 0 : for
kj,t ¿ 0 (5) d—h?j ? hj,t — Consistently, the level of food deprivation in rats
is demonstrated to increases the breakpoint in progressive ratio schedules [10].
3.3

Inhibitory eﬀect of the irrelevant drive

4

A large body of behavioral experiments shows that deprivation level for one
need has an inhibitory eﬀect on the reinforcing value of outcomes that satisfy
irrelevant needs. (see [11] for review). It is well known that high levels of irrele-
vant thirst impairs Pavlovian as well as instrumental responses for food during
both acquisition and extinction. Reciprocally, food deprivation is demonstrated
to suppress Pavlovian and instrumental water-related responses. As some other
examples, increased calcium appetite is shown to reduce appetite for phospho-
rus, and increased level of hunger is demonstrated to inhibit sexual behavior.
It is straightforward to show that the speciﬁc functional form proposed for the
drive function can capture this inhibitory-like interaction between irrelevant
drives: dr(Ht , Kt ) ¡0 : d—h?i ? hi,t —

for all i ?= j and kj,t ¿ 0
(6)
Intuitively, one does not play chess, or even search for sex, with an empty
stomach. This behavioral pattern can be interpreted as competition among
diﬀerent motivational systems (diﬀerent dimensions of the homeostatic space),
and is consistent with the notion of ?complementary? relation between some
goods in economics, like between cake and coﬀee. Each of two complement goods
are highly rewarding, only when the other one is also available; and taking one
good when the other one is lacking, is not that rewarding. 3.4

Risk aversion
Risk aversion, as a fundamental concept in both psychology and economics,
and supported by a wealth of behavioral experiments, is deﬁned by reluctance of
individuals to select choices with uncertain outcomes, compared to choices with
more certain payoﬀs, even when the expected payoﬀ of the former is higher than
that of the latter. It is easy to show that a concave reward (utility) function 4
(in respect to the quantity of the outcome), is equivalent to risk aversion.
It is due to this feature that concavity of the utility function has become a
fundamental assumption in the microeconomic theory. The proposed form of
the drive function can capture risk-aversion: d2 r(Ht , Kt ) ¡0 : 2 dkj,t

for kj,t ¿ 0
(7)
It is noteworthy that as Kt consists of substances that fulﬁl physiological
needs, one should be careful in extending this and other features of the model
to the case of monetary rewards, or any other type of stimuli that does not
seem to have a corresponding regulatory system (like social rewards, novelty-
induced reward, etc.).
It is clear that the four mentioned properties of the
reward function depend on the speciﬁc functional form adopted for the drive
function (equation 2). In fact, the drive-reduction deﬁnition of reward allows
for the validity of the form of drive function to be experimentally tested in
behavioral tasks.

4
Homeostatic control through learning mechanisms
Despite signiﬁcant day-to-day variations in energy expenditure and food
availability, the homeostatic regulation system involved in control of food-intake
and energy balance is a remarkably precise system. This adaptive nature of

5

homeostatic regulation system can be achieved by employing the animals learn-
ing mechanisms, which are capable of adopting ﬂexible behavioral strategies
to cope with changes in the environmental conditions. In this section we are
interested in looking at behavioral and theoretical implications of interaction
between homeostatic regulation and reward learning systems. One theoretical
implication of the proposed deﬁnition of reward is that it reconciles the RL
and homeostatic regulation theories, in terms of normative assumptions behind
them. In more precise words, if any reward learning system, like RL algorithms,
uses the drive-reduction deﬁnition of reward proposed in equation 3, then a
behavioral policy that maximizes the sum of discounted rewards is at the same
time minimizing the sum of discounted drives (or sum of discounted deviations
from the setpoint), and vice versa (see Supplementary Methods: Proposition
1). In this respect, reward maximization can be seen as just means that guide
animal?s behavior toward satisfying the more basic objective of maintaining
homeostasis. Since the reward function deﬁned by equation 3 depends on the
internal state and thus, is nonstationary, some appropriate adjustments in the
classical RL algorithms that try to ﬁnd an optimal policy must be thought of.
One straightforward solution is to deﬁne an augmented Markov decision pro-
cess (MDP) implied by the cross-product of internal and external states, an
then use a variant of RL algorithms to learn action-values in that problem-
space. Consistent with this view, some behavioral studies show that internal
state can work in the same way that external state works. That is, animals
are able to acquire responses conditioned upon some certain motivational states
(e.g. motivational state induced by benzodiazepine agonist) [11]. Although
this approach, in theory, guarantees convergence to the optimal policy, high
dimensionality of the resulting state-space makes learning rather impossible in
practice. Moreover, since the next external state only depends on the current
external but not internal state, such an augmented MDP will have signiﬁcant
redundant structure. From a machine learning point of view, as argued in [12],
an appropriate function approximator speciﬁcally designed to take advantage of
such a structure can be used to reduce state-space dimensionality. Beside this
algorithm-independent expansion of state-space argued above, the proposed def-
inition of reward provides an opportunity for discussing how diﬀerent associate
learning systems in the brain take the animal?s internal state into account. Here
we discuss motivational sensitivity in habitual (hypothesized to use a model-free
RL, like temporal diﬀerence algorithm [13]), goal-directed (hypothesized to use
a model-based RL [13]), and Pavlovian learning systems. 5

A model-based RL algorithm learns the state-transition matrix (action-
outcome contingencies), as well as the reward function (the incentive value of
each outcome), and then uses them to compute the value of possible actions
in a given state, using Bellman optimality equation[1]. In our framework, as
long as a model-based algorithm is involved in decision making, all that the
animal needs to do when its internal state shifts is to update the incentive
value (reward function) of each potential outcome. The reward function be-
ing updated, the animal will be able to take the optimal policy, given that the
state-transition function is learned completely. In order to update the reward

6

function, one way is that the animal re-experiences outcomes in its new moti-
vational state. This way seems to be how the goal-directed system works, since
re-exposure is demonstrated to be necessary in order for the animals? behav-
ior to be sensitive to changes in motivational state [11]. The second way is
to update the reward function without re-exposure, but through directly esti-
mating the drivereduction eﬀect of outcomes in the current motivational state,
using equation 3. This way seems to be how the Pavlovian system works, since
numerous experiments show that Pavlovian conditioned or unconditioned re-
sponses are sensitive to the internal state in an outcome-speciﬁc way, without
reexposure being required [11]. This Pavlovian-type behavioral adaptation is
observed even when the animal has never experienced the outcome in its cur-
rent motivational state during its whole life. This shows that animals are able
to directly estimate the drive-reduction eﬀect of at least some certain types of
outcomes. Furthermore, the fact that this motivational sensitivity is outcome-
speciﬁc shows that the underlying associative learning structure is model-based
(i.e. based on learning the causal contingencies between events). The habitual
system (hypothesized to use a model-free RL[13]) is demonstrated, through out-
comedevaluation experiments, that cannot directly (i.e. without new learning)
adapt the animal?s behavioral response after shifts in the motivational state
[11]. It might be concluded from this observation that action-values in the ha-
bitual system only depend on the internal state of the animal during the course
of learning (past experiences), but not performance. This is consistent with
the information storage scheme in model-free RL, where cached action-values
lose connection with the identity of the outcomes. Thus, the habitual system
doesn?t know what speciﬁc action-values should be updated when a novel inter-
nal state is being experienced. However, it has been argued by some authors [14]
that even though habitual responses are insensitive to sensory-speciﬁc satiety,
they are sensitive to motivational manipulations in a general, outcomeindepen-
dent way. Note that the previous form of motivational insensitivity concerns
lack of behavioral adaptation in an outcome-speciﬁc way (for example, lack of
greater preference for food-seeking behavior, compared to water-seeking behav-
ior, after a shift from satiety to hunger state). Borrowing from the Hullian
concept of ?generalized drive? [8], it has been proposed that transition from
an outcome-sated to an outcome-deprived motivational state will energize all
pre-potent habitual responses, irrespective of whether or not those actions re-
sult in that certain outcome [14]. For example, a motivational shift from satiety
to hunger will result in energization of both food-seeking and water-seeking
habitual responses. Taking a normative perspective, we argue here that this
outcome-independent energizing eﬀect is an approximate way of updating the
value of state-action pairs when the motivational state shifts instantaneously.
Assuming that the animal is trained under the ﬁxed internal state H0 , and then
tested in a novel internal state H1 , the cached values in the habitual system
can be approximated in the new motivational state by: Q1 (s, a) =

d(H1 ) .Q0 (s, a) : for all state-action pairs d(H0 )
(8)
Where Q0 (s, a) represents action-values learned by the habitual system af-

7

ter the training period. According to this update rule, all the prepotent actions
will get energized if deviation from the homeostatic setpoint increases in the
new internal state, whether or not the outcome of those actions are more de-
sired in the new state. Proposition 2 (see Supplementary Methods) shows that
this update rule is a perfect approximation only when H1 = c.H0 , where c ?
0. This means that the energizing eﬀect will result in rational behavior after
motivational shift, only when the new internal state is an 6

ampliﬁcation or abridge of the old internal state in all the dimension of the
homeostatic space, with equal magnitude. Since the model-free system does
not learn the causal model of the environment, it cannot show motivational
sensitivity in an outcome-speciﬁc way, and this general energizing eﬀect is the
best approximate way to react to motivational manipulations. 4.1

Anticipatory responses
The notion of predictive homeostasis [3, 4], as opposed to the classical reac-
tive homeostasis where the existence of negative feedback (physiological deple-
tion) is essential, suggests that through anticipating future needs, individuals
make anticipatory responses in order to prevent deviation of regulated variables
from their setpoints. Anticipatory eating and drinking, as two examples, are
deﬁned by taking food and water in the absence of any detectable decrease in
the corresponding physiological signals. Although it is quite clear that explain-
ing such behavioral patterns requires integrating homeostatic mechanisms and
learning (as predictive) processes, to our knowledge, no well-deﬁned mechanism
has been proposed for it so far. We show here, through an example, how the
proposed model can reconcile anticipatory responses to the homeostatic regu-
lation theory. Temperature regulation provides a clear example for predictive
homeostasis. Body temperature, which has long been a topic of interest in the
homeostatic regulation literature, is shown to increase back to its normal level
by shivering, after the animal is placed into a cold place. Interestingly, cues that
predict being placed into a cold place induce anticipatory shivering and result
in the body temperature to go above the normal temperature of the animal [15].
Similarly, cues that predict receiving a drug that decreases body temperature
is shown to have the same eﬀect. This behavior is interpreted as an attempt by
the animal to alleviate the severity of deviation from the setpoint. To model
this example, lets assume that x? is the normal temperature of the animal, and
that putting the animal in the cold place will result in a decrease of lx units
in the body temperature. Furthermore, assume that when presented with the
coldness-predicting cue (SC ), the animal chooses how much to shiver and thus,
increases its body temperature by kx units. In a scenario like this, after observ-
ing the coldness-predicting cue, the animals temperature will shift from x? to x?
+ kx , as a result of anticipatory shivering. Assuming that the animal will then
experience coldness after a delay of one time-unit, its temperature will transit
from x? + kx to x? + kx ? lx . The rewarding value of this transition will be
discounted with the rate of ?. Finally, by assuming that after one more time-
unit the body temperature will go back to the normal level, x? , the animal will
receive another reward, discounted with the rate of ? 2 . The sum of discounted
rewards can be written as below: V (SC , kX ) = [d(x? )?d(x? +kX )]+?.[d(x?

8

+kX )?d(x? +kX ?lX )]+? 2 .[d(x? +kX ?lX )?d(x? )] (9) Proposition 3 (see
Supplementary Methods) shows that the optimal strategy for maximizing the
sum of discounted rewards in this scenario is when kx = lx /2, assuming that
the discount factor is not equal to one, but is suﬃciently close to it. In fact,
the model predicts that the best strategy is to perform anticipatory shivering
to the extent that keep it as close as possible to the setpoint: turning around
but close to the setpoint is preferred to getting far from it and coming back.
In fact this example, which can be easily generalized to anticipatory eating and
drinking, shows that when learning mechanisms play a regulatory role, it is not
only the initial and ﬁnal motivational states of a policy that matters, but also
the trajectory of the motivational state in the homeostatic space through that
policy matters. It is in fact due to discounting future rewards. If the discount
factor is one, then regardless of the trajectory of the motivational state, the sum
of rewards for all policies that start from a certain homeostatic point and ﬁnish
at another point, will be equal. In that case, the sum of rewards for all values
of kx in the anticipatory shivering example will be zero and thus, anticipatory
strategies will not be preferred to a reactive-homeostasis strategy. In fact, the
model predicts that decreasing animal?s discount rate (e.g. through pharmaco-
logical agents known to modulate discount rate) should increase the probability
that the animal show an anticipatory response, and vice versa. 7

5
Discussion
Despite considerable diﬀerences, some common principles are argued to gov-
ern all motivational systems. we have proposed a model that captures some of
these commonalities between homoestatically regulated motivational systems.
We showed how the rewarding value of an outcome can be computed as a func-
tion of the animal?s internal state and the constituting elements of the outcome,
through the drive reduction equation. We further demonstrated how this com-
puted reward can be used by diﬀerent learning mechanisms to form appropri-
ate Pavlovian or instrumental associations. However, it should be noted that
concerning food (and other ingestible) outcomes, the basic form of the drive-
reduction deﬁnition of reward (equation 2) has four interrelated problems, some
of them used traditionally to criticize the drive reduction theory: (1) Post-
digestive nutritive feedback of food, deﬁned by the drive reduction equation,
might occur hours after ingestion. Such a long delay between an instrumen-
tal response and its consequent drive reduction eﬀect (reward) would make it
diﬃcult for an appropriate association to be established.
In fact, according
to the temporal contiguity rule of associative learning, unconditioned stimuli
must follow immediately the conditioned stimuli, for an association to be es-
tablished between them. (2) Dopamine neurons, which are supposed to carry
reward learning signal, are demonstrated to show instantaneous burst activity
in response to unexpected food rewards, without waiting for the food to be
digested, and drive to be reduced [16]. (3) Intravenous injection (and intragas-
tric intubation, in some cases) of food is not rewarding, even though its drive
reduction eﬀect is equal to when that food is ingested orally. As mentioned
before, oral ingestion of the same outcome is shown to have signiﬁcant reinforc-

9

ing eﬀect [7]. (4) Palatable foods have reinforcing eﬀect, even when they do
not have any nutritional value (i.e. they do not reduce any physiological need)
[16]. Making the story even more complicated, this taste-dependent rewarding
value of food is demonstrated to be modulated by not only the approximated
nutritional content of the food, but also the internal physiological state of the
animal [16]. However, assuming that taste and other sensory properties of a
food outcome give an estimate, k?1,t , of its true nutritional content, k1,t ,
the rewarding eﬀect of food can be approximated by equation 3, as soon as
the food is sensed, or taken. This association between sensory information and
post-ingestive eﬀects of food might have been established through learning, or
evolution. This simple plausible assumption clearly resolves the four problems
listed above for the classical notion of drive reduction. It explains that gastric,
olfactory, or visual information of food is necessary for its reinforcing eﬀect to
be induced and thus, intravenous injection of food is not reinforcing due to lack
of appropriate sensory information. Moreover, there is no delay in this mecha-
nism between food intake and its drive-reduction eﬀect and therefore, Dopamine
neurons can respond instantaneously. Finally, as equation 3 predicts, this taste-
dependent rewarding value is modulated by the motivational state of the animal.
Previous computational accounts in the psychological literature attempting to
incorporate internalstate dependence of motivation into the RL models use ad
hoc addition or multiplication of drive state with the a priori reward magnitude
[17, 13].
In the machine learning literature, among others, Bersini [18] uses
an RL model where the agent gets punished if its internal state transgresses a
predeﬁned viability zone. Simulation results show that such a setting motivates
the agent to maintain its internal variables in a bounded zone. A more recent
work [12] also uses RL framework where reward is generated by drive diﬀer-
ence. It is demonstrated that this design allows the agent to make a balance in
satisfying diﬀerent drives. Apart from physiological and behavioral plausibility,
the theoretical novelty of our proposed framework is in formalizing the hypo-
thetical concept of drive, as a mapping from physiological to motivational state.
This has allowed the model to show analytically that reward maximization and
deviation minimization can be seen as two sides of the same coin.

6 Acknowledgements MK and BG are supported by grants from Frontiers

du Vivant, the French MESR, CNRS, INSERM, ANR, ENP and NERF. 8

2 References

[1] R. S. Sutton and A. G. Barto. Reinforcement Learning: An Introduction.
MIT Press, Cambridge, 1998. [2] W. Schultz, P. Dayan, and P. R. Montague. A
neural substrate of prediction and reward. Science, 275(5306):1593?1599, 1997.
[3] F. M. Toates. Motivational Systems. Problems in the behavioral sciences.
Cambridge University Press, New York, 1986. [4] J. E. R. Staddon. Adaptive
behavior and learning. Cambridge University Press, New York, 1983.
[5] K.
C. Berridge. Motivation concepts in behavioral neuroscience. Physiol Behav,
81(2):179? 209, 2004.
[6] S.C. Woods and R.J. Seeley. Hunger and energy

10

In C. R. Gallistel, editor, Volume 3 of Steven?s Handbook of
homeostasis.
Experimental Psychology: Learning, Motivation, and Emotion, pages 633?68.
Wiley, New York, third edition, 2002.
[7] N. E. Miller and M. L. Kessen. Re-
ward eﬀects of food via stomach ﬁstula compared with those of food via mouth.
J Comp Physiol Psychol, 45(6):555?564, 1952.
[8] C. L. Hull. Principles of
behavior: an introduction to behavior theory. The Century psychology se-
ries. Appleton-Century-Crofts, New York, 1943. [9] P. Skjoldager, P. J. Pierre,
and G. Mittleman. Reinforcer magnitude and progressive ratio responding in
the rat: Eﬀects of increased eﬀort, prefeeding, and extinction. Learn motiv,
24(3):303?343, 1993. [10] W. Hodos. Progressive ratio as a measure of reward
[11] A. Dickinson and B. W. Balleine.
strength. Science, 134:943?944, 1961.
The role of learning in motivation.
In C. R. Gallistel, editor, Volume 3 of
Steven?s Handbook of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Motivation, and
Emotion, pages 497?533. Wiley, New York, third edition, 2002.
[12] George
Konidaris and Andrew Barto. An adaptive robot motivational system. In Pro-
ceedings of the 9th international conference on Simulation of adaptive behavior
:
[13] N. D. Daw, Y. Niv,
and P. Dayan. Uncertainty-based competition between prefrontal and dorsolat-
eral striatal systems for behavioral control. Nat Neurosci, 8(12):1704?11, 2005.
[14] Y. Niv, D. Joel, and P. Dayan. A normative perspective on motivation.
Trends Cogn Sci, 10(8):375?381, 2006.
[15] J. G. Mansﬁeld, R. S. Benedict,
and S. C. Woods. Response speciﬁcity of behaviorally augmented tolerance to
ethanol supports a learning interpretation. Psychopharmacology, 79(23):94?98,
1983. [16] L. H. Schneider. Orosensory self-stimulation by sucrose involves brain
dopaminergic mechanisms. Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci, 575:307?319, 1989.
[17] J.
Zhang, K. C. Berridge, A. J. Tindell, K. S. Smith, and J. W. Aldridge. A neural
computational model of incentive salience. PLoS Comp Biol, 5(7), 2009.
[18]
Hugues Bersini. Reinforcement learning for homeostatic endogenous variables.
In Proceedings of the third international conference on Simulation of adaptive
behavior : from animals to animats 3, page 325333, Brighton, United Kingdom,
1994. MIT Press. ACM ID: 189936.

from animals to animats 9, pages 346?356, 2006.

9

11

