Greedy Algorithms for Structurally Constrained

High Dimensional Problems

Authored by:

Inderjit S. Dhillon

Pradeep K. Ravikumar

Ambuj Tewari

Abstract

A hallmark of modern machine learning is its ability to deal with high
dimensional problems by exploiting structural assumptions that limit the
degrees of freedom in the underlying model. A deep understanding of the
capabilities and limits of high dimensional learning methods under spe-
ciﬁc assumptions such as sparsity, group sparsity, and low rank has been
attained. Eﬀorts (Negahban et al., 2010, Chandrasekaran et al., 2010}
are now underway to distill this valuable experience by proposing gen-
eral uniﬁed frameworks that can achieve the twin goals of summarizing
previous analyses and enabling their application to notions of structure
hitherto unexplored. Inspired by these developments, we propose and an-
alyze a general computational scheme based on a greedy strategy to solve
convex optimization problems that arise when dealing with structurally
constrained high-dimensional problems. Our framework not only uniﬁes
existing greedy algorithms by recovering them as special cases but also
yields novel ones. Finally, we extend our results to inﬁnite dimensional
problems by using interesting connections between smoothness of norms
and behavior of martingales in Banach spaces.

1 Paper Body

Increasingly in modern settings, in domains across science and engineering, one
is faced with the challenge of working with high-dimensional models where the
number of parameters is large, particularly when compared to the number of
observations. In such high-dimensional regimes, a growing body of literature
in machine learning and statistics has shown that it is typically iropossible to
obtain

consistent estimators unless some low-dimensional ”structure” is imposed on
the high dimensional object that is being estimated from the data. For instance,
the sigoal could be sparse in some basis, could lie on some manifold, have some
graphical model structure, or be matrix-structured with a low rank. Indeed,

1

given the variety of high dimensional problems that researchers face, it is natu-
ral that many novel notions of such low-dimensional structure will continue to
appear in the future. There are a variety of issues that researchers have grap-
pled with in this area but two themes stand out. First, there is the statistical
problem of identifyiog the miniroum amount of data needed to accurately esti-
mate high-¡limensional objects that are structurally constrained. Second is the
computational issue of desigoing eﬃcient algurithms that, in the ideal case, can
recover high dimensional objects from a limited amount of data. Both of these
themes have spurred a huge amount of work over the past decade. For each of
the speciﬁc structures, a large body of work has studied regularized and

1
constrained M -estimators, where some loss function such as the negative
log-likelihood of the data which measures goodness of ﬁt to the data, is regular-
ized by a function appropriate to the assumed structure, or constrained to lie
within an appropriately chosen set. In recent years, researchers [I, 2] studying
the statistical properties of such estimators have started discovering common-
alities among proofs and analyses and have proposed uniﬁed frameworks that
take advantage of such commonalities. Speciﬁcally, using a single theorem, they
are able to rederive a wide range of known results on high-dimensional consis-
teney and error bounds for the various regularized and constrained estimators.
The potential beneﬁts are obvious: distillation of existing ideas and knowledge
and the enabling of novel applications that are unexplored to date. In this pa-
per, we consider the computational facet of such high-dimensional estimation,
and propose a general computational scheme that can be used for recovering
objects with low-dimensional structure in the high dimensional setting. A key
feature of our general method is that, at each step, it greedily chooses to add
a single ”simple element” or ”atom” to the current representation. The idea,
of course, is not new. Indeed we show that our general framework yields sev-
eral existing greedy algorithms if we specialize it appropriately. It also yields
novel algorithms that, to the best of our knowledge, have not appeared in the
literature so far. Greedy algorithms for optimizing smooth convex functions
over the ii-ball [3,4,5], the probability simplex [6] and the trace norm ball [7]
have appeared in the recent literature. Other recent references on greedy leam-
ing algorithm for high-dimensional problems include [8, 9]. Greedy algorithms
have also been studied in approximation theory [10, II] to approximate a given
function, viewed as an element of a Banach space of functions, using convex
combinations of ”simple” functions. There is also the well-known viewpoint of
seeing boosting algorithms as greedy minimization algorithms in function space
(see, for example, [12, Section 3], and the references therein). Often, the proofs
and results in these various settings resemble each other to a great extent. There
is thus clearly a need for uniﬁcation of ideas and proofs. In this paper, we focus
on the underlying similarities between the greedy algorithms mentioned above.
All these algorithms can be seen as specializations of a general computational
scheme, with speciﬁc choices of the loss function, regularization or constraint
set, and assumptions on the lowdimensional structure. Is there a commonal-
ity in their analyses of convergence rates, and are there key properties that

2

inform such analyses? Here, we identify two such key properties. The ﬁrst is
a restricted smoothness property (RSP) parameter (see also [13], for a simi-
lar quantity), which relates the smoothness of the function when restricted to
sets with low-dimensional structure, and which depends on the ambient space
norm, as well as a potentially distinct norm in which smoothness is established.
The other, established in [I, 2], measures the size of the low-dimensional struc-
tured object with respect to an ”atomic” norm. Using these two quantities,
we are able to provide a general theorem that yields convergence rates for gen-
eral greedy methods. We recover a wide range of existing results, as well as
some potentially novel ones, such as for block-sparse matrices, lowrank tensors,
and permutation matrices. In certain cases, most notably for low rank tensors,
the scheme appears to lead to a greedy step that is intractable, which leads to
intriguing questions about tractable approximations that we hope will be ad-
equately addressed in the future. We then show how to extend these results
to a general inﬁnite-dimensional setting, by extending our deﬁnition of the re-
stricted smoothness property (RSP) parameter, which allows us to obtain rates
for L. spaces as well Banach spaces with Martingale type p. For the latter,
the RSP parameter binges on the rate at which martingale diﬀerence sequences
concentrate in that space, which provides yet another connection to the folk-
lore statement that the ”curse of dimensionality” in high dimensional settings
is sometimes accompanied with the ”blessings of concentration of measure”.

2 PreUminaries 2.1
Atnms, Norms, and Structure
In Negahban et al.’s work[I], any speciﬁc structure such as sparsity is related
to a low-dimensional subspace of structured vectors. In Chandrasekaran et al.’s
work [2], this notion of structure is distilled further by the use of ”atoms.”
Speciﬁcally, given a set A of very ”simple” objects, called atoms, we can say
that a vector x is simple (with some low-dimensional structure) if it can be
written as a linear combination of few atoms: x = LZI C,8;, where k is small
relative to the ambient 2

dimensionality. They then use these atoms to generalize the idea behind
the use of i , -norm for sparsity, trace or nuclear norm for low rank, etc. Let
A be a collection of atoms. We start by assuming [2] that these atoms lie
in a ﬁnite-dimensional space, and that in particular A is a compact subset of
some Euclidean space RP. Later, in Section 6, we will extend our treatment to
include the case where the atoms belong to an inﬁnite-dimensional space. Let
CA denote the convex hull of A and deﬁne the gauge:

IlxiiA := inf{t ¡’: a : x E tCA)} .
(I)
Note that the gauge II . IIA is not a norm in general, unless for instance A
satisﬁes a technical condition, namely that it be centrally symmetric: x E A iﬀ
- x E A. Also, deﬁne the support function, IlxiiA := sup{ (x, a) : a E A}. If II
. IIA happens to be a norm, then this is just the dual norm of I . IIA.

2.2 Examples Example 1. (Sparse vectors) A huge amount of recent literature
deals with the notion of sparsity of high-dimensional vectors. Here, the set A
c RP of atoms is ﬁnite and consists of the 2p vectors ?ei. This is a centrally

3

symmetric set and hence II? IIA becomes a norm, viz. the i , -norm. Example 2.
(Sparse non-negative vectors) Using a slight variation on the previous example,
the atoms can be the p non-negative basis vectors ei. The convex hull CA is
the (p - I)-dimensional probability simplex. This is not centrally symmetric
and hence I . IIA is not a norm. Example 3. (Group sparse matrices) Here
the structure we have in mind for a p x k matrix is that it only has a few
non-zero rows. This generalizes Example I which can be thought of as the case
when k = 1. There are an inﬁnite number of atoms: all matrices with a single
non-zero row where that row has i.-norm I for some q ¿ 1. The convex hull CA
becomes the unit ball of the I . 11.,1 group normonRPxk that is deﬁned to be the
sum ofthel.-norms of the rows of its matrix argument. Example 4. (Low rank
matrices) This is another example that has attracted a huge amount of attention
in the recent literature. The set I A E RPxp of atoms here is inﬁnite and consists
of rankone matrices with Frobenius norm 1. This is centrally symmetric and
II?IIA becomes the trace norm (also called the nucleaTor Schatten-I norm, it
is equal to the sum of the singular values of a matrix). Example 5. (Low rank
tensors) This is a generalization of the previous example to higher order tensors.
Considering order three tensors, the set A of atoms can be taken to be all rank-
one tensors of the form U1 ¡8l U2 ¡8l Ua E Rpxpxp for Ui E RP, 1111;112 = 1.
Their convex hull is the unit ball of II . IIA which can thought of as the tensor
nuclear norm. Unfortunately, the tensor nuclear norm is intractable to compute
and hence there is a need to consider relaxations to retain tractability. Example
6. (Permutation matrices) Here, we consider permutation matrices2 of size p x
p as the set A of atoms. Even though there are p! of them, their convex hull
has a succinct description thanks to the BiTklwﬀ-von Newnann theorem: the
convex hull of permutation matrices is the set of doubly stochastic matrices.
As we shall see later, this fact will be crucial for the greedy algorithm to be
tractable in this case.

3 Problem. Setup We consider the general optimization problem
min
x: IIxIlA1t
f(x),
(2)
where f is a convex and smooth function, and {x: IlxiiA ::; ,,} is the atomic
norm constraint set that encourages some speciﬁc structure. This is a convex
optimiwtion problem that is a constrained version of the usual regularized prob-
lem, minx f(x) + I’llxIlA. A line of recent work (see, for example, [2], and the
references therein) has focused on diﬀerent cases, with diﬀerent atomic norms, i
For simplicity we consider square matrices. It is deﬁnitely also possible to con-
sider rectangular matrices in lRP1 XP2 for PI =f:. P2 2A pennutation matrix
is one consisting only of O’s & l’s such that there is exactly a single 1 in each
row & column. A non-negative matrix with every row & column sum equal to
1 is called a doubly stochastic matrix.

3
but largely on the linear case, where f(x) = lly - q.xll, for a given y E Rn and
a linear map ¡P : RP -¿ Rn. ¡P is typically a linear measurement operator that

4

generates a noisy measurement y E Rn from an underlying ”simple” signal Xt,
and 11?112 is the standard Euclidean norm in Rn. For the linear case, projected
gradient type methods have been suggested [2]. In this paper, we consider the
general problem in (2), with a general loss function f(x), and a general constraint
set induced by a structure-inducing atomic ”norm” II? IIA. 3 1

Smoothness
We now discuss our assumptions on the loss function f in (2). We start
by deﬁning a restricted smoothness property that we require for our analysis.
Consider a convex function f : RP -¿ R that is diﬀerentiable on some convex
subset S of RP. Given a norm 11?11 on RP, we would like to measure how
”smooth” the function f is on S with respect to 11?11. Towards this end, we
deﬁne the following: Deﬁnition 1. Given a set S, and nonn II ,11, we deﬁne the
Restricted Smoothness Property (RSP) constant of a function f : RP -¿ R as

L [[?11 (f ; S) :=
sup
x,yES,a:E(O,l]
f((l - a)x + ay) - f(x) - (V f(x), a(y - x)) 211 112 a Y- x
(3)
Since f is convex, it is clear that LII’II (f; S) ¡’: O. The larger it is, the larger
the function f ”curves up” on the set S. Remark 1. (Connection to Lipschitz
continuity of the gradient) Recall that a function f : RP -¿ R is said to have
L-Upschitz continuous gradients w.r.t. II ?11 if for all x, y E RP, we have IIV
f(x) V f(y)ll* ::; L ’lIx - yll where II . 11* is the norm dual to II . II. Using the
mean value theorem it is easy to see that if f has L-Upschitz continuous gradient
w.r.t. 11?11 then LII’II (f; S) ::; L. However, LII’II (f; S) can be much smaller
since it only looks at the behavior of f on S and cares less about the global
smoothness of f. Remark 2. (Connection to boundetiness of the Hessian) If the
function f is twice diﬀerentiable on S, using second order Taylor expansion, L II
’ II (f; S) can be bounded as LII’II (f; S)::;

sup
x,y,zES
(V2 f(z)(y - x),y - x) II xl12 Y
(4)
Again, suppose we have global control on V 2 f(x) in the form’lz E RP, IIIV2
fez) III ::; H where 111?111 is the II . II -¿ II . 11* operator norm of the matrix
M deﬁned as 111M III := sUPllxIl91IMxll*. Then, we immediately have LII’II
(f; S) ::; H but this inequality might be loose in general. In the statement of our
results, we will derive convergence rates that would depend on this Restricted
Smoothness Property (RSP) constant of the loss function f in (2).

4 Greedy Algorithm and Analysis In this section, we consider a general
greedy scheme to solve the general optimization problem in (2) where f is a
convex, smooth function. The idea is to add one atom to our representation at
a time in a way that the stucture of the set of atoms can be exploited to perform
the greedy step eﬃciently. Our greedy method is applicable to any constrained
problem where the objective is suﬃciently smooth.

5

Algorithm 1 A general greedy algorithm to minimize a convex function f over
the ”,-scaled atomicnorm ”ball” 1: Xo +- ”,ao for an arbitrary atom ao E A 2:
for t = 0, 1, 2, 3, ... do 3: a, +- argminaEA (V f(x,), a) 4: at +- argrninaE[o,l]
f(x, + a(”,at - Xt)) 5: Xt+l +- Xt + G’t(x;at - Xt) 6: end for

4
Theorem 1. Assume that ! is convex and diﬀerentiable and let II . II be any
norm. Then, for any 1. the iterates generated by Algorithm 1 lie in !¡CA and
satisfy.

T
(5)
for any solution x* o! (2). Here LII’II (/; !¡CA) is the smoothness constant

as deﬁned in (3) and IIAII := sUP.EA II all?

Proof. Let us use the abbreviations L and R for LII’II (/; S) and IIAII
respeetively. The fact that the iterates lie in !¡CA follows inunediately from the
deﬁnition of the algorithm and a simple induction. Now assuming Xt E ”CA.
we have, by deﬁnition of L, for any a E [0,1], 2 !(Xt + a(”at - Xt)) :S !(Xt) +
a (V!(Xt), ”at - Xt} + a2 LII”at - Xtl1 :S !(Xt) + a (V!(Xt), ”at - Xt} + a2 L
(211”atI1 2 + 211Xt112) :S !(Xt) - a( - (V!(Xt), ”at} + (V!(Xt),Xt)) + 2a2L,,2
R2 . (6) The last inequality holds because II”atll, IIXtl1 :S ”R. Now, for any
minimizer x* of!, we have, by convexity of !,
8t := !(Xt) - !(x*) :S (V !(Xt), Xt - x*) = (V!(Xt), Xt} - (V !(Xt), x*) :S (V
!(Xt), Xt) - (V!(Xt), ”at} .

(7)
The last inequality holds because, at is the minimizer of the linear function
(V!(Xt), -} over A (and Plugging (7) into (6), hence also over CA ) and x* /”
E CA. Thus, (V!(Xt), at} :S (V !Xt), x* we have, for any a 0, !(xt+a(”at -Xt))
:S !(Xt) -a8t +2a L,,2R . SinceXt+1 is chosen by minimizing theLHS over a E
[0,1]. we have !(Xt+1) :S !(Xt) + mina E[o,1] (-a8 t + 2a2L,,2R2). Thus, we
have, for all t O,8t +1 :S 8t + mina E[O,1] (-a8t + 2a2L,,2R2). For t = 0,
choose a = 1 on the RHS to get 8, :S 2L,,2 R2. Since 8t’s are decreasing, this
shows 8t :S 2L,,2 R2 for all t 1. Hence, for t 1, we can choose a = 8’;4L,,2 R2
E [0, ] on the RHS to get 1ft I, 8t+1 :S

t,,}.
8t -
8L!i R?. Solving this recursion easily gives, for all t I, !(Xt+1) - !(x*) :S

8.’..R’.

D
Remark 3. We emphasize that the norm II . II appears only in the analysis
and not in the algorithm. Since the bound of Theorem 1 is simultaneously
true for all norms II ,11, the best bound is achieved by choosing a norm that
minimizes the product of IIAI12 and LII’[[ (/; !¡CA). Remark 4. We make the
simple but useful observation that the iterate Xt can be written as a convex
combination of at most t + 1 atoms, namely Ro, a” ... , at. Remark 5. Given ”,
Algorithm 1 is completely parameter free. This is a nice feature from a practical
perspective as it frees the practitioner from the task of tuning parameters.

6

5 Special Cases Let us revisit the examples from Section 2.2 to see what
concrete algorithms and accuracy bounds we get by speeializing Algorithm 1
and its bound (Theorem I) to them. Sparse vectors

The greedy step reduces to at
¡-
argmin aE?{el, ... ,ep
(V!(Xt), a} . }
Clearly, assuming that the gradient is already available, this can be done in
O(P) time by ﬁnding j E {I, ... ,p} such thatj = argmaxj’ I[V!(Xt)];.I and setting
at = - sign([V!(xt)]j)ej. This actually gives a well-known algorithm whose roots
go back to the 1950s [3]. More recently, a vatiant appeared as the Forward
Greedy Selection algorithm in [5] (see also [4]). In fact, the original FrankWolfe
algorithm can be applied whenever the set CA is polyhedral. If we choose the
norm 11?11 to be iq then II All is 1 irrespective of q E [1,00] and the smoothness
constant LII’II (/; !¡CA) is an increasing function of q. Hence to minimize the
boond, we should choose p = 1 and measure smoothness of! over the It-scaled i
, -ball using the i , -norm. When !(x) = Ily - ef?xll. we can use the connection to
Hessian bounds (Remark 2) and inunediately get the upper bound 8,,2 . lief? T
ef?111oo/T where the norm IIMII¿oo := sUPllxll,¡;1 IIMxlloo is simply maxi,j
IMi,j I.

5
Sparse non-negative vectors
The greedy step becomes
a, ¡-
argmin
(’il J(x,), aJ
.
aE{el, ... ,e p }
& in the previous example, this can be done in O(P) time given the gradient
entries by computing j = argmin;’E{l, ... ,p} [’ilJ(x,)I;’ and setting a, = e;. This
particular algorithm to optimize a smooth function over the (scaled) probability
simplex appears in [6]. Following the same reasoning as above, we get the best
(among all i.-norms) bound if we choose II . II to be II . 111 and then our
smoothness constant becomes similar to Clarkson’s ”nonlinearity measure” that
he denotes by C f.

Group sparse matrices But still the greedy step
This is an interesting case since there are an inﬁnite number of atoms.
a, ¡-
(’ilJ(x,), aJ
argmin a: nnzrows(a)=l,IIBllq,l=l
(where nozrows counts the number of non-zero rows of a matrix) can be
computed easily as follows. Let ri be the dual exponent of q that satisﬁes I/q
+ I/ri = I and ﬁnd the row j of ’il J(x,) with maximal norm. Then, set a, to be
the matrix all of whose rows are zero except row j. In row j, place the vector
u T where u E Rkx1 is such that’ (u, [’ilJ(xtllD = -11[’ilJ(x,)lIII ?? and lIull.
= 1. Such a vector u can be found in closed form. For the case J(x,) = Ily -

7

il?xll, choosing the norm 11?11 in Theorem I to be 11,11.,1 (and this gives the
optinlal bound among allll?II.,r norms for r ¿ I), we get the accuracy bound:
8,,2 ’11iI?T il?11.,1 .,=/Twhere the q, I -+ q, 00 norm of the operator il?T iI?
is deﬁned as sup{lliI? T il?MII.,= : M E RPx., IIMII.,l :0; I}. This algorithm
and its analysis are novel to the best of our knowledge. However, we note that
a related greedy algorithm (that does not directly optimize the objective (2?
called Group-OMP appears in [14, 15].

i..
!
Low rank matrices As in the previous case, we have an inﬁnite number of

atoms: all rank-I matrices with Frobenius norm I. Yet, the greedy step

a, ¡-
argmin
(’il J(x,),
aJ
a: rank(a)=l,lIaIlF=l
can be done in polynomial time by computing the SVD, ’ilJ(x,) = UEV T
and setting a = -U1V! where U” v, are the left, right singular vectors correspond-
ing to the largest singular value 0’1. Since we only need the singular vectors
corresponding to the largest singular value, the computation of a, can be done
much faster than the time it takes to compute a full SVD. For the case J(x) =
Illy - il?xll, the bound of Theorem I is minimized, among all Schatten-pnorms”
by using 11?11 = Ils(l), i.e. the trsce or nuclear norm. Since the objective is
twice diﬀerentiable, using Remark 2 we get the following upper bound on the
accuracy: 8,,2 . IliI?T il?lls(l)s(=)/T which depends on the S(I) -+ operator
norm of iI? T iI? which is deﬁned as sup{lIiI? T il?Mlls(=) : M E RPxp, IIM-
lls(l) :0; I}. This algorithm was recently independently discovered and analyzed
in [7].
ﬀ?
stool
Low rank tensors
Here, the greedy step
a, ¡-
argmin
(’il J(x,), aJ
a: a=ul@u2I8lus,lIuiI12=1
appears intrsctable.

Indeed, the above problem is closely related to the
problem of ﬁnding the best rank-one approximLltion to a given tensor which is
known to be NP-hard [16] already for order-3 tensors. However, as described
in [2], it is possible to construct a fanilly of outer approximLltions CA ¡;; ???
¡;; THk+!
¡;; THk such that, for any ﬁxed k, THk can be described by a
semideﬁnite program of size polynomial in k. So, even though the exact greedy
step above may not be tractable, we can use these ”theta bodies” (whence the
notation ’TH”) to approximate the greedy step. The iterates will no longer
lie strictly in the tensor nuclear ball of the given radius. Understanding the
implications of such approximations and their analysis are interesting questions

8

to pursue but lie beyond the scope of the current paper. 3We use MATLAB
notation M j ,: to denote row j of a matrix M. 4The Schatten-q norm of a matrix
is the i q norm of its singular values. 6

Permutation matrices
Here, fortunately, we again do not face intractability: the step axgmin
aT ¡-
(V/(xt),a)
a : a is a permutation matrix
reduces to solving a linear assignment problem with costs C(i,j) = [V/(xtlk;.
This can be eﬃciently done using, for example, the Hungarian algorithm. An-
other way to see that the above step does not involve combinatorial explosion
is to appeal to the Birkhoﬀ-von Neumann theorem that statea that the convex
hull of permutation matrices is the set of doubly stochastic matrices. As a re-
sult, the above reduces to minimizing a linear objective (V I(xtl, M) subject to
polynomially many constraints: M 2’: 0, M1 = 1 and MT 1 = 1.

6 Extension to Inﬁnite Dimensional Banach Spaces 1n !hi section, we con-
sider an extension of the framework behind Algorithm 1 to the case when the
set of atoms are in some inﬁnite dimensional (real) Banach space (V, II . II). For
example, the atoms could be some ”simple” real valued functions on some inter-
val [a, b] JR. The two ingredients in our framework were the atomic norms, and
the Restricted Smoothness Property (RSP) parameters. 1n [2], and in Section
2.1, the atoms were considered as belonging to a ﬁnite dimensional Euclidean
space. Note however that the deﬁnition of the atomic norms in (1) did not make
use of the topology of the ambient space, and hence is applicable even when the
atoms belong to some Banach space (V, 11?11). However, our deﬁnition of the
RSP parameter in (3) relied critically on the Euclidean inner product, whence
we will now extend this to the inﬁnite dimensional case in the sequel. Consider
a convex continuous Frechet diﬀerentiable function I : V –+ JR, and let V I(x)
denote the Frechet derivative of I at x. Let (.,.) : V* x V –+ JR denotea the
bilinear function (which is not an inner product in general) (X, x) := X(x) for
x E V and X in the dual space V* (consisting of bounded linear functions on
V). Deﬁnition 2. Given a Banach space (V, II . II), and a set S V, and some
r E [1,2], we deﬁne the Restricted Uniform Smoothness Property (RUSP) con-
stant of a convex continuous Frechet diﬀerentiable function I : V –+ JR as 1((1
- a)x + ay) - I(x) - (V I(x), a(y - x)} Lr (/; S) := sup (8) (l/r) arlly - xll r
x,yES,o:E[O,l] This need not be bounded in general, but would be bounded for
instance if the function I were runiformly smooth (though this would be a far
stronger condition). Suppose the set of atoms A V is such that max.,E.A (X, a)
is deﬁned for any X E V*. Then, we can deﬁne a straightforward extension of
Algorithm I given as Algorithm 2. Algorithm 2 A general greedy algorithm to
minimize a continuous Frechet diﬀerentiable convex function lover the convex
hull of a set of atoms A in a Banach space (V, II ,11) 1: Xo ¡- ao for an arbitrary
atom ao E A 2: for t = 0, 1, 2, 3, ... do 3: X t E V* +- V I(xt), the Frechet
derivative of I at Xt 4: at ¡- argmaxaE.A (-Xt,a) 5: at +- argminaE[O,l] I(xt +
a(at - Xt)) 6: Xt+l +- Xt + at( at - Xt) 7: end for The following result proves
a general rate of convergence for Algorithm 2. Since the proof follows the proof

9

of Theorem I very closely, we defer it to the appendix. Theorem 2. Suppose
that (V, II . II) is a Banach space and let I : V –+ JR be a convex continuous
Frechet diﬀerentiable function. Let A be a set of atoms such that II all :¡; Rfor
all a E A, and let S = conv(A). Suppose the Restricted Uniform Smoothness
Property (RUSP) constant Lr (/; S) of I is boundedfor some r E [1,2]. Then,

I(xt) - inf I(x)
=
xES
where the hidden constant depends on r only. 7
0 (Lr (/; S)
tr
1
RT)
6.1 Rates of Convex Approximation in Lp spaces For p E (1,00) the space
Lp([a, b]) consists of all functions 9 :
[a, b] –¿ IR such that the (Lebesgue)
integral Ig(x)IPda; is ﬁoite. The space Lp is a Banach space once we eqoip it
with the norm

J:
(J:
IlgiIL. := Ig(x)IPda;) 1/? . LetA be a set of atoms in L. with bounded
norm and let hE L. be a function that we wish to approximate using convex
combinations of the atoms. Since, the function 9 r-¿ Ilgll is 1” = min{p, 2}
uoiformly smooth for p E(1,00), we can use Algorithm 2 to generate a sequence?
of functions 91, !J2, ... such that gt is a convex combination of only t atoms.
Moreover,
(,.t, ).
we will have the guarantee: Ilgt+1 - hll( - infgEconv(A) Ilg - hll( = 0 Such
rates of convex approximation in non-Hilbert spaces have been studied earlier
(see, for example, [10, II]). Note that, unlike [10), we do not assume that h E
conv(A). If that is the case, the above rate simpliﬁes to the rates given in [10):
O(t-1+) for p E (1,2), and orr!) for p ¿ 2.

6.2 Rates of Convex Approximation in Spaces with Martingale Type p Note
the fact that, in the previous subsection, the only property of L. spaces that
we used to get rates was the fact that the norm to some power was a uoiformly
smooth convex function.
It tums out that the existence ofuoiformly smooth
functions in a given Banach space is intimately connected to the behavior of
martingale diﬀerence sequences in that space. To precisely state the connection,
we need to deﬁne the notion of martingale type (also called Haar type) [17, p.
320). A Banach space (V, 11?11) is said to have martingale type p (M-type p in
short) if there exists a constant K. such that, for all T ;::: I, and any V -valued
martingale diﬀerence sequence d” ... ,dT, we have

Note that, by triangle inequality for norms, any Banach space always has M-
type I while a Hilbert space (i.e. the norm II . II comes from an inner product)
has M-type 2. Hilbert space essentially have the best M-type in the sense that
no Banach space has M-type p for p ¿ 2. The conoection of M-type to uoiform
smoothness is made precise by the following remarkable theorem (see also [18]).

10

Theorem (Pisier, [19). A Banach space has M-type p iﬀ there is an equivalent
norm’ 11?11# such thar the function II’II is p-uniformly smooth. Consider the
setting of the previous subsection where we have some hE conv(A) for some set
A of atoms in an arbitrary Banach space (V, 11?11). Using Pisier’s theorem, we
get the following corollary. Corollary3. Suppose A is a seto/atoms in a Banach
space (V, 11?11) that has M-typepand let hE conv(A). Suppose Algorithm 2
generates iterates g” g2, ... when run on the function 9 r-¿ Ilgll whose existence
is guaranteed byPisier’s theorem Then, we have,

Ilg’+1 - hll =
0
(C1+*).
7 Future Work First, we envisage the algorithm being used to compute the
entire regularization parh corresponding to all values of the constraint parameter
1¡. Using a warm start strategy, where the algorithm for higher values of I¡ is
ioitialized with the solution for lower values, can be very helpful here. Exploring
this to get a general practical algorithm to compute the entire path would be
very oice. Third, linear convergence guaraotees for projected gradient type
methods have been obtained by [13) where they make the additional assumption
of (generali2ed) restricted strong convexity.
It should be possible to derive
similar faster rates for our greedy algorithm.

Acknowledgments We gratefully acknowledge the support of NSF under
grant IIS-1018426. ISD acknowledges support from the Moncrief Grand Chal-
lenge Award.

’Thatis,cLII?1I
11’11# cull’ II forsomecL,cu ¿ O. 8

2 References

[I] S. Negahban, P. Ravikumar, M. Wainwrigbt, and B. Yu. A uniﬁed frame-
work for higb-dimensional analysis of M-estimators with decomposable regular-
izers. In Advances in Neural In/onnation Processing Systems 22, pages 1341¿-
1356,2009.

[2] V. Chandrasekaran, B. Rech P. A. Parri1o, and A. S. Willsky. The convex
geometry of linear inverse problems. In Proceedings of the 48th Annual Allerton
Conference on Communication, Control and Computing, pages 699-703, 2010.
[3] M. Frank and P. Wolfe. An algorithm for quadratic programming. Naval Re-
search Logistics Quarterly, 3(1-2):95-110,1956. [4] T. Zhang. Sequential greedy
approximation for certain convex optimization problems. IEEE Transactions
on Information T!reory, 49(3):682-{;91, 2003. [5] S. Shalev-Shwartz, N. Sre-
bro, and T. Zhang. Trading accuracy for sparsity in optimization problems with
sparsity constraints. SIAM Journal on Optimiuztion, 20(6):2807-2832, 2010.

[6] K. Clarkson. Coresets, sparse greedy approximation” and the Frank-
Wolfe algorithm.
In Proceedings of the nineteenth annual ACM-SIAM sym-
posiwn on discrete algorithms, pages 922-931. Society for Industrial and Applied
Matherustics, 2008.

11

[7] S. Shalev-Shwartz, A. Gonen, and O. Shamir. Large-scale convex mini-
mization with a low-rank constraint. In Proceedings o/the 28th International
Conference on Machine Learning. pages 329-336, 2011. [8] H. Liu and X. Chen.
Nonpararnetric greedy algorithms for the sparse learning problem. In Advances
in Neuralinformation Processing Systems 22, pages 1141-1149,2009. [9] A. Das
and D. Kempe. Submodular meets spectral: Greedy algorithms for subset selec-
tion” sparse approximation and dictionary selection. In Proceedings of the 28th
International Conference on Machine Learning, pages 1057-1064,2011. [10] M. 1.
Donahue, C. Darken, L. Gurvits, and E. Sontag. Rates of convex approximation
in non-Hilbert spaces. Constructive Approximation, 13(2):187-220,1997. [II] V.
N. Thmlyakov. Greedy approximation. Acta Numerica. 17:235-409,2008. [12]
R. E. Schapire. The boosting approach to machine learning: an overview. In D.
D. Denison, M. H. Hansen” C. C. Holmes, B. Mallick, and B. Yu, editors, Non-
linear estimation and classiﬁcation, volume 171 of Lecture Notes in Statistics,
pages 149-172. Springer, 2003.

[13] A. Agarwal, S. Negahban, and M. Wainwright. Fast global convergence
rates of gradient methods for high-dimensional statistical recovery. In Advances
in Neural Information Processing Systems 23, pages 37-45,2010.
[14] A. C.
Lozano, G. Swirszcz, and N. Abe. Grouped orthogonal matching pursuit for
variable selection and prediction. In Advances in Neural Information Processing
Systems 22, pages 1150–1158, 2009. [15] A. C. Lozano, G. Swirszcz, and N. Abe.
Grouped orthogonal matching pursuit for logistic regression. In Proceedings of
the Fourteenth International Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence and Statistics,
volume 15 of JMLR Workshop and Conference Proceedings, 2011. [16] C. Hillar
andL.-H. Lim. Most tensor problems areNF hard, 2010. available at http:/ /
arxiv. org/ abs/0911.1393v2.

[17] A. Pietsch. History of Banach spaces and linear operators. Birkhiuser,
2007. [18] 1. Borwein, A. 1. Guirao, P. Hljek, and 1. Vanderwerﬀ. Uniformly
convex functions in Banach spaces. Proceedings of the American Marhematical
Society, 137(3):1081-1091, 2009.

[19] G. Pisier. Martingales with values in uniformly convex spaces. Israel

Journal of Mathematics, 20(34):326-350, 1975.

9

12

