Probabilistic Low-Rank Subspace Clustering

Authored by:

Shinichi Nakajima

S. D. Babacan

Minh Do

Abstract

In this paper, we consider the problem of clustering data points into
low-dimensional subspaces in the presence of outliers. We pose the prob-
lem using a density estimation formulation with an associated generative
model. Based on this probability model, we ﬁrst develop an iterative
expectation-maximization (EM) algorithm and then derive its global so-
lution. In addition, we develop two Bayesian methods based on variational
Bayesian (VB) approximation, which are capable of automatic dimension-
ality selection. While the ﬁrst method is based on an alternating opti-
mization scheme for all unknowns, the second method makes use of recent
results in VB matrix factorization leading to fast and eﬀective estimation.
Both methods are extended to handle sparse outliers for robustness and
can handle missing values. Experimental results suggest that proposed
methods are very eﬀective in clustering and identifying outliers.

1 Paper Body

Modeling data using low-dimensional representations is a fundamental approach
in data analysis, motivated by the inherent redundancy in many datasets and
to increase the interpretability of data via dimensionality reduction. A classical
approach is principal component analysis (PCA), which implicitly models data
to live in a single low-dimensional subspace within the high-dimensional ambi-
ent space. However, a more suitable model in many applications is the union of
multiple low-dimensional subspaces. This modeling leads to the more challeng-
ing problem of subspace clustering, which attempts to simultaneously cluster
data points into multiple subspaces and ﬁnd the basis of the corresponding sub-
space for each cluster. Mathematically, subspace clustering can be deﬁned as
follows: Let Y be the M ? N data matrix consisting of N vectors {yi ? RM }N
i=1 , which are assumed be drawn from a union of K linear (or aﬃne) subspaces
Sk of unknown dimensions dk = dim(Sk ) with 0 ¡ dk ¡ M . The subspace clus-
tering problem is to ﬁnd the number of subspaces K, their dimensions {dk }K
k=1 , the subspace bases, and the clustering of vectors yi into these subspaces.

1

Subspace clustering is widely investigated problem due to its application in a
large number of ﬁelds, including computer vision [6, 12, 23], machine learning
[11, 22] and system identiﬁcation [31] (see [22, 28] for comprehensive reviews).
Some of the common approaches include algebraicgeometric approaches such as
generalized PCA (GPCA) [19, 29], spectral clustering [18], and mixture models
[9, 26]. Recently, there has been a great interest in methods based on sparse
and/or low-rank representation of the data [5, 7, 8, 14?17, 25]. The general
approach in these methods is to ﬁrst ﬁnd a sparse/low-rank representation X of
the data and then apply a spectral clustering method on X. It has been shown
that with appropriate modeling, X provides information about the seg1

mentation of the vectors into the subspaces. Two common models for X are
summarized below. ? Sparse Subspace Clustering (SSC) [7, 25]: This approach
is based on representing data points yi as sparse linear combinations of other
data points. A possible optimization formulation is min ?kY ? Dk2F + kD ?
DXk2F + ?kXk1 , subject to diag(X) = 0 , (1) D,X

where k ? kF is the Frobenius norm and k ? k1 is the l1 -norm. ? Low-Rank
Representation (LRR) [8, 14?17] : These methods are based on a principle
similar to SSC, but X is modeled as low-rank instead of sparse. A general
formulation for this model is min ?kY ? Dk2F + kD ? DXk2F + ?kXk? , (2)
D,X

where k ? k? is the nuclear norm.

In these formulations, D is a clean
dictionary and data Y is assumed to be the noisy version of D possibly with
outliers. When ? ? ?, Y = D, and thus the data itself is used as the dictionary
[7,15,25]. If the subspaces are disjoint or independent1 , the solution X in both
formulations is shown to be such that Xik 6= 0 only if data points yi and yk
belong to the same subspace [7, 14, 15, 25]. That is, the sparsest/lowest rank
solution is obtained when each point yi is represented as a linear combination
of points in its own subspace. The estimated X is used to deﬁne an aﬃnity
matrix [18] such as —X— + —XT — and a spectral clustering algorithm, such
as normalized cuts [24], is applied on this aﬃnity to cluster the data vectors.
The subspace bases can then be obtained in a straightforward manner using
this clustering. These methods have also been extended to include sparse out-
liers. In this paper, we develop probabilistic modeling and inference procedures
based on a principle similarly to LRR. Speciﬁcally, we formulate the problem
using a latent variable model based on the factorized form X = AB, and develop
inference procedures for estimating A, B, D (and possibly outliers), along with
the associated hyperparameters. We ﬁrst show a maximum-likelihood formula-
tion of the problem, which is solved using an expectation-maximization (EM)
method. We derive and analyze its global solution, and show that it is related
to closed-form solution of the rankminimization formulation (2) in [8]. To in-
corporate automatic estimation of the latent dimensionality of subspaces and
the algorithmic parameters, we further present two Bayesian approaches: The
ﬁrst one is based on same probability model as the EM method, but additional
priors are placed on the latent variables and variational Bayesian inference is
employed for approximate marginalization to avoid overﬁtting. The second one
is based on a matrix-factorization formulation, and exploits the recent results on

2

Bayesian matrix factorization [20] to achieve fast estimation that is less prone to
errors due to alternating optimization. Finally, we extent both methods to han-
dle large errors (outliers) in the data, to achieve robust estimation. Compared
to deterministic methods, proposed Bayesian methods have the advantages of
automatically estimating the dimensionality and the algorithmic parameters.
This is crucial in unsupervised clustering as the parameters can have a drastic
eﬀect on the solution, especially in the presence of heavy noise and outliers.
While our methods are closely related to Bayesian PCA [2, 3, 20] and mixture
models [9, 26], our formulation is based on a diﬀerent model and leads to ro-
bust estimation less dependent on the initialization, which is one of the main
disadvantages of such methods.

2
Probabilistic Model for Low-Rank Subspace Clustering
In the following, without loss of generality we assume that M ? N and Y is
full row-rank. We also assume that each subspace is suﬃciently sampled, that
is, for each Si of dimension di , there exist at least di data vectors yi in Y that
span Si . As for notation, the expectations are denoted by h ? i, N is the
normal distribution, and diag() denotes the diagonal of a matrix. We do not
diﬀerentiate the variables from the parameters of the model to have a uniﬁed
presentation throughout the paper. We formulate the latent variable model as
yi = di + nY , di = DAbi + nD ,

i = 1, . . . , N
(3) (4)
L PK L 1 The subspaces Sk are called independent if dim( K the direct sum.
k=1 SK ) = k=1 dim(Sk ) with The subspaces are disjoint if they only intersect
at the origin.

2
where D is M ? N , A is N ? N , and nY , nD are i.i.d. Gaussian noise

independent of the data. The associated probability model is given by2

p(yi —di ) = N yi — di , ?y2 IM , (5)
p(di —D, A, bi ) = N di — DAbi , ?d2 IM , (6) p(bi ) = N (bi —0, IN ) .
(7) QN
We model the components as independent such that p(Y—D) = i=1 p(yi
—di ), p(D—A, B) = QN QN i=1 p(di —D, A, bi ), and p(B) = i=1 p(bi ).
This model has the generative interpretation where latent vectors bi are drawn
from an isotropic Gaussian distribution, shaped by A to obtain Abi , which then
chooses a sample of points from the dictionary D to generate the ith dictionary
element di . In this sense, matrix DA has a role similar to principal subspace
matrix in probabilistic principal component analysis (PPCA) [26]. However,
notice that in contrast to this and related approaches such as mixture of PPCAs
[9, 26], the principal subspaces are deﬁned using the data itself in (6). In (5),
the observations yi are modeled as corrupted versions of dictionary elements di
with iid Gaussian noise. Such separation of D and Y is not necessary if there
are no outliers, as the presence of noise nY and nD makes them unidentiﬁable.
However, we use this general formulation to later include outliers. 2.1

An Expectation-Maximization (EM) Algorithm

3

In (5) - (7), latent variables bi can be regarded as missing data and D, A
as parameters, and an EM algorithm can be devised for their joint estimation.
The complete log-likelihood is given by LC =

N X
log p(yi , bi )
(8)
i=1
with p(yi , bi ) = p(yi —di ) p(di —D, A, bi ) p(bi ). The EM algorithm
can be obtained by taking the expectation of this log-likelihood with respect to
(w.r.t.) B (E-step) and maximizing it w.r.t. D, A, ?d , and ?y (M-step). In the
E-step, the distribution p(B—D, A, ?d2 ) is found as N (hBi, ?B ) with hBi =
?B

1 T T A D D, ?d2
??1 B =I+
1 T T A D DA , ?d2
(9)
and the expectation of the likelihood is taken w.r.t. this distribution. In the
M-step, maximizing the expected log-likelihood w.r.t. D and A in an alternating
fashion yields the update equations

?1 ?1 1 1 1 T T , A = hBi hBBT i , (10) D = 2 Y 2 I + 2 h (I ? AB) (I ?
AB) iB ?y ?y ?d with hBBT i = BBT + N ?B . Finally, the estimates of ?d2
and ?y2 are found as ?d2 =

kD ? DAhBik2F + N tr(AT DT DA?B ) , MN
?y2 =
kY ? Dk2F . MN
(11)
In summary, the maximum likelihood solution is obtained by an alternating
iterative procedure where ﬁrst the statistics of B are calculated using (9), fol-
lowed by the M-step updates for D, A, ?d , and ?y in (10) and (11), respectively.
2.2

Global Solution of the EM algorithm
Although the iterative EM algorithm above can be applied to estimate A,
B, D, the global solutions can in fact be found in closed form. Speciﬁcally, the
optimal solution is found (see the supplementary) as either AhBi = 0 or

? ?2 VT , AhBi = Vq Iq ? N ?d2 ? q q
(12)
2 Here we assume that Abi 6= wi where wi is a zero vector with 1 as the
ith coeﬃcient, to have a proper density. This is a reasonable assumption if each
subspace is suﬃciently sampled and the dictionary element di belongs to one of
them (i.e., it is not an outlier). Outliers are explicitly handled later.

3
? ? j = max(?j , N ?d ). Here, D = U?VT ? q is a q ? q diagonal matrix
with coeﬃcients ? where ? is the singular value decomposition (SVD) of D, and
Vq contains ? its q right singular vectors that correspond to singular values
that are larger than or equal to N ?d . Hence, the solution (12) is related to the
rank-q shape interaction matrix (SIM) Vq VqT [6], while in addition it involves

4

scaling of the singular vectors via thresholded singular values of D. Using AhBi
in (10), the singular vectors of the optimal D and Y are found to be the same,
and the singular values ?j of D are related to the singular values ?j of Y as ? (
?j + N ?y2 ??1 N ?d j , if ?j ¿ ? ?j = (13) ?y2 +?d2 ?j ? 2 , if ?j ? N ?d d

This is a combination of two operations: down-scaling and the solutions
a quadratic equation, where the latter is a polynomial thresholding operation
on the singular values ?j of Y (see supplementary). Hence, the optimal D is
obtained by applying the thresholding operation (13) on the singular values of
Y, where the shrinkage amount is small for large singular values so that they
are preserved, whereas small singular values are shrank by down-scaling. This
is an interesting result, as there is no explicit penalty on the rank of D in our
modeling. As shown in [8], the nuclear norm formulation (2) leads to a similar
closed-form solution, but it requires the solution of a quartic equation. Finally,
at the stationary points, the noise variance ?d2 is found as ?d2 =

1 N ?q
N X
?2q0 ,
(14)
q 0 =q+1
that is, the average of the squared discarded singular values of D when
computing DAhBi. A simple closed form expression of ?y2 cannot be found
due to the polynomial thresholding in (13), but it can simply be calculated
using (11). In summary, if ?y2 and ?d2 are given, the optimal D and AhBi are
found by taking the SVD of Y and applying shrinkage/thresholding operations
on the singular values of Y. However, this method requires setting ?y2 and
?d2 manually. When Y itself is used as the dictionary D (i.e., ?y2 = 0), an
alternative method is to choose q, the total number of independent dimensions
to be retained in DAhBi, calculate ?d2 from (14), and ﬁnally use (12) to obtain
AhBi. However, when ?y2 6= 0, q cannot directly be set and a trial-and-error
procedure is required to ﬁnd it. Although ?d2 and ?y2 can also be estimated
automatically using the iterative EM procedure in Sec. 2.1, this method is
susceptible to local minima, as the trivial solution AhBi = 0 also maximizes the
likelihood. These issues can be overcome by employing a Bayesian estimation to
automatically determine the eﬀective dimensionality of D and AB. We develop
two methods towards this goal, which are described next.

3
Variational Bayesian Low-Rank Subspace Clustering
Bayesian estimation of D, A and B can be achieved by treating them as
latent variables to be marginalized over to avoid overﬁtting and trivial solutions
such as AB = 0. Here we develop such a method based on the probability
model in the previous section but with additional priors introduced on A, B
and the noise variances. Before presenting our complete probability model, we
ﬁrst introduce the matrix-variate normal distribution as its use signiﬁcantly
simpliﬁes the algorithm derivation. For a M ? N matrix X, the matrix-variate
normal distribution is given by [10]

NM N M 1 T N (X—M, ?, ?) = (2?) 2 —?—? 2 —?—? 2 exp ? tr ??1 (X ?

5

M) ??1 (X ? M) (15) 2 where M is the mean, and ?, ? are M ? M row and N ?
N column covariances, respectively. To automatically determine the number of
principal components in AB, we employ an automatic relevance determination
mechanism [21] on the columns of A and rows of B using priors p(A) = N (A—0,
I, CA ), p(B) = N (B—0, CB , I), where CA and CB are diagonal matrices with
CA = diag(cA,i ) and CB = diag(cB,i ), i = 1, . . . , N . Jeﬀrey?s priors are
placed on cA,i and cB,i , and they are assumed to be independent. To avoid
scale ambiguity, the columns of A and rows of B can also be coupled using the
same set of hyperparameters CA = CB , as in [1]. 4

For inference, we employ the variational Bayesian (VB) method [4] which
leads to a fast algorithm. Let q(D, A, B, CA , CB , ?d2 , ?y2 ) be the distribution
that approximates the posterior. The variational free energy is given by the
following functional F = h log q(D, A, B, CA , CB , ?d2 , ?y2 ) ? log p(Y, D,
A, B, CA , CB , ?d2 , ?y2 )i .

(16)
Using the mean ﬁeld approximation, the approximate posterior is factorized
as q(D, A, B, CA , CB , ?d2 , ?y2 ) = q(D) q(A) q(B) q(CA ) q(CB ) q(?d2
) q(?y2 ). Using the priors deﬁned above with the conditional distributions in
(5) and (6), the approximating distributions of D, A and B minimizing the free
energy F are found as matrix-variate normal distributions3 q(D) = N (hDi, I,
?D ), q(A) = N (hAi, ?A , ?A ) and q(B) = N (hBi, ?B , I), with parameters

1 1 1 T hDi = 2 Y ?D , ??1 = IN + 2 h (I ? AB) (I ? AB) i (17) D 2 h?y
i h?y i h?d i 1 1 tr(?A hBBT i) hDT Di tr(C?1 (18) ??1 A ?A ) I + A = N N
?d2 1 1 ??1 tr(?A hDT Di) hBBT i tr(?A )C?1 (19) A = A + N N ?d2 1 1 T T
T T (20) hAiC?1 A + 2 hD DihAihBB i = 2 hD DihBi ?d ?d 1 1 ?1 hBi = ?B
2 hAT DT Di, ??1 hAT DT DAi . (21) B = CB + h?d i h?d2 i The estimate
hAi in (20) is solved using ﬁxed-point iterations. The hyperparameter updates
are given by hc?1 A,i i =

N , hAT Aiii
hc?1 B,i i =
N , diag(hBBT iii )
(22)
hkD ? DABk2F i hkY ? Dk2F i , h?y2 i = . (23) MN MN Explicit forms of the
required moments are given in the supplementary. In summary, the algorithm
alternates between calculating the suﬃcient statistics of the distributions of D,
A and B, and the updates of the hyperparameters cA,i , cB,i , ?d2 and ?y2 . The
convergence can be monitored during iterations using the variational free energy
F. F is also useful in model comparison, which we use for detecting outliers, as
explained in Sec. 5. h?d2 i =

Similarly to the matrix factorization approaches [2, 3, 13], automatic dimen-
sionality selection is invoked via hyperparameters cA,i and cB,i , which enforce
sparsity in the columns and rows of A and B, respectively. Speciﬁcally, when a
particular set of variances cA,i , cB,i assume very small values, the posteriors of
the ith column of A and ith row of B will be concentrated around zero, such that
the eﬀective number of principal directions in AB will be reduced. In practice,
this is performed via thresholding of variances cA,i , cB,i with a small threshold

6

(e.g., 10?10 ).

4
A Factorization-Based Variational Bayesian Approach
Another Bayesian method can be developed by further investigating the
probability model. Essentially, the estimates of A and B is based on the fac-
torization of D and are independent of Y. Thus, one can apply a matrix factor-
ization method to D, and relate this factorization to DAB to ﬁnd AB. Based
on this idea, we modify the probabilistic model to p(D) = N (D—DL DR , I,
?12 I), d p(DL ) = N (DL —0, I, CL ), p(DR ) = N (DR —0, CR , I), where
diagonal covariances CL and CR are used to induce sparsity in the columns of
DL and rows of DR , respectively. It has been shown in [20] that when varia-
tional Bayesian inference is applied to this model, the global solution is found
analytically and given by DL DR = U?F VT ,

(24)
3 The optimal distribution q(A) does not have a matrix-variate normal form.
However, we force it to have this form for computational eﬃciency (see supple-
mentary for details).

5
where U, V contain the singular vectors of D, and ?F is a diagonal matrix,
obtained by applying a speciﬁc shrinkage method to the singular values of D [20].
The number of retained singular values are therefore automatically determined.
Then, setting DL DR equal to DAB, we obtain the solution T AB = Vf ??1 f
?F Vf , where the subscript f denotes the retained singular value and vectors.
The only modiﬁcation to the method in the previous section is to replace the
estimation of A and T B in (18)-(21) with the global solution Vf ??1 f ?F Vf
. Thus, this method allows us to avoid the alternating optimization for ﬁnding
A and B, which potentially can get stuck in undesired local minima. Although
the probability model is slightly diﬀerent than the one described in the previous
section, we anticipate that its global solution to be related to the factorization-
based solution.

5
Robustness to Outliers
Depending on the application, the outliers might be in various forms. For
instance in motion tracking applications, an entire data point might become an
outlier if the tracker fails at that instance. In other applications, only a subset
of coordinates might be corrupted with large errors. Both types (and possibly
others) can be handled in our modeling. The only required change in the model
is in the conditional distribution of the observations as p(Y—D) = N (Y—D +
E, ?y2 ) ,

(25)
where E is the sparse outlier matrix for which we introduce the prior R C R

p(E) = N (E—0, CC E , CE ) = N (vec(E)—0, CE ? CE ) .

(26)
R The shape of the column covariance matrix CC E and row covariance
matrix CE depends on the nature C of outliers. If only entire data points might
be corrupted, we can use CE = I and independent terms R R in CR E such that

7

CE = diag(cE,i ), i = 1, . . . , N . When entire coordinates can be corrupted,
C C row-sparsity in E can be imposed using CR E = I and CE = diag(cE,i ).
In the ﬁrst case, the VB estimation rule becomes q(ei ) = N (hei i, I, ?ei ) with
!?1 1 1 1 hei i = ?ei 2 (yi ? hdi i) ?ei = diag + , (27) h?y i h?y2 i hcR E,i i T
with the hyperparameter update hcR E,i i = hei i hei i+tr (?ei ). The
estimation rules for other outlier models can be derived in a similar manner. In
the presence of outlier data points, there is an inherent unidentiﬁability between
AB and E which can prevent the detection of outliers and hence reduce the
performance of subspace clustering. Speciﬁcally, an outlier yi can be included
in the sparse component as ei = yi or included in the dictionary D with its own
subspace, which leads to (AB)ii ? 1. To avoid the latter case, we introduce
a heuristic inspired by the birth and death method in [9]. During iterations,
data points yi with (AB)ii larger than a threshold (e.g., 0.95) are assigned to
the sparse component ei . As this might initially increase the variational energy
F, we monitor its progress over a few iterations and reject this ?birth? of the
sparse component if F does not decrease below its original state. This method
is observed to be very eﬀective in identifying outliers and alleviating the eﬀect
of the initialization. Finally, missing valuesQ in Y can also be handled by
modifying the distribution of the observations in (5) to p(yi —di ) = k?Zi N yik
— dik , ?y2 , where Zi is the set containing the indices of the observed entries
in vector yi . The inference procedures can be modiﬁed with relative ease to
accommodate this change.

6
Experiments
In this section, we evaluate the performance of the three algorithms intro-
duced above, namely, the EM method in Sec. 2.2, the variational Bayesian
method in Sec. 3 (VBLR) and the factorizationbased method in Sec. 4 (VBLR-
Fac). We also include comparisons with deterministic subspace clustering and
mixture of PPCA (MPPCA) methods. In all experiments, the estimated AB
matrix is used to ﬁnd the aﬃnity matrix and the normalized cuts algorithm [24]
is applied to ﬁnd the clustering and hence the subspaces. 6

110
LRR (? = 0.01) LRR (? = 0.16) VBLR VBLR?Fac MPPCA
Clustering accuracy (%)
100 90 80 70 60 50 40
(a)
(b)
30 0
Figure 1: Clustering 1D subspaces (points in the same cluster are in the
same color) (a) MPPCA [3] result, (b) the result of the EM algorithm (global
solution). The Bayesian methods give results almost identical to (b).

20
40 60 80 Percentage of Outliers (%)
100
Figure 2: Accuracy of clustering 5 independent subspaces of dimension 5 for

diﬀerent percentage of outliers.

8

Synthetic Data. We generated 27 line segments intersecting at the origin,
as shown in Fig. 1, where each contains 800 points slightly corrupted by iid
Gaussian noise of variance 0.1. Each line can be considered as a separate 1D
subspace, and the subspaces are disjoint but not independent. We ﬁrst applied
the mixture of PPCA [3] to which we provided the dimensions and the number
of the subspaces. This method is sensitive to the proximity of the subspaces, and
in all of our trials gave results similar to Fig. 1(a), where close lines are clustered
together. On the other hand, the EM method accurately clusters the lines into
diﬀerent subspaces (Fig. 1(b)), and it is extremely eﬃcient involving only one
SVD. Both Bayesian methods VBLR and VBLR-Fac gave similar results and
accurately estimated the subspace dimensions, while the VB-variant of MPPCA
[9] gave results similar to Fig. 1(a). Next, similarly to the setup in [15], we
construct 5 independent subspaces {Si } ? R50 of dimension 5 with bases Ui
generated as follows: We ﬁrst generate a random 50 ? 5 orthogonal matrix U1 ,
and then rotate it with random orthonormal matrices Ri to obtain Ui = Ri U1 ,
i = 2, 3, 4. Dictionary D is obtained by sampling 25 points from each subspace
using Di = Ui Vi where Vi are 5 ? 25 matrices with elements drawn from N (0,
1). Finally, Y is obtained by corrupting D with outliers sampled from N (0, 1)
and normalized to lie on the unit sphere. We applied our methods VBLR and
VBLR-Fac to cluster the data into 5 groups, and compare their performance
with MPPCA and LRR. Average clustering errors (over 20 trials) in Fig. 2
show that LRR and the proposed methods provide much better performance
than MPPCA. VBLR and VBLR-Fac gave similar results, while VBLR-Fac
converges much faster (generally about 10 vs 100 iterations). Although LRR
also gives very good results, its performance varies with its parameters. As
an example, we included its results obtained by the optimal and a slightly
diﬀerent parameter value, where in the latter case the degradation in accuracy
is evident. Table 1: Clustering errors (%) on the Hopkins155 motion database
Method Mean Max Std

GPCA [19] 30.51 55.67 11.79
LSA [30] 8.77 38.37 9.80
SSC [7] 3.66 37.44 7.21
LRR [15] 1.71 32.50 4.85
VBLR 1.75 35.13 4.92
VBLR-Fac 1.85 37.32 5.10
Real Data with Small Corruptions. The Hopkins155 motion database [27] is
frequently used to test subspace clustering methods. It consists of 156 sequences
where each contains 39 to 550 data vectors corresponding to either 2 or 3 mo-
tions. Each motion corresponds to a subspace and each sequence is regarded as
a separate clustering task. While most existing methods use a pre-processing
stage that generally involves dimensionality reduction using PCA, we do not em-
ploy pre-processing and apply our Bayesian methods directly (the EM method
cannot handle outliers and thus is not included in the experiments). The mean
and maximum clustering errors and the standard deviation in the whole set are
shown in Table 1. The proposed methods provide close to state-of-the-art per-
formance, while competing methods require manual tuning of their parameters,

9

which can aﬀect their performance. For instance, the results of LRR is obtained
by setting its parameter ? = 4, while changing it to ? = 2.4 gives 3.13% error
[15]. The method in [8], which is similar to our EM7

method except that it also handles outliers, achieves an error rate of 1.44%.
Finally, the deterministic method [17] achieves an error rate of 0.85% and to
our knowledge, is the best performing method in this dataset. Real Data with
Large Corruptions. To test our methods in real data with large corruptions, we
use the Extended Yale Database B [12] where we chose the ﬁrst 10 classes that
contain 640 frontal face images. Each class contains 64 images and each image
is resized to 48 ? 42 and stacked to generate the data vectors. Figure 3 depicts
some example images, where signiﬁcant corruption due to shadows and heavy
noise is evident. The task is to cluster the 640 images into 10 classes. The
segmentation accuracies achieved by the proposed methods and some existing
methods are listed in Table 2, where it is evident that the proposed meth-
ods achieve state-of-art-performance. Example recovered clean dictionary and
sparse outlier components are shown in Fig. 3. Table 2: Clustering accuracy
(%) on the Extended Yale Database B Method Average

Y
LSA [30] 31.72
SSC [7] 37.66
VBLR DAB
LRR [15] 62.53
E
VBLR 69.72
VBLR-Fac 67.62
VBLR-Fac DAB E
Figure 3: Examples of recovered clean data and large corruptions. Origi-
nal images are shown in the left column (denoted by Y), the clean dictionary
elements obtained by VBLR and VBLR-Fac are shown in columns denoted by
DAB, and columns denoted by E show corruption captured by the sparse ele-
ment.
7
Conclusion
In this work we presented a probabilistic treatment of low dimensional
subspace clustering. Using a latent variable formulation, we developed an
expectation-maximization method and derived its global solution. We further
proposed two eﬀective Bayesian methods both based on the automatic relevance
determination principle and variational Bayesian approximation for inference.
While the ﬁrst one, VBLR, relies completely on alternating optimization, the
second one, VBLR-Fac, makes use of the global solution of VB matrix factor-
ization to eliminate one alternating step and leads to faster convergence. Both
methods have been extended to handle sparse large corruptions in the data
for robustness. These methods are advantageous over deterministic methods
as they are able to automatically determine the total number of principal di-
mensions and all required algorithmic parameters. This property is particularly
important in unsupervised settings. Finally, our formulation can potentially be

10

extended for modeling multiple nonlinear manifolds, by the use of kernel meth-
ods. Acknowledgments. The authors thank anonymous reviewers for helpful
comments. SDB acknowledges the Beckman Institute Postdoctoral Fellowship.
SN thanks the support from MEXT Kakenhi 23120004. MND was partially
supported by NSF CHE 09-57849. 8

2 References

In CVPR, pages 2790?2797, 2009.

[2] C. M. Bishop. Bayesian principal components.

[1] S. D. Babacan, M. Luessi, R. Molina, and A. K. Katsaggelos. Sparse Bayesian
methods for low-rank matrix estimation. IEEE Trans. Signal Proc., 60(8), Aug
2012.
In NIPS, volume
[3] C. M. Bishop. Variational principal components.
11, pages 382?388, 1999.
In Proc. of ICANN, volume 1, pages 514?509, 1999.
[4] C.M. Bishop. Pat-
tern Recognition and Machine Learning. Springer, 2006.
[5] E. J. Cand‘es,
X. Li, Y. Ma, and J. Wright. Robust principal component analysis? CoRR,
[6] J. P. Costeira and T. Kanade. A multibody factor-
abs/0912.3599, 2009.
ization method for independently moving objects.
Int. J. Comput. Vision,
[7] E. Elhamifar and R. Vidal. Sparse sub-
29(3):159?179, September 1998.
space clustering.
[8] P. Favaro, R. Vidal,
and A. Ravichandran. A closed form solution to robust subspace estimation
and clustering. In CVPR, pages 1801?1807, 2011. [9] Z. Ghahramani and M. J.
Beal. Variational inference for Bayesian mixtures of factor analysers. In NIPS,
volume 12, pages 449?455, 2000.
[10] A. K. Gupta and D. K. Nagar. Matrix
Variate Distributions. Chapman & Hall/CRC, New York, 2000. [11] K. Huang
and S. Aviyente. Sparse representation for signal classiﬁcation. In NIPS, 2006.
[12] K.-C. Lee, J. Ho, and D. Kriegman. Acquiring linear subspaces for face
recognition under variable lighting. IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Machine In-
[13] Y. J. Lim and T. W. Teh. Variational Bayesian
tell., 27:684?698, 2005.
approach to movie rating prediction.
In Proc. of KDD Cup and Workshop,
2007.
[14] G. Liu, Z. Lin, S. Yan, J. Sun, Y. Yu, and Y. Ma. Robust recov-
ery of subspace structures by low-rank representation. CoRR, abs/1010.2955,
[15] G. Liu, Z. Lin, and Y. Yu. Robust subspace segmentation by low-
2012.
rank representation. In ICML, pages 663?670, 2010.
[16] G. Liu, H. Xu, and
S. Yan. Exact subspace segmentation and outlier detection by low-rank repre-
sentation. In AISTATS, 2012.
[17] G. Liu and S. Yan. Latent low-rank rep-
resentation for subspace segmentation and feature extraction. In ICCV, 2011.
[18] U. Luxburg. A tutorial on spectral clustering. Statistics and Computing,
17(4):395?416, December 2007. [19] Y. Ma, A. Yang, H. Derksen, and R. Fos-
sum. Estimation of subspace arrangements with applications in modeling and
segmenting mixed data,. SIAM Review, 50(3):413?458, 2008.
[20] S. Naka-
jima and M. Sugiyama. Theoretical analysis of Bayesian matrix factorization.
Journal of Machine Learning Research, 12:2583?2648, 2011.
[21] R. M. Neal.
Bayesian Learning for Neural Networks. Springer, 1996. [22] H. Peterkriegel, P.
Kroger, and A. Zimek. Clustering high-dimensional data: a survey on subspace
slustering, pattern-based clustering, and correlation clustering. In Proc. KDD,

11

2008. [23] S. Rao, R. Tron, R. Vidal, and Y. Ma. Motion segmentation in the
presence of outlying, incomplete, or corrupted trajectories. IEEE Trans. Pat-
tern Anal. Machine Intell., 32(10):1832?1845, 2010.
[24] J. Shi and J. Malik.
Normalized cuts and image segmentation. IEEE Trans. Pattern Anal. Machine
Intell., 22(8):888 ?905, aug 2000. [25] M. Soltanolkotabi and E. J. Cand‘es. A
geometric analysis of subspace clustering with outliers. CoRR, 2011.
[26] M.
E. Tipping and C. M. Bishop. Mixtures of probabilistic principal component
analyzers. Neural Comput., 11(2):443?482, February 1999. [27] R. Tron and R.
Vidal. A benchmark for the comparison of 3-d motion segmentation algorithms.
In CVPR, June 2007.
[28] R. Vidal. Subspace clustering. IEEE Signal Pro-
cess. Mag., 28(2):52?68, 2011. [29] R. Vidal, Y. Ma, and S. Sastry. Generalized
principal component analysis (gpca). IEEE Trans. on PAMI, 27(12):1945?1959,
2005. [30] J. Yan and M. Pollefeys. A general framework for motion segmenta-
tion: Independent, articulated, rigid, non-rigid, degenerate and non-degenerate.
In ECCV, volume 4, pages 94?106, 2006.
[31] C. Zhang and R. R. Bitmead.
Subspace system identiﬁcation for training-based MIMO channel estimation.
Automatica, 41:1623?1632, 2005.

9

12

