Rational inference of relative preferences

Authored by:

Paul R. Schrater

Nisheeth Srivastava

Abstract

Statistical decision theory axiomatically assumes that the relative de-
sirability of diﬀerent options that humans perceive is well described by
assigning them option-speciﬁc scalar utility functions. However, this as-
sumption is refuted by observed human behavior, including studies wherein
preferences have been shown to change systematically simply through vari-
ation in the set of choice options presented. In this paper, we show that
interpreting desirability as a relative comparison between available op-
tions at any particular decision instance results in a rational theory of
value-inference that explains heretofore intractable violations of rational
choice behavior in human subjects. Complementarily, we also character-
ize the conditions under which a rational agent selecting optimal options
indicated by dynamic value inference in our framework will behave iden-
tically to one whose preferences are encoded using a static ordinal utility
function.

1 Paper Body

Normative theories of human choice behavior have long been based on how eco-
nomic theory has postulated they should be made. The standard version of the
theory states that consumers seek to maximize innate, stable preferences over
the options they consume. Preferences are represented by numerical encoding of
value in terms of utilities, and subjects are presumed to select the option with
the maximum expected utility. The most diﬃcult part of this theory is that
preferences must exist before decisions can be made. The standard response,
in both economics and decision theory, to the basic question ?Where do pref-
erences come from?? is ?We?ll leave that one to the philosophers, utilities are
simply abstractions we assume for the work we do.?, which, while true, is not
an answer. While this question has been studied before in the form of learning
utility values from behavior [5, 14, 10], human preferences exhibit patterns of
behavior that are impossible to reconcile with the idea that stable numerical
representations of value can be ascribed to each item they choose between. Be-
havioral experiments in the last half century have conclusively demonstrated
(see [18] for a comprehensive review) that human choice strongly violates the

1

key axioms that the existence of stable utility values depends on. A particular
subset of these violations, called context eﬀects, wound the utility maximiza-
tion program the most deeply, since such violations cannot be explained away as
systematic distortions of underlying utility and/or probability representations
[22]. Consider for instance, the ?frog legs? thought problem, pictured in Fig-
ure 1, introduced by Luce and Raiﬀa in their seminal work [15]. No possible
algebraic reformulation of option-speciﬁc utility functions can possibly explain
preference reversals of the type exhibited in the frog legs example. Preference
reversals elicited through choice set variation have been observed in multiple
empirical studies, using a variety of experimental tasks, and comprise one of the
most powerful criticisms of the use of expected utility as a normative standard
in various economic programs, e.g.
in public goods theory. However, for all
its problems, the mathematical simplicity of the utility framework and lack of
principled alternatives has allowed it to retain its central role in microeconomics
[12], machine learning [1], computational cognitive science [7] and neuroscience
[11]. 1

(a) When asked to select between just (b) When presented with an additional
third salmon and steak, the diner picks salmon, in- menu item, the diner picks
steak, indicating dicating salmon steak by his choice steak salmon

Figure 1: Illustration of Luce?s ?frog legs? thought experiment. No possi-
ble absolute utility assignation to individual items can account for the choice
behavior exhibited by the diner in this experiment. The frog legs example is
illustrative of reversals in preference occuring solely through variation in the
set of options a subject has to choose from. Our contribution in this paper is
the development of a rational model that infers preferences from limited infor-
mation about the relative value of options. We postulate that there is a value
inference process that predicts the relative goodness of items in enabling the
agent to achieve its homeostatic and other longer-range needs (e.g. survival and
reproductive needs). While this process should be fully explicated, we simply
don?t know enough to make detailed mathematical models. However, we show
that we only have to postulate that feedback from decisions provides limited in-
formation about the relative worth of options within the choice set for a decision
to retrieve an inductive representation of value that is equivalent to traditional
preference relations. Thus, instead of assuming utilities as being present in the
environment, we learn an equivalent sense of option desirability from informa-
tion in a limited format that depends on the set of options in the decision set.
This inductive methodology naturally makes choice sets informative about the
value of options, and hence aﬀords simple explanations for context eﬀects. We
show how to formalize the idea of relative value inference, and that it provides
a new rational foundation for understanding the origins of human preferences.

2
Human Preferences via Value Inference
We begin by reviewing and formalizing probabilistic decision-making under
uncertainty. An agent selects between possibilities x in the world represented
by the set X . The decision-making problem can be formulated as one wherein
the agent forms a belief b(x), x ? X about the relative desirability of diﬀerent

2

possibilities in X and uses this belief to choose an element or subset X ? ? X .
When these beliefs satisfy the axioms of utility, the belief function simply the
expected utility associated with individual possibilities u(x), u : X ? R. We
assume these desirabilities must be learned from experience, suggesting a rein-
forcement learning approach. The agent?s belief about the relative desirability
of the world is constantly updated by information that it receives about the
desirability of options in terms of value signals r(x). Belief updating produces
transition dynamics on bt (x). Given a sequence of choices, the normative
expectation is for agents to select possibilities in a way that maximizes their
inﬁnite-horizon cumulative discounted desirability, ? X arg max ? t bt (x). (1)
x(t)
t
The sequence of choices selected describes the agent?s expected desirability

maximizing behavior in a belief MDP-world. 2

From a Bayesian standpoint, it is critical to describe the belief updating
about the desirability of diﬀerent states. Let p(x—r(1:t) ) represent the belief
a value x is the best option given a sequence of value signals. Since the agent
learns this distribution from observing r(x) signals from the environment, an
update of the form, p(x—r(t) ) = p(r(t) —x) ? p(x—{r(1) , r(2) ? ? ? , r(t?1)
}),

(2)
reﬂects the basic process of belief formation via value signals. When value
signals are available for every option, independent of other options, the likeli-
hood term p(r—x) in Equation (2) is a probabilistic representation of observed
utility, which remains unaﬀected in the update by the agent?s history of sam-
pling past possibilities and hence is invariant to transition probabilities. Such
separation between utilities and probabilities in statistical decision theory is
called probabilistic sophistication, an axiom that underlies almost all existing
computational decision theory models [11]. The crux of our new approach is
that we assume that value signals p(r—x) are not available for every option .
Instead, we assume we get partial information about the value of one or more
options within the set of options c available in the decision instance t. In this
case value signals are hidden for most options x. However, the set of options c
? C ? P(X )1 observed can now potentially be used as auxiliary information to
impute values for options whose value has not been observed. In such a scenario,
the agent requires a more sophisticated inference process, Z 1 p(x—r(1:t) ) =
p(x, c, r(1:t) ), p(r(1:t) ) c Z 1 = [p(rt —x, c)p(c—x)] ? p(x—{r(1) , r(2) ?
? ? , r(t?1) }). p(r(1:t) ) c Importantly, we concentrate on understanding the
meaning of utility in this framework. As in the case of value observability for
all options, a probabilistic representation of utility under indirect observability
must be equivalent to, R R p(r, x, c) p(r—x, c)p(x—c)p(c) p(r, x) p(r—x)
= =Rc = c R . (3) p(x) p(x—c)p(c) p(x—c)p(c) c c The resulting prediction
of value of an option couples value signals received across decision instances
with diﬀerent option sets, or contexts. The intuition behind this approach is
contained in the frog leg?s example - the set of options become informative
about the hidden state of the world, like whether the restaurant has a good

3

chef. Naively, one could assume that altering existing theory to include this
additional source of information would be an incremental exercise. However, a
formidable epistemological diﬃculty arises as soon as we attempt to incorpo-
rate context into utility-based accounts of decision-making. To see this, let us
assume that we have deﬁned a measure of utility u(x, c) that is sensitive to the
context c of observing possibility x. Now, for such a utility measure, if it is true
that for any two possibilities {xi , xj } and any two contexts {ck , cl }, u(xi
, ck ) ¿ u(xj , ck ) ? u(xi , cl ) ¿ u(xj , cl ), then the choice behavior of an
agent maximizing u(x, c) would be equivalent to one maximizing u(x). Thus,
for the inclusion of context to have any eﬀect, there must exist at least some
{xi , xj , ck , cl } for which the propositions u(xi , ck ) ¿ u(xj , ck ) and u(xi
, cl ) ¡ u(xj , cl ) can hold simultaneously. Note however, that the context in
this operationalization is simply a collection of other possibilities, i.e. c ? X
which ultimately implies u(x, c) = u(X ? ) = u(X ), X ? = {x, c} ? X . Such
a measure could assign absolute numbers to each of the possibilities, but any
such static assignment would make it impossible for the propositions u(x1 , X )
¿ u(x2 , X ) and u(x1 , X ) ¡ u(x2 , X ) to hold simultaneously, as is desired of
a context-sensitive utility measure. Thus, we see that it is impossible to design
a utility function u such that u : X ? C ? R. If we wish to incorporate the
eﬀects of context variation on the desirability of a particular world possibility,
we must abandon a foundational premise of existing statistical decision theory
- the representational validity of absolute utility. 1

P(?) references the power set operation throughout this paper.
3
3
Rational decisions without utilities
In place of the traditional utility framework, we deﬁne an alternative con-
ceptual partitioning of the world X as a discrete choice problem. In this new
formulation, at any decision instant t, agents observe the feasibility of a subset
o(t) ? X of all the possibilities in the world. In the following exposition, we use
y t to denote an indicator function on X encoding the possibilities observed as
o(t) , X y t (x) = ?(x ? i), i?o(t)

. An intelligent agent will encode its understanding of partial observability as
a belief over which possibilities of the world likely co-occur. We call an agent?s
belief about the co-occurrence of possibilities in the world its understanding of
the context of its observation. We instantiate contexts c as subsets of X that
the agent believes will co-occur based on its history of partial observations of
the world and index them with an indicator function z on X , so that for context
c(t) , X z t (x) = ?(x ? i). i?c(t)

Instead of computing absolute utilities on all x ? X , a context-aware agent
evaluates the comparable desirability of only those possibilities considered fea-
sible in a particular context c. Hence, instead of using scalar values to indicate
which possibility is more preferable, we introduce preference information into
our system via a desirability function d that simply ?points? to the best option
in a given context, i.e. d(c) = B, where B is a binary relation (c, c, m) and
mi = 1 iﬀ ci ci0 ?ci0 ? c {ci } and zero otherwise. The desirability indicated

4

by d(c) can be remapped on to the larger set of options by deﬁning a relative
desirability across all possibilities r(x) = m, x ? c and zero otherwise. Recall
now that we have already deﬁned what we mean by utility in our system in
Equation 3. Instantiated in the discrete choice setting, this can be restated as a
probabilistic deﬁnition of relative desirability at decision instant t as, PC p(r(t)
—x, c)p(x—c)p(c) R(t) (x) = p(r(t) —x) = c PC , (4) c p(x—c)p(c) where it is
understood that p(c) = p(c—{o1 , o2 , ? ? ? , ot?1 }) is a distribution on the
set of all possible contexts inferred from the agent?s observation history. From
the deﬁnition of desirability, we can also obtain a simple deﬁnition of p(r—x,
c) as p(ri —xi , c) = 1 iﬀ ri xi = 1 and zero otherwise. To instantiate Eqn
(4) concretely, it is ﬁnally necessary to deﬁne a speciﬁc form for the likelihood
term p(x—c). While multiple mathematical forms can be proposed for this
expression, depending on quantitative assumptions about the amount of un-
certainty intrinsic to the observation, the underlying intuition must remain one
that obtains the highest possible value for c = o and penalizes mismatches in set
membership. Such deﬁnitions can be introduced in the mathematical deﬁnition
of the elementwise mismatch probability, p(?yit —zit ). Since p(xi —c(t) ) =
1 ? p(?yit —zit ), we can use these elementwise probabilities to compute the
likelihood of any particular observation o(t) as, ? (t) ? —o — —c(t) — —X —
[ [ X (t) (t) t t ? ? P (o —c ) = 1 ? p {?yi }— {zi } , = 1 ? ? p(?yit —zit ), i

i
i
where ? is a parameter controlling the magnitude of the penalty imposed for
each mismatch observed. This likelihood function can then be used to update
the agent?s posterior belief about the contexts it considers viable at decision
instance t, given its observation history as, p(o(t) —c)p(c—{o(1) , o(2) , ? ? ?
, o(t?1) }) , p(c(t) —{o(1) , o(2) , ? ? ? , o(t) }) = PC (t) (1) , o(2) , ? ? ? ,
o(t?1) }) c p(o —c)p(c—{o

(5)
To outline a decision theory within this framework, observe that, at decision
instant t, a Bayesian agent could represent its prior preference for diﬀerent world
possibilities in the form of a probability 4
distribution over the possible outcomes in X , conditioned on desirability
information obtained in earlier decisions, p(x—c(t) , {r(1) , r(2) , ? ? ? r(t?1)
}). New evidence for the desirability of outcomes observed in context c(t) is
incorporated using p(r(t) —x, c(t) ), a distribution encoding the relative de-
sirability information obtained from the environment at the current time step,
conditioned on the context in which the information is obtained. This formula-
tion immediately yields the belief update, p(x—c(t) , r(t) ) ? p(r(t) —c(t) , x)
? p(x—c(t) , {r(1) , r(2) , ? ? ? r(t?1) }),

(6)
to obtain a posterior probability encoding the desirability of diﬀerent possi-
bilities x, while also accounting tractably for the context in which desirability
information is obtained at every decision instance. Deﬁning a choice function
to select the mode of the posterior belief completes a rational context-sensitive
decision theory.

5

4
Demonstrations
To demonstrate the value of the relative desirability-based encoding of pref-
erences, in Section 4.1, we describe situations in which the inﬂuence of context
shifting signiﬁcantly aﬀects human preference behavior in ways that utility-
based decision theories have historically been hard-pressed to explain. Com-
plementarily, in Section 4.2 we characterize conditions under which the relative
desirability framework yields predictions of choice behavior equivalent to that
predicted by ordinal utility theories, and hence, is an equivalent representation
for encoding preferences. 4.1
Where context matters ...
In this section, we show how our inductive theory of context-sensitive value
inference leads, not surprisingly, to a simple explanation for the major vari-
eties of context eﬀects seen in behavioral experiments. These are generally
enumerated as attraction, similarity, comparison and reference point eﬀects [2].
Interestingly, we ﬁnd that each of these eﬀects can be described as a special
case of the frog legs example, with the specialization arising out of additional
assumptions made about the relationship of the new option added to the choice
set. Table 1, with some abuse of notation, describes this relationship between
the eﬀects in set-theoretic terms. Space constraints necessitate Eﬀect name Frog
legs Similarity Attraction Compromise Reference point
Description c1 ? {X, Y } ? X Y , c2 ? {X, Y, Z} ? Y X c1 ? {X, Y } ? X
Y , c2 ? {X, Y, Z} ? Y X c1 ? {X, Y } ? X ? Y , c2 ? {X, Y, Z} ? X Y c1 ?
{X, Y } ? X Y , c2 ? {X, Y, Z} ? Y X c1 ? {X, Y } ? X ? Y , c2 ? {X, Y, Z}
? X (?) Y

Assumptions Z?X XZ Y (c) X, Z ZX
Table 1: A uniﬁed description of context eﬀects.

indicates stochastic pref-
erence for one item over another. (c) indicates that the preference in question
holds only in some observation contexts. (?) indicates that the preference in
question is stochastically weaker than before. an abbreviate description of our
results. Detailed descriptions of these eﬀects, supplemented with an explanation
of how they may be elicited in our framework, is provided in SI. We use available
space to completely describe how the most general version of preference rever-
sal, as seen in the frog legs example, emerges from our framework and provide
a brief overview of the other results. To instantiate our likelihood deﬁnition in
(5), we deﬁne a speciﬁc mismatch probability,

1 p(?yit —zit ) = (1 ? zit )yit + (1 ? yit )zit , (7) —X — with ? = 1
for all our demonstrations. In the frog legs example, the reversal in preferences
is anecdotally explained by the diner originally forming a low opinion of the
restaurant?s chef, given the paucity of choices on the menu, deciding to pick
the safe salmon over a possibly a burnt steak. However, the waiter?s presenting
frog legs as the daily special suddenly raises the diner?s opinion of the chef?s
abilities, causing him to favor steak. This intuition maps very easily into our
framework of choice selection, wherein the diner?s partial 5
menu observations o1 = {steak, salmon} and o2 = {steak, salmon, frog legs}
are associated with two separate contexts c1 and c2 of observing the menu X

6

. Bad experiences related to ordering steak in menus typically observed under
context c1 (interpretable as ?cheap restaurants?) may be encoded by deﬁning
the vector m = {1, 0, 0, 0} for c1 and good experiences ordering steak oﬀ menues
observed in context c2 (interpretable as ?upscale restaurants?) as m = {0, 1,
0, 0} for c2 . Then, by deﬁnition, p(r—salmon, c1 ) ¿ p(r—steak, c1 ), while
p(r—salmon, c2 ) ¡ p(r—steak, c2 ). For the purposes of this demonstration,
let us assume these probability pairs, obtained through the diner?s past experi-
ences in restaurants to be {0.7, 0.3} and {0.3, 0.7} respectively. Now, when the
waiter ﬁrst oﬀers the diner a choice between steak or salmon, the diner com-
putes relative desirabilities using (4), where the only context for the observation
is {salmon, steak}. Hence, the relative desirabilities of steak and salmon are
computed over a single context, and are simply R(salmon) = 0.7, R(steak) =
0.3. When the diner is next presented with the possibility of ordering frog legs,
he now has two possible contexts to evaluate the desirability of his menu op-
tions: {salmon, steak} and {salmon, steak, frog legs}. Based on the sequence of
his history of experience with both contexts, the diner will have some posterior
belief p(c) = {p, 1 ? p} on the two contexts. Then, the relative desirability of
salmon, after having observed frog legs on the menu can be calculated using (4)
as, p(r—salmon, c1 )p(salmon—c1 )p(c1 ) + p(r—salmon, c2 )p(salmon—c2
)p(c2 ) , p(salmon—c1 )p(c1 ) + p(salmon—c2 )p(c2 ) 0.7 ? 1 ? p + 0.3 ? 1 ?
(1 ? p) = = 0.7p + 0.3(1 ? p). 1 ? p + 1 ? (1 ? p)

R(salmon) =
Similarly, we obtain R(steak) = 0.3p + 0.7(1 ? p). Clearly, for 1 ? p
¿ p, R(steak) ¿ R(salmon), and the diner would be rational in switching his
preference. Thus, through our inferential machinery, we retrieve the anecdotal
explanation for the diner?s behavior: if he believes that he is more likely to be in
a good restaurant (with probability (1 ? p)) than not, he will prefer steak. Along
identical lines, making reasonable assumptions about the contexts of past ob-
servations, our decision framework accomodates parsimonious explanations for
each of the other eﬀects detailed in Table 1. Attraction eﬀects are traditionally
studied in market research settings where a consumer is unsure about which of
two items to prefer. The introduction of a third item that is clearly inferior
to one of the two earlier options leads the consumer towards preferring that
particular earlier option. Our framework elicits this behavior through the in-
troduction of additional evidence of the desirability of one of the options from
a new context, causing the relative desirability of this particular option to rise.
Similarity eﬀects arise when, given that a consumer prefers one item to another,
giving him further options that resemble his preferred item causes him to sub-
sequently prefer the item he earlier considered inferior. This eﬀect is elicited
simply as a property of division of probability among multiple similar options,
resulting in reduced desirabiliy of the previously superior option. Compromise
eﬀects arise when the introduction of a third option to a choice set where the
consumer already prefers one item to another causes the consumer to consider
the previously inferior option as a compromise between the formerly superior
option and the new option, and hence prefer it. We ﬁnd that the compromise
eﬀect arises through a combination of reduction in the desirability of the su-

7

perior option through negative comparions with the new item and increase in
the desirability of the formerly inferior item through positive comparisons with
the new item, and that this inference occurs automatically in our framework as-
suming equal history of comparisons between the existing choice set items and
the new item. Reference point eﬀects have typically not been associated with
explicit studies of context variation, and may in fact be used to reference a num-
ber of behavior patterns that do not satisfy the deﬁnition we provide in Table 1.
Our deﬁnition of the reference point eﬀect is particularized to explain data on
pain perception collected by [23], demonstrating relativity in evaluation of ob-
jectively identical pain conditions depending on the magnitude of alternatively
experienced pain conditions. In concord with empirical observation, we show
that the relative (un)desirability of an intermediate pain option reduces upon
the experience of greater pain, a simple demonstration of prospect relativity
that utility-based accounts of value cannot match. Competing hypotheses that
seek to explain these behaviors are either normative and static, (e.g. extended
discrete choice models ( [13] provides a recent review), componential context
theory [21], quantum cognition [8]) or descriptive and dynamic, (speciﬁcally,
decision ﬁeld theory [3]). In contrast, our approach not only takes a dynamic
inductive view of value elicitation, it retains a normativity criterion (Bayes ra-
tionality) for falsifying observed predictions, a standard that is expected of any
rational model of decision-making [6]. 6

4.2
... and where it doesn?t
It could be conjectured that the relative desirability indicator d will be an in-
adequate representation of preference information compared with scalar utility
signals assigned to each world possibility, which would leave open the possi-
bility that we may have retrieved a context-sensitive decision theory at the
expense of theoretical assurance of rational choice selection, as has been the
case in many previous attempts cited above. Were this conjecture to be true,
it would severely limit the scope and applicability of our proposal. To antici-
pate this objection, we theoretically prove that our framework reduces to the
standard utility-based representation of preferences under equivalent epistemic
conditions, showing that our theory retains equivalent rational representational
ability as utility theory in simple, and simply extends this representational abil-
ity to explain preference behaviors that utility theory can?t. What does it mean
for a measure to represent preference information? To show that a utility func-
tion u completely represents a preference relation on X it is suﬃcient [12] to
show that, ?x1 , x2 ? X , x1 x2 ? u(x1 ) ¿ u(x2 ). Hence, equivalently, to show
that our measure of relative desirability R also completely represents preference
information, it should be suﬃcient to show that, for any two possibilities xi , xj
? X , and for any observation context c xi xj ? R(xi ) ¿ R(xj ).

(8)
In SI, we prove that (8) holds at decision instant t under three conditions,
(I) Context consistency: ?c ? C, s.t. xi xj ? xi xj ?c ? Cij , {xi , xj } ? Cij ? C.
(II) Transitivity between contexts: if xi xj in c1 and xj xk in c2 , ?c ? C, xi xk
. (t)

8

(t)
(III) Symmetry in context observability: ?xi , xj ? X , limt?? —Cij — =
—Cji —.2 . Of the three assumptions we need to prove this equivalence result,
(I) and (II) simply deﬁne a stable preference relation across observation contexts
and ﬁnd exact counterparts in the completeness and transitivity assumptions
necessary for representing preferences using ordinal utility functions. (III), the
only additional assumption we require, ensures that the agent?s history of par-
tial observations of the environment does not contain any useful information.
The restriction of inﬁnite data observability, while stringent and putatively im-
plausible, actually uncovers an underlying epistemological assumption of utility
theory, viz. that utility/desirability values can somehow be obtained directly
from the environment. Any inference based preference elicitation procedure
will therefore necessarily need inﬁnite data to attain formal equivalence with
the utility representation. Finally, we point out that our equivalence result does
not require us to assume continuity or the equivalent Archimedean property
to encode preferences, as required in ordinal utility deﬁnitions. This is be-
cause the continuity assumption is required as a technical condition in mapping
a discrete mathematical object (a preference relation) to a continuous utility
function. Since relative desirability is deﬁned constructively on Q ? Q, —Q— ¡
?, a continuity assumption is not needed.

5
Discussion
Throughout this exegesis, we have encountered three diﬀerent representa-
tions of choice preferences: relative (ordinal) utilities, absolute (cardinal) utili-
ties and our own proposal, viz. relative desirability. Each representation leads
to a slightly diﬀerent deﬁnition of rationality, so that, assuming a rational set
selection function ? in each case we have, ? Economic rationality: x ? ?(X ) ?
@y ? X , s.t. y x, predominantly used in human preference modeling in neo-
classical economics [12]], e.g. discrete choice modeling [9]. ? VNM-rationality:
x ? ?(X ) ? @y ? X , s.t. u(y) ¿ u(x), predominantly used in studying decision-
making under risk [19], e.g. reinforcement learning [1]. ? Bayes rationality: x
? ?(X ) ? @y ? X , s.t. R(y, {H}) ¿ R(x, {H}), which we have proposed. The
term {H} here is shorthand for {o1 , o2 , ? ? ? , ot?1 }, {r1 , r2 , ? ? ? rt?1
}, the entire history of choice set and relative desirability observations made by
an agent leading up to the current decision instance. 2

The notation Cij references the subset of all observed contexts that contain

xi but not xj .

7
Bayes rationality simply claims that value inference with the same history of
partial observations will lead to a consistent preference for a particular option
in discrete choice settings. In Section 4.2, we have shown conditions on choice
set observations under which Bayes-rationality will be equivalent to economic
rationality. VNM-rationality is a further specialization of economic rational-
ity, valid for preference relations that, in addition to being complete, transitive
and continuous (as required for economic preferences representable via ordinal
utilities) also satisfy an independence of irrelevant attributes (IIA) assumption

9

[16]. Bayes-rationality specializes to economic rationality once we instantiate
the underlying intuitions behing the completeness and transitivity assumptions
in a context-sensitive preference inference theory. Therefore, rational value in-
ference in the form we propose can formally replace static assumptions about
preference orderings in microeconomic models that currently exclusively use
ordinal utilities [12]. As such, context-sensitive preference elicitation is im-
mediately useful for the nascent agent-based economic modeling paradigm as
well as in dynamic stochastic general equilibrium models of economic behavior.
Further work is necessary to develop a context-sensitive equivalent of the IIA
assumption, which is necessary for our system to be directly useful in model-
ing decision-making behaviors under uncertainty. However, even in its current
form, our inference model can be used in conjunction with existing ?inverse
planning? models of utility elicitation from choice data [17] that infer abso-
lute utilities from choice data using extraneous constraints on the form of the
utility function from the environment.
In such a synthesis, our model could
generate a preference relation sensitive to action set observability, which inverse
planning models could use along with additional information from the environ-
ment to generate absolute utilities that account for observational biases in the
agent?s history. A philosophically astute reader will point out a subtle ﬂaw in
our inferential deﬁnition of rationality. Namely, while we assume an intuitive
notion of partial observability of the world, in practice, our agents compile de-
sirability statistics on the set of all possibilities, irrespective of whether they
have ever been observed, a problem that is rooted in an inherent limitation
of Bayesian epistemology of being restricted to computing probabilities over a
ﬁxed set of hypotheses. How can a desirability representation that assumes that
observers maintain probabilistic preferences over all possible states of the world
be more epistemologically realistic than one that assumes that observers main-
tain scalar utility values over the same state space3 ? As a partial response to
this criticism, we point out that we do not require an ontic commitment to the
computation of joint probability distributions on all x ? X . In practice, it is
likely that Bayesian computations are implemented in the brain via sampling
schemes that, in hierarchical formulations, allow approximating information of
the joint distribution as a set of the most likely marginals (in our case, relative
desirability in typical observation contexts). Neural implementations of such
sampling schemes have been proposed in the recent cognitive science literature
[20]. Devising a sampling scheme that matches the intuition of context retrieval
from memory to supplement our value-inference scheme presents a promising
direction for future research. Another straightforward extension of our frame-
work would imbue observable world possibilities with attributes, resulting in
the possibility of deriving a more general deﬁnition of contexts as clusters in the
space of attributes. Such an extension would result in the possibility of transfer-
ring preferences to entirely new possibilities, allowing the set X to be modiﬁed
dynamically, which would further address the epistemological criticism above.
Even further, such an extension maps directly to the intuition of value infer-
ence resulting from organisms? monitoring of internal need states, here modeled
as attributes. Canini?s recent modeling of transfer learning using hierarchical

10

Dirichlet processes [4] provides most of the mathematical apparatus required to
perform such an extension, making this a promising direction for future work
in our project.
In conclusion, it has long been recognized that state-speciﬁc
utility representations of the desirability of options are insuﬃcient to capture
the rich variety of systematic behavior patterns that humans exhibit. In this
paper, we show that reformulating the atomic unit of desirability as a context-
sensitive ?pointer? to the best option in the observed set recovers a rational
way of representing desirability in a manner suﬃciently powerful to describe a
broad range of context eﬀects in decisions. Since it is likely that preferences
for options do not exist a priori and are induced via experience, our present
proposal is expected to approximate the true mechanisms for the emergence
of context-sensitive preference variation better than alternative static theories,
while retaining normativity criteria missing in alternative dynamic accounts. 3
One could argue that we are essentially observing the state space (to be able to
index using its membership), but pretending to not observe it.

8

2 References

[1] A.G. Barto and R.S. Sutton. Reinforcement Learning: an introduction. Uni-
vesity of Cambridge Press, 1998. [2] J. R. Busemeyer, R. Barkan, S. Mehta, and
A. Chaturvedi. Context eﬀects and models of preferential choice: implications
for consumer behavior. Marketing Theory, 7(1):39?58, 2007. [3] J.R. Busemeyer
and J.T. Townsend. Decision ﬁeld theory: A dynamic cognition approach to
decision making. Psychological Review, 100:432?459, 1993.
[4] K. Canini, M.
Shashkov, and T. Griﬃths. Modeling transfer learning in human categorization
with the hierarchical dirichlet process. In ICML, pages 151?158, 2010.
[5] U.
Chajewska, D. Koller, and D. Ormoneit. Learning an agent?s utility function
by observing behavior. In ICML, pages 35?42, 2001.
[6] N. Chater. Rational
and mechanistic perspectives on reinforcement learning. Cognition, 113(3):350
? 364, 2009. Reinforcement learning and higher cognition.
[7] N. Daw and
M. Frank. Reinforcement learning and higher level cognition: Introduction to
special issue. Cognition, 113(3):259 ? 261, 2009. Reinforcement learning and
higher cognition. [8] L. Gabora and D. Aerts. Contextualizing concepts using a
mathematical generalization of the quantum formalism. Joural of Experimental
and Theoretical Artiﬁcial Intelligence, 14(4):327? 358, 2002. [9] D. Hensher, J.
Rose, and W. Greene. Applied Choice Analysis: A Primer. Cambridge Univer-
sity Press, 2005. [10] A. Jern, C. Lucas, and C. Kemp. Evaluating the inverse
decision-making approach to preference learning.
In NIPS, pages 2276?2284,
2011. [11] D. Kahneman. Perception, action and utility: the tangled skein. In
M. Rabinovich, K. Friston, and P. Varona, editors, Principles of Brain Dynam-
ics: Global State Interactions. MIT Pres, 2012.
[12] D. Kreps. A Course in
Microeconomic Theory, pages 17?69. Princeton University Press, 1990. [13] W.
Leong and D. Hensher. Embedding decision heuristics in discrete choice mod-
els: A review. Transport Reviews, 32(3):313?331, 2012.
[14] C.G. Lucas, T.

11

Griﬃths, F. Xu, and C. Fawcett. A rational model of preference learning and
choice prediction by children. In NIPS, pages 985?992, 2008.
[15] R. D. Luce
and H. Raiﬀa. Games and Decisions: Introduction and Critical Survey. Wiley,
New York, 1957.
[16] J.v. Neumann and O. Morgenstern. Theory of Games
and Economic Behavior. Princeton University Press, 1953. [17] A. Y. Ng and S.
J. Russell. Algorithms for inverse reinforcement learning. In Proceedings of the
Seventeenth International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML ?00, pages
663?670, 2000. [18] M. Rabin. Psychology and economics. Journal of Economic
Literature, 36(1):pp. 11?46, 1998.
[19] S.J. Russell and P. Norvig. Artiﬁcial
Intelligence: A Modern Approach. MIT Press, 1998.
[20] L. Shi and T. Grif-
ﬁths. Neural Implementation of Hierarchical Bayesian Inference by Importance
Sampling. In Y. Bengio, D. Schuurmans, J. Laﬀerty, C. K. I. Williams, and
A. Culotta, editors, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 22,
[21] A. Tversky and I. Simonson. Context-dependent
pages 1669?1677. 2009.
preferences. Management Science, 39(10):pp. 1179?1189, 1993.
[22] I. Vlaev,
N. Chater, N. Stewart, and G. Brown. Does the brain calculate value? Trends
in Cognitive Sciences, 15(11):546 ? 554, 2011. [23] I. Vlaev, B. Seymour, R.J.
Dolan, and N. Chater. The price of pain and the value of suﬀering. Psycholog-
ical Science, 20(3):309?317, 2009.

9

12

