Understanding Dropout

Authored by:

Pierre Baldi

Peter J. Sadowski

Abstract

Dropout is a relatively new algorithm for training neural networks
which relies on stochastically dropping out” neurons during training in
order to avoid the co-adaptation of feature detectors. We introduce a
general formalism for studying dropout on either units or connections,
with arbitrary probability values, and use it to analyze the averaging and
regularizing properties of dropout in both linear and non-linear networks.
For deep neural networks, the averaging properties of dropout are char-
acterized by three recursive equations, including the approximation of
expectations by normalized weighted geometric means. We provide esti-
mates and bounds for these approximations and corroborate the results
with simulations. We also show in simple cases how dropout performs
stochastic gradient descent on a regularized error function.”

1 Paper Body

Dropout is an algorithm for training neural networks that was described at NIPS
2012 [7]. In its most simple form, during training, at each example presentation,
feature detectors are deleted with probability q = 1 ? p = 0.5 and the remain-
ing weights are trained by backpropagation. All weights are shared across all
example presentations. During prediction, the weights are divided by two. The
main motivation behind the algorithm is to prevent the co-adaptation of feature
detectors, or overﬁtting, by forcing neurons to be robust and rely on population
behavior, rather than on the activity of other speciﬁc units. In [7], dropout is
reported to achieve state-of-the-art performance on several benchmark datasets.
It is also noted that for a single logistic unit dropout performs a kind of ?geo-
metric averaging? over the ensemble of possible subnetworks, and conjectured
that something similar may occur also in multilayer networks leading to the
view that dropout may be an economical approximation to training and using
a very large ensemble of networks. In spite of the impressive results that have
been reported, little is known about dropout from a theoretical standpoint, in
particular about its averaging, regularization, and convergence properties. Like-
wise little is known about the importance of using q = 0.5, whether diﬀerent

1

values of q can be used including diﬀerent values for diﬀerent layers or diﬀerent
units, and whether dropout can be applied to the connections rather than the
units. Here we address these questions.

2
Dropout in Linear Networks
It is instructive to ﬁrst look at some of the properties of dropout in linear
networks, since these can be studied exactly in the most general setting of a
multilayer feedforward network described by an underlying acyclic graph. The
activity in unit i of layer h can be expressed as: Sih (I) =

XX l¡h
hl l wij Sj
j
1
with Sj0 = Ij
(1)
where the variables w denote the weights and I the input vector. Dropout

applied to the units can be expressed in the form Sih =

XX l¡h
hl l l wij ?j Sj
with
Sj0 = Ij
(2)
j
where ?jl is a gating 0-1 Bernoulli variable, with P (?jl = 1) = plj . Through-
out this paper we assume that the variables ?jl are independent of each other,
independent of the weights, and independent of the activity of the units. Sim-
ilarly, dropout applied to the connections leads to the random variables Sih
=

XX l¡h
hl hl l ?ij wij Sj
with
Sj0 = Ij
(3)
j
For brevity in the rest of this paper, we focus exclusively on dropout applied
to the units, but all the results remain true for the case of dropout applied to the
connections with minor adjustments. For a ﬁxed input vector, the expectation
of the activity of all the units, taken over all possible realizations of the gating
variables hence all possible subnetworks, is given by: E(Sih ) =

XX l¡h
hl l wij pj E(Sjl )
for h ¿ 0
(4)
j

2

with E(Sj0 ) = Ij in the input layer.

In short, the ensemble average can
easily be computed by hl hl l feedforward propagation in the original network,
simply replacing the weights wij by wij pj .

3 3.1
Dropout in Neural Networks Dropout in Shallow Neural Networks
Pn Consider ﬁrst a single logistic unit with n inputs O = ?(S) = 1/(1 +
ce??S ) and S = 1 wj Ij . To achieve the greatest level of generality, we assume
that the unit produces diﬀerent outputs OP 1 , . . . , Om , corresponding to
diﬀerent sums S1 . . . , Sm with diﬀerent probabilities P1 , . . . , Pm ( Pm =
1). In the most relevant case, these outputs and these sums are associated with
the m = 2n possible subnetworks of the unit. The probabilities P1 , . . . , Pm
could be generated, for instance, by using Bernoulli gating variables, although
this isP not necessary for this derivation. It is useful to deﬁne the following four
quantities: the mean E = Pi Oi ; the mean of the complements P Q E0 = Pi (1
? Oi ) = 1 ? E; the weighted geometric mean (W GM ) G = i OiPi ; and the
Q weighted geometric mean of the complements G0 = i (1 ? Oi )Pi . We also
deﬁne the normalized weighted geometric mean N W GM = G/(G + G0 ). We
can now prove the key averaging theorem for logistic functions: 1 = ?(E(S)) 1
+ ce??E(S)

(5)
1 1 Q Q = (1?Oi )Pi (1??(Si ))Pi 1 + Q Pi 1 + Q ?(S )Pi
(6)
N W GM (O1 , . . . , Om ) = To prove this result, we write N W GM (O1

, . . . , Om ) =

Oi
i
??x
The logistic function satisﬁes the identity [1 ? ?(x)]/?(x) = ce
and thus
1 1 P Q ??S P = N W GM (O1 , .

.

.

, Om ) = = ?(E(S)) (7) i i ??
Pi Si 1 + [ce ] 1 + ce Thus in the case of Bernoulli gating variables, we can
compute the N WP GM over all possible n dropout conﬁgurations by simple
forward propagation by: N W GM = ?( 1 wj pj Ij ). A similar result is true also
for normalized exponential transfer functions. Finally, one can also show that
the only class of functions f that satisfy N W GM (f ) = f (E) are the constant
functions and the logistic functions [1]. 2

3.2
Dropout in Deep Neural Networks
We can now deal with the most interesting case of deep feedforward networks
of sigmoidal units 1 , described by a set of equations of the form Oih = ?(Sih )
= ?(

XX
hl l wij Oj )
with
Oj0 = Ij
(8)

3

j
l¡h
where Oih is the output of unit i in layer h. Dropout on the units can be

described by Oih = ?(Sih ) = ?(

XX l¡h
hl l l wij ?j Oj )
with Oj0 = Ij
(9)
j
using the Bernoulli selector variables ?jl . For each sigmoidal unit N W GM

(Oih ) = Q

h P (N ) N (Oi ) Q h P (N ) + N (1 ? N (Oi )
Q
Oih )P (N )
(10)
where N ranges over all possible subnetworks. Assume for now that the N
W GM provides a good approximation to the expectation (this point will be
analyzed in the next section). Then the averaging properties of dropout are
described by the following three recursive equations. First the approximation
of means by NWGMs: E(Oih ) ? N W GM (Oih )

(11)
Second, using the result of the previous section, the propagation of expecta-

tion symbols:

N W GM (Oih ) = ?ih E(Sih )
(12)
And third, using the linearity of the expectation with respect to sums, and

to products of independent random variables: E(Sih ) =

XX l¡h
hl l wij pj E(Ojl )
(13)
j
Equations 11, 12, and 13 are the fundamental equations explaining the aver-
aging properties of the dropout procedure. The only approximation is of course
Equation 11 which is analyzed in the next section. If the network contains linear
units, then Equation 11 is not necessary for those units and their average can be
computed exactly. In the case of regression with linear units in the top layers,
this allows one to shave oﬀ one layer of approximations. The same is true in
binary classiﬁcation by requiring the output layer to compute directly the N W
GM of the ensemble rather than the expectation. It can be shown that for any
error function that is convex up (?), the error of the mean, weighted geometric
mean, and normalized weighted geometric mean of an ensemble is always less
than the expected error of the models [1]. Equation 11 is exact if and only if the
numbers Oih are identical over all possible subnetworks N . h Thus it is useful
to measure the consistency C(Oi , I) of neuron i in layer h for input I by using
the variance V ar Oih (I) taken over all subnetworks N and their distribution
when the input I is ﬁxed. The larger the variance is, the less consistent the

4

neuron is, and the worse we can expect the approximation in Equation 11 to
be. Note that for a random variable O in [0,1] the variance cannot exceed 1/4
anyway. This is because V ar(O) = E(O2 ) ? (E(O))2 ? E(O) ? (E(O))2 =
E(O)(1 ? E(O)) ? 1/4. This measure can also be averaged over a training set
or a test set. 1 Given the results of the previous sections, the network can also
include linear units or normalized exponential units.

3
4
The Dropout Approximation
Given a set of numbers O1 , . . . , Om between 0 and 1, with probabilities P1
, . . . , PM (corresponding to the outputs of a sigmoidal neuron for a ﬁxed input
and diﬀerent subnetworks), we are primarily interested in the approximation of
E by N W GM . The N W GM provides a good approximation because we
show below that to a ﬁrst order of approximation: E ? N W GM and E ? G.
Furthermore, there are formulae in the literature for bounding the error E ? G in
terms of the consistency (e.g. the Cartwright and Field inequality [6]). However,
one can suspect that the N W GM provides even a better approximation to E
than the geometric mean. For instance, if the numbers Oi satisfy 0 ¡ Oi ? 0.5
(consistently low), then G E G ? 0 and therefore G ? ?E (14) G0 E G + G0
This is proven by applying Jensen?s inequality to the function ln x ? ln(1 ? x)
for x ? (0, 0.5]. It is also known as the Ky Fan inequality [2, 8, 9]. To get even
better results, one must consider a second order approximation. For this, we
write Oi = 0.5 + i with 0 ? —i — ? 0.5. Thus we have E(O) = 0.5 + E() and
V ar(O) = V ar(). Using a Taylor expansion: ? ? ? X X pi (pi ? 1) X 1 Y X
pi 1 G= (2i )n = ?1 + pi 2i + (2i )2 + 4pi pj i j + R3 (i )? 2 i n=0 n 2 2 i i i¡j
(15) where R3 (i ) is the remainder and R3 (i ) =

pi (2i )3 3 (1 + ui )3?pi
(16)
where —ui — ? 2—i —. Expanding the product gives X X 1 X 1 G= + pi
i +( i )2 ? pi 2i +R3 () = +E()?V ar()+R3 () = E(O)?V ar(O)+R3 () 2 i 2 i
(17) By symmetry, we have G0 =

Y (1 ? Oi )pi = 1 ? E(O) ? V ar(O) + R3 ()
(18)
i
where R3 () is the higher order remainder. Neglecting the remainder and
writing E = E(O) and V = V ar(O) we have G E?V G0 1?E?V ? and ? (19) 0
0 G+G 1 ? 2V G+G 1 ? 2V Thus, to a second order, the diﬀerences between
the mean and the geometric mean and the normalized geometric means satisfy
E?G?V

and E ?
G V (1 ? 2E) ? 0 G+G 1 ? 2V
(20)
and G0 V (1 ? 2E) ? (21) 0 G+G 1 ? 2V Finally it is easy to check that the
factor (1 ? 2E)/(1 ? 2V ) is always less or equal to 1. In addition we always
have V ? E(1 ? E), with equality achieved only for 0-1 Bernoulli variables. Thus
1 ? E ? G0 ? V

5

and
(1 ? E) ?
4
V —1 ? 2E— E(1 ? E)—1 ? 2E— G —? ? ? 2E(1 ? E)—1 ? 2E— (22) G +
G0 1 ? 2V 1 ? 2V The ﬁrst inequality is optimal in the sense that it is attained in
the case of a Bernoulli variable with expectation E and, intuitively, the second
inequality shows that the approximation error is always small, regardless of
whether E is close to 0, 0.5, or 1. In short, the NWGM provides a very good
approximation to E, better than the geometric mean G. The property is always
true to a second order of approximation and it is exact when the activities are
consistently low, or when N W GM ? E, since the latter implies G ? N W GM
? E. Several additional properties of the dropout approximation, including the
extension to rectiﬁed linear units and other transfer functions, are studied in
[1]. —E ?

5
Dropout Dynamics
Dropout performs gradient descent on-line with respect to both the training
examples and the ensemble of all possible subnetworks. As such, and with
the appropriately decreasing learning rates, it is almost surely convergent like
other forms of stochastic gradient descent [11, 4, 5]. To further understand the
properties of dropout, it is again instructive to look at the properties of the
gradient in the linear case. 5.1

Single Linear Unit
In the case of a single linear unit, consider the two error functions EEN S and
ED associated with the ensemble of all possible subnetworks and the network
with dropout. For a single input I, these are deﬁned by:

EEN S
n X 1 1 2 = (t ? OEN S ) = (t ? pi wi Ii )2 2 2 i=1
(23)
n X 1 1 (t ? OD )2 = (t ? ?i wi Ii )2 2 2 i=1
(24)
ED =
We use a single training input I for notational simplicity, otherwise the errors
of each training example can be combined additively. The learning gradient is
given by ?EEN S ?OEN S = ?(t ? OEN S ) = ?(t ? OEN S )pi Ii ?wi ?wi X
?ED ?OD = ?(t ? OD ) = ?(t ? OD )?i Ii = ?t?i Ii + wi ?i2 Ii2 + wj ?i ?j Ii Ij
?wi ?wi
(25)
(26)
j6=i
The dropout gradient is a random variable and we can take its expectation.

A short calculation yields

E
?ED ?wi
=
?EEN S ?EEN S + wi pi (1 ? pi )Ii2 + wi Ii2 V ar(?i ) ?wi ?wi

6

(27)
Thus, remarkably, in this case the expectation of the gradient with dropout

is the gradient of the regularized ensemble error n

E = EEN S +
1X 2 2 w I V ar(?i ) 2 i=1 i i
(28)
The regularization term is the usual weight decay or Gaussian prior term
based on the square of the weights to prevent overﬁtting. Dropout provides
immediately the magnitude of the regularization term which is adaptively scaled
by the inputs and by the variance of the dropout variables. Note that pi = 0.5
is the value that provides the highest level of regularization. 5

5.2
Single Sigmoidal Unit
The previous result generalizes to a sigmoidal unit O = ?(S) = 1/(1 + ce??S
) trained to minimize the relative entropy error E = ?(t log O + (1 ? t) log(1 ?
O)). In this case, ?ED ?S = ??(t ? O) = ??(t ? O)?i Ii (29) ?wi ?wi The terms
O and Ii are not independent but using a Taylor expansion with the N W GM
approximation gives

?EEN S ?ED ? + ?? 0 (SEN S )wi Ii2 V ar(?i ) (30) E ?wi ?wi P with SEN
S = j wj pj Ij . Thus, as in the linear case, the expectation of the dropout
gradient is approximately the gradient of the ensemble network regularized by
weight decay terms with the proper adaptive coeﬃcients. A similar analysis,
can be carried also for a set of normalized exponential units and for deeper
networks [1].

5.3
Learning Phases and Sparse Coding
During dropout learning, we can expect three learning phases: (1) At the
beginning of learning, when the weights are typically small and random, the
total input to each unit is close to 0 for all the units and the consistency is high:
the output of the units remains roughly constant across subnetworks (and equal
to 0.5 with c = 1). (2) As learning progresses, activities tend to move towards 0
or 1 and the consistency decreases, i.e. for a given input the variance of the units
across subnetworks increases. (3) As the stochastic gradient learning procedure
converges, the consistency of the units converges to a stable value. Finally, for
simplicity, assume that dropout is applied only in layer h where the units have
an output P hl l l of the form Oih = ?(Sih ) and Sih = l¡h wij ?j Oj . For a ﬁxed
input, Ojl is a constant since dropout is not applied to layer l. Thus V ar(Sih )
=

X
hl 2 (wij ) (Ojl )2 plj (1 ? plj )
(31)
l¡h
under the usual assumption that the selector variables ?jl are independent
of each other. Thus V ar(Sih ) depends on three factors. Everything else
being equal, it is reduced by: (1) Small weights which goes together with the
regularizing eﬀect of dropout; (2) Small activities, which shows that dropout is

7

not symmetric with respect to small or large activities. Overall, dropout tends
to favor small activities and thus sparse coding; and (3) Small (close to 0) or
large (close to 1) values of the dropout probabilities plj . Thus values plj = 0.5
maximize the regularization eﬀect but may also lead to slower convergence to
the consistent state. Additional results and simulations are given in [1].

6
Simulation Results
We use Monte Carlo simulation to partially investigate the approximation
framework embodied by the three fundamental dropout equations 11, 12, and
13, the accuracy of the second-order approximation and bounds in Equations 20
and 22, and the dynamics of dropout learning. We experiment with an MNIST
classiﬁer of four hidden layers (784-1200-1200-1200-1200-10) that replicates the
results in [7] using the Pylearn2 and Theano software libraries[12, 3]. The
network is trained with a dropout probability of 0.8 in the input, and 0.5 in
the four hidden layers. For ﬁxed weights and a ﬁxed input, 10,000 Monte Carlo
simulations are used to estimate the distribution of activity O in each neuron.
Let O? be the activation under the deterministic setting with the weights scaled
appropriately. The left column of Figure 1 conﬁrms empirically that the second-
order approximation in Equation 20 and the bound in Equation 22 are accurate.
The right column of Figure 1 shows the diﬀerence between the true ensemble
average E(O) and the prediction-time neuron activity O? . This diﬀerence grows
very slowly in the higher layers, and only for active neurons. 6

Figure 1: Left: The diﬀerence E(O) ? N W GM (O), it?s second-order
approximation in Equation 20, and the bound from Equation 22, plotted for
four hidden layers and a typical ﬁxed input. Right: The diﬀerence between
the true ensemble average E(O) and the ﬁnal neuron prediction O? . Next, we
examine the neuron consistency during dropout training. Figure 2a shows the
three phases of learning for a typical neuron. In Figure 2b, we observe that the
consistency does not decline in higher layers of the network. One clue into how
this happens is the distribution of neuron activity. As noted in [10] and section
5 above, dropout training results in sparse activity in the hidden layers (Figure
3). This increases the consistency of neurons in the next layer.

7
(a) The three phases of learning. For a particular input, a typical active
neuron (red) starts out with low variance, experiences a large increase in vari-
ance during learning, and eventually settles to some steady constant value. In
contrast, a typical inactive neuron (blue) quickly learns to stay silent. Shown
are the mean with 5% and 95% percentiles.

(b) Consistency does not noticeably decline in the upper layers. Shown here
are the mean Std(O) for active neurons (0.1 ¡ O after training) in each layer,
along with the 5% and 95% percentiles.

Figure 2
Figure 3: In every hidden layer of a dropout trained network, the distribution
of neuron activations O? is sparse and not symmetric. These histograms were
totalled over a set of 100 random inputs.

8

8

2 References

[1] P. Baldi and P. Sadowski. The Dropout Learning Algorithm. Artiﬁcial
[2] E. F. Beckenbach and R. Bellman. Inequal-
Intelligence, 2014. In press.
ities. Springer-Verlag Berlin, 1965.
[3] J. Bergstra, O. Breuleux, F. Bastien,
P. Lamblin, R. Pascanu, G. Desjardins, J. Turian, D. Warde-Farley, and Y.
Bengio. Theano: a CPU and GPU math expression compiler.
In Proceed-
ings of the Python for Scientiﬁc Computing Conference (SciPy), Austin, TX,
June 2010. Oral Presentation.
[4] L. Bottou. Online algorithms and stochas-
In D. Saad, editor, Online Learning and Neural Net-
tic approximations.
works. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK, 1998.
[5] L. Bottou.
Stochastic learning. In O. Bousquet and U. von Luxburg, editors, Advanced
Lectures on Machine Learning, Lecture Notes in Artiﬁcial Intelligence, LNAI
3176, pages 146?168. Springer Verlag, Berlin, 2004. [6] D. Cartwright and M.
Field. A reﬁnement of the arithmetic mean-geometric mean inequality. Pro-
ceedings of the American Mathematical Society, pages 36?38, 1978.
[7] G.
Hinton, N. Srivastava, A. Krizhevsky, I. Sutskever, and R. R. Salakhutdinov.
Improving neural networks by preventing co-adaptation of feature detectors.
http://arxiv.org/abs/1207.0580, 2012. [8] E. Neuman and J. S?andor. On the
Ky Fan inequality and related inequalities i. MATHEMATICAL INEQUALI-
TIES AND APPLICATIONS, 5:49?56, 2002.
[9] E. Neuman and J. Sandor.
On the Ky Fan inequality and related inequalities ii. Bulletin of the Aus-
tralian Mathematical Society, 72(1):87?108, 2005.
Improving
Neural Networks with Dropout. PhD thesis, University of Toronto, Toronto,
Canada, 2013.
[11] H. Robbins and D. Siegmund. A convergence theorem
for non negative almost supermartingales and some applications. Optimizing
methods in statistics, pages 233?257, 1971.
[12] D. Warde-Farley, I. Goodfel-
low, P. Lamblin, G. Desjardins, F. Bastien, and Y. Bengio. pylearn2. 2011.
http://deeplearning.net/software/pylearn2.

[10] S. Nitish.

9

9

