Memoized Online Variational Inference for

Dirichlet Process Mixture Models

Authored by:

Michael C. Hughes

Erik Sudderth

Abstract

Variational inference algorithms provide the most eﬀective framework
for large-scale training of Bayesian nonparametric models. Stochastic on-
line approaches are promising, but are sensitive to the chosen learning
rate and often converge to poor local optima. We present a new algo-
rithm, memoized online variational inference, which scales to very large
(yet ﬁnite) datasets while avoiding the complexities of stochastic gradi-
ent. Our algorithm maintains ﬁnite-dimensional suﬃcient statistics from
batches of the full dataset, requiring some additional memory but still
scaling to millions of examples. Exploiting nested families of variational
bounds for inﬁnite nonparametric models, we develop principled birth
and merge moves allowing non-local optimization. Births adaptively add
components to the model to escape local optima, while merges remove
redundancy and improve speed. Using Dirichlet process mixture models
for image clustering and denoising, we demonstrate major improvements
in robustness and accuracy.

1 Paper Body

Bayesian nonparametric methods provide a ﬂexible framework for unsupervised
modeling of structured data like text documents, time series, and images. They
are especially promising for large datasets, as their nonparametric priors should
allow complexity to grow smoothly as more data is seen. Unfortunately, con-
temporary inference algorithms do not live up to this promise, scaling poorly
and yielding solutions that represent poor local optima of the true posterior. In
this paper, we propose new scalable algorithms capable of escaping local optima.
Our focus is on clustering data via the Dirichlet process (DP) mixture model,
but our methods are much more widely applicable. Stochastic online variational
inference is a promising general-purpose approach to Bayesian nonparametric
learning from streaming data [1]. While individual steps of stochastic optimiza-
tion algorithms are by design scalable, they are extremely vulnerable to local
optima for non-convex unsupervised learning problems, frequently yielding poor

1

solutions (see Fig. 2). While taking the best of multiple runs is possible, this
is unreliable, expensive, and ineﬀective in more complex structured models.
Furthermore, the noisy gradient step size (or learning rate) requires external
parameters which must be ﬁne-tuned for best performance, often requiring an
expensive validation procedure. Recent work has proposed methods for au-
tomatically adapting learning rates [2], but these algorithms? progress on the
overall variational objective remains local and non-monotonic. In this paper, we
present an alternative algorithm, memoized online variational inference, which
avoids noisy gradient steps and learning rates altogether. Our method is useful
when all data may not ﬁt in memory, but we can aﬀord multiple full passes
through the data by processing successive batches. The algorithm visits each
batch in turn and updates a cached set of suﬃcient statistics which accurately
reﬂect the entire dataset. This allows rapid and noise-free updates to global
parameters at every step, quickly propagating information and speeding con-
vergence. Our memoized approach is generally applicable in any case batch or
stochastic online methods are useful, including topic models [1] and relational
models [3], though we do not explore these here. 1

We further develop a principled framework for escaping local optima in the
online setting, by integrating birth and merge moves within our algorithm?s
coordinate ascent steps. Most existing meanﬁeld algorithms impose a restric-
tive ﬁxed truncation in the number of components, which is hard to set a priori
on big datasets: either it is too small and inexpressive, or too large and com-
putationally ineﬃcient. Our birth and merge moves, together with a nested
variational approximation to the posterior, enable adaptive creation and prun-
ing of clusters on-the-ﬂy. Because these moves are validated by an exactly
tracked global variational objective, we avoid potential instabilities of stochas-
tic online split-merge proposals [4]. The structure of our moves is very diﬀerent
from split-merge MCMC methods [5, 6]; applications of these algorithms have
been limited to hundreds of data points, while our experiments show scaling of
memoized split-merge proposals to millions of examples. We review the Dirich-
let process mixture model and variational inference in Sec. 2, outline our novel
memoized algorithm in Sec. 3, and evaluate on clustering and denoising appli-
cations in Sec. 4.

2 Variational inference for Dirichlet process mixture models The Dirich-
let process (DP) provides a nonparametric prior for partitioning exchangeable
datasets into discrete clusters [7]. An instantiation G of a DP is an inﬁnite col-
lection of atoms, each of which represents one mixture component. Component
k has mixture weight wk sampled as follows: G ? DP(?0 H),

G,
? X
wk ??k ,
vk ? Beta(1, ?0 ),
wk = vk
k=1
k?1 Y
(1 ? v? ).

2

(1)
?=1
This stick-breaking process provides mixture weights and parameters. Each
data item n chooses an assignment zn ? Cat(w), and then draws observations
xn ? F (?zn ). The data-generating parameter ?k is drawn from a base measure
H with natural parameters ?0 . We assume both H and F belong to exponential
families with log-normalizers a and suﬃcient statistics t: n o n o p(?k — ?0
) = exp ?T0 t0 (?k ) ? a0 (?0 ) , p(xn — ?k ) = exp ?Tk t(xn ) ? a(?k ) .
(2) For simplicity, we assume unit reference measures. The goal of inference is
to recover stick-breaking proportions vk and data-generating parameters ?k for
each global mixture component k, as well as discrete cluster assignments z =
{zn }N n=1 for each observation. The joint distribution is p(x, z, ?, v) =

N Y
F (xn — ?zn )Cat(zn — w(v))
n=1
? Y
Beta(vk — 1, ?0 )H(?k — ?0 )
(3)
k=1
While our algorithms are directly applicable to any DP mixture of expo-
nential families, our experiments focus on D-dimensional real-valued data xn
, for which we take F to be Gaussian. For some data, we consider full-mean,
full-covariance analysis (where H is normal-Wishart), while other applications
consider zero-mean, full-covariance analysis (where H is Wishart). 2.1 Mean-
ﬁeld variational inference for DP mixture models To approximate the full (but
intractable) posterior over variables z, v, ?, we consider a fullyfactorized varia-
tional distribution q, with individual factors from appropriate exponential fam-
ilies:1 q(z, v, ?) =

N Y
n=1
q(zn ) = Cat(zn — r?n1 , . . . r?nK ),
q(zn —? rn )
K Y
? k ), q(vk —? ?1 , ? ? 0 )q(?k —?
(4)
k=1
q(vk ) = Beta(vk — ? ? k1 , ? ? k0 ),
? k ). q(?k ) = H(?k — ?
(5)
To tractably handle the inﬁnite set of components available under the DP
prior, we truncate the discrete assignment factor to enforce q(zn = k) = 0 for k ¿
K. This forces all data to be explained by only the ﬁrst K components, inducing
conditional independence between observed data and any global parameters vk
, ?k with index k ¿ K. Inference may thus focus exclusively on a ﬁnite set of K
components, while reasonably approximating the true inﬁnite posterior for large
K. To ease notation, we mark variables with hats to distinguish parameters ??

3

of variational factors q from parameters ? of the generative model p. In this
way, ?k and ??k always have equal dimension. 1

2
Crucially, our truncation is nested: any learned q with truncation K can be
represented exactly under truncation K +1 by setting the ﬁnal component to
have zero mass. This truncation, previously advocated by [8, 4], has consider-
able advantages over non-nested direct truncation of the stick-breaking process
[7], which places artiﬁcally large mass on the ﬁnal component. It is more eﬃ-
cient and broadly applicable than an alternative trunction which sets the stick-
breaking ?tail? to its prior [9]. Variational algorithms optimize the parameters
of q to minimize the KL divergence from the true, intractable posterior [7]. The
optimal q maximizes the evidence lower bound (ELBO) objective L: h i (6) log
p(x — ?0 , ?0 ) ? L(q) , Eq log p(x, v, z, ? — ?0 , ?0 ) ? log q(v, z, ?)

For DP mixtures of exponential family distributions, L(q) has a simple form.
For each component k, ?k and expected suﬃcient statistic sk (x). All but one
term in L(q) can we store its expected mass N then be written using only these
summaries and expectations of the global parameters v, ?: ?k , Eq N

N hX
n=1
L(q) =
K X
N i X r?nk , znk =
sk (x) , Eq
n=1
N hX
n=1
N i X znk t(xn ) = r?nk t(xn ),
(7)
n=1
?k Eq [a(?k )] + N ?k Eq [log wk (v)] ? Eq [?k ]T sk (x) ? N
N X
r?nk log r?nk
n=1
k=1
!
Beta(vk — 1, ?0 ) H(?k — ?0 ) + Eq log (8) + Eq log ?k ) q(vk — ? ? k1 , ?
? k0 ) q(?k — ? P Excluding the entropy term ? r?nk log r?nk which we discuss
later, this bound is a simple linear ?k , sk (x). Given precomputed entropies
and summaries, evaluation of function of the summaries N L(q) can be done
in time independent of the data size N . We next review variational algorithms
for optimizing q via coordinate ascent, iteratively updating individual factors
of q. We describe algorithms in terms of two updates [1]: global parameters
(stick-breaking proportions vk and datagenerating parameters ?k ), and local
parameters (assignments of data to components zn ).

2.2 Full-dataset variational inference Standard full-dataset variational infer-
ence [7] updates local factors q(zn — r?n ) for all observations n = 1, . . . , N by

4

visiting each item n and computing the fraction r?nk explained by component
k:

r?nk r?nk = exp Eq [log wk (v)] + Eq [log p(xn — ?k )] , r?nk = PK . (9)

?n? ?=1 r

? k ) for each component k. After computing Next, we update global factors
q(vk —? ?k1 , ? ? k0 ), q(?k —? ? summary statistics Nk , sk (x) given the
new r?nk via Eq. (7), the update equations become ?k , ? ? k1 = ?1 + N

? ? k0 = ?0 +
K X
?? , N
? k = ?0 + sk (x). ?
(10)
?=k+1
While simple and guaranteed to converge, this approach scales poorly to big
datasets. Because global parameters are updated only after a full pass through
the data, information propagates slowly. 2.3 Stochastic online variational in-
ference Stochastic online (SO) variational inference scales to huge datasets [1].
Instead of analyzing all data at once, SO processes only a subset (?batch?) Bt
at each iteration t. These subsets are assumed sampled uniformly at random
from a larger (but ﬁxed size N ) corpus. Given a batch, SO ﬁrst updates local
factors q(zn ) for n ? Bt via Eq. (9). It then updates global factors via a noisy
gradient step, using suﬃcient statistics of q(zn ) from only the current batch.
These steps optimize a noisy function, which in expectation (with respect to
batch sampling) converges to the true objective (6). Natural gradient steps are
computationally tractable for exponential family models, involving nearly the
same computations as the full-dataset updates [1]. For example, to update the
variational param? k from (5) at iteration t, we ﬁrst compute the global update
given only data in the current batch, eter ? 3

? ? = ?0 + ampliﬁed to be at full-dataset scale: ? k
N —Bt — sk (Bt ). Then, we interpolate between this and ? ? + (1 ? ?t)?

? (t?1) . The learn? (t) ? ?t ? ﬁnal result: ? k k k

the previous global parameters to arrive at the ing rate ?t controls how ?for-
getful? the algorithm is of previous values; if it decays at appropriate rates,
stochastic inference provably converges to a local optimum of the global ob-
jective L(q) [1]. This online approach has clear computational advantages and
can sometimes yield higher quality solutions than the full-data algorithm, since
it conveys information between local and global parameters more frequently.
However, performance is extremely sensitive to the learning rate decay schedule
and choice of batch size, as we demonstrate in later experiments.

3 Memoized online variational inference Generalizing previous incremental
variants of the expectation maximization (EM) algorithm [10], we now develop
our memoized online variational inference algorithm. We divide the data into
B ﬁxed b ? batches {Bb }B b=1 . For each batch, we maintain memoized
suﬃcient statistics Sk = [Nk (Bb ), sk (Bb )] 0 ? for each component k. We
also track the full-dataset statistics Sk = [Nk , sk (x)]. These compact sum-
mary statistics allow guarantees of correct full-dataset analysis while processing

5

only one small batch at a time. Our approach hinges on the fact that these
suﬃcient statistics are additive: summaries of an entire dataset can be written
exactly as the addition of summaries of distinct batches. Note that our memo-
ization of deterministic analyses of batches of data is distinct from the stochastic
memoization, or ?lazy? instantiation, of random variables in some Monte Carlo
methods [11, 12]. Memoized inference proceeds by visiting (in random order)
each distinct batch once in a full pass through the data, incrementally updating
the local and global parameters related to that batch b. First, we update local
parameters for the current batch (q(zn — r?n ) for n ? Bb ) via Eq. (9). Next,
we update cached global suﬃcient statistics for each component: we subtract
the old (cached) summary of batch b, compute a new batch-level summary, and
add the result to the full-dataset summary: h X i X Sk0 ? Sk0 ? Skb , Skb ?
r?nk , r?nk t(xn ) , Sk0 ? Sk0 + Skb . (11) n?Bb

n?Bb
Finally, given the new full-dataset summary Sk0 , we update global parame-
ters exactly as in Eq. (10). Unlike stochastic online algorithms, memoized infer-
ence is guaranteed to improve the full-dataset ELBO at every step. Correctness
follows immediately from the arguments in [10]. By construction, each local or
global step will result in a new q that strictly increases the objective L(q). In
the limit where B = 1, memoized inference reduces to standard full-dataset up-
dates. However, given many batches it is far more scalable, while maintaining all
guarantees of batch inference. Furthermore, it generally converges faster than
the full-dataset algorithm due to frequently interleaving global and local up-
dates. Provided we can store memoized suﬃcient statistics for each batch (not
each observation), memoized inference has the same computational complexity
as stochastic methods while avoiding noise and sensitivity to learning rates. Re-
cent analysis of convex optimization algorithms [13] demonstrated theoretical
and practical advantages for methods that use cached fulldataset summaries to
update parameters, as we do, instead of stochastic current-batch-only updates.
This memoized algorithm can compute the full-dataset objective L(q) exactly
at any point (after visiting all Pitems once). To do so eﬃciently, we need to
compute and store the assignment entropy Hkb = ? n?Bb rnk log rnk after vis-
iting each batch b. We also need to track the full-data entropy PB Hk0 = b=1
Hkb , which is additive just like the suﬃcient statistics and incrementally up-
dated after each batch. Given both Hk0 and Sk0 , evaluation of the full-dataset
ELBO in Eq. (8) is exact and rapid. 3.1 Birth moves to escape local optima We
now propose additional birth moves that, when interleaved with conventional
coordinate ascent parameter updates, can add useful new components to the
model and escape local optima. Previous methods [14, 9, 4] for changing vari-
ational truncations create just one extra component via a ?split? move that is
highly-specialized to particular likelihoods. Wang and Blei [15] explore trunca-
tion levels via a local collapsed Gibbs sampler, but samplers are slow to make
large changes. In contrast, our births add many components at once and apply
to any exponential family mixture model. 4

Birth Move After
Before

6

1
1
6
2 3 4 5
2
Batch 1
!
7
?kb 1) Create new Memoized summary N components expected count of

each component 2) Adopt in one pass thru data 1 2 3 4 5 6 7

Batch b current position
Batch b+1
Learn fresh DP-GMM on subsample via VB Subsample data explained by 1
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
0
!
Add fresh components to expand original model
Batch B 3) Merge to remove redundancy
batches not-yet updated on this pass do not use any new components
Figure 1: One pass through a toy dataset for memoized learning with birth
and merge moves (MO-BM), showing creation (left) and adoption (right) of new
components. Left: Scatter plot of 2D observed data, and a subsample targeted
via the ﬁrst mixture component. Elliptical contours show component covariance
matrices. ?kb for each batch. Not shown: Memoized suﬃcient statistics sbk .
Right: Bar plots of memoized counts N Creating new components in the online
setting is challenging. Each small batch may not have enough examples of
a missing component to inspire a good proposal, even if that component is
wellsupported by the full dataset. We thus advocate birth moves that happen
in three phases (collection, creation, and adoption) over two passes of the data.
The ﬁrst pass collects a targeted data sample more likely to yield informative
proposals than a small, predeﬁned batch. The second pass, shown in Fig. 1,
creates new components and then updates every batch with the expanded model.
Successive births are interleaved; at each pass there are proposals both active
and in preparation. We sketch out each step of the algorithm below. For
complete details, see the supplement. Collection During pass 1, we collect a
targeted subsample x? of the data, of size at most N ? = 104 . This subsample
targets a single component k ? . When visiting each batch, we copy data
xn into x? if r?nk? ¿ ? (we set ? = 0.1). This threshold test ensures the

7

subsample contains related data, but also promotes diversity by considering
data explained partially by other components k 6= k ? . Targeted samples vary
from iteration to iteration because batches are visited in distinct, random orders.
Creation Before pass 2, we create new components by ﬁtting a DP mixture
model with K ? (we take K ? = 10) components to x? , running variational
inference for a limited budget of iterations. Taking advantage of our nested
truncation, we expand our current model to include all K + K ? components,
as shown in Fig. 1. Unlike previous work [9, 4], we do not immediately assess
the change in ELBO produced by these new components, and always accept
them. We rely on subsequent merge moves (Sec. 3.2) to remove unneeded
components. Adoption During pass 2, we visit each batch and perform local
and global parameter updates for the expanded (K + K ? )-component mixture.
These updates use expanded global summaries S 0 that include summaries S
? from the targeted analysis of x? . This results in two interpretations of the
subset x? : assignment to original components (mostly k ? ) and assignment to
brand-new components. If the new components are favored, they will gain mass
via new assignments made at each batch. After the pass, we subtract away S
? to yield both S 0 and global parameters exactly consistent with the data x.
Any nearly-empty new component will likely be pruned away by later merges.
By adding many components at once, our birth move allows rapid escape from
poor local optima. Alone, births may sometimes cause a slight ELBO decrease
by adding unnecessary components. However, in practice merge moves reliably
reject poor births and restore original conﬁgurations. In Sec. 4, births are so
eﬀective that runs started at K = 1 recover necessary components on-the-ﬂy.
3.2 Merge moves that optimize the full data objective The computational cost
of inference grows with the number of components K. To keep K small, we
develop merge moves that replace two components with a single merged one.
Merge moves were ﬁrst explored for batch variational methods [16, 14]. For
hierarchical DP topic models, stochastic 5

6
3
log evidence x10
log evidence x106
1.04 1.03 1.02 1.01 1 0.99
Full K=25 MO K=25 GreedyMerge MO?BM K=1 6 9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30

num. passes thru data (N=100000)

Data: 5x5 patches
worst MO-BM
1.04 1.03 1.02 1.01 1 0.99 3
SOa K=25 SOb K=25 SOc K=25 6 9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 num. passes thru

data (N=100000)

worst MO
worst Full
best SOb
0.13
0.13

8

0.12
0.12
0.00
0.00
0.13
0.12
0.00
0.00
0.25
0.13
0.25
0.13
0.12
0.12
0.13
0.13
0.13
0.12
0.13
0.25
0.25
0.13
0.13
0.25
0.25
0.00
0.13
0.13
0.13
0.00
Figure 2: Comparison of full-data, stochastic (SO), and memoized (MO) on
toy data with K = 8 true components (Sec. 4.1). Top: Trace of ELBO during
training across 10 runs. SO compared with learning rates a,b,c. Bottom Left:
Example patch generated by each component. Bottom: Covariance matrix and
weights wk found by one run of each method, aligned to true components. ?X?:
no comparable component found.

variational inference methods have been augmented to evaluate merge pro-
posals based on noisy, single-batch estimates of the ELBO [4]. This can result in
accepted merges that decrease the fulldata objective (see Sec. 4.1 for an empiri-
cal illustration). In contrast, our algorithm accurately computes the full ELBO
for each merge proposal, ensuring only useful merges are accepted. Given two
components ka , kb to merge, we form a candidate q ? with K ? 1 components,
where merged component km takes over all assignments to ka , kb : r?nkm =
r?nka + r?nkb . Instead of computing new assignments explicitly, additivity
allows direct construction of merged global suﬃcient statistics: Sk0m = Sk0a
+ Sk0b . Merged global parameters follow from Eq. (10). Our merge move

9

has three steps: select components, form the candidate conﬁguration q ? , and
accept q ? if the ELBO improves. Selecting ka , kb to merge at random is
unlikely to yield an improved conﬁguration. After choosing ka at random, we
select kb using a ratio of marginal likelihoods M which compares the merged
and separated conﬁgurations, easily computed with cached summaries:

M (Ska + Skb ) p(kb — ka ) ? , M (Sk ) = exp a0 (?0 + sk (x)) . (12) M
(Ska )M (Skb ) Our memoized approach allows exact evaluation of the full-data
ELBO to compare the existing q to merge candidate q ? . As shown in Eq.
(8), evaluating L(q ? ) is a linear function of merged suﬃcient PN rnka +
r?nkb ). statistics, except for the assignment entropy term: Hab = ? n=1 (?
rnka + r?nkb ) log(? We compute this term in advance for all possible merge
pairs. This requires storing one set of K(K ? 1)/2 scalars, one per candidate
pair, for each batch. This modest precomputation allows rapid and exact merge
moves, which improve model quality and speed-up post-merge iterations. In one
pass of the data, our algorithm performs a birth, memoized ascent steps for all
batches, and several merges after the ﬁnal batch. After a few passes, it recovers
high-quality, compact structure.

4 Experimental results We now compare algorithms for learning DP-Gaussian
mixture models (DP-GMM), using our own implementations of full-dataset,
stochastic online (SO), and memoized online (MO) inference, as well as our new
birth-merge memoized algorithm (MO-BM). Code is available online. To exam-
ine SO?s sensitivity to learning rate, we use a recommended [1] decay schedule
?t = (t + d)?? with three diverse settings: a) ? = 0.5, d = 10, b) ? = 0.5,
d = 100, and c)? = 0.9, d = 10. 4.1 Toy data: How reliably do algorithms
escape local optima? We ﬁrst study N = 100000 synthetic image patches gen-
erated by a zero-mean GMM with 8 equallycommon components. Each one is
deﬁned by a 25 ? 25 covariance matrix producing 5 ? 5 patches with a strong
edge. We investigate whether algorithms recover the true K = 8 structure. Each
ﬁxedtruncation method runs from 10 ﬁxed random initializations with K = 25,
while MO-BM starts at K = 1. Online methods traverse 100 batches (1000
examples per batch). 6

6
Random Initialization
?2.85
log evidence x10
log evidence x10
6
Smart (k-means++) Initialization ?2.9 ?2.95 ?3 ?3.05 ?3.1
SOa SOb SOc
Full
20 batches 100 batches MO MO?BM Kuri
?3 ?3.5 ?4 ?4.5
SOa SOb SOc
num. components K
Alignment accuracy

10

0.82 0.8 0.78 0.76 0.74 0.72 0.7 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 110 Eﬀective num.

components K

Full
20 batches 100 batches MO MO?BM Kuri
100 80 60 40
Full MO MO?BM 0 0 40 80 120 160 200 num. pass thru data (N=60000) 20
Figure 3: MNIST. Top: Comparison of ﬁnal ELBO for multiple runs of each
method, varying initialization and number of batches. Stochastic online (SO)
compared at learning rates a,b,c. Bottom left: Visualization of cluster means
for MO-BM?s best run. Bottom center: Evaluation of cluster alignment to true
digit label. Bottom right: Growth in truncation-level K as more data visited
with MO-BM.

Fig. 2 traces the training-set ELBO as more data arrives for each algorithm
and shows estimated covariance matrices for the top 8 components for select
runs. Even the best runs of SO do not recover ideal structure. In contrast, all
10 runs of our birth-merge algorithm ﬁnd all 8 components, despite initializa-
tion at K = 1. The ELBO trace plots show this method escaping local optima,
with slight drops indicating addition of new components followed by rapid in-
creases as these are adopted. They further suggest that our ﬁxed-truncation
memoized method competes favorably with full-data inference, often converg-
ing to similar or better solutions after fewer passes through the data. The fact
that our MO-BM algorithm only performs merges that improve the full-data
ELBO is crucial. Fig. 2 shows trace plots of GreedyMerge, a memoized online
variant that instead uses only the current-batch ELBO to assess a proposed
merge, as done in [4]. Given small batches (1000 examples each), there is not
always enough data to warrant many distinct 25 ? 25 covariance components.
Thus, this method favors merges that in fact remove vital structure. All 5 runs
of this GreedyMerge algorithm ruinously accept merges that decrease the full
objective, consistently collapsing down to just one component. Our memoized
approach ensures merges are always globally beneﬁcial. 4.2 MNIST digit clus-
tering We now compare algorithms for clustering N = 60000 MNIST images of
handwritten digits 0-9. We preprocess as in [9], projecting each image down to
D = 50 dimensions via PCA. Here, we also compare to Kurihara?s public imple-
mentation of variational inference with split moves [9]. MO-BM and Kurihara
start at K = 1, while other methods are given 10 runs from two K = 100 ini-
tialization routines: random and smart (based on k-means++ [17]). For online
methods, we compare 20 and 100 batches, and three learning rates. All runs
complete 200 passes through the full dataset. The ﬁnal ELBO values for every
run of each method are shown in Fig. 3. SO?s performance varies dramatically
across initialization, learning rate, and number of batches. Under random ini-
tialization, SO reaches especially poor local optima (note lower y-axis scale). In
contrast, our memoized approach consistently delivers solutions on par with full
inference, with no apparent sensitivity to the number of batches. With births
and merges enabled, MO-BM expands from K = 1 to over 80 components, ﬁnd-
ing better solutions than every smart K = 100 initialization. MO-BM even
outperforms Kurihara?s oﬄine split algorithm, yielding 30-40 more components

11

and higher ELBO values. Altogether, Fig. 3 exposes SO?s extreme sensitivity,
validates MO as a more reliable alternative, and shows that our birth-merge
algorithm is more eﬀective at avoiding local optima. Fig. 3 also shows cluster
means learned by the best MO-BM run, covering many styles of each digit. We
further compute a hard segmentation of the data using the q(z) from smart
initialization runs. Each DP-GMM cluster is aligned to one digit by majority
vote of its members. A plot of alignment accuracy in Fig. 3 shows our MO-BM
consistently among the best, with SO lagging signiﬁcantly. 7

7
log evidence x10
?1.55 ?1.56 ?1.57 ?1.58 ?1.59 ?1.6 ?1.61 ?1.62 5
SOa K=100 SOb K=100 Full K=100 MO K=100 MO?BM K=1 10 15 20 25

30 35 40 45 50 num. passes thru data (N=108754)

4.4 4.35 4.3 4.25
MO?BM K=1 MO K=100 SOa K=100 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 num.

passes thru data (N=1880200)

300 MO?BM K=1 250 MO K=100 200 SOa K=100 150 100 50 0 0 10 20 30

40 50 60 70 80 90 100 num. passes thru data (N=1880200)

log evidence x109
4.45
num. components K
log evidence x108
Figure 4: SUN-397 tiny images. Left: ELBO during training. Right: Visu-
alization of 10 of 28 learned clusters for best MO-BM run. Each column shows
two images from the top 3 categories aligned to one cluster. 2.06 2.04 2.02 2
1.98 1.96 4

MO?BM K=1 MO K=100 SOa K=100 8 12 16 20 24 28 32 36 40 num.

passes thru data (N=8640000)

Figure 5: 8 ? 8 image patches. Left: ELBO during training, N = 1.88
million. Center: Eﬀective truncationlevel K during training, N = 1.88 million.
Right: ELBO during training, N = 8.64 million.

4.3 Tiny image clustering We next learn a full-mean DP-GMM for tiny, 32
? 32 images from the SUN-397 scene categories dataset [18]. We preprocess
all 108754 color images via PCA, projecting each example down to D = 50
dimensions. We start MO-BM at K = 1, while other methods have ﬁxed K =
100. Fig. 4 plots the training ELBO as more data is seen. Our MO-BM runs
surpass all other algorithms. To verify quality, Fig. 4 shows images from the
3 most-related scene categories for each of several clusters found by MO-BM.
For each learned cluster k, we rank all 397 categories to ﬁnd those with the
largest fraction of members assigned to k via r??k . The result is quite sensible,
with clusters for tall free-standing objects, swimming pools and lakes, doorways,
and waterfalls. 4.4 Image patch modeling Our last experiment applies a zero-
mean, full-covariance DP-GMM to learn the covariance structures of natural
image patches, inspired by [19, 20]. We compare online algorithms on N = 1.88
million 8 ? 8 patches, a dense subsampling of all patches from 200 images of the
Berkeley Segmentation dataset. Fig. 5 shows that our birth-merge memoized

12

algorithm started at K = 1 can consistently add useful components and reach
better solutions than alternatives. We also examined a much bigger dataset of
N = 8.64 million patches, and still see advantages for our MO-BM. Finally, we
perform denoising on 30 heldout images, using code from [19]. Our best MO-BM
run on the 1.88 million patch dataset achieves PSNR of 28.537 dB, within 0.05
dB of the PSNR achieved by [19]?s publicly-released GMM with K = 200 trained
on a similar corpus. This performance is visually indistinguishable, highlighting
the practical value of our new algorithm.

5 Conclusions Our novel memoized online variational algorithm avoids noisi-
ness and sensitivity inherent in stochastic methods. Our birth and merge moves
successfully escape local optima. These innovations are applicable to common
nonparametric models beyond the Dirichlet process. Acknowledgments This re-
search supported in part by ONR Award No. N00014-13-1-0644. M. Hughes
supported in part by an NSF Graduate Research Fellowship under Grant No.
DGE0228243.

8

2 References

In NIPS, 2012.

[1] M. Hoﬀman, D. Blei, C. Wang, and J. Paisley. Stochastic variational infer-
ence. JMLR, 14:1303?1347, 2013. [2] R. Ranganath, C. Wang., D. Blei, and E.
Xing. An adaptive learning rate for stochastic variational inference. In ICML,
[3] P. Gopalan, D. M. Mimno, S. Gerrish, M. J. Freedman, and D. M.
2013.
Blei. Scalable inference of overlapping communities.
[4] M.
Bryant and E. Sudderth. Truly nonparametric online variational inference for
hierarchical Dirichlet processes. In NIPS, 2012.
[5] S. Jain and R.M. Neal. A
split-merge Markov chain Monte Carlo procedure for the Dirichlet process mix-
ture model. Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics, 13(1):158?182,
2004.
[6] D. B. Dahl. Sequentially-allocated merge-split sampler for conju-
gate and nonconjugate Dirichlet process mixture models. Submitted to Journal
of Computational and Graphical Statistics, 2005.
[7] D. M. Blei and M. I.
Jordan. Variational inference for Dirichlet process mixture models. Bayesian
Analysis, 1(1):121?144, 2006.
[8] Y. W. Teh, K. Kurihara, and M. Welling.
Collapsed variational inference for HDP. In NIPS, 2008.
[9] K. Kurihara, M.
Welling, and N. Vlassis. Accelerated variational Dirichlet process mixtures. In
[10] R. M. Neal and G. E. Hinton. A view of the EM algorithm
NIPS, 2006.
that justiﬁes incremental, sparse, and other variants.
In Learning in graphi-
[11] O. Papaspiliopoulos and G. O. Roberts. Retrospective
cal models, 1999.
Markov chain Monte Carlo methods for Dirichlet process hierarchical models.
Biometrika, 95(1):169?186, 2008. [12] N. Goodman, V. Mansinghka, D. M. Roy,
K. Bonawitz, and J. Tenenbaum. Church: A language for generative models. In
Uncertainty in Artiﬁcial Intelligence, 2008. [13] N. Le Roux, M. Schmidt, and
F. Bach. A stochastic gradient method with an exponential convergence rate for
ﬁnite training sets. In NIPS, 2012. [14] N. Ueda and Z. Ghahramani. Bayesian
model search for mixture models based on optimizing variational bounds. Neu-

13

ral Networks, 15(1):1223?1241, 2002. [15] C. Wang and D. Blei. Truncation-free
stochastic variational inference for Bayesian nonparametric models. In NIPS,
2012. [16] N. Ueda, R. Nakano, Z. Ghahramani, and G. Hinton. SMEM algo-
rithm for mixture models. Neural Computation, 12(9):2109?2128, 2000. [17] D.
Arthur and S. Vassilvitskii. k-means++: The advantages of careful seeding. In
ACM-SIAM Symposium on Discrete Algorithms, pages 1027?1035, 2007.
[18]
J. Xiao, J. Hays, K. Ehinger, A. Oliva, and A. Torralba. SUN database: Large-
scale scene recognition from abbey to zoo. In CVPR, 2010. [19] D. Zoran and Y.
Weiss. From learning models of natural image patches to whole image restora-
tion. In ICCV, 2011.
[20] D. Zoran and Y. Weiss. Natural images, Gaussian
mixtures and dead leaves. In NIPS, 2012.

9

14

