Least Informative Dimensions

Authored by:

Fabian Sinz
Anna Stockl
Jan Grewe
Jan Benda

Abstract

We present a novel non-parametric method for ﬁnding a subspace of
stimulus features that contains all information about the response of a
system. Our method generalizes similar approaches to this problem such
as spike triggered average, spike triggered covariance, or maximally in-
formative dimensions. Instead of maximizing the mutual information be-
tween features and responses directly, we use integral probability metrics
in kernel Hilbert spaces to minimize the information between uninforma-
tive features and the combination of informative features and responses.
Since estimators of these metrics access the data via kernels, are easy to
compute, and exhibit good theoretical convergence properties, our method
can easily be generalized to populations of neurons or spike patterns. By
using a particular expansion of the mutual information, we can show that
the informative features must contain all information if we can make the
uninformative features independent of the rest.

1 Paper Body

An important aspect of deciphering the neural code is to determine those stim-
ulus features populations of sensory neurons are most sensitive to. Approaches
to that problem include white noise analysis [2, 14], in particular spike-triggered
average [4] or spike-triggered covariance [3, 19], canonical correlation analysis or
population receptive ﬁelds [12], generalized linear models [18, 15], or maximally
informative dimensions [22]. All these techniques have in common that they op-
timize a statistical dependency measure between stimuli and spike responses over
the choice of a linear subspace. The particular algorithms diﬀer in the dimen-
sionality of the subspace they extract (one- vs. multi-dimensional), the statisti-
cal measure they use (correlation, likelihood, relative entropy), and whether an
extension to population responses is feasible or not. While spike-triggered aver-
age uses correlation and is restricted to a single subspace, spike-triggered covari-
ance and canonical correlation analysis can already extract multi-dimensional

1

subspaces but are still restricted to second-order statistics. Maximally infor-
mative dimensions is the only technique of the above that can extract multiple
dimensions that are informative also with respect to higher-order statistics.
However, an extension to spike patterns or population responses is not straight-
forward because of the curse of dimensionality. Here we approach the problem
from a diﬀerent perspective and propose an algorithm that can extract a multi-
dimensional subspace containing all relevant information about the neural re-
sponses Y in terms of Shannon?s mutual information (if such a subspace exists).
Our method does not commit to a particular parametric model, and can easily
be extended to spike patterns or population responses. 1

In general, the problem of ﬁnding the most informative subspace of the stim-
uli X about the responses Y can be described as ﬁnding an orthogonal matrix
Q (a basis for Rn ) that separates X ¿ into informative and non-informative
features (U , V ) = QX. Since Q is orthogonal, the mutual information I [X : Y
] between X and Y can be decomposed as [5]

p (U , V , Y ) I [Y : X] = I [Y : U , V ] = EX,Y log p (U , V ) p (Y )
p (Y , V — U ) = I [Y : U ] + EY ,V log p (Y — U ) p (V — U ) = I [Y : U
] + EU [I [Y — U : V — U ]] . (1) Since the two terms on the right hand side of
equation (1) are always positive and sum up to the mutual information between
Y and X, two ways to obtain maximally informative features U about Y would
be to either maximize I [Y : U ] or to minimize EU [I [Y —U : V —U ]] via
the choice of Q. The ﬁrst possibility is along the lines of maximally informative
dimensions [22] and involves direct estimation of the mutual information. The
second possibility which avoids direct estimation has been proposed by Fuku-
mizu and colleagues [5, 6] (we discuss both in Section 3). Here, we explore
a third possibility, which trades practical advantages against a slightly more
restrictive objective. The idea is to obtain maximally informative features U
by making V as independent as possible from the combination of U and Y .
For this reason, we name our approach least informative dimensions (LID). For-
mally, least informative dimensions tries to minimize the mutual information
between the pair Y , U and V . Using the chain rule for multi information we
can write it as (see supplementary material) I [Y , U : V ]

= I [Y : X] + I [U : V ] ? I [Y : U ] .
(2)
This means that minimizing I [Y , U : V ] is equivalent to maximizing I [Y : U
] while simultaneously minimizing I [U : V ]. Note that I [Y , U : V ] = 0 implies
I [U : V ] = 0. Therefore, if Q can be chosen such that I [Y , U : V ] = 0 equation
(2) reduces to I [Y : X] = I [Y : U ], pushing all information about Y into U .
Since each new choice of Q requires the estimation of the mutual information
between (potentially high-dimensional) variables, direct optimization is hard or
unfeasible. For this reason, we resort to another dependency measure which is
easier to estimate but shares its minimum with mutual information, that is, it is
zero if and only if the mutual information is zero. The objective is to choose Q
such that (Y , U ) and V are independent in that dependency measure. If we can
ﬁnd such a Q, then we know that I [Y , U : V ] is zero as well, which means that U
are the most informative features in terms of the Shannon mutual information.

2

This will allow us to obtain maximally informative features without ever having
to estimate a mutual information. The easier estimation procedure comes at
the cost of only being able to link the alternative dependency measure to the
mutual information if both of them are zero. If there is no Q that achieves this,
we will still get informative features in the alternative measure, but it is not
clear how informative they are in terms of mutual information.

2
Least informative dimensions
This section describes how to eﬃciently ﬁnd a Q such that I [Y , U : V ] = 0
(if such a Q exists). ¿ Unless noted otherwise, (U , V ) = QX where U denotes
the informative and V the uninformative features. The mutual information is a
special case of the relative entropy

log p (X) DKL [p —— q] = EX?p log q (X) between two distribution p and
q. While being linked to the rich theoretical background of Shannon information
theory, the relative entropy is known to be hard to estimate [25]. Alternatives
to relative entropy of increasing practical interest are the integral probability
metrics (IPM), deﬁned as [25, 17] ?F (X : Z)

=
sup —EX [f (X)] ? EZ [f (Z)]— .
(3)
f ?F
Intuitively, the metric in equation (3) searches for a function f , which can
detect a diﬀerence in the distributions of two random variables X and Z. If no
such witness function can be found, the 2

distributions must be equal. If F is chosen to be a suﬃciently rich repro-
ducing kernel Hilbert space H [21], then the supremum in equation (3) can be
computed explicitly and the divergence can be computed in closed form [7].
This particular type of IPM is called maximum mean discrepancy (MMD) [9,
7, 10]. A kernel k : X ? X ? R is a symmetric function such that the matrix
Kij = k (xi , xj ) is positive (semi)-deﬁnite for every selection of points x1 , ...,
xm ? X [21]. In that case, the functions k (?, x) are elements of a reproducing
kernel Hilbert space (RKHS) of functions H. This space is endowed with a dot
product h?, ?iH with the so called reproducing property hk (?, x) , f iH = f (x)
for f ? H. In particular, hk (?, x) , k (?, x0 )iH = k (x, x0 ). When setting F in
equation (3) to be the unit ball in H, then the IPM can be computed in closed
form as the norm of the diﬀerence between the mean functions in H [7, 10, 8,
26]: ?H (X : Z)

= =
kEX [k (?, X)] ? EZ [k (?, Z)]kH
12 EX,X 0 k X, X 0 ? 2EX,Z [k (X, Z)] + EZ,Z 0 k Z, Z 0 ,
(4)
where the ﬁrst equality is derived in [7], and second equality uses the bi-
linearity of the dot product and the reproducing property of k. Furthermore,
(X, X 0 ) ? PX ? PX and (Z, Z 0 ) ? PZ ? PZ are two independent random
variables drawn from the marginal distributions of X and Z, respectively. The
function EX [k (?, X)] is an embedding of the distribution of X into the RKHS

3

H via X 7? EX [k (?, X)]. If this map is injective, that is, if it uniquely rep-
resents the probability distribution of X, then equation (4) is zero if and only
if the probability distributions of X and X 0 are the same. Kernels with that
property are called characteristic in analogy to the characteristic function ?X
(t) 7? EX exp it¿ X [26, 27]. This means that for characteristic kernels MMD is
zero exactly if the relative entropy DKL [pkq] is zero as well. Since the mutual
information is the relative entropy between the joint distribution and the prod-
ucts of the marginals, we can use MMD to search for a Q such that ?H (PY ,U
,V : PY ,U ? PV ) is zero1 , which then implies that I [Y , U : V ] = 0 as well.
The ﬁnite sample version of (4) is simply given by replacing the expectations
with the empirical mean (and possibly some bias correction) [7, 10, 8]. The
estimation of ?H therefore only involves summation over three kernel matrices
and can be done in a few lines of code. Unlike for the relative entropy, the em-
pirical estimation of MMD is therefore much more feasible. Further? more, the
residual error of the empirical estimator can be shown to decrease on the order
of 1/ m where m is the number of data points [25]. Note in particular, that this
rate does not depend on the dimensionality of the data. Objective function The
objective function for our optimization problem now has the following form: We
transform input examples xi into features ui and v i via (ui , v i ) = Qxi . Then
we use a kernel k (ui , v i , y i ) , uj , v j , y j to compute and minimize MMD
with respect to the choice of Q. In order to do that eﬃciently, a few adaptations
are required. First, without loss of generality, we minimize the squared MMD
instead of MMD itself

2 ?H (Z 1 , Z 2 ) = EZ 1 ,Z 01 k Z 1 , Z 01 ? 2EZ 1 ,Z 2 [k (Z 1 , Z 2 )] +
EZ 2 ,Z 02 k Z 2 , Z 02 , (5) where Z 1 = (Y , U , V ) ? PY ,U ,V and Z 2 =
(Y , U , V ) ? PY ,U ? PV . Second, in order to get samples from PY ,U ? PV
,we assume that our kernel takes the form

k (ui , v i , y i ) , uj , v j , y j = k1 (ui , y i ) , uj , y j ? k2 (v i , v j ). For
this special case, one can incorporate the independence assumption between U
, Y and V directly by using the fact that for independent random variables, the
expectation of the product is equal to the product of expectations, that is,

E k1 (ui , y i ) , uj , y j ? k2 (v i , v j ) = E k1 (ui , y i ) , uj , y j E [k2
(v i , v j )] . This special case of MMD is equivalent to the Hilbert-Schmidt
Independence Criterion (HSIC) [9, 23] and can be computed as 1 2 ??hs (6) =
2 tr (K1 HK2 H) , (m ? 1) m
where K1 and K2 denote the matrices of pairwise kernel values between the
data sets {(ui , y i )}i=1 m and {v i }i=1 , respectively, and Hij = ?ij ? m?1 .
1

With some abuse of notation, we wrote MMD as a function of the probability

measures.

3
Note, however, that one could in principle also optimize (5) for a non-
factorizing kernel by simply shuﬄing the (ui , y i ) and v i across examples.
We can also use shuﬄing to assess whether the 2 optimal value ??hs found dur-
ing the optimization is signiﬁcantly diﬀerent from zero by comparing 2 the value
to a null distribution over ??hs obtained from datasets where the (ui , y i ) and

4

v i have been permuted across examples. Minimization procedure and gradients
For optimizing (6) with respect to Q we use gradient descent over the orthogonal
group SO(n). The optimization can be carried out by computing the uncon-
strained gradient ?Q ? of the objective function with respect to Q (treating Q
as an ordinary matrix), projecting that gradient onto the tangent space of SO
(n), and performing a line search along the gradient direction. We now present
the necessary formulae to implement the optimization in a modular fashion. We
ﬁrst show how to compute the gradient ?Q ? in terms of the gradients 2 2 ?ui
,vi ??hs , then we show how to compute the ?ui ,vi ??hs in terms of derivatives
of kernel functions, and ﬁnally demonstrate how the formulae change when ap-
proximating the kernel matrices with an incomplete Cholesky decomposition.
Given the unconstrained gradient ?Q ? the projection onto the tangent space is
given by ? = Q?Q ? ¿ Q ? ?Q ? [13, eq. (22)]. The function is then minimized
by performing a line-search along ? (Q + t?), where ? is the projection onto
SO (n) which can easily be computed via singular value decomposition of Q +
t? and setting the singular values to one [13, prop. 7]. This means that all
we need for the gradient descent on SO(n) is the unconstrained gradient ?Q ?.
This gradient takes the form of a sum of outer products [16, eq. (20)]

m 2 2 X ?? ?hs ?? ?hs 2 ¿ ?Q ??hs = ? x¿ , = J ?, J = i ? (ui , v i ) ? (ui ,

v i ) i i=1 where the matrix ? contains the stimuli xi in its rows. (u)

The ﬁrst k columns J? corresponding to the dimension of the features ui and
the last n?k columns J (v) corresponding to the dimension of the features v i
are given by

2 2 (u)¿ (v) (v)¿ J?(u) = diag HK HD and J = diag HK HD , 2 1 ? ? ? 2 2

(m ? 1) (m ? 1) where

D?(u)
= ij
? k (ui , v i , y i ) , uj , v j , y j ?ui?
ij
th
contains the partial derivatives of the kernel with respect to the ? dimension
of u (and analogously for v) in the ﬁrst argument (see supplementary material for
the derivation). Eﬃcient implementation with incomplete Cholesky decomposi-
tion of the kernel matrix So far, the evaluation of HSIC requires the computation
of two m ? m kernel matrices in each step. For larger datasets this can quickly
become computationally prohibitive. In order to speed up computation time,
we approximate the kernel matrices by an incomplete Cholesky decomposition
K = LL¿ , where L ? Rm¿ is a ?tall? matrix [1]. In that case, HSIC can be
computed much faster as the trace of a product of two ‘ ? ‘ matrices because

2 ¿ 2 tr (K1 HK2 H) = tr L¿ 1 H L2 L2 H L1 , where HLk can be eﬃciently
computed by centering Lk on its row mean. Also in this case, the matrix J
can be computed eﬃciently in terms of derivatives of sub-matrices of the kernel
matrix (see supplementary material for the exact formulae).

3
Related work

5

Kernel dimension reduction in regression [5, 6] Fukumizu and colleagues ﬁnd
maximally informative features U by minimizing EU [I [V — U : Y — U ]] in
equation (1) via conditional kernel 4

covariance operators. They show that the covariance operator equals zero if
and only if Y is conditionally independent of V given U , that is, Y ??V — U
. In that case, U carries all information about Y . Although their approach is
closest to ours, it diﬀers in a few key aspects: In contrast to our approach, their
objective involves the inversion of a?potentially large?kernel matrix which needs
additional regularization in order to be invertible. A conceptual diﬀerence is that
we are optimizing a slightly more restrictive problem because their objective
does not attempt to make U independent of V as well. However, this will not
make a diﬀerence in many practical cases, since many stimulus distributions
are Gaussian for which the dependencies between U and V can be removed by
prewhitening the stimulus data before training LID. In that case I [U : V ] =
0 for every choice of Q and equation (2) becomes equivalent to maximizing the
mutual information between U and Y . The advantage of our formulation of the
problem is that it allows us to detect and quantify independence by comparing
the current ??hs to its null distribution obtained by shuﬄing the (y i , ui )
against v i across examples. This is hardly possible in the conditional case.
Also note that for spherically symmetric data I [U : V ] = const.
for every
choice of Q. In that case equation (2) becomes equivalent to maximizing I [Y
: U ]. However, a residual redundancy remains which would show up when 2
comparing ??hs to its null distribution. Finally, the use of kernel covariance
operators is bound to kernels that factorize. In principle, our method is also
applicable to non-factorizing kernels if we use ?H instead of ?hs and obtain the
samples from the product distribution of PY ,U ? PV via shuﬄing. Maximally
informative dimensions [22]

Sharpee and colleagues maximize the relative entropy Ispike = DKL p v ¿
s—spike —— p v ¿ s between the distribution of stimuli projected onto infor-
mative dimensions given a spike, to the marginal distribution of the projection.
This relative entropy is the part of the mutual information which is carried by
the arrival of a single spike, since
I v ¿ s : {spike, no spike} = p (spike) ? Ispike + p (no spike) Ino spike
. Their method is also completely non-parametric and captures higher order
dependencies between a stimulus and a single spike. However, by focusing on
single spikes and the spike triggered density only, it neglects the dependencies
between spikes and the information carried by the silence of the neuron [28].
Additionally, the generalization to spike patterns or population responses is
non-trivial between the projected stimuli and spike patterns $ 1 , ..., $ ‘ be
becausethe information P comes I v ¿ s : $ = p ($ ) ? I$i . This requires the
estimation of a conditional distribution i i

¿ p v s—$ i for each pattern $ i which can quickly become prohibitive when

the number of patterns grows exponentially.

4
Experiments
In all the experiments below, we demonstrate the validity of our methods

6

on controlled artiﬁcial examples and on P-unit recordings from electric ﬁsh. We
use an RBF kernel on the v i and a tensor RBF kernel on the (ui , y i ): !

¿ 2
kui y ¿ kv i ? v j k2 i ? uj y j k k (v i , v j ) = exp ? and k (ui , y i )
, uj , y j = exp ? . ?2 ?2 The derivatives of the kernels can be found in the
supplementary material. Unless noted otherwise the ? were chosen to be the
median of pairwise Euclidean distances between data points.
In all artiﬁcial
experiments, Q was chosen randomly. Linear Non-Linear Poisson Model (LNP)
In this experiment, we trained LID on a simple linear nonlinear Poisson (LNP)
neuron yi ? Poisson bhw, xi i ? ?c+ with an exponentially decaying ﬁlter and
a rectifying non-linearity (see Figure 1, left). We used m = 5000 data points xi
from a 20-dimensional standard normal distribution N (0, I) as input. The oﬀset
was chosen such that approximately 35% non-zero spike counts in the yi were
obtained. We used one informative and 19 non-informative dimensions, and set
? = 1 for the tensor kernel. After optimization, the h ﬁrst dimension q 1 of Q
converged i to the ﬁlter w (Figure 1). We compared the HSIC values ??hs {(y i
, ui )}i=1,...,m : {v i }i=1,...,m before and after the optimization to their null
distribution obtained by shuﬄing. Before the optimization, the dependence of
(Y , U ) and V 5

Figure 1: Left: LNP Model. The informative dimension (gray during opti-
mization, black after optimization) converges to the true ﬁlter of an LNP model
(blue line). Before optimization (Y , U ) and V are dependent as shown by
the left inset (null distribution obtained via shuﬄing in gray, dashed line shows
actual HSIC value). After the optimization (right inset) the HSIC value is even
below the null distribution. Right: Two state neuron. LID correctly identiﬁes
the subspace (blue dashed) in which the two true ﬁlters (solid black) reside
since projections of the ﬁlters on the subspace (red dashed) closely resemble
the original ﬁlters.
is correctly detected (Figure 1, left, insets). After conver-
gence the actual HSIC value lies left to the null distribution?s domain. Since
the appropriate test for independence would be one-sided, the null hypothesis
?(Y , U ) is independent of V ? would not be rejected in this case. Two state
neuron In this experiment, we simulated a neuron with two states that were
both attained in 50% of the trials (see Figure 1, right). This time, the output
consisted of four ?bins? whose statistics varied depending on the state. In the
ﬁrst?steady rate?state, the four bins contained spike counts drawn from an LNP
neuron with exponentially decaying ﬁlter as above. In the second?burst?state,
the ﬁrst two bins were drawn from Poisson distribution with a ﬁxed base rate
independent of the stimulus. The second two bins were drawn from an LNP
neuron with a modulated exponential ﬁlter and higher gain. We used m = 8000
input stimuli from a 20-dimensional standard normal distribution. We use two
informative dimensions and set ? of the tensor kernel to two times the median
of the pairwise distances. LID correctly identiﬁed the subspace associated with
the two ﬁlters also in this case (Figure 1, right). Artiﬁcial complex cell In a
second experiment, we estimated the two-dimensional subspace associated with
a artiﬁcial complex cell. We generated a quadrature pair w1 and w2 of two
10dimensional ﬁlters (see Figure 2, left). We used m = 8000 input points from

7

a standard normal distribution. Responses were generated from a Poisson dis-
tribution with the rate given by 2 2 ?i = hw1 , xi i + hw2 , xi i . This led to
about 34% non-zero neural responses. When using two informative subspaces,
LID was able to identify the subspace correctly (Figure 2, left). When compar-
ing the HSIC value against the null distribution found via shuﬄing, the ﬁnal
value indicated no further dependencies. When only a one-dimensional subspace
was used (Figure 2, right), LID did not converge to the correct subspace. Im-
portantly, the HSIC value after optimization was clearly outside the support of
the null distribution, thereby correctly indicating residual dependencies. P-Unit
recordings from weakly electric ﬁsh Finally, we applied our method to P-unit
recordings from the weakly electric ﬁsh Eigenmannia virescens. These weakly
electric ﬁsh generate a dipolelike electric ﬁeld which changes polarity with a
frequency at about 300Hz. Sensors in the skin of the ﬁsh are tuned to this
carrier frequency and respond to amplitude changes caused by close-by objects
with diﬀerent conductive properties than water [20]. In the present recordings,
the immobilized ﬁsh was stimulated with 10s of 300 ? 600Hz low-pass ﬁltered
full ﬁeld frozen Gaussian white noise amplitude modulations of its own ﬁeld.
Neural activity was recorded intra-cellularly from the P-unit aﬀerents. Spikes
were binned with 1ms precision. We selected m = 8400 random time points
in the spike response and the corresponding preceding 20ms of the input (20
dimensions). We used the same 6

Figure 2: Artiﬁcial Complex Cell. Left: The original ﬁlters are 90? phase
shifted Gabor ﬁlters which form an orthogonal basis for a two-dimensional sub-
space. After optimization, the two informative dimensions of LID (ﬁrst two
rows of Q) converge to that subspace and also form a pair of 90? phase shifted
ﬁlters (note that even if the ﬁlters are not the same, they span the same sub-
space). Comparing the HSIC values before and after optimization shows that
this subspace contains the relevant information (left and right inset). Right:
If only a one-dimensional informative subspace is used, the ﬁlter only slightly
converges to the subspace. After optimization, a comparison of the HSIC value
to the null distribution obtained via shuﬄing indicates residual dependencies
which are not explained by the one-dimensional subspace (left and right inset).
Figure 3: Most informative feature for a weakly electric ﬁsh P-Unit: A
random ﬁlter (blue trace) exhibits HSIC values that are clearly outside the
domain of the null distribution (left inset). Using the spike triggered average
(red trace) moves the HSIC values of the ﬁrst feature of Q already inside the null
distribution (middle inset). Further optimization with LID reﬁnes the feature
(black trace) and brings the HSIC values closer to zero (right inset). After
optimization, the informative feature U is independent of the features V because
the ﬁrst row and column of the covariance matrix of the transformed Gaussian
input show no correlations. The fact that one informative feature is suﬃcient
to bring the HSIC values inside the null distribution indicates that a single
subspace captures all information conveyed by these sensory neurons.

kernels as in the experiment on the LNP model. We initialized the ﬁrst
row in Q with the normalized spike triggered average (STA; Figure 3, left, red
trace). We neither pre-whitened the data for computing the STA nor for the

8

optimization of LID. Unlike a random feature (Figure 3, left, blue trace), the
spike triggered average already achieves HSIC values within the null distribution
(Figure 3, left and middle inset). The most informative feature corresponding
to U looks very similar to the STA but shifts the HSIC value deeper into the
domain of the null distribution (Figure 3, right inset). 7

This indicates that one single subspace in the input is suﬃcient to carry all

information between the input and the neural response.

5
Discussion
Here we presented a non-parametric method to estimate a subspace of the
stimulus space that contains all information about a response variable Y . Even
though our method is completely generic and applicable to arbitrary input-
output pairs of data, we focused on the application in the context of sensory
neuroscience. The advantage of the generic approach is that Y can in principle
be anything from spike counts, to spike patterns or population responses. Since
our method ﬁnds the most informative dimensions by making the complement
of those dimensions as independent from the data as possible, we termed it
least informative dimensions (LID). We use the Hilbert-Schmidt independence
criterion to minimize the dependencies between the uninformative features and
the combination of informative features and outputs. This measure is easy to
implement, avoids the need to estimate mutual information, and its estimator
has good convergence properties independent of the dimensionality of the data.
Even though our approach only estimates the informative features and not mu-
tual information itself, it can help to estimate mutual information by reducing
the number of dimensions. As in the approach by Fukumizu and colleagues, it
might be that no Q exists such that I [Y , U : V ] = 0. In that situation, the
price to pay for an easier measure is that it is hard to make deﬁnite statements
about the informativeness of the features U in terms of the Shannon informa-
tion, since ?H = I [Y , U : V ] = 0 is the point that connects ?H to the mutual
information. As demonstrated in the experiments, we can detect this case by
comparing the actual value of ??H to an empirical null distribution of ??H val-
ues obtained by shuﬄing the v i against the ui , y i pairs. However, if ?H 6=
0, theoretical upper bounds on the mutual information are unfortunately not
available. 2 In fact, using results from [25] and Pinsker?s inequality one can
show that ?H bounds the mutual information from below. One might now be
tempted to think that maximizing ?H [Y , U ] might be a better way to ﬁnd
informative features. While this might be a way to get some informative fea-
tures [24], it is not possible to link the features to informativeness in terms of
Shannon mutual information, because the point that builds the bridge between
the two dependency measures is where both of them are zero. Anywhere else
the bound may not be tight so the maximally informative features in terms of
?H and in terms of mutual information can be diﬀerent. Another problem our
approach shares with many algorithms that detect higher-order dependencies is
the non-convexity of the objective function. In practice, we found that the de-
gree to which this poses a problem very much depends on the problem at hand.
For instance, while the subspaces of the LNP or the two state neuron were de-

9

tected reliably, the two dimensional subspace of the artiﬁcial complex cell seems
to pose a harder problem. It is likely that the choice of kernel has an inﬂuence
on the landscape of the objective function. We plan to explore this relationship
in more detail in the future. In general, a good initialization of Q helps to get
close to the global optimum. Beyond that, however, integral probability metric
approaches to maximally informative dimensions oﬀer a great chance to avoid
many problems associated with direct estimation of mutual information, and to
extend it to much more interesting output structures than single spikes.

Acknowledgements Fabian Sinz would like to thank Lucas Theis and Se-
bastian Gerwinn for helpful discussions and comments on the manuscript. This
study is part of the research program of the Bernstein Center for Computational
Neuroscience, T?ubingen, funded by the German Federal Ministry of Education
and Research (BMBF; FKZ: 01GQ1002).

2 References

[1] F. R. Bach and M. I. Jordan. Predictive low-rank decomposition for ker-
nel methods. In Proceedings of the 22nd international conference on Machine
learning - ICML ?05, pages 33?40, New York, New York, USA, 2005. ACM
Press. [2] E. D. Boer and P. Kuyper. Triggered Correlation, 1968.

8
[3] N. Brenner, W. Bialek, and R. De Ruyter Van Steveninck. Adaptive
rescaling maximizes information transmission. Neuron, 26(3):695?702, 2000.
[4] E. J. Chichilnisky. A simple white noise analysis of neuronal light responses.
Network: Comput. Neural Syst, 12:199?213, 2001.
[5] K. Fukumizu, F. R.
Bach, and M. I. Jordan. Dimensionality Reduction for Supervised Learning
with Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Spaces. Journal of Machine Learning Re-
search, 5(1):73?99, 2004. [6] K. Fukumizu, F. R. Bach, and M. I. Jordan. Kernel
dimension reduction in regression. Annals of Statistics, 37(4):1871?1905, 2009.
[7] A. Gretton, K. M. Borgwardt, M. Rasch, B. Sch?olkopf, and A. Smola. A
kernel method for the two sample problem.
In B. Sch?olkopf, J. Platt, and
T. Hoﬀman, editors, Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 19,
pages 513?-520, Cambridge, MA, 2007. MIT Press.
[8] A. Gretton, K. M.
Borgwardt, M. J. Rasch, B. Sch?olkopf, and A. Smola. A Kernel Two-Sample
Test. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 13:723?773, 2012. [9] A. Gretton,
O. Bousquet, A. Smola, and B. Sch?olkopf. Measuring Statistical Dependence
with HilbertSchmidt Norms. In S. Jain, H. U. Simon, and E. Tomita, editors,
Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 63?77. Springer
Berlin / Heidelberg, 2005.
[10] A. Gretton, K. Fukumizu, Z. Harchaoui, and
B. K. Sriperumbudur. A Fast, Consistent Kernel Two-Sample Test. In Y Ben-
gio, D Schuurmans, J Laﬀerty, C K I Williams, and A Culotta, editors, Ad-
vances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 673?681. Curran, Red
Hook, NY, USA, 2009. [11] J. D. Hunter. Matplotlib: A 2D graphics environ-
ment. Computing In Science & Engineering, 9(3):90?95, 2007.
[12] J. Macke,
G. Zeck, and M. Bethge. Receptive Fields without Spike-Triggering. Advances

10

in Neural Information Processing Systems 20, pages 1?8, 2007. [13] J. H. Man-
ton. Optimization algorithms exploiting unitary constraints. Signal Processing,
IEEE Transactions on, 50(3):635?650, 2002. [14] P. Z. Marmarelis and K. Naka.
White-noise analysis of a neuron chain: an application of the Wiener theory.
Science, 175(27):1276?1278, 1972. [15] P McCullagh and J A Nelder. General-
ized Linear Models, Second Edition. Chapman and Hall, 1989. [16] T. P. Minka.
Old and New Matrix Algebra Useful for Statistics. MIT Media Lab Note, pages
1?19, 2000. [17] A. M?uller. Integral Probability Metrics and Their Generating
Classes of Functions. Advances in Applied Probability, 29(2):429?443, 1997.
[18] L. Paninski. Maximum likelihood estimation of cascade point-process neu-
ral encoding models. Network: Computation in Neural Systems, 15(4):243?262,
2004. [19] J. W. Pillow and E. P. Simoncelli. Dimensionality reduction in neural
models: an information-theoretic generalization of spike-triggered average and
covariance analysis. Journal of Vision, 6(4):414?428, 2006. [20] H. Scheich, T.
H. Bullock, and R. H Hamstra. Coding properties of two classes of aﬀerent nerve
ﬁbers: high-frequency electroreceptors in the electric ﬁsh, Eigenmannia. Jour-
nal of Neurophysiology, 36(1):39? 60, 1973. [21] B. Sch?olkopf and A. J. Smola.
Learning with Kernels: Support Vector Machines, Regularization, Optimiza-
tion, and Beyond, volume 98 of Adaptive computation and machine learning.
MIT Press, 2001.
[22] T. Sharpee, N. C. Rust, and W. Bialek. Analyzing
neural responses to natural signals: maximally informative dimensions. Neural
Computation, 16(2):223?250, 2004.
[23] A. Smola, A. Gretton, L. Song, and
B. Sch?olkopf. A Hilbert Space Embedding for Distributions. In Algorithmic
Learning Theory: 18th International Conference, pages 13?31. Springer-Verlag,
Berlin/Heidelberg, 2007. [24] L. Song, A. Smola, A. Gretton, J. Bedo, and K.
Borgwardt. Feature selection via dependence maximization. Journal of Ma-
chine Learning Research, 13(May):1393?1434, 2012. [25] B. K. Sriperumbudur,
K. Fukumizu, A. Gretton, and G. R. G. Lanckriet. On Integral Probability
Metrics, phi-divergences and binary classiﬁcation. Technical Report 1, arXiv,
2009. [26] B. K. Sriperumbudur, A. Gretton, K. Fukumizu, G. Lanckriet, and
B. Sch?olkopf.
Injective Hilbert Space Embeddings of Probability Measures.
In Proceedings of the 21st Annual Conference on Learning Theory, number i,
pages 111?122. Omnipress, 2008.
[27] B. K. Sriperumbudur, A. Gretton, K.
Fukumizu, B. Sch?olkopf, and G.R. G. Lanckriet. Hilbert Space Embeddings
and Metrics on Probability Measures. Journal of Machine Learning Research,
11(1):48, 2010. [28] R. S. Williamson, M. Sahani, and J. W. Pillow. Equating
information-theoretic and likelihood-based methods for neural dimensionality
reduction. Technical Report 1, arXiv, 2013.

9

11

