Variational Inference for Mahalanobis Distance

Metrics in Gaussian Process Regression

Authored by:

Michalis Titsias RC AUEB

Miguel Lazaro-Gredilla

Abstract

We introduce a novel variational method that allows to approximately
integrate out kernel hyperparameters, such as length-scales, in Gaussian
process regression. This approach consists of a novel variant of the varia-
tional framework that has been recently developed for the Gaussian pro-
cess latent variable model which additionally makes use of a standardised
representation of the Gaussian process. We consider this technique for
learning Mahalanobis distance metrics in a Gaussian process regression
setting and provide experimental evaluations and comparisons with exist-
ing methods by considering datasets with high-dimensional inputs.

1 Paper Body

Gaussian processes (GPs) have found many applications in machine learning and
statistics ranging from supervised learning tasks to unsupervised learning and
reinforcement learning. However, while GP models are advertised as Bayesian
models, it is rarely the case that a full Bayesian procedure is considered for train-
ing. In particular, the commonly used procedure is to ﬁnd point estimates over
the kernel hyperparameters by maximizing the marginal likelihood, which is the
likelihood obtained once the latent variables associated with the GP function
have been integrated out (Rasmussen and Williams, 2006). Such a procedure
provides a practical algorithm that is expected to be robust to overﬁtting when
the number of hyperparameters that need to be tuned are relatively few com-
pared to the amount of data. In contrast, when the number of hyperparameters
is large this approach will suﬀer from the shortcomings of a typical maximum
likelihood method such as overﬁtting. To avoid the above problems, in GP
models, the use of kernel functions with few kernel hyperparameters is common
practice, although this can lead to limited ﬂexibility when modelling the data.
For instance, in regression or classiﬁcation problems with high dimensional in-
put data the typical kernel functions used are restricted to have the simplest
possible form, such as a squared exponential with common length-scale across

1

input dimensions, while more complex kernel functions such as ARD or Ma-
halanobis kernels (Vivarelli and Williams, 1998) are not considered due to the
large number of hyperparameters needed to be estimated by maximum likeli-
hood. On the other hand, while full Bayesian inference for GP models could be
useful, it is pragmatically a very challenging task that currently has been at-
tempted only by using expensive MCMC techniques such as the recent method
of Murray and Adams (2010). Deterministic approximations and particularly
the variational Bayes framework has not been applied so far for the treatment of
kernel hyperparameters in GP models. To this end, in this work we introduce a
variational method for approximate Bayesian inference over hyperparameters in
GP regression models with squared exponential kernel functions. This approach
consists of a novel variant of the variational framework introduced in (Titsias
and Lawrence, 2010) for the Gaussian process latent variable model. Further-
more, this method uses the concept of a standardised GP process and allows for
learning Mahalanobis distance metrics (Weinberger and Saul, 2009; Xing et al.,
2003) in Gaussian process regression settings using Bayesian inference. In 1

the experiments, we compare the proposed algorithm with several existing
methods by considering several datasets with high-dimensional inputs. The
remainder of this paper is organised as follows: Section 2 provides the motivation
and theoretical foundation of the variational method, Section 3 demonstrates
the method in a number of challenging regression datasets by providing also a
comprehensive comparison with existing methods. Finally, the paper concludes
with a discussion in Section 4.

2
Theory
Section 2.1 discusses Bayesian GP regression and motivates the variational
method. Section 2.2 explains the concept of the standardised representation of
a GP model that is used by the variational method described in Section 2.3.
Section 2.4 discusses setting the prior over the kernel hyperparameters together
with a computationally analytical way to reduce the number of parameters to be
optimised during variational inference. Finally, Section 2.5 discusses prediction
in novel test inputs. 2.1

Bayesian GP regression and motivation for the variational method
Suppose we have data {yi , xi }ni=1 , where each xi ? RD and each yi is
a real-valued scalar output. We denote by y the vector of all output data and
by X all input data. In GP regression, we assume that each observed output is
generated according to yi = f (xi ) + i , i ? N (0, ? 2 ), where the full length
latent function f (x) is assigned a zero-mean GP prior with a certain covariance
or kernel function kf (x, x0 ) that depends on hyperparameters ?. Throughout
the paper we will consider the following squared exponential kernel function 1

0 T
kf (x, x0 ) = ?f2 e? 2 (x?x )
WT W(x?x0 )
1
0
2

2

1
2
0
= ?f2 e? 2 ——Wx?Wx —— = ?f2 e? 2 dW (x,x ) ,
(1)
where dW (x, x0 ) = ——Wx ? Wx0 ——. In the above, ?f is a global scale
parameter while the matrix W ? RK?D quantiﬁes a linear transformation that
maps x into a linear subspace with dimension at most K. In the special case
where W is a square and diagonal matrix, the above kernel function reduces to
PD 2 0 2 1 (2) kf (x, x0 ) = ?f2 e? 2 d=1 wd (xd ?xd ) , which consists of the
well-known ARD squared exponential kernel commonly used in GP regression
applications (Rasmussen and Williams, 2006). In other cases where K ¡ D, dW
(x, x0 ) deﬁnes a Mahalanobis distance metric (Weinberger and Saul, 2009;
Xing et al., 2003) that allows for supervised dimensionality reduction to be
applied in a GP regression setting (Vivarelli and Williams, 1998).
In a full
Bayesian formulation, the hyperparameters ? = (?f , W) are assigned a prior
distribution p(?) and the Bayesian model follows the hierarchical structure
depicted in Figure 1(a). According to this structure the random function f
(x) and the hyperparameters ? are a priori coupled since the former quantity
is generated conditional on the latter. This can make approximate, and in
particular variational, inference over the hyperparameters to be troublesome.
To clarify this, observe that the joint density induced by the ﬁnite data is p(y,
f , ?) = N (y—f , ? 2 I)N (f —0, Kf ,f )p(?),

(3)
where the vector f stores the latent function values at inputs X and Kf ,f is the
n ? n kernel matrix obtained by evaluating the kernel function on those inputs.
Clearly, in the term N (f —0, Kf ,f ) the hyperparameters ? appear non-linearly
inside the inverse and determinant of the kernel matrix Kf ,f . While there
exist a recently developed variational inference method applied to Gaussian
process latent variable model (GP-LVM) (Titsias and Lawrence, 2010), that
approximately integrates out inputs that appear inside a kernel matrix, this
method is still not applicable to the case of kernel hyperparameters such as
length-scales. This is because the augmentation with auxiliary variables used
in (Titsias and Lawrence, 2010), that allows to bypass the intractable term N
(f —0, Kf ,f ), leads to an inversion of a matrix Ku,u that still depends on the
kernel hyperparameters. More precisely, the Ku,u matrix is deﬁned on auxiliary
values u comprising points of the function f (x) at some arbitrary and freely
optimisable inputs (Snelson and Ghahramani, 2006a; Titsias, 2009). While this
kernel matrix does not depend on the inputs X any more (which need to be
integrated out in the GP-LVM case), it still depends on ?, making a possible
variational treatment of those parameters 2

intractable. In Section 2.3, we present a novel modiﬁcation of the approach in
(Titsias and Lawrence, 2010) which allows to overcome the above intractability.
Such an approach makes use of the socalled standardised representation of the
GP model that is described next. 2.2

The standardised representation

3

Consider a function s(z), where z ? RK , which is taken to be a random
sample drawn from a GP indexed by elements in the low K-dimensional space
and assumed to have a zero mean function and the following squared exponential
kernel function: 1

0
2
ks (z, z0 ) = e? 2 ——z?z —— ,
(4)
where the kernel length-scales and global scale are equal to unity. The above
GP is referred to as standardised process, whereas a sample path s(z) is referred
to as a standardised function. The interesting property that a standardised
process has is that it does not depend on kernel hyperparameters since it is
deﬁned in a space where all hyperparameters have been neutralised to take the
value one. Having sampled a function s(z) in the low dimensional input space
RK , we can deterministically express a function f (x) in the high dimensional
input space RD according to f (x) = ?f s(Wx),

(5)
K?D
where the scalar ?f and the matrix W ? R are exactly the hyperparameters
deﬁned in the previous section. The above simply says that the value of f (x)
at a certain input x is the value of the standardised function s(z), for z = Wx
? RK , times a global scale ?f that changes the amplitude or power of the new
function. Given (?f , W), the above assumptions induce a GP prior on the
function f (x), which has zero mean and the following kernel function 1

0
2
kf (x, x0 ) = E[?f s(Wx)?f s(Wx0 )] = ?f2 e? 2 dW (x,x ) ,
(6)
which is precisely the kernel function given in eq. (1) and therefore, the
above construction leads to the same GP prior distribution described in Section
2.1. Nevertheless, the representation using the standardised process also implies
a reparametrisation of the GP regression model where a priori the hyperparam-
eters ? and the GP function are independent. More precisely, one can now
represent the GP model according to the following structure: s(z) ? GP(0, ks
(z, z0 )), ? ? p(?) f (x) = ?f s(Wx) yi

?
N (yi —f (xi ), ? 2 ), i = 1, . . . , n
(7)
which is depicted graphically in Figure 1(b). The interesting property of this
representation is that the GP function s(z) and the hyperparameters ? interact
only inside the likelihood function while a priori are independent. Furthermore,
according to this representation one could now consider a modiﬁcation of the
variational method in (Titsias and Lawrence, 2010) so that the auxiliary vari-
ables u are deﬁned to be points of the function s(z) so that the resulting kernel
matrix Ku,u which needs to be inverted does not depend on the hyperparame-

4

ters but only on some freely optimisable inputs. Next we discuss the details of
this variational method. 2.3

.

.

Variational inference using auxiliary variables
We deﬁne a set of m auxiliary variables u ? Rm such that each ui is a value
of the standardised function so that ui = s(zi ) and the input zi ? RK lives in
dimension K. The set of all inputs Z = (z1 , .
, zm ) are referred to as
inducing inputs and consist of freely-optimisable parameters that can improve
the accuracy of the approximation. The inducing variables u follow the Gaussian
density p(u) = N (u—0, Ku,u ), (8) where [Ku,u ]ij = ks (zi , zj ) and ks is the
standardised kernel function given by eq. (4). Notice that the density p(u) does
not depend on the kernel hyperparameters and particularly on the matrix W.
This is a rather critical point, that essentially allows the variational method to
be applicable, and comprise the novelty of our method compared to the initial
framework in (Titsias and Lawrence, 2010). The vector f of noise-free latent
function values, such that [f ]i = ?f s(Wxi ), covary with the vector u based on
the cross-covariance function 1

2
kf,u (x, z) = E[?f s(Wx)s(z)] = ?f E[s(Wx)s(z)] = ?f e? 2 ——Wx?z—— =

?f ks (Wx, z). 3

(9)
4.5
?
s(x)
4
?
5 3.5 10
f (x)
Input dimension
f (x)
Relevance
3
2.5
2
15
20
1.5
25
1
0.5
y
30
y
0
1
2
3

5

4
5
6
7
8
9 10
2
Latent dimension (sorted)
(a)
(b)
4
6
8
10
Latent dimension (sorted)
(c)
Figure 1: The panel in (a) shows the usual hierarchical structure of a GP
model where the middle node corresponds to the full length function f (x) (al-
though only a ﬁnite vector f is associated with the data). The panel in (b)
shows an equivalent representation of the GP model expressed through the
standardised random function s(z), that does not depend on hyperparameters,
and interacts with the hyperparameters at the data generation process. The
rectangular node for f (x) corresponds to a deterministic operation representing
f (x) = ?f s(Wx). The panel in (c) shows how the latent dimensionality of the
Puma dataset is inferred to be 4, roughly corresponding to input dimensions 4,
5, 15 and 16 (see Section 3.3).

Based on this function, we can compute the cross-covariance matrix Kf ,u
and subsequently express the conditional Gaussian density (often referred to as
conditional GP prior): T ?1 p(f —u, W) = N (f —Kf ,u K?1 u,u u, Kf ,f ? Kf
,u Ku,u Kf ,u ),

so that p(f —u, W)p(u) allows to obtain the initial conditional GP R prior
p(f —W), used in eq. (3), after a marginalisation over the inducing variables,
i.e. p(f —W) = p(f —u, W)p(u)du. We would like now to apply variational
inference in the augmented joint model1 p(y, f , u, W) = N (y—f , ? 2 I)p(f
—u, W)p(u)p(W), in order to approximate the intractable posterior distribution
p(f , W, u—y). We introduce the variational distribution q(f , W, u) = p(f
—u, W)q(W)q(u), (10) where p(f —u, W) is the conditional GP prior that
appears in the joint model, q(u) is a free-form variational distribution that after
optimisation is found to be Gaussian (see Section B.1 in the supplementary
material), while q(W) is restricted to be the following factorised Gaussian: q(W)
=

K Y D Y
2 N (wkd —?dk , ?kd ),
(11)
k=1 d=1

6

The variational lower bound that minimises the Kullback Leibler (KL) di-
vergence between the variational and the exact posterior distribution can be
written in the form F = F1 ? KL(q(W)——p(W)),

(12)
where the analytical form of F1 is given in Section B.1 of the supplementary
material, whereas the KL divergence term KL(q(W)——p(W)) that depends on
the prior distribution over W is described in the next section. The variational
lower bound is maximised using gradient-based methods over the variational
pa2 K,D rameters {?kd , ?kd }k=1,d=1 , the inducing inputs Z (which are
also variational parameters) and the hyperparameters (?f , ? 2 ). 1 The scale
parameter ?f and the noise variance ? 2 are not assigned prior distributions,
but instead they are treated by Type II ML. Notice that the treatment of (?f , ?
2 ) with a Bayesian manner is easier and approximate inference could be done
with the standard conjugate variational Bayesian framework (Bishop, 2006).

4
2.4
Prior over p(W) and analytical reduction of the number of optimisable pa-

rameters

To set the prior distribution for the parameters W, we follow the automatic
relevance determination (ARD) idea introduced in (MacKay, 1994; Neal, 1998)
and subsequently considered in several models such as sparse linear models
(Tipping, 2001) and variational Bayesian PCA (Bishop, 1999). Speciﬁcally, the
prior distribution takes the form p(W) =

K Y D Y
N (wkd —0, ‘2k ),
(13)
k=1 d=1
where the elements of each row of W follow a zero-mean Gaussian distri-
bution with a common variance. Learning the set of variances {‘2k }K k=1
can allow to automatically select the dimensionality associated with the Maha-
lanobis distance metric dW (x, x0 ). This could be carried out by either applying
a Type II ML estimation procedure or a variational Bayesian approach, where
the latter assigns a conjugate Gamma prior on the variances and optimises a
variational distribution q({‘2k }K k=1 ) over them. The optimisable quantities
in both these procedures can be removed analytically and optimally from the
variational lower bound as described next. Consider the case where we apply
Type II ML for the variances {‘2k }K k=1 . These parameters appear only
in the KL(q(W)——p(W)) term (denoted by KL in the following) of the lower
bound in eq. (12) which can be written in the form: ”P # K D D 2 2 2 X ? +
? 1X ? dk d=1 dk KL = ?D? log dk . 2 ‘2k ‘2k k=1

d=1
By ﬁrst minimizing this term with respect to these former hyperparameters
we ﬁnd that PD ? 2 + ?2dk , k = 1, .
, K, ‘2k = d=1 dk D and then by
substituting back these optimal values into the KL divergence we obtain ”D !
# K D X 1X X 2 2 KL = log ?dk ? D log ?dk + ?2dk + D log D , 2 k=1

.

.

d=1

7

(14)
(15)
d=1
which now depends only on variational parameters. When we treat {‘2k }K

k=1 in a Bayesian manner,

? ?2 ? ???1 ? we assign inverse Gamma prior to each variance ‘2k , p(‘2k
) = ?(?) ‘2k e ‘k . Then, by following a similar procedure as the one above we
can remove optimally the variational factor q({‘2k }K k=1 ) (see Section B.2 in
the supplementary material) to obtain ! X

K D K D X 1 XX D 2 2 2 +? log 2? + ?kd + ?kd + log(?kd ) + const, (16)

KL = ? 2 2 k=1

d=1
k=1 d=1
which, as expected, has the nice property that when ? = ? = 0, so that the
prior over variances becomes improper, it reduces to the quantity in (15). Fi-
nally, it is important to notice that diﬀerent and particularly non-Gaussian pri-
ors for the parameters W can be also accommodated by our variational method.
More precisely, any alternative prior for W changes only the form of the negative
KL divergence term in the lower bound in eq. (12). This term remains analyti-
cally tractable even for priors such as the Laplace or certain types of spike and
slab priors. In the experiments we have used the ARD prior described above
while the investigation of alternative priors is intended to be studied as a future
work. 2.5 Predictions Assume we have a test input x? and we would like to
predict the corresponding output y? . The exact predictive density p(y? —y)
is intractable and therefore we approximate it with the density obtained by av-
eraging over the variational posterior distribution: Z q(y? —y) = N (y? —f? ,
? 2 )p(f? —f , u, W)p(f —u, W)q(u)q(W)df? df dudW, (17) 5

where p(f —u, W)q(u)q(W) is the variational distribution and p(f? —f , u,
W) is the conditional GP prior over the test value f? given the training function
R values f and the inducing variables u. By performing ﬁrst the integration over
f , we obtain p(f? —f , u, W)p(f —u, W)df = p(f? —u, W) which yields as a
consequence of the consistency property of the Gaussian process prior. Given
that p(f? —u, W) and q(u) (see Section B.1 in the supplementary material) are
Gaussian densities with respect to f? and u, the above can be further simpliﬁed
to Z q(y? —y) = N (y? —?? (W), ??2 (W) + ? 2 )q(W)dW, where the
mean ?? (W) and variance ??2 (W) obtain closed-form expressions and consist
of nonlinear functions of W making the above integral intractable. However,
by applying Monte Carlo integration based on drawing independent samples
from the Gaussian distribution q(W) we can eﬃciently approximate the above
according to q(y? —y) =

T 1X N (y? —?? (W(t) ), ??2 (W(t) ) + ? 2 ), T t=1
(18)
which is the quantity used in our experiments. Furthermore, although the
predictive density is not Gaussian, its mean and variance can be computed
analytically as explained in Section B.1 of the supplementary material.

3

8

Experiments
In this section we will use standard data sets to assess the performance of
the proposed VDMGP in terms of normalised mean square error (NMSE) and
negative log-probability density (NLPD). We will use as benchmarks a full GP
with automatic relevance determination (ARD) and the stateof-the-art SPGP-
DR model, which is described below. Also, see Section A of the supplementary
material for an example of dimensionality reduction on a simple toy example.
3.1

Review of SPGP-DR
The sparse pseudo-input GP (SPGP) from Snelson and Ghahramani (2006a)
is a well-known sparse GP model, that allows the computational cost of GP
regression to scale linearly with the number of samples in a the dataset. This
model is sometimes referred to as FITC (fully independent training conditional)
and uses an active set of m pseudo-inputs that control the speed vs. performance
tradeoﬀ of the method. SPGP is often used when dealing with datasets con-
taining more than a few thousand samples, since in those cases the cost of a
full GP becomes impractical. In Snelson and Ghahramani (2006b), a version of
SPGP with dimensionality reduction (SPGP-DR) is presented. SPGP-DR ap-
plies the SPGP model to a linear projection of the inputs. The K ? D projection
matrix W is learned so as to maximise the evidence of the model. This can be
seen simply as a specialisation of SPGP in which the covariance function is a
squared exponential with a Mahalanobis distance deﬁned by W¿ W. The idea
had already been applied to the standard GP in (Vivarelli and Williams, 1998).
Despite the apparent similarities between SPGP-DR and VDMGP, there are
important diﬀerences worth clarifying. First, SPGP?s pseudo-inputs are model
parameters and, as such, ﬁtting a large number of them can result in overﬁtting,
whereas the inducing inputs used in VDMGP are variational parameters whose
optimisation can only result in a better ﬁt of the posterior densities. Second,
SPGP-DR does not place a prior on the linear projection matrix W; it is in-
stead ﬁtted using Maximum Likelihood, just as the pseudo-inputs. In contrast,
VDMGP does place a prior on W and variationally integrates it out. These dif-
ferences yield an important consequence: VDMGP can infer automatically the
latent dimensionality K of data, but SPGP-DR is unable to, since increasing K
is never going to decrease its likelihood. Thus, VDMGP follows Occam?s razor
on the number of latent dimensions K. 3.2

Temp and SO2 datasets
We will assess VDMGP on real-world datasets. For this purpose we will use
the two data sets from the WCCI-2006 Predictive Uncertainty in Environmental
Modeling Competition run by Gavin 6

1.5
Full GP VDMGP SPGP?DR
0.55 0.5
Full GP VDMGP SPGP?DR
1.4
Full GP VDMGP SPGP?DR
1.4

9

1.2
0.45
1.3 1
0.4 1.2
0.35
0.8 0.3
1.1 0.6
0.25 1
0.2
0.4 0.15 0.9 0.2
0.1 0.05
0.8 100
200
500
1000
2000
5000 7117
100
200
500
1000
2000
5000
15304
100
200
500
1000
2000
5000 7168
(a) Temp, avg. NMSE ? 1 (b) SO2 , avg. NMSE ? 1 (c) Puma, avg. NMSE

? 1 std. dev. of avg. std. dev. of avg. std. dev. of avg. 2

6
Full GP VDMGP SPGP?DR
1.8
Full GP VDMGP SPGP?DR
5.8
1.6
Full GP VDMGP SPGP?DR
1.8 1.6
5.6 1.4
1.4 5.4
1.2
1.2 1
5.2 1
0.8

10

5 0.8
0.6 0.6
4.8
0.4
4.6
0.2
4.4
0.4 0.2 0
0
?0.2 100
200
500
1000
2000
5000 7117
100
200
500
1000
2000
5000
15304
100
200
500
(d) Temp, avg. NLPD ? one (e) SO2 , avg. NLPD ? one (f) Puma, avg. std.

dev. of avg. std. dev. of avg. std. dev. of avg.

1000
2000
5000 7168
NLPD ? one
Figure 2: Average NMSE and NLPD for several real datasets, showing the

eﬀect of diﬀerent training set sizes.

Cawley2 , called Temp and SO2 . In dataset Temp, maximum daily temper-
ature measurements have to be predicted from 106 input variables representing
large-scale circulation information. For the SO2 dataset, the task is to predict
the concentration of SO2 in an urban environment twenty-four hours in advance,
using information on current SO2 levels and meteorological conditions.3 These
are the same datasets on which SPGP-DR was originally tested (Snelson and
Ghahramani, 2006b), and it is worth mentioning that SPGP-DR?s only entry in
the competition (for the Temp dataset) was the winning one. We ran SPGP-DR
and VDMGP using the same exact initialisation for the projection matrix on
both algorithms and tested the eﬀect of using a reduced number of training data.
For SPGP-DR we tested several possible latent dimensions K = {2, 5, 10, 15, 20,
30}, whereas for VDMGP we ﬁxed K = 20 and let the model infer the number
of dimensions. The number of inducing variables (pseudo-inputs for SPGP-DR)

11

was set to 10 for Temp and 20 for SO2 . Varying sizes for the training set be-
tween 100 and the total amount of available samples were considered. Twenty
independent realisations were performed. Average NMSE as a function of train-
ing set size is shown in Figures 2(a) and 2(b). The multiple dotted blue lines
correspond to SPGP-DR with diﬀerent choices of latent dimensionality K. The
dashed black line represents the full GP, which has been run for training sets up
to size 2000. VDMGP is shown as a solid red line. Similarly, average NLPD is
shown as a function of training set size in Figures 2(d) and 2(e). When feasible,
the full GP performs best, but since it requires the inversion of the full kernel
matrix, it cannot by applied to large-scale problems such as the ones considered
in this subsection. Also, even in reasonably-sized problems, the full GP may
run into trouble if several noise-only input dimensions are present. SPGP-DR
works well for large training set sizes, since there is enough information for it to
avoid overﬁtting and the advantage of using a prior on W is reduced. However,
2 Available at http://theoval.cmp.uea.ac.uk/?gcc/competition/ Temp: 106 di-
mensions 7117/3558 training/testing data, SO2 : 27 dimensions 15304/7652
training/testing data. 3 For SO2 , which contains only positive labels yn , a
logarithmic transformation of the type log(a + yn ) was applied, just as the
authors of (Snelson and Ghahramani, 2006b) did. However, reported NMSE
and NLPD ﬁgures still correspond to the original labels.

7
for smaller training sets, performance is quite bad and the choice of K be-
comes very relevant (which must be selected through cross-validation). Finally,
VDMGP results in scalable performance: It is able to perform dimensionality
reduction and achieve high accuracy both on small and large datasets, while
still being faster than a full GP. 3.3 Puma dataset In this section we consider
the 32-input, moderate noise version of the Puma dataset.4 This is realistic
simulation of the dynamics of a Puma 560 robot arm. Labels represent angular
accelerations of one of the robot arm?s links, which have to be predicted based
on the angular positions, velocities and torques of the robot arm. 7168 samples
are available for training and 1024 for testing. It is well-known from previous
works (Snelson and Ghahramani, 2006a) that only 4 out of the 32 input di-
mensions are relevant for the prediction task, and that identifying them is not
always easy. In particular, SPGP (the standard version, with no dimensional-
ity reduction), fails at this task unless initialised from a ?good guess? about
the relevant dimensions coming from a diﬀerent model, as discussed in (Snel-
son and Ghahramani, 2006a). We thought it would be interesting to assess the
performance of the discussed models on this dataset, again considering diﬀerent
training set sizes, which are generated by randomly sampling from the training
set. Results are shown in Figures 2(c) and 2(f). VDMGPR determines that
there are 4 latent dimensions, as shown in Figure 1(c). The conclusions to be
drawn here are similar to those of the previous subsection: SPGP-DR has trou-
ble with ?small? datasets (where the threshold for a dataset being considered
small enough may vary among diﬀerent datasets) and requires a parameter to be
validated, whereas VDMGPR seems to perform uniformly well. 3.4 A note on
computational complexity The computational complexity of VDMGP is O(N

12

M 2 K +N DK), just as that of SPGP-DR, which is much smaller than the
O(N 3 +N 2 D) required by a full GP. However, since the computation of the
variational bound of VDMGP involves more steps than the computation of the
evidence of SPGPDR, VDMGP is slower than SPGP-DR. In two typical cases
using 500 and 5000 training points full GP runs in 0.24 seconds (for 500 training
points) and in 34 seconds (for 5000 training points), VDMGP runs in 0.35 and
3.1 seconds while SPGP-DR runs in 0.01 and 0.10 seconds.

4
Discussion and further work
A typical approach to regression when the number of input dimensions is
large is to ﬁrst use a linear projection of input data to reduce dimensionality
(e.g., PCA) and then apply some regression technique. Instead of approaching
this method in two steps, a monolithic approach allows the dimensionality re-
duction to be tailored to the speciﬁc regression problem. In this work we have
shown that it is possible to variationally integrate out the linear projection of
the inputs of a GP, which, as a particular case, corresponds to integrating out
its length-scale hyperparameters. By placing a prior on the linear projection, we
avoid overﬁtting problems that may arise in other models, such as SPGP-DR.
Only two parameters (noise variance and scale) are free in this model, whereas
the remaining parameters appearing in the bound are free variational parame-
ters, and optimizing them can only result in improved posterior estimates. This
allows us to automatically infer the number of latent dimensions that are needed
for regression in a given problem, which is also not possible using SPGP-DR.
Finally, the size of the data sets that the proposed model can handle is much
wider than that of SPGP-DR, which performs badly on small-size data. One
interesting topic for future work is to investigate non-Gaussian sparse priors
for the parameters W. Furthermore, given that W represents length-scales it
could be replaced by a random function W(x), such a GP random function,
which would render the length-scales input-dependent, making such a formu-
lation useful in situations with varying smoothness across input space. Such
a smoothness-varying GP is also an interesting subject of further work. Ac-
knowledgments MKT greatly acknowledges support from ?Research Funding at
AUEB for Excellence and Extroversion, Action 1: 2012-2014?. MLG acknowl-
edges support from Spanish CICYT TIN2011-24533. 4 Available from Delve,
see http://www.cs.toronto.edu/?delve/data/pumadyn/desc. html.

8

2 References

Bishop, C. M. (1999). Variational principal components.
In In Proceedings
Ninth International Conference on Artiﬁcial Neural Networks, ICANN?99, pages
509?514. Bishop, C. M. (2006). Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning (In-
formation Science and Statistics). Springer, 1st ed. 2006 edition. MacKay, D.
J. (1994). Bayesian non-linear modelling for the energy prediction competition.
SHRAE Transactions, 4:448?472. Murray, I. and Adams, R. P. (2010). Slice

13

sampling covariance hyperparameters of latent Gaussian models. In Laﬀerty,
J., Williams, C. K. I., Zemel, R., Shawe-Taylor, J., and Culotta, A., editors,
Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 23, pages 1723?1731. Neal,
R. M. (1998). Assessing relevance determination methods using delve. Neural
Networksand Machine Learning, pages 97?129. Rasmussen, C. and Williams,
C. (2006). Gaussian Processes for Machine Learning. Adaptive Computation
and Machine Learning. MIT Press. Snelson, E. and Ghahramani, Z. (2006a).
Sparse Gaussian processes using pseudo-inputs. In Advances in Neural Infor-
mation Processing Systems 18, pages 1259?1266. MIT Press. Snelson, E. and
Ghahramani, Z. (2006b). Variable noise and dimensionality reduction for sparse
Gaussian processes. In Uncertainty in Artiﬁcial Intelligence. Tipping, M. E.
(2001). Sparse bayesian learning and the relevance vector machine. Journal
of Machine Learning Research, 1:211?244. Titsias, M. K. (2009). Variational
learning of inducing variables in sparse Gaussian processes.
In Proc. of the
12th International Workshop on AI Stats. Titsias, M. K. and Lawrence, N. D.
(2010). Bayesian Gaussian process latent variable model. Journal of Machine
Learning Research - Proceedings Track, 9:844?851. Vivarelli, F. and Williams,
C. K. I. (1998). Discovering hidden features with Gaussian processes regres-
sion. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 613?619.
Weinberger, K. Q. and Saul, L. K. (2009). Distance metric learning for large
margin nearest neighbor classiﬁcation. J. Mach. Learn. Res., 10:207?244. Xing,
E., Ng, A., Jordan, M., and Russell, S. (2003). Distance metric learning, with
application to clustering with side-information.

9

14

