Optimistic Concurrency Control for Distributed

Unsupervised Learning

Authored by:

Stefanie Jegelka
Michael I. Jordan

Xinghao Pan

Joseph E. Gonzalez
Tamara Broderick

Abstract

Research on distributed machine learning algorithms has focused pri-
marily on one of two extremes—algorithms that obey strict concurrency
constraints or algorithms that obey few or no such constraints. We
consider an intermediate alternative in which algorithms optimistically
assume that conﬂicts are unlikely and if conﬂicts do arise a conﬂict-
resolution protocol is invoked. We view this optimistic concurrency con-
trol” paradigm as particularly appropriate for large-scale machine learning
algorithms, particularly in the unsupervised setting. We demonstrate our
approach in three problem areas: clustering, feature learning and online
facility location. We evaluate our methods via large-scale experiments in
a cluster computing environment. ”

1 Paper Body

The desire to apply machine learning to increasingly larger datasets has pushed
the machine learning community to address the challenges of distributed algo-
rithm design: partitioning and coordinating computation across the processing
resources. In many cases, when computing statistics of iid data or transform-
ing features, the computation factors according to the data and coordination is
only required during aggregation. For these embarrassingly parallel tasks, the
machine learning community has embraced the map-reduce paradigm, which
provides a template for constructing distributed algorithms that are fault toler-
ant, scalable, and easy to study. However, in pursuit of richer models, we often
introduce statistical dependencies that require more sophisticated algorithms
(e.g., collapsed Gibbs sampling or coordinate ascent) which were developed and
studied in the serial setting. Because these algorithms iteratively transform a
global state, parallelization can be challenging and often requires frequent and

1

complex coordination. Recent eﬀorts to distribute these algorithms can be di-
vided into two primary approaches. The mutual exclusion approach, adopted by
[1] and [2], guarantees a serializable execution preserving the theoretical proper-
ties of the serial algorithm but at the expense of parallelism and costly locking
overhead. Alternatively, in the coordination-free approach, proposed by [3] and
[4], processors communicate frequently without coordination minimizing the
cost of contention but leading to stochasticity, data-corruption, and requiring
potentially complex analysis to prove algorithm correctness. In this paper we
explore a third approach, optimistic concurrency control (OCC) [5] which oﬀers
the performance gains of the coordination-free approach while at the same time
ensuring a serializable execution and preserving the theoretical properties of the
serial algorithm. Like the coordinationfree approach, OCC exploits the infre-
quency of data-corrupting operations. However, instead of allowing occasional
data-corruption, OCC detects data-corrupting operations and applies correcting
computation. As a consequence, OCC automatically ensures correctness, and
the analysis is only necessary to guarantee optimal scaling performance. 1

We apply OCC to distributed nonparametric unsupervised learning?including
but not limited to clustering?and implement distributed versions of the DP-
Means [6], BP-Means [7], and online facility location (OFL) algorithms. We
demonstrate how to analyze OCC in the context of the DP-Means algorithm
and evaluate the empirical scalability of the OCC approach on all three of the
proposed algorithms. The primary contributions of this paper are: 1. Con-
currency control approach to distributing unsupervised learning algorithms. 2.
Reinterpretation of online nonparametric clustering in the form of facility lo-
cation with approximation guarantees. 3. Analysis of optimistic concurrency
control for unsupervised learning. 4. Application to feature modeling and clus-
tering.

2
Optimistic Concurrency Control
Many machine learning algorithms iteratively transform some global state
(e.g., model parameters or variable assignment) giving the illusion of serial de-
pendencies between each operation. However, due to sparsity, exchangeability,
and other symmetries, it is often the case that many, but not all, of the state-
transforming operations can be computed concurrently while still preserving
serializability: the equivalence to some serial execution where individual opera-
tions have been reordered. This opportunity for serializable concurrency forms
the foundation of distributed database systems. For example, two customers
may concurrently make purchases exhausting the inventory of unrelated prod-
ucts, but if they try to purchase the same product then we may need to serialize
their purchases to ensure suﬃcient inventory. One solution (mutual exclusion)
associates locks with each product type and forces each purchase of the same
product to be processed serially. This might work for an unpopular, rare prod-
uct but if we are interested in selling a popular product for which we have a
large inventory the serialization overhead could lead to unnecessarily slow re-
sponse times. To address this problem, the database community has adopted
optimistic concurrency control (OCC) [5] in which the system tries to satisfy

2

the customers requests without locking and corrects transactions that could
lead to negative inventory (e.g., by forcing the customer to checkout again).
Optimistic concurrency control exploits situations where most operations can
execute concurrently without conﬂicting or violating serialization invariants. For
example, given suﬃcient inventory the order in which customers are satisﬁed
is immaterial and concurrent operations can be executed serially to yield the
same ﬁnal result. However, in the rare event that inventory is nearly depleted
two concurrent purchases may not be serializable since the inventory can never
be negative. By shifting the cost of concurrency control to rare events we can
admit more costly concurrency control mechanisms (e.g., re-computation) in
exchange for an eﬃcient, simple, coordination-free execution for the majority of
the events. Formally, to apply OCC we must deﬁne a set of transactions (i.e.,
operations or collections of operations), a mechanism to detect when a trans-
action violates serialization invariants (i.e., cannot be executed concurrently),
and a method to correct (e.g., rollback) transactions that violate the serializa-
tion invariants. Optimistic concurrency control is most eﬀective when the cost
of validating concurrent transactions is small and conﬂicts occur infrequently.
Machine learning algorithms are ideal for optimistic concurrency control. The
conditional independence structure and sparsity in our models and data often
leads to sparse parameter updates substantially reducing the chance of conﬂicts.
Similarly, symmetry in our models often provides the ﬂexibility to reorder serial
operations while preserving algorithm invariants. Because the models encode
the dependency structure, we can easily detect when an operation violates serial
invariants and correct by rejecting the change and rerunning the computation.
Alternatively, we can exploit the semantics of the operations to resolve the
conﬂict by accepting a modiﬁed update. As a consequence OCC allows us to
easily construct provably correct and eﬃcient distributed algorithms without
the need to develop new theoretical tools to analyze complex non-deterministic
distributed behavior. 2

2.1
The OCC Pattern for Machine Learning
Optimistic concurrency control can be distilled to a simple pattern (meta-
algorithm) for the design and implementation of distributed machine learning
systems. We begin by evenly partitioning N data points (and the correspond-
ing computation) across the P available processors. Each processor maintains
a replicated view of the global state and serially applies the learning algorithm
as a sequence of operations on its assigned data and the global state.
If an
operation mutates the global state in a way that preserves the serialization in-
variants then the operation is accepted locally and its eﬀect on the global state,
if any, is eventually replicated to other processors. However, if an operation
could potentially conﬂict with operations on other processors then it is sent to
a unique serializing processor where it is rejected or corrected and the result-
ing global state change is eventually replicated to the rest of the processors.
Meanwhile the originating processor either tentatively accepts the state change
(if a rollback operator is deﬁned) or proceeds as though the operation has been
deferred to some point in the future. While it is possible to execute this pattern

3

asynchronously with minimal coordination, for simplicity we adopt the bulk-
synchronous model of [8] and divide the computation into epochs. Within an
epoch t, b data points B(p, t) are evenly assigned to each of the P processors.
Any state changes or serialization operations are transmitted at the end of the
epoch and processed before the next epoch. While potentially slower than an
asynchronous execution, the bulk-synchronous execution is deterministic and
can be easily expressed using existing systems like Hadoop or Spark [9].

3
OCC for Unsupervised Learning
Much of the existing literature on distributed machine learning algorithms
has focused on classiﬁcation and regression problems, where the underlying
model is continuous.
In this paper we apply the OCC pattern to machine
learning problems that have a more discrete, combinatorial ﬂavor?in particular
unsupervised clustering and latent feature learning problems. These problems
exhibit symmetry via their invariance to both data permutation and cluster or
feature permutation. Together with the sparsity of interacting operations in
their existing serial algorithms, these problems oﬀer a unique opportunity to
develop OCC algorithms. The K-means algorithm provides a paradigm exam-
ple; here the inferential goal is to partition the data. Rather than focusing solely
on K-means, however, we have been inspired by recent work in which a general
family of K-means-like algorithms have been obtained by taking Bayesian non-
parametric (BNP) models based on combinatorial stochastic processes such as
the Dirichlet process, the beta process, and hierarchical versions of these pro-
cesses, and subjecting them to smallvariance asymptotics where the posterior
probability under the BNP model is transformed into a cost function that can
be optimized [7]. The algorithms considered to date in this literature have been
developed and analyzed in the serial setting; our goal is to explore distributed
algorithms for optimizing these cost functions that preserve the structure and
analysis of their serial counterparts. 3.1

OCC DP-Means
We ﬁrst consider the DP-means algorithm (Alg. 1) introduced by [6]. Like
the K-means algorithm, DP-Means alternates between updating the cluster as-
signment zi for each point xi and recomputing K the centroids C = {?k }k=1
associated with each clusters. However, DP-Means diﬀers in that the number of
clusters is not ﬁxed a priori. Instead, if the distance from a given data point to
all existing cluster centroids is greater than a parameter ?, then a new cluster
is created. While the second phase is trivially parallel, the process of introduc-
ing clusters in the ﬁrst phase is inherently serial. However, clusters tend to be
introduced infrequently, and thus DP-Means provides an opportunity for OCC.
In Alg. 3 we present an OCC parallelization of the DP-Means algorithm in
which each iteration of the serial DP-Means algorithm is divided into N/(P b)
bulk-synchronous epochs. The data is evenly partitioned {xi }i?B(p,t) across
processor-epochs into blocks of size b = —B(p, t)—. During each epoch t, each
processor p evaluates the cluster membership of its assigned data {xi }i?B(p,t)
using the cluster centers C from the previous epoch and optimistically proposes
a new set of cluster ? At the end of each epoch the proposed cluster centers, C,

4

? are serially validated using Alg. 2. centers C. 3

Algorithm 1: Serial DP-means
Algorithm 3: Parallel DP-means
Input: data threshold ? C?? while not converged do for i = 1 to N do ?? ?
argmin??C kxi ? ?k if kxi ? ?? k ¿ ? then zi ? x i C ? C ? xi // New cluster
Input: data {xi }N i=1 , threshold ? Input: Epoch size b and P processors
Input: Partitioning B(p, t) of data {xi }i?B(p,t) to processor-epochs where b =
—B(p, t)— C?? while not converged do for epoch t = 1 to N/(P b) do C? ? ?
// New candidate centers for p ? {1, . . . , P } do in parallel // Process local
data for i ? B(p, t) do ?? ? argmin??C kxi ? ?k // Optimistic Transaction if
kxi ? ?? k ¿ ? then zi ? Ref(xi ) C? ? C? ? xi else zi ? ?? // Always Safe

{xi }N i=1 ,
else zi ? ??
// Use nearest
for ? ? C do // Recompute Centers ? ? Mean({xi — zi = ?})
Output: Accepted cluster centers C
Algorithm 2: DPValidate Input: Set of proposed cluster centers C? C?? for
x ? C? do ?? ? argmin??C kx ? ?k if kxi ? ?? k ¡ ? then // Reject Ref(x) ? ??
// Rollback Assgs else C ? C ? x Output: Accepted cluster centers C

// Serially validate clusters ? C ? C ? DPValidate(C)
for ? ? C do // Recompute Centers ? ? Mean({xi — zi = ?})
// Accept
Output: Accepted cluster centers C
Figure 1: The Serial DP-Means algorithm and distributed implementation
using the OCC pattern. The validation process accepts cluster centers that are
not covered by (i.e., not within ? of) already accepted cluster centers. When a
cluster center is rejected we update its reference to point to the already accepted
center, thereby correcting the original point assignment. 3.2

OCC Facility Location
The DP-Means objective turns out to be equivalent to the classic Facility
Location (FL) objective: P 2 J(C) = x?X min??C kx ? ?k + ?2 —C—,which
selects the set of cluster centers (facilities) ? ? C 2 that minimizes the shortest
distance kx ? ?k to each point (customer) x as well as the penalized 2 cost
of the clusters ? —C—. However, while DP-Means allows the clusters to be
arbitrary points (e.g., C ? RD ), FL constrains the clusters to be points C ?
F in a set of candidate locations F. Hence, we obtain a link between combi-
natorial Bayesian models and FL allowing us to apply algorithms with known
approximation bounds to Bayesian inspired nonparametric models. As we will
see in Section 4, our OCC algorithm provides constant-factor approximations
for both FL and DP-means. Facility location has been studied intensely. We
build on the online facility location (OFL) algorithm described by Meyerson
[10]. The OFL algorithm processes each data point x serially in a single pass 2
by either adding x to the set of clusters with probability min(1, min??C kx ? ?k
/?2 ) or assigning x to the nearest existing cluster. Using OCC we are able to
construct a distributed OFL algorithm (Alg. 4) which is nearly identical to the
OCC DP-Means algorithm (Alg. 3) but which provides strong approximation

5

bounds. The OCC OFL algorithm diﬀers only in that clusters are introduced
and validated stochastically?the validation process ensures that the new clusters
are accepted with probability equal to the serial algorithm. 3.3

OCC BP-Means
BP-means is an algorithm for learning collections of latent binary features,
providing a way to deﬁne groupings of data points that need not be mutually
exclusive or exhaustive like clusters. 4

Algorithm 4: Parallel OFL
Algorithm 5: OFLValidate
Input: Same as DP-Means for epoch t = 1 to N/(P b) do C? ? ? for p ? {1,

. . . , P } do in parallel for i ? B(p, t) do d ? min??C kxi ? ?k

with probability min d2 , ?2 /?2 C? ? C? ? (xi , d)
Input: Set of proposed cluster centers C? C?? for (x, d) ? C? do d? ?

min??C kx ? ?k

with probability min d?2 , d2 /d2 C ?C?x // Accept Output: Accepted

cluster centers C

? C ? C ? OFLValidate(C) Output: Accepted cluster centers C
Figure 2: The OCC algorithm for Online Facility Location (OFL). As with
serial DP-means, there are two phases in serial BP-means (Alg. 6). In the ﬁrst
phase, each data point xi is labeled with binary assignments from a collection
of features P (zik = 0 if xi doesn?t belong to feature k; otherwise zik = 1)
to construct a representation xi ? k zik fk . In the ? are updated based on
the assignments. second phase, parameter values (the feature means fk ? C)
The ﬁrst step also includes the possibility of introducing an additional feature.
While the second phase is trivially parallel, the inherently serial nature of the
ﬁrst phase combined with the infrequent introduction of new features points to
the usefulness of OCC in this domain. The OCC parallelization for BP-means
follows the same basic structure as OCC DP-means. Each transaction operates
P on a data point xi in two phases. In the ﬁrst, analysis Pphase, the optimal
representation k zik fk is found. If xi is not well represented (i.e., kxi ? k zik
fk k ¿ ?), the diﬀerence is proposed as a new feature in the second validation
phase. At the end of epoch t, ? For the proposed features {ﬁnew } are serially
validated to obtain a set of accepted features C. new new each proposed feature
f , the validation process ﬁrst ﬁnds the optimal representation f ? i i P new is
not well represented, the diﬀerence ﬁnew ? fk ?C? zik fk using newly accepted
features. If ﬁ P ? fk ?C? zik fk is added to C and accepted as a new feature.
Finally, to update the feature means, let F be the K-row matrix of feature
means. The feature means update FP? (Z T Z)?1 Z T X can be evaluated as a
single transaction by computing the T T sums Z TP Z = i zi zi (where zi is a K
? 1 column vector so zi zi is a K ? K matrix) and Z T X = i zi xTi in parallel.
We present the pseudocode for the OCC parallelization of BP-means in

Appendix A.

4
Analysis of Correctness and Scalability
In contrast to the coordination-free pattern in which scalability is trivial and
correctness often requires strong assumptions or holds only in expectation, the

6

OCC pattern leads to simple proofs of correctness and challenging scalability
analysis. However, in many cases it is preferable to have algorithms that are
correct and probably fast rather than fast and possibly correct. We ﬁrst estab-
lish serializability: Theorem 4.1 (Serializability). The distributed DP-means,
OFL, and BP-means algorithms are serially equivalent to DP-means, OFL and
BP-means, respectively. The proof (Appendix B) of Theorem 4.1 is relatively
straightforward and is obtained by constructing a permutation function that de-
scribes an equivalent serial execution for each distributed execution. The proof
can easily be extended to many other machine learning algorithms. Serializ-
ability allows us to easily extend important theoretical properties of the serial
algorithm to the distributed setting. For example, by invoking serializability,
we can establish the following result for the OCC version of the online facility
location (OFL) algorithm: 5

Theorem 4.2. If the data is randomly ordered, then the OCC OFL algorithm
provides a constantfactor approximation for the DP-means objective. If the data
is adversarially ordered, then OCC OFL provides a log-factor approximation to
the DP-means objective. The proof (Appendix B) of Theorem 4.2 is ﬁrst derived
in the serial setting then extended to the distributed setting through serializabil-
ity. In contrast to divide-and-conquer schemes, whose approximation bounds
commonly depend multiplicatively on the number of levels [11], Theorem 4.2
is unaﬀected by distributed processing and has no communication or coarsen-
ing tradeoﬀs. Furthermore, to retain the same factors as a batch algorithm on
the full data, divide-and-conquer schemes need a large number of preliminary
centers at lower levels [11, 12]. In that case, the communication cost can be
high, since all proposed clusters are sent at the same time, as opposed to the
OCC approach. We address the communication overhead (the number of rejec-
tions) for our scheme next. Scalability The scalability of the OCC algorithms
depends on the number of transactions that are rejected during validation (i.e.,
the rejection rate). While a general scalability analysis can be challenging, it is
often possible to gain some insight into the asymptotic dependencies by making
simplifying assumptions. In contrast to the coordination-free approach, we can
still safely apply OCC algorithms in the absence of a scalability analysis or when
simplifying assumptions do not hold. To illustrate the techniques employed in
OCC scalability analysis we study the DP-Means algorithm, whose scalability
limiting factor is determined by the number of points that must be serially val-
idated. We show that the communication cost only depends on the number of
clusters and processing resources and does not directly depend on the number of
data points. The proof is in Appendix C. Theorem 4.3 (DP-Means Scalability).
Assume N data points are generated iid to form a random number (KN ) of
well-spaced clusters of diameter ?: ? is an upper bound on the distances within
clusters and a lower bound on the distance between clusters. Then the expected
number of serially validated points is bounded above by P b + E [KN ] for P
processors and b points per epoch. Under the separation assumptions of the
theorem, the number of clusters present in N data points, KN , is exactly equal
to the number of clusters found by DP-Means in N data points; call this latter
quantity kN . The experimental results in Figure 3 suggest that the bound of

7

P b + kN may hold more generally beyond the assumptions above. Since the
master must process at least kN points, the overhead caused by rejections is P
b and independent of N .

5
Evaluation
For our experiments, we generated synthetic data for clustering (DP-means
and OFL) and feature modeling (BP-means). The cluster and feature propor-
tions were generated nonparametrically as described below. All data points
were generated in R16 space. We ﬁxed threshold parameter ? = 1. Clustering:
The cluster proportions and indicators were generated simultaneously using the
stickbreaking procedure for Dirichlet processes??sticks? are ?broken? on-the-
ﬂy to generate new clusters as necessary. For our experiments, we used a ﬁxed
concentration parameter ? = 1. Cluster means were sampled ?k ? N (0, I16
), and data points were generated at xi ? N (?zi , 41 I16 ). Feature modeling:
We use the stick-breaking procedure of [13] to generate feature weights. Un-
like with Dirichlet processes, we are unable to perform stick-breaking on-the-ﬂy
with Beta processes. Instead, we generate enough features so that with high
probability (¿ 0.9999) the remaining non-generated features will have negligible
weights (¡ 0.0001). The concentration parameter was P also ﬁxed at ? = 1. We
generated feature means fk ? N (0, I16 ) and data points xi ? N ( k zik fk , 14
I16 ).
5.1
Simulated experiments
To test the eﬃciency of our algorithms, we simulated the ﬁrst iteration (one
complete pass over all the data, where most clusters / features are created
and thus greatest coordination is needed) of each algorithm in MATLAB. The
number of data points, N , was varied from 256 to 2560 in intervals of 256. We
also varied P b, the number of data points processed in one epoch, from 16 to
256 in powers of 2. For each value of N and P b, we empirically measured kN ,
the number of accepted clusters / 6

(a) OCC DP-means
(b) OCC OFL
(c) OCC BP-means
Figure 3: Simulated distributed DP-means, OFL and BP-means: expected
number of data points proposed but not accepted as new clusters / features is
independent of size of data set.

features, and MN , the number of proposed clusters / features. This was
the

repeated 400 times to obtain ? N ? kN ] of the number of rejections.
empirical average E[M

? N ? kN ] is bounded above by P b (Fig. 3a), and that this For OCC DP-
means, we observe E[M bound is independent of the data set size, even when the
assumptions of Thm 4.3 are violated. (We also veriﬁed that similar empirical
results are obtained when the assumptions are not violated; see Appendix C.)
The same behavior is observed for the other two OCC algorithms (Fig. 3b and
Fig. 3c). 5.2

Distributed implementation and experiments

8

We also implemented1 the distributed algorithms in Spark [9], an open-
source cluster computing system. The DP-means and BP-means algorithms
were initialized by pre-processing a small number of data points (1/16 of the
ﬁrst P b points)?this reduces the number of data points sent to the master on
the ﬁrst epoch, while still preserving serializability of the algorithms. Our Spark
implementations were tested on Amazon EC2 by processing a ﬁxed data set on
1, 2, 4, 8 m2.4xlarge instances. Ideally, to process the same amount of data, an
algorithm and implementation with perfect scaling would take half the runtime
on 8 machines as it would on 4, and so on. The plots in Figure 4 shows this
comparison by dividing all runtimes by the runtime on one machine. DP-means:
We ran the distributed DP-means algorithm on 227 ? 134M data points, using
? = 2. The block size b was chosen to keep P b = 223 ? 8M constant. The
algorithm was run for 5 iterations (complete pass over all data in 16 epochs).
We were able to get perfect scaling (Figure 4a) in all but the ﬁrst iteration,
when the master has to perform the most synchronization of proposed centers.
OFL: The distributed OFL algorithm was run on 220 ? 1M data points, using ?
= 2. Unlike DP-means and BP-means, OFL is a single-pass algorithm and we
did not perform any initialization clustering. The block size b was chosen such
that P b = 216 ? 66K data points are processed each epoch, which gives us 16
epochs. Figure 4b shows that we get no scaling in the ﬁrst epoch, where all P b
data points are sent to the master. Scaling improves in the later epochs, as the
master?s workload decreases with fewer proposals but the workers? workload
increases with more centers. BP-means: Distributed BP-means was run on 223
? 8M data points, with ? = 1; block size was chosen such that P b = 219 ?
0.5M is constant. Five iterations were run, with 16 epochs per iteration. As
with DP-means, we were able to achieve nearly perfect scaling; see Figure 4c.

6
Related work
Others have proposed alternatives to mutual exclusion and coordination-free
[14] proposed transform-
parallelism for machine learning algorithm design.
ing the underlying model to expose additional parallelism while preserving the
marginal posterior. However, such constructions can be challenging or infeasible
and many hinder mixing or convergence. Likewise, [15] proposed a reparam-
eterization of the underlying model to expose additional parallelism through
conditional independence. Additional 1

Code will be made available at our project page https://amplab.cs.berkeley.edu/projects/ccml/.
7
(a) OCC DP-means
(b) OCC OFL
(c) OCC BP-means
Figure 4: Normalized runtime for distributed algorithms. Runtime of each

iteration / epoch is divided by that

using 1 machine (P = 8). Ideally, the runtime with 2, 4, 8 machines (P =
16, 32, 64) should be respectively 1/2, 1/4, 1/8 of the runtime using 1 machine.
OCC DP-means and BP-means obtain nearly perfect scaling for all iterations.
OCC OFL rejects a lot initially, but quickly gets better in later epochs.

9

work similar in spirit to ours using OCC-like techniques includes [16] who
proposed an approximate parallel sampling algorithm for the IBP which is made
exact by introducing an additional MetropolisHastings step, and [17] who pro-
posed a look-ahead strategy in which future samples are computed optimistically
based on the likely outcomes of current samples. There has been substantial
work on scalable clustering algorithms [18, 19, 20]. Several authors [11, 21, 22,
12] have proposed streaming approximation algorithms that rely on hierarchical
divideand-conquer schemes. The approximation factors in these algorithms are
multiplicative in the hierarchy and demand a careful tradeoﬀ between commu-
nication and approximation quality which is obviated in the OCC framework.
Several methods [12, 25, 21] ﬁrst collect and then re-cluster a set of centers, and
therefore need to communicate all intermediate centers. Our approach avoids
these stages, since a center causes no rejections in the epochs after it is estab-
lished: the rejection rate does not grow with K. Finally, the OCC framework
can easily integrate and exploit many of the ideas in the cited works.

7
Discussion
In this paper we have shown how optimistic concurrency control can be use-
fully employed in the design of distributed machine learning algorithms. As
opposed to previous approaches, this preserves correctness, in most cases at a
small cost. We established the equivalence of our distributed OCC DPmeans,
OFL and BP-means algorithms to their serial counterparts, thus preserving
their theoretical properties.
In particular, the strong approximation guaran-
tees of serial OFL translate immediately to the distributed algorithm. Our
theoretical analysis ensures OCC DP-means achieves high parallelism without
sacriﬁcing correctness. We implemented and evaluated all three OCC algo-
rithms on a distributed computing platform and demonstrate strong scalability
in practice. We believe that there is much more to do in this vein.
Indeed,
machine learning algorithms have many properties that distinguish them from
classical database operations and may allow going beyond the classic formula-
tion of OCC. In particular we may be able to partially or probabilistically accept
non-serializable operations in a way that preserves underlying algorithm invari-
ants. Laws of large numbers and concentration theorems may provide tools for
designing such operations. Moreover, the conﬂict detection mechanism can be
treated as a control knob, allowing us to softly switch between stable, theo-
retically sound algorithms and potentially faster coordination-free algorithms.
Acknowledgments This research is supported in part by NSF CISE Expeditions
award CCF-1139158 and DARPA XData Award FA8750-12-2-0331, and gifts
from Amazon Web Services, Google, SAP, Blue Goji, Cisco, Clearstory Data,
Cloudera, Ericsson, Facebook, General Electric, Hortonworks, Intel, Microsoft,
NetApp, Oracle, Samsung, Splunk, VMware and Yahoo!. This material is also
based upon work supported in part by the Oﬃce of Naval Research under con-
tract/grant number N00014-11-1-0688. X. Pan?s work is also supported in part
by a DSO National Laboratories Postgraduate Scholarship. T. Broderick?s work
is supported by a Berkeley Fellowship.

8

10

2 References

[1] J. Gonzalez, Y. Low, A. Gretton, and C. Guestrin. Parallel Gibbs sampling:
From colored ﬁelds to thin junction trees.
In Proceedings of the 14th Inter-
national Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), pages
324?332, 2011. [2] Yucheng Low, Joseph Gonzalez, Aapo Kyrola, Danny Bick-
son, Carlos Guestrin, and J. M. Hellerstein. Distributed GraphLab: A frame-
work for machine learning and data mining in the cloud.
In Proceedings of
the 38th International Conference on Very Large Data Bases (VLDB, Istanbul,
2012.
[3] Benjamin Recht, Christopher Re, Stephen J. Wright, and Feng Niu.
Hogwild: A lock-free approach to parallelizing stochastic gradient descent. In
Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 24, pages 693?701,
Granada, 2011.
[4] Amr Ahmed, Mohamed Aly, Joseph Gonzalez, Shravan
Narayanamurthy, and Alexander J. Smola. Scalable inference in latent vari-
able models. In Proceedings of the 5th ACM International Conference on Web
Search and Data Mining (WSDM), 2012. [5] Hsiang-Tsung Kung and John T
Robinson. On optimistic methods for concurrency control. ACM Transactions
on Database Systems (TODS), 6(2):213?226, 1981. [6] Brian Kulis and Michael
I. Jordan. Revisiting k-means: New algorithms via Bayesian nonparametrics.
In Proceedings of 29th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML),
Edinburgh, 2012.
[7] Tamara Broderick, Brian Kulis, and Michael I. Jordan.
MAD-bayes: MAP-based asymptotic derivations from Bayes. In Proceedings
of the 30th International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2013.
[8]
Leslie G. Valiant. A bridging model for parallel computation. Communications
of the ACM, 33(8):103?111, 1990.
[9] Matei Zaharia, Mosharaf Chowdhury,
Michael J Franklin, Scott Shenker, and Ion Stoica. Spark: Cluster computing
with working sets. In Proceedings of the 2nd USENIX Conference on Hot Top-
ics in Cloud Computing, 2010.
[10] A. Meyerson. Online facility location. In
Proceedings of the 42nd Annual Symposium on Foundations of Computer Sci-
ence (FOCS), Las Vegas, 2001. [11] A. Meyerson, N. Mishra, R. Motwani, and
L. O?Callaghan. Clustering data streams: Theory and practice. IEEE Transac-
tions on Knowledge and Data Engineering, 15(3):515?528, 2003. [12] N. Ailon,
R. Jaiswal, and C. Monteleoni. Streaming k-means approximation. In Advances
in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 22, Vancouver, 2009.
[13]
John Paisley, David Blei, and Michael I Jordan. Stick-breaking Beta processes
and the Poisson process. In Proceedings of the 15th International Conference
on Artiﬁcial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS), 2012. [14] D. Newman, A.
Asuncion, P. Smyth, and M. Welling. Distributed inference for Latent Dirich-
let Allocation. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS)
20, Vancouver, 2007.
[15] D. Lovell, J. Malmaud, R. P. Adams, and V. K.
Mansinghka. ClusterCluster: Parallel Markov chain Monte Carlo for Dirichlet
process mixtures. ArXiv e-prints, April 2013. [16] F. Doshi-Velez, D. Knowles,
S. Mohamed, and Z. Ghahramani. Large scale nonparametric Bayesian infer-
ence: Data parallelisation in the Indian Buﬀet process. In Advances in Neural
Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 22, Vancouver, 2009. [17] Tianbing Xu
and Alexander Ihler. Multicore Gibbs sampling in dense, unstructured graphs.

11

In Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence
and Statistics (AISTATS). 2011.
[18] I. Dhillon and D.S. Modha. A data-
clustering algorithm on distributed memory multiprocessors. In Workshop on
Large-Scale Parallel KDD Systems, 2000. [19] A. Das, M. Datar, A. Garg, and
S. Ragarajam. Google news personalization: Scalable online collaborative ﬁlter-
ing. In Proceedings of the 16th World Wide Web Conference, Banﬀ, 2007. [20]
A. Ene, S. Im, and B. Moseley. Fast clustering using MapReduce. In Proceed-
ings of the 17th ACM SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data
Mining, San Diego, 2011.
[21] M. Shindler, A. Wong, and A. Meyerson. Fast
and accurate k-means for large datasets. In Advances in Neural Information
Processing Systems (NIPS) 24, Granada, 2011.
[22] Moses Charikar, Liadan
O?Callaghan, and Rina Panigrahy. Better streaming algorithms for clustering
problems. In Proceedings of the 35th Annual ACM Symposium on Theory of
Computing (STOC), 2003. [23] Mihai B?adoiu, Sariel Har-Peled, and Piotr In-
dyk. Approximate clustering via core-sets. In Proceedings of the 34th Annual
ACM Symposium on Theory of Computing (STOC), 2002.
[24] D. Feldman,
A. Krause, and M. Faulkner. Scalable training of mixture models via coresets.
In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 24, Granada,
2011. [25] B. Bahmani, B. Moseley, A. Vattani, R. Kumar, and S. Vassilvitskii.
Scalable kmeans++. In Proceedings of the 38th International Conference on
Very Large Data Bases (VLDB), Istanbul, 2012.

9

12

