Modeling Clutter Perception using Parametric

Proto-object Partitioning

Authored by:

Dimitris Samaras

Chen-Ping Yu
Wen-Yu Hua
Greg Zelinsky

Abstract

Visual clutter, the perception of an image as being crowded and dis-
ordered, aﬀects aspects of our lives ranging from object detection to aes-
thetics, yet relatively little eﬀort has been made to model this important
and ubiquitous percept. Our approach models clutter as the number of
proto-objects segmented from an image, with proto-objects deﬁned as
groupings of superpixels that are similar in intensity, color, and gradient
orientation features. We introduce a novel parametric method of merging
superpixels by modeling mixture of Weibull distributions on similarity
distance statistics, then taking the normalized number of proto-objects
following partitioning as our estimate of clutter perception. We validated
this model using a new $text{90}-$image dataset of realistic scenes rank
ordered by human raters for clutter, and showed that our method not only
predicted clutter extremely well (Spearman’s $rho = 0.81$, $p ¡ 0.05$),
but also outperformed all existing clutter perception models and even a
behavioral object segmentation ground truth. We conclude that the num-
ber of proto-objects in an image aﬀects clutter perception more than the
number of objects or features.

1 Paper Body

Visual clutter, deﬁned colloquially as a ?confused collection? or a ?crowded
disorderly state?, is a dimension of image understanding that has implications
for applications ranging from visualization and interface design to marketing
and image aesthetics. In this study we apply methods from computer vision
to quantify and predict human visual clutter perception. The eﬀects of visual
clutter have been studied most extensively in the context of an object detec-
tion task, where models attempt to describe how increasing clutter negatively
impacts the time taken to ﬁnd a target object in an image [19][25][29][18][6].
Visual clutter has even been suggested as a surrogate measure for set size eﬀect,

1

the ﬁnding that search performance often degrades with the number of objects
in a scene [32]. Because human estimates of the number of objects in a scene
are subjective and noisy - one person might consider a group of trees to be an
object (a forest or a grove) while another person might label each tree in the
same scene as an ?object?, or even each trunk or branch of every tree - it may
be possible to capture this seminal search relationship in an objectively deﬁned
measure of visual clutter [21][25]. One of the earliest attempts to model visual
clutter used edge density, i.e. the ratio of the number of edge pixels in an image
to image size [19]. The subsequent feature congestion model ignited interest in
clutter perception by estimating 1

Figure 1: How can we quantify set size or the number of objects in these
scenes, and would this object count capture the perception of scene clutter?
image complexity in terms of the density of intensity, color, and texture fea-
tures in an image [25]. However, recent work has pointed out limitations of the
feature congestion model [13][21], leading to the development of alternative ap-
proaches to quantifying visual clutter [25][5][29][18]. Our approach is to model
visual clutter in terms of proto-objects: regions of locally similar features that
are believed to exist at an early stage of human visual processing [24].
Im-
portantly, proto-objects are not objects, but rather the fragments from which
objects are built. In this sense, our approach ﬁnds a middle ground between fea-
tures and objects. Previous work used blob detectors to segment proto-objects
from saliency maps for the purpose of quantifying shifts of visual attention [31],
but this method is limited in that it results in elliptical proto-objects that do not
capture the complexity or variability of shapes in natural scenes. Alternatively,
it may be possible to apply standard image segmentation methods to the task
of proto-object discovery. While we believe this approach has merit (see Section
4.3), it is also limited in that the goal of these methods is to approximate a
human segmented ground truth, where each segment generally corresponds to a
complete and recognizable object. For example, in the Berkeley Segmentation
Dataset [20] people were asked to segment each image into 2 to 20 equally im-
portant and distinguishable things, which results in many segments being actual
objects. However, one rarely knows the number of objects in a scene, and am-
biguity in what constitutes an object has even led some researchers to suggest
that obtaining an object ground truth for natural scenes is an ill-posed problem
[21]. Our clutter perception model uses a parametric method of proto-object
partitioning that clusters superpixels, and requires no object ground truth. In
summary, we create a graph having superpixels as nodes, then compute feature
similarity distances between adjacent nodes. We use Earth Mover?s Distance
(EMD) [26] to perform pair-wise comparisons of feature histograms over all ad-
jacent nodes, and model the EMD statistics with mixture of Weibulls to solve
an edge-labeling problem, which identiﬁes and removes between-cluster edges
to form isolated superpixel groups that are subsequently merged. We refer to
these merged image fragments as proto-objects. Our approach is based on the
novel ﬁnding that EMD statistics can be modeled by a Weibull distribution
(Section 2.2), and this allows us to model such similarity distance statistics
with a mixture of Weibull distribution, resulting in extremely eﬃcient and ro-

2

bust superpixel clustering in the context of our model. Our method runs in
linear time with respect to the number of adjacent superpixel pairs, and has an
endto-end run time of 15-20 seconds for a typical 0.5 megapixel image, a size
that many supervised segmentation methods cannot yet accommodate using
desktop hardware [2][8][14][23][34].

2 2.1
Proto-object partitioning Superpixel pre-processing and feature similarity
To merge similar fragments into a coherent proto-object region, the term
fragment and the measure of coherence (similarity) must be deﬁned. We deﬁne
an image fragment as a group of pixels that share similar low-level image fea-
tures:
intensity, color, and orientation. This conforms with processing in the
human visual system, and also makes a fragment analogous to an image su-
perpixel, which is a perceptually meaningful atomic region that contains pixels
similar in color and texture [30]. However, superpixel segmentation methods
in general produce a ﬁxed number of superpixels from an image, and groups of
nearby superpixels may belong to the same proto-object due to the intended
over-segmentation. Therefore, we extract superpixels as image fragments for
pre-processing, 2

and subsequently merge similar superpixels into proto-objects. We deﬁne
that a pair of adjacent superpixels belong to a coherent proto-object if they
are similar in all three low-level image features. Thus we need to determine a
similarity threshold for each of the three features, that separates the similarity
distance values into ?similar?, and ?dissimilar? populations, detailed in Section
2.2. In this work, the similarity statistics are based on comparing histograms of
intensity, color, and orientation features from an image fragment. The intensity
feature is a 1D 256 bin histogram, the color feature is a 76?76 (8 bit color) 2D
histogram using hue and saturation from the HSV colorspace, and the orienta-
tion feature is a symmetrical 1D 360 bin histogram using gradient orientations,
similar to the HOG feature [10]. All three feature histograms are normalized
to have the same total mass, such that bin counts sum to one. We use Earth
Mover?s Distance (EMD) to compute the similarity distance between feature
histograms [26], which is known to be robust to partially matching histograms.
For any pair of adjacent superpixels va and vb , their normalized feature simi-
larity distances for each of the intensity, [ f , where xn;f decolor, and orientation
features are computed as: xn;f = EMD(va;f , vb;f )/EMD notes the similarity
(0 is exactly the same, and 1 means completely opposite) between the nth pair
(n = 1, ..., N ) of nodes va and vb under feature f ? {i, c, o} as intensity, color,
and orientation. [ f is the maximum possible EMD for each of the three image
features; it is well deﬁned in EMD this situation such that the largest diﬀerence
between intensities is black to white, hues that are [ f normalizes 180? apart,
and a horizontal gradient against a vertical gradient. Therefore, EMD xn;f ?
[0, 1]. In the subsequent sections, we explain our proposed method for ﬁnding
the adaptive similarity threshold from xf , which is the EMDs of all pairs of
adjacent nodes . 2.2

EMD statistics and Weibull distributon
Any pair of adjacent superpixels are either similar enough to belong to the

3

same proto-object, or they belong to diﬀerent proto-objects, as separated by the
adaptive similarity threshold ?f that is diﬀerent for every image. We formulate
this as an edge labeling problem: given a graph G = (V, E), where va ? V and vb
? V are two adjacent nodes (superpixels) having edge ea,b ? E, a 6= b between
them, also the nth edge of G. The task is to label the binary indicator variable
yn;f = I(xn;f ¡ ?f ) on edge ea,b such that yn;f = 1 if xn;f ¡ ?f , which means va;f
and vb;f are similar (belongs to the same proto-object), otherwise yn;f = 0 if va;f
and vb;f are dissimilar (belongs to diﬀerent protoobjects). Once ?f is computed,
removing the edges such that yf = 0 results in isolated clusters of locally similar
image patches, which are the desired groups of proto-objects. Intuitively, any
pair of adjacent nodes is either within the same proto-object cluster, or between
diﬀerent clusters (yn;f = {1, 0}), therefore we consider two populations (the
within-cluster edges, and the between-cluster edges) to be modeled from the
density of xf in a given image. In theory, this would mean that the density of
xf is a distribution exhibiting bi-modality, such that the left mode corresponds
to the set of xf that are considered similar and coherent, while the right mode
contains the set of xf that represent dissimilarity. At ﬁrst thought, applying
k-means with k = 2 or a mixture of two Gaussians would allow estimation
of the two populations. However, there is no evidence showing that similarity
distances follow symmetrical or normal distributions. In the following, we argue
that the similarity distances xf computed by EMD follow Weibull distribution,
which is a distribution of the Exponential family that is skewed in shape. Pm
Pn 0 Pm Pn 0 0 We deﬁne EMD(P, Q) = ( i f d )/( i f ), with an optimal ﬂow
ﬁj such that P 0 P 0 P j ij0 ij Pj ijP 0 f ? p , f ? q , f = min( p , q ), and
f ? 0, where P = i j i j ij j ij i ij i,j i,j i j {(x1 , p1 ), ..., (xm , pm )} and
Q = {(y1 , q1 ), ..., (yn , qn )} are the two signatures to be compared, and
dij denotes a dissimilarity metric (i.e. L2 distance) between xi and yj in Rd .
When P and Q are normalized to have the Pnsame total mass, EMD becomes
identical to Mallows distance [17], deﬁned as Mp (X, Y ) = ( n1 i=1 —xi ?
yi —p )1/p , where X and Y are sorted vectors of the same size, and Mallows
distance is an Lp -norm based distance measurement. Furthermore, Lp -norm
based distance metrics are Weibull distributed if the two feature vectors to be
compared are correlated and non-identically distributed [7]. We show that our
features assumptions are satisﬁed in Section 4.1. Hence, we can model each
feature of xf as a mixture of two Weibull distributions separately, and compute
the corresponding ?f as the boundary locations between the two components
of the mixtures. Although the Weibull distribution has been used in modeling
actual image features such 3

as texture and edges [12][35], it has not been used to model EMD similarity

distance statistics until now. 2.3

Weibull mixture model
Our Weibull mixture model (WMM) takes the following general form: W K

(x; ?) =
K X
?k ?k (x; ?k ) ,
?(x; ?, ?, c) =

4

k=1
? x ? c ??1 ?( x?c )? ( ) e ? ? ?
(1)
where ?k = (?k , ?k , ck ) is the parameter vector for the k th mixture
component, and ? denotes the three-parameter Weibull Ppdf with the scale (?),
shape (?), and location (c) parameter, and the mixing parameter ? such that k
?k = 1. In this case, our two-component WMM contains a 7-parameter vector
? = (?1 , ?1 , c1 , ?2 , ?2 , c2 , ?) that yields the following complete form: W
2 (x; ?) = ?(

1 ?1 2 ?2 ?1 x ? c1 ?1 ?1 ?( x?c ?2 x ? c2 ?2 ?1 ?( x?c ( ) )e ?1 ) + (1 ? ?)(

( ) )e ?2 ) ?1 ?1 ?2 ?2

(2)
To estimate the parameters of W 2 (x; ?), we tested two optimization meth-
ods: maximum likelihood estmation (MLE), and nonlinear least squares min-
imization (NLS). Both MLE and NLS requires an initial parameter vector ?0
to begin the optimization, and the choice of ?0 is crucial to the convergence ?
In our case, the initial guess is quite well deﬁned: for any node of the optimal
parameter vector ?. N of a speciﬁc feature vj;f , and its set of adjacent neighbors
vj;f = N (vj;f ), the neighbor that is most similar to vj;f is most likely to belong
to the same cluster as vj;f , and it is especially true under an over-segmention
scenario. Therefore, the initial guess for the ﬁrst mixture component ?1;f is the
0 N MLE of ?1;f (?1;f ; x0f ), such that x0f = {min(EMD(vj;f , vj;f ))—vj;f ; j =
1, ..., z, f ? {i, c, o}}, where z is the total number of superpixels, and x0f ? xf
. After obtaining ?10 = (?10 , ?10 , c01 ), several ?20 can be computed for the
re-start purpose via MLE from the data taken by P r(xf —?10 ) ¿ p, where P r is
the cumulative distribution function, and p is a range of percentiles. Together,
they form the complete initial guess parameter vector ?0 = (?10 , ?10 , c01 ,
?20 , ?20 , c02 , ? 0 ) where ? 0 = 0.5. 2.3.1

Parameter estimation
Maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) estimates the parameters by maxi-
mizing the log-likelihood function of the observed samples. The log-likelihood
function of W 2 (x; ?) is given by:

ln L(?; x) =
N X n=1
ln{?(
?1 xn ? c1 ?1 ?1 ?( xn??c1 )?1 ?2 xn ? c2 ?2 ?1 ?( xn??c2 )?2 1 2 ( ) )e ) )e

+(1??)( ( } ?1 ?1 ?2 ?2 (3)

Due to the complexity of this log-likelihood function and the presence of the
location parameters c1,2 , we adopt the Nelder-Mead method as a derivative-
free optimization of MLE that performs parameter estimation with direct-search
[22][16], by minimizing the negative log-likelihood function of Eq. 3. For the
NLS optimization method, ﬁrst xf are approximated with histograms much like a
box ﬁlter that smoothes a curve. The appropriate histogram bin-width for data
representation is computed by w = 2(IQR)n?1/3 , where IQR is the interquartile
range of the data with n observations [15]. This allows us to optimize a two
component WMM to the height of each bin with NLS as a curve ﬁtting problem,

5

which is a robust alternative to MLE when the noise level can be reduced by
some approximation scheme. Then, we ﬁnd the least squares minimizer by
using the trust-region method [27][28]. Both the Nelder-Mead MLE algorithm
and the NLS method are detailed in the supplementary material. Figure 2
shows the WMM ﬁt using the Nelder-Mead MLE method. In addition to the
good ﬁt of the mixture model to the data, it also shows that the right skewed
data (EMD statistics) is remarkably Weibull, this further validates that EMD
statistics follow Weibull distribution both in theory and experiments. 4

Figure 2: (a) original image, (b) after superpixel pre-processing [1] (977
initial segments), (c) ﬁnal proto-object partitioning result (150 segments). Each
ﬁnal segment is shown with its mean RGB value to approximate proto-object
perception. (d) W 2 (xf ; ?f ) optimized using the Nelder-Mead algorithm for
intensity, (e) color, and (f) orientation based on the image in (b). The red line
indicates the individual Weibull components; and the blue line is the density of
the mixture W 2 (xf ; ?f ). 2.4

Visual clutter model with model selection
At times, the dissimilar population can be highly mixed in with the similar
population, the density of which would resemble more of a single Weibull in
shape such as Figure 2d. Therefore, we ﬁt a single Weibull as well as a two
component WMM over xf , and apply the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC)
to prevent any possible over-ﬁttings by the two component WMM. AIC tends
to place a heavier penalty on the simpler model, which is suitable in our case to
ensure that the preference is placed on the two-population mixture models. For
models optimized using MLE, the standard AIC is used; for the NLS cases, the
corrected AIC (AICc) for smaller sample size (generally when n/k ? 40) with
residual sum of squares (RSS) is used, and it is deﬁned as AICc = n ln(RSS/n)
+ 2k +2k(k +1)/(n?k ?1), where k is the number of model parameters, n is the
number of samples. The optimal ?f can then be determined as follows:

?f =
? ?max(x, ), ?
s.t. ?1 ?1;f (x—?1;f ) = ?2 ?2;f (x—?2;f ) AIC(W 2 ) ? AIC(W 1 ) (4)
max(??1 (ln(1 ? ? ))1/?1 , )
Otherwise
The ﬁrst case is when the mixture model is preferred, then the optimal ?f
is the crossing point between the mixture components, and the equality can be
solved in linear time by searching over the values of the vector xf ; in the second
case when the single Weibull is preferred by model selection, ?f is calculated
by the inverse CDF of W 1 , which computes the location of a given percentile
parameter ? . Note that ?f is lower bounded by a tolerance parameter in
both cases to prevent unusual behaviors when an image is nearly blank (?f
? [, 1]), making ? and the only model parameters in our framework. We
perform Principle Component Analysis (PCA) on the similarity distance values
xf of intensity, color, and orientation and obtain the combined distance feature
value by projecting xf to the ﬁrst principle component, such that the relative
importance of each distance feature is captured by its variance through PCA.
This projected distance feature is used to construct a minimum spanning tree

6

over the superpixels to form the structure of graph G, which weakens the inter-
cluster connectivity by removing cycles and other excessive graph connections.
Finally, each edge of G is labeled 5

according to Section 2.2 given the computed ?f , such that an edge is labeled
as 1 (similar) only if the pair of superpixels are similar in all three features.
Edges labeled as 0 (dissimilar) are removed from G to form isolated clusters
(proto-objects), and our visual clutter model produces a normalized clutter
measure that is between 0 and 1 by dividing the number of proto-objects by
the initial number of superpixels such that it is invariant to diﬀerent scales of
superpixel over-segmentation.

3
Dataset and ground truth
Various in-house image datasets have been used in previous work to evaluate
their models of visual clutter. The feature congestion model was evaluated on
25 images of US city/road maps and weather maps [25]; the models in [5] and
[29] were evaluated on another 25 images consisting of 6, 12, or 24 synthetically
generated objects arranged into a grid ; and the model from [18] used 58 images
of six map or chart categories (airport terminal maps, ﬂowcharts, road maps,
subway maps, topographic charts, and weather maps). In each of these datasets,
each image must be rank ordered for visual clutter with respect to every other
image in the set by the same human subject, which is a tiring and time consum-
ing process. This rank ordering is essential for a clutter perception experiment
as it establishes a stable clutter metric that is meaningful across participants;
alas it limits the dataset size to the number of images each individual observer
can handle. Absolute clutter scales are undesirable as diﬀerent raters might use
diﬀerent ranges on this scale. We created a comparatively large clutter percep-
tion dataset consisting of 90 800?600 real world images sampled from the SUN
Dataset images [33] for which there exists human segmentations of objects and
object counts. These object segmentations serve as one of the ground truths
in our study. The high resolution of these images is also important for the ac-
curate perception and assessment of clutter. The 90 images were selected to
constitute six groups based on their ground truth object counts, with 15 images
in each group. Speciﬁcally, group 1 had images with object counts in the 1-10
range, group 2 had counts in the 11-20 range, up to group 6 with counts in the
51-60 range. These 90 images were rated in the laboratory by 15 college-aged
participants whose task was to order the images in terms of least to most per-
ceived visual clutter. This was done by displaying each image one at a time
and asking participants to insert it into an expanding set of previously rated
images. Participants were encouraged to take as much time as they needed,
and were allowed to freely scroll through the existing set of clutter rated images
when deciding where to insert the new image. A diﬀerent random sequence of
images was used for each participant (in order to control for biases and order
eﬀects), and the entire task lasted approximately one hour. The average cor-
relation (Spearman?s rank-order correlation) over all pairs of participants was
0.6919 (p ¡ 0.001), indicating good agreement among raters. We used the me-
dian ranked position of each image as the ground truth for clutter perception

7

in our experiments.

4 4.1
Experiment and results Image feature assumptions
In their demonstration that similarity distances adhere to a Weibull dstri-
bution, Burghouts et al. [7] derived and related Lp -norm based distances from
the statistics of sums [3][4] such that for nonPN identical and correlated random
variables Xi , the sum i=1 Xi is Weibull distributed if Xi are p upper-bounded
with a ﬁnite N , where Xi = —si ? Ti — such that N is the dimensionality of
the feature vector, i is the index, and s, t ? T are diﬀerent sample vectors of the
same feature. The three image features used in this model are ﬁnite and upper
bounded, and we follow the procedure from [7] with L2 distance to determine
whether they are correlated. We consider distances from one reference super-
pixel feature vector s to 100 other randomly selected superpixel feature vectors
T (of the same feature), and compute the diﬀerences at index i such that we
are obtaining the random variable Xi = —si ? Ti —p . Pearson?s correlation
is then used to determine the relationship between Xi and Xj , i 6= j at a
conﬁdence level of 0.05. This procedure is repeated 500 times per image for all
three feature types over all 90 images. As predicted, we found an almost per-
fect correlation between feature value diﬀerences for each of the features tested:
Intensity: 100%, Hue: 99.2%, Orientation: 98.97%). This conﬁrms that the low
level image features used in this study follow a Weibull distribution. 6

WMM-mle 0.8038
WMM-nls 0.7966
MS[9] 0.7262
GB[11] 0.6612
PL[6] 0.6439
ED[19] 0.6231
FC[25] 0.5337
# Obj 0.5255
C3[18] 0.4810
Table 1: Correlations between human clutter perception and all the evalu-
ated methods. WMM is the Weibull mixture model underlying our proto-object
partitioning approach, with both optimization methods. 4.2

Model evaluation
We ran our model with diﬀerent parameter settings of ? {0.01, 0.02, ...,
0.20} and ? ? {0.5, 0.6, ..., 0.9} using SLIC superpixels [1] initialized at 1000
seeds. We then correlated the number of proto-objects formed after super-
pixel merging with the ground truth behavioral clutter perception estimates
by computing the Spearman?s Rank Correlation (Spearman?s ?) following the
convention of [25][5][29][18]. A model using MLE as the optimization method
achieved the highest correlation, ? = 0.8038, p ¡ 0.001 with = 0.14 and ? = 0.8.
Because we did not have separate training/testing sets, we performed 10-fold
cross-validation and obtained an average testing correlation of r = 0.7599, p ¡
0.001. When optimized using NLS, the model achieved a maximum correlation
of ? = 0.7966, p ¡ 0.001 with = 0.14 and ? = 0.4, and the corresponding 10-fold
cross-validation yielded an average testing correlation of r = 0.7375, p ¡ 0.001.

8

The high cross-validation averages indicate that our model is highly robust, and
generalizable to unseen data. It is worth pointing out that, the optimal value of
the tolerance parameter showed a peak correlation at 0.14. To the extent that
this is meaningful and extends to people, it suggests that visual clutter percep-
tion may ignore feature dissimilarity on the order of 14% when deciding whether
two adjacent regions are similar and should be merged. We compared our model
to four other state-of-the-art models of clutter perception: the feature conges-
tion model [25], the edge density method [19], the power-law model [6], and the
C3 model [18]. Table 1 shows that our model signiﬁcantly out-performed all
of these previously reported methods. The relatively poor performance of the
recent C3 model was surprising, and can probably be attributed to the previous
evaluation of that model using charts and maps rather than arbitrary realis-
tic scenes (personal communication with authors). Collectively, these results
suggest that a model that merges superpixels into proto-objects best describes
human clutter perception, and that the beneﬁt of using a proto-object model for
clutter prediction is not small; our model resulted in an improvement of at least
15% over existing models of clutter perception. Although we did not record
run-time statistics on the other models, our model, implemented in Matlab1 ,
had an end-to-end (excluding superpixel pre-processing) run-time of 15-20 sec-
onds using 800?600 images running on an Win7 Intel Core i-7 computer with 8
Gb RAM. 4.3

Comparison to image segmentation methods
We also attempted to compare our method to state of the art image segmen-
tation algorithms such as gPb-ucm [2], but found that the method was unable
to process our image dataset using either an Intel Core i-7 machine with 8 Gb
RAM or an Intel Xeon machine with 16 Gb RAM, at the high image resolutions
required by our behavioral clutter estimates. A similar limitation was found
for image segmentation methods that utilizes gPb contour detection as pre-
processing, such as [8][14], while [23][34] took 10 hours on a single image and did
not converge. Therefore, we limit our evaluation to mean-shift [9] and Graph-
based method [11], as they are able to produce variable numbers of segments
based on the unsupervised partitioning of the 90 images from our dataset. De-
spite using the best dataset parameter settings for these unsupervised methods,
our method remains the highest correlated model with the clutter perception
ground truth as shown in Table 1, and that methods allowing quantiﬁcation
of proto-object set size (WMM, Mean-shift, and Graph-based) outperformed
all of the previous clutter models . We also correlated the number of objects
segmented by humans (as provided in the SUN Dataset) with the clutter per-
ception ground truth, denoted as # obj in Table 1. Interestingly, despite object
1

Code is available at mysbﬁles.stonybrook.edu/cheyu/projects/proto-objects.html
7
Figure 3: Top: Four images from our dataset, rank ordered for clutter per-
ception by human raters, median clutter rank order from left to right: 6, 47,
70, 87. Bottom: Corresponding images after parametric proto-object partition-
ing, median clutter rank order from left to right: 7, 40, 81, 83. count being a

9

human-derived estimate, it produced among the lowest correlations with clutter
perception. This suggests that clutter perception is not determined by simply
the number of objects in a scene; it is the proto-object composition of these
objects that is important.

5
Conclusion
We proposed a model of visual clutter perception based on a parametric
image partitioning method that is fast and able to work on large images. This
method of segmenting proto-objects from an image using mixture of Weibull dis-
tributions is also novel in that it models similarity distance statistics rather than
feature statistics obtained directly from pixels. Our work also contributes to the
behavioral understanding of clutter perception. We showed that our model is
an excellent predictor of human clutter perception, outperforming all existing
clutter models, and predicts clutter perception better than even a behavioral
segmentation of objects. This suggests that clutter perception is best described
at the proto-object level, a level intermediate to that of objects and features.
Moreover, our work suggests a means of objectively quantifying a behaviorally
meaningful set size for scenes, at least with respect to clutter perception. We
also introduced a new and validated clutter perception dataset consisting of a
variety of scene types and object categories. This dataset, the largest and most
comprehensive to date, will likely be used widely in future model evaluation and
method comparison studies. In future work we plan to extend our parametric
partitioning method to general image segmentation and data clustering prob-
lems, and to use our model to predict human visual search behavior and other
behaviors that might be aﬀected by visual clutter.

6
Acknowledgment
We appreciate the authors of [18] for sharing and discussing their code, Dr.
Burghouts for providing detailed explanations to the feature assumption part
in [7], and Dr. Matthew Asher for providing their human search performance
data on their work in Journal of Vision, 2013. This work was supported by NIH
Grant R01-MH063748 to G.J.Z., NSF Grant IIS-1111047 to G.J.Z. and D.S.,
and the SUBSAMPLE Project of the DIGITEO Institute, France.

2 References

[1] R. Achanta, A. Shaji, K. Smith, A. Lucchi, P. Fua, and S. Susstrunk. Slic
superpixels compared to stateof-the-art superpixel methods.
IEEE TPAMI,
2012. [2] P. Arbelaez, M. Maire, C. Fowlkes, and J. Malik. Contour detection
and hierarchical image segmentation. IEEE TPAMI, 2010. [3] E. Bertin. Global
fuctuations and gumbel statistics. Physical Review Letters, 2005.

8
[4] E. Bertin and M. Clusel. Generalised extreme value statistics and sum of
correlated variables. Journal of Pnysics A, 2006. [5] M. J. Bravo and H. Farid.
Search for a category target in clutter. Perception, 2004. [6] M. J. Bravo and

10

In CVPR, 2005.

H. Farid. A scale invariant measure of clutter. Journal of Vision, 2008. [7] G.
J. Burghouts, A. W. M. Smeulders, and J.-M. Geusebroek. The distribution
family of similarity distances. In NIPS, 2007. [8] J. Carreira and C. Sminchis-
escu. Constrained parametric min-cuts for automatic object segmentation. In
CVPR, 2010.
[9] D. Comaniciu and P. Meer. Mean shift: A robust approach
toward feature space analysis. IEEE TPAMI, 2002. [10] N. Dalal and B. Triggs.
Histograms of oriented gradients for human detection.
[11]
P. F. Felzenszwalb and H. D. P. Eﬃcient graph-based image segmentation. In
ICCV, 2004. [12] J.-M. Geusebroek and A. W. Smeulders. A six-stimulus the-
ory for stochastic texture. IJCV, 2005.
[13] J. M. Henderson, M. Chanceaux,
and T. J. Smith. The inﬂuence of clutter on real-world scene search: Evidence
from search eﬃciency and eye movements. Journal of Vision, 2009.
[14] A.
Image segmentation by ﬁgure-ground
Ion, J. Carreira, and C. Sminchisescu.
composition into maximal cliques. In ICCV, 2011. [15] A. J. Izenman. Recent
developments in nonparametric density estimation. Journal of the American
Statistical Association, 1991.
[16] J. C. Lagarias, J. A. Reeds, M. H. Wright,
and P. E. Wright. Convergence properties of the nelder-mead simplex method
in low dimensions. SIAM Journal on Optimization, 1998.
[17] E. Levina and
P. Bickel. The earth mover?s distance is the mallows distance: some insights
from statistics. In ICCV, 2001. [18] M. C. Lohrenz, J. G. Trafton, R. M. Beck,
and M. L. Gendron. A model of clutter for complex, multivariate geospatial
displays. Human Factors, 2009. [19] M. L. Mack and A. Oliva. Computational
estimation of visual complexity. In the 12th Annual Object, Perception, Atten-
tion, and Memory Conference, 2004.
[20] D. Martin, C. Fowlkes, D. Tal, and
J. Malik. A database of human segmented natural images and its application
to evaluating segmentation algorithms and measuring ecological statistics. In
ICCV, 2001. [21] M. B. Neider and G. J. Zelinsky. Cutting through the clutter:
searching for targets in evolving complex scenes. Journal of Vision, 2011. [22]
J. A. Nelder and R. Mead. A simplex method for function minimization. The
computer journal, 1965. [23] S. R. Rao, H. Mobahi, A. Y. Yang, S. Sastry, and
Y. Ma. Natural image segmentation with adaptive texture and boundary en-
coding. In ACCV, 2009. [24] R. A. Rensink. Seeing, sensing, and scrutinizing.
[25] R. Rosenholtz, Y. Li, and L. Nakano. Measuring
Vision Research, 2000.
visual clutter. Journal of Vision, 2007.
[26] Y. Rubner, C. Tomasi, and L. J.
Guibas. A metric for distributions with applications to image databases.
In
ICCV, 1998.
[27] T. Steihaug. The conjugate gradient method and trust re-
gions in large scale optimization. SIAM Journal on Numerical Analysis, 1983.
[28] P. L. Toint. Towards an eﬃcient sparsity exploiting newton method for
minimization. Sparse Matrices and Their Uses, 1981. [29] R. van den Berg, F.
W. Cornelissen, and J. B. T. M. Roerdink. A crowding model of visual clutter.
Journal of Vision, 2009.
[30] O. Veksler, Y. Boykov, and P. Mehrani. Super-
pixels and supervoxels in an energy optimization framework. In ECCV, 2010.
[31] M. Wischnewski, A. Belardinelli, W. X. Schneider, and J. J. Steil. Where
to look next? combining static and dynamic proto-objects in a tva-based model
of visual attention. Cognitive Computation, 2010.
[32] J. M. Wolfe. Visual
[33] J. Xiao, J. Hays, K. Ehinger, A. Oliva, and A.
search. Attention, 1998.

11

Torralba. SUN database: Large-scale scene recognition from abbey to zoo. In
[34] A. Y. Yang, J. Wright, Y.Ma, and S. Sastry. Unsupervised
CVPR, 2010.
segmentation of natural images via lossy data compression. CVIU, 2008.
[35]
V. Yanulevskaya and J.-M. Geusebroek. Signiﬁcance of the Weibull distribution
and its sub-models in natural image statistics. In Int. Conference on Computer
Vision Theory and Applications, 2009.

9

12

