Learning Generative Models with Visual

Attention

Authored by:

Ruslan R. Salakhutdinov

Nitish Srivastava

Yichuan Tang

Abstract

Attention has long been proposed by psychologists to be important
for eﬃciently dealing with the massive amounts of sensory stimulus in
the neocortex.
Inspired by the attention models in visual neuroscience
and the need for object-centered data for generative models, we propose
a deep-learning based generative framework using attention. The atten-
tional mechanism propagates signals from the region of interest in a scene
to an aligned canonical representation for generative modeling. By ig-
noring scene background clutter, the generative model can concentrate
its resources on the object of interest. A convolutional neural net is em-
ployed to provide good initializations during posterior inference which
uses Hamiltonian Monte Carlo. Upon learning images of faces, our model
can robustly attend to the face region of novel test subjects. More impor-
tantly, our model can learn generative models of new faces from a novel
dataset of large images where the face locations are not known.

1 Paper Body

Building rich generative models that are capable of extracting useful, high-level
latent representations from high-dimensional sensory input lies at the core of
solving many AI-related tasks, including object recognition, speech perception
and language understanding. These models capture underlying structure in
data by deﬁning ﬂexible probability distributions over high-dimensional data as
part of a complex, partially observed system. Some of the successful generative
models that are able to discover meaningful high-level latent representations
include the Boltzmann Machine family of models: Restricted Boltzmann Ma-
chines, Deep Belief Nets [1], and Deep Boltzmann Machines [2]. Mixture models,
such as Mixtures of Factor Analyzers [3] and Mixtures of Gaussians, have also
been used for modeling natural image patches [4]. More recently, denoising
auto-encoders have been proposed as a way to model the transition operator
that has the same invariant distribution as the data generating distribution [5].

1

Generative models have an advantage over discriminative models when part of
the images are occluded or missing. Occlusions are very common in realistic
settings and have been largely ignored in recent literature on deep learning. In
addition, prior knowledge can be easily incorporated in generative models in
the forms of structured latent variables, such as lighting and deformable parts.
However, the enormous amount of content in high-resolution images makes gen-
erative learning diﬃcult [6, 7]. Therefore, generative models have found most
success in learning to model small patches of natural images and objects: Zoran
and Weiss [4] learned a mixture of Gaussians model over 8?8 image patches;
Salakhutdinov and Hinton [2] used 64?64 centered and uncluttered stereo im-
ages of toy objects on a clear background; Tang et al. [8] used 24?24 images of
centered and cropped faces. The fact that these models require curated training
data limits their applicability on using the (virtually) unlimited unlabeled data.
In this paper, we propose a framework to infer the region of interest in a big
image for generative modeling. This will allow us to learn a generative model
of faces on a very large dataset of (unlabeled) images containing faces. Our
framework is able to dynamically route the relevant information to the genera-
tive model and can ignore the background clutter. The need to dynamically and
selectively route information is also present in the biological brain. Plethora of
evidence points to 1

the presence of attention in the visual cortex [9, 10]. Recently, in visual neu-
roscience, attention has been shown to exist not only in extrastriate areas, but
also all the way down to V1 [11]. Attention as a form of routing was originally
proposed by Anderson and Van Essen [12] and then extended by Olshausen et
al. [13]. Dynamic routing has been hypothesized as providing a way for achiev-
ing shift and size invariance in the visual cortex [14, 15]. Tsotsos et al.
[16]
proposed a model combining search and attention called the Selective Tuning
model. Larochelle and Hinton [17] proposed a way of using third-order Boltz-
mann Machines to combine information gathered from many foveal glimpses.
Their model chooses where to look next to ﬁnd locations that are most infor-
mative of the object class. Reichert et al.
[18] proposed a hierarchical model
to show that certain aspects of covert object-based attention can be modeled
by Deep Boltzmann Machines. Several other related models attempt to learn
where to look for objects [19, 20] and for video based tracking [21]. Inspired by
Olshausen et al.
[13], we use 2D similarity transformations to implement the
scaling, rotation, and shift operation required for routing. Our main motivation
is to enable the learning of generative models in big images where the location
of the object of interest is unknown a-priori.

2
Gaussian Restricted Boltzmann Machines
Before we describe our model, we brieﬂy review the Gaussian Restricted
Boltzmann Machine (GRBM) [22], as it will serve as the building block for our
attention-based model. GRBMs are a type of Markov Random Field model that
has a bipartite structure with real-valued visible variables v ? RD connected
to binary stochastic hidden variables h ? {0, 1}H . The energy of the joint
conﬁguration {v, h} of the Gaussian RBM is deﬁned as follows: X 1 X (vi ?

2

bi )2 X ? c h ? Wij vi hj , (1) EGRBM (v, h; ?) = j j 2 i ?i2 j ij where ? =
{W, b, c, ?} P are the model parameters. The marginal distribution over the
visible vector 1 v is P (v; ?) = Z(?) h exp (?E(v, h; ?)) and the corresponding
conditional distributions take the following form: X
p(hj = 1—v) = 1/ 1 + exp(? Wij vi ? cj ) , (2) i
p(vi —h)
= N (vi ; ?i , ?i2 ), where ?i = bi + ?i2
X
Wij hj .
(3)
j
Observe that conditioned on the states of the hidden variables (Eq. 3), each
visible unit is modeled by a Gaussian distribution, whose mean is shifted by the
weighted combination of the hidden unit activations. Unlike directed models,
an RBM?s conditional distribution over hidden nodes is factorial and can be
easily computed. We can also add a binary RBM on top of the learned GRBM
by treating the inferred h as the ?visible? layer together with a second hidden
layer h2 . This results in a 2-layer Gaussian Deep Belief Network (GDBN) [1]
that is a more powerful model of v. Speciﬁcally, in a GDBN model, p(h1 , h2 )
is modeled by the energy function of the 2nd-layer RBM, while p(v1 —h1 ) is
given by Eq. 3. Eﬃcient inference can be performed using the greedy approach
of [1] by treating each DBN layer as a separate RBM model. GDBNs have been
applied to various tasks, including image classiﬁcation, video action and speech
recognition [6, 23, 24, 25].

3
The Model
Let I be a high resolution image of a scene, e.g. a 256?256 image. We
want to use attention to propagate regions of interest from I up to a canonical
representation. For example, in order to learn a model of faces, the canonical
representation could be a 24?24 aligned and cropped frontal face image. Let
v ? RD represent this low resolution canonical image. In this work, we focus
on a Deep Belief Network1 to model v. This is illustrated in the diagrams of
Fig. 1. The left panel displays the model of Olshausen et.al. [13], whereas the
right panel shows a graphical diagram of our proposed generative model with an
attentional mechanism. Here, h1 and h2 represent the latent hidden variables
of the DBN model, and 1

Other generative models can also be used with our attention framework.
2
2d similarity transformation
Our model
Olshausen et al. 93
Figure 1: Left: The Shifter Circuit, a well-known neuroscience model for
visual attention [13]; Right: The proposed model uses 2D similarity transfor-
mations from geometry and a Gaussian DBN to model canonical face images.
Associative memory corresponds to the DBN, object-centered frame correspond

3

to the visible layer and the attentional mechanism is modeled by 2D similarity
transformations.

4x, 4y, 4?, 4s (position, rotation, and scale) are the parameters of the 2D
similarity transformation. The 2D similarity transformation is used to rotate,
scale, and translate the canonical image v onto the canvas that we denote by I.
Let p = [x y]T be a pixel coordinate (e.g. [0, 0] or [0, 1]) of the canonical image
v. Let {p} be the set of all coordinates of v. For example, if v is 24?24, then
{p} ranges from [0, 0] to [23, 23]. Let the ?gaze? variables u ? R4 ? [4x, 4y,
4?, 4s] be the parameter of the Similarity transformation. In order to simplify
derivations and to make transformations be linear w.r.t.
the transformation
parameters, we can equivalently redeﬁne u = [a, b, 4x, 4y], where a = s sin(?)
? 1 and b = s cos(?) (see [26] for details). We further deﬁne a function w :=
w(p, u) ? p0 as the transformation function to warp points p to p0 : h 0 i h ih
i h i 1+a ?b x 4x x p0 , = + . (4) 0 y b 1+a y 4y We use the notation I({p})
to denote the bilinear interpolation of I at coordinates {p} with antialiasing.
Let x(u) be the extracted low-resolution image at warped locations p0 : x(u) ,
I(w({p}, u)).

(5)
Intuitively, x(u) is a patch extracted from I according to the shift, rotation
and scale parameters of u, as shown in Fig. 1, right panel. It is this patch of
data that we seek to model generatively. Note that the dimensionality of x(u) is
equal to the cardinality of {p}, where {p} denotes the set of pixel coordinates of
the canonical image v. Unlike standard generative learning tasks, the data x(u)
is not static but changes with the latent variables u. Given v and u, we model
the top-down generative process over2 x with a Gaussian distribution having a
diagonal covariance matrix ? 2 I:

1 X (xi (u) ? vi )2 p(x—v, u, I) ? exp ? . (6) 2 i ?i2 The fact that we
do not seek to model the rest of the regions/pixels of I is by design. By using
2D similarity transformation to mimic attention, we can discard the complex
background of the scene and let the generative model focus on the object of
interest. The proposed generative model takes the following form: p(x, v, u—I)
= p(x—v, u, I)p(v)p(u),

(7)
where for p(u) we use a ﬂat prior that is constant for all u, and p(v) is
deﬁned by a 2-layer Gaussian Deep Belief Network. The conditional p(x—v, u,
I) is given by a Gaussian distribution as in Eq. 6. To simplify the inference
procedure, p(x—v, u, I) and the GDBN model of v, p(v), will share the same
noise parameters ?i . 2

We will often omit dependence of x on u for clarity of presentation.
3
4
Inference
While the generative equations in the last section are straightforward and
intuitive, inference in these models is typically intractable due to the compli-
cated energy landscape of the posterior. During inference, we wish to compute
the distribution over the gaze variables u and canonical object v given the big

4

image I. Unlike in standard RBMs and DBNs, there are no simplifying fac-
torial assumptions about the conditional distribution of the latent variable u.
Having a 2D similarity transformation is reminiscent of third-order Boltzmann
machines with u performing top-down multiplicative gating of the connections
between v and I. It is well known that inference in these higher-order models is
rather complicated. One way to perform inference in our model is to resort to
Gibbs sampling by computing the set of alternating conditional posteriors: The
conditional distribution over the canonical image v takes the following form:

? + x(u) (8) ; ?2 , p(v—u, h1 , I) = N 2 P where ?i = bi + ?i2 j Wij h1j is the
top-down inﬂuence of the DBN. Note that if we know the gaze variable u and
the ﬁrst layer of hidden variables h1 , then v is simply deﬁned by a Gaussian
distribution, where the mean is given by the average of the top-down inﬂuence
and bottom-up information from x. The conditional distributions over h1 and h2
given v are given by the standard DBN inference equations [1]. The conditional
posterior over the gaze variables u is given by: p(x—u, v)p(u) p(u—x, v) =
, p(x—v) 1 X (xi (u) ? vi )2 log p(u—x, v) ? log p(x—u, v) + log p(u) =
+ const. (9) 2 i ?i2 Using Bayes? rule, the unnormalized log probability of
p(u—x, v) is deﬁned in Eq. 9. We stress that this equation is atypical in that
the random variable of interest u actually aﬀects the conditioning variable x
(see Eq. 5) We can explore the gaze variables using Hamiltonian Monte Carlo
(HMC) algorithm [27, 28]. Intuitively, conditioned on the canonical object v
that our model has in ?mind?, HMC searches over the entire image I to ﬁnd a
region x with a good match to v. If the goal is only to ﬁnd the MAP estimate
of p(u—x, v), then we may want to use second-order methods for optimizing u.
This would be equivalent to the Lucas-Kanade framework in computer vision,
developed for image alignment [29]. However, HMC has the advantage of being
a proper MCMC sampler that satisﬁes detailed balance and ﬁts nicely with our
probabilistic framework. The HMC algorithm ﬁrst speciﬁes the Hamiltonian
over the position variables u and auxiliary momentum variables r: H(u, r) = U
(u) + K(r), where the potential function is deﬁned by 2 P P i) U (u) = 21 i (xi
(u)?v and the kinetic energy function is given by K(r) = 12 i ri2 . The dy?i2
namics of the system is deﬁned by: ?u ?r ?H = r, =? (10) ?t ?t ?u ?H (x(u)
? v) ?x(u) = , (11) ?u ?2 ?u ?x ?x ?w({p}, u) X ?xi ?w(pi , u) = = . (12)
?u ?w({p}, u) ?u ?w(p , u) ?u i i Observe that Eq. 12 decomposes into sums
over single coordinate positions pi = [x y]T . Let us denote p0 i = w(pi , u) to
be the coordinate pi warped by u. For the ﬁrst term on the RHS of Eq. 12,
?xi = ?I(p0 i ), (dimension 1 by 2 ) (13) ?w(pi , u) where ?I(p0 i ) denotes the
sampling of the gradient images of I at the warped location pi . For the second
term on the RHS of Eq. 12, we note that we can re-write Eq. 4 as: ” a # h 0 i
h i h i x x ?y 1 0 b x = + , (14) 0 y y x 0 1 4x y 4y 4

giving us ?w(pi , u) h x = y ?u
?y x
1 0
i 0 . 1
(15)
HMC simulates the discretized system by performing leap-frog updates of

5

u and r using Eq. 10. Additional hyperparameters that need to be speciﬁed
include the step size , number of leap-frog steps, and the mass of the variables
(see [28] for details). 4.1 Approximate Inference HMC essentially performs gra-
dient descent with momentum, therefore it is prone to getting stuck at local
optimums. This is especially a problem for our task of ﬁnding the best trans-
formation parameters. While the posterior over u should be unimodal near the
optimum, many local minima exist away from the global optimum. For exam-
ple, in Fig. 2(a), the big image I is enclosed by the blue box, and the canonical
image v is enclosed by the green box. The current setting of u aligns together
the wrong eyes. However, it is hard to move the green box to the left due to
the local optima created by the dark intensities of the eye. Resampling the mo-
mentum variable every iteration in HMC does not help signiﬁcantly because we
are modeling real-valued images using a Gaussian distribution as the residual,
leading to quadratic costs in the diﬀerence between x(u) and v (see Eq. 9). This
makes the energy barriers between modes extremely high.

(a) Average
A B
To alleviate this problem we need to ﬁnd good initializations of u. We use
a Convolutional Network (ConvNet) to perform eﬃcient approximate inference,
resulting in good initial (b) guesses. Speciﬁcally, given v, u and I, we predict
the change Figure 2: (a) HMC can easily get in u that will lead to the maximum
log p(u—x, v). In other stuck at local optima. (b) Importance words, instead
of using the gradient ﬁeld for updating u, we of modeling p(u—v, I). Best
in color.
learn a ConvNet to output a better vector ﬁeld in the space of u.
We used a fairly standard ConvNet architecture and the standard stochastic
gradient descent learning procedure. We note that standard feedforward face
detectors seek to model p(u—I), while completely ignoring the canonical face
v. In contrast, here we take v into account as well. The ConvNet is used to
initialize u for the HMC algorithm. This is important in a proper generative
model because conditioning on v is appealing when multiple faces are present
in the scene. Fig. 2(b) is a hypothesized Euclidean space of v, where the black
manifold represents canonical faces and the blue manifold represents cropped
faces x(u). The blue manifold has a low intrinsic dimensionality of 4, spanned
by u. At A and B, the blue comes close to black manifold. This means that
there are at least two modes in the posterior over u. By conditioning on v,
we can narrow the posterior to a single mode, depending on whom we want to
focus our attention. We demonstrate this exact capability in Sec. 6.3. Fig. 3
demonstrates the iterative process of how approximate inference works in our
model. Speciﬁcally, based on u, the ConvNet takes a window patch around x(u)
(72?72) and v (24?24) as input, and predicts the output [4x, 4y, 4?, 4s]. In step
2, u is updated accordingly, followed by step 3 of alternating Gibbs updates of
v and h, as discussed in Sec. 4. The process is repeated. For the details of the
ConvNet see the supplementary materials.

5
Learning
While inference in our framework localizes objects of interest and is akin to

6

object detection, it is not the main objective. Our motivation is not to com-
pete with state-of-the-art object detectors but rather propose a probabilistic
generative framework capable of generative modeling of objects which are at
unknown locations in big images. This is because labels are expensive to ob-
tain and are often not available for images in an unconstrained environment.
To learn generatively without labels we propose a simple Monte Carlo based
ExpectationMaximization algorithm. This algorithm is an unbiased estimator
of the maximum likelihood objec5

1 Gibbs step
ConvNet
Step 1
ConvNet
Step 4
Step 3
Step 2
Figure 3: Inference process: u in step 1 is randomly initialized. The average
v and the extracted x(u) form the input to a ConvNet for approximate inference,
giving a new u. The new u is used to sample p(v—I, u, h). In step 3, one step
of Gibbs sampling of the GDBN is performed. Step 4 repeats the approximate
inference using the updated v and x(u). V

X 1
2
3
Inference steps
4
5
6 HMC
Figure 4: Example of an inference step. v is 24?24, x is 72?72. Approximate
inference quickly ﬁnds a good initialization for u, while HMC provides further
adjustments. Intermediate inference steps on the right are subsampled from 10
actual iterations.

tive. During the E-step, we use the Gibbs sampling algorithm developed
in Sec. 4 to draw samples from the posterior over the latent gaze variables
u, the canonical variables v, and the hidden variables h1 , h2 of a Gaussian
DBN model. During the M-step, we can update the weights of the Gaussian
DBN by using the posterior samples as its training data. In addition, we can
update the parameters of the ConvNet that performs approximate inference.
Due to the fact that the ﬁrst E-step requires a good inference algorithm, we
need to pretrain the ConvNet using labeled gaze data as part of a bootstrap
process. Obtaining training data for this initial phase is not a problem as we
can jitter/rotate/scale to create data. In Sec. 6.2, we demonstrate the ability to
learn a good generative model of face images from the CMU Multi-PIE dataset.

6
Experiments
We used two face datasets in our experiments. The ﬁrst dataset is a frontal
face dataset, called the Caltech Faces from 1999, collected by Markus Weber. In

7

this dataset, there are 450 faces of 27 unique individuals under diﬀerent lighting
conditions, expressions, and backgrounds. We downsampled the images from
their native 896 by 692 by a factor of 2. The dataset also contains manually
labeled eyes and mouth coordinates, which will serve as the gaze labels. We also
used the CMU Multi-PIE dataset [30], which contains 337 subjects, captured
under 15 viewpoints and 19 illumination conditions in four recording sessions
for a total of more than 750,000 images. We demonstrate our model?s ability to
perform approximate inference, to learn without labels, and to perform identity-
based attention given an image with two people. 6.1 Approximate inference We
ﬁrst investigate the critical inference algorithm of p(u—v, I) on the Caltech
Faces dataset. We run 4 steps of approximate inference detailed in Sec. 4.1 and
diagrammed in Fig. 3, followed by three iterations of 20 leap-frog steps of HMC.
Since we do not initially know the correct v, we initialize v to be the average
face across all subjects. Fig. 4 shows the image of v and x during inference for
a test subject. The initial gaze box is colored yellow on the left. Subsequent
gaze updates progress from yellow to blue. Once ConvNet-based approximate
inference gives a good initialization, starting from step 5, ﬁve iterations of 20
leap-frog steps of HMC are used to sample from the the posterior. Fig. 5 shows
the quantitative results of Intersection over Union (IOU) of the ground truth
face box and the inferred face box. The results show that inference is very
robust to initialization and requires 6

Accuracy of Approximate Inference
Accuracy of Approximate Inference
Accuracy Improvements
1.1
0.3
Average IOU Improvements
1 0.2
0.9 0.8 0.7 0.6 0.5 0
Trials with IOU ¿ 0.5 Average IOU 20
40
60
0.8
Accuracy
Accuracy
Accuracy
1
0.6 0.4 Trials with IOU ¿ 0.5 Average IOU
0.2 80
100
0 0
Initial Pixel Oﬀset
5
10
0.1 0 ?0.1
15

8

# of Inference Steps
?0.2 0
20
40
60
80
100
Initial Pixel Oﬀset
(a) (b) (c) Figure 5: (a) Accuracy as a function of gaze initialization (pixel
oﬀset). Blue curve is the percentage success of at least 50% IOU. Red curve
is the average IOU. (b) Accuracy as a function of the number of approximate
inference steps when initializing 50 pixels away. (c) Accuracy improvements of
HMC as a function of gaze initializations.

(a) DBN trained on Caltech
(b) DBN updated with Multi-PIE
Figure 6: Left: Samples from a 2-layer DBN trained on Caltech. Right:
samples from an updated DBN after training on CMU Multi-PIE without labels.
Samples highlighted in green are similar to faces from CMU.

only a few steps of approximate inference to converge. HMC clearly improves
model performance, resulting in an IOU increase of about 5% for localization.
This is impressive given that none of the test subjects were part of the training
and the background is diﬀerent from backgrounds in the training set. We also
compared our inference algorithm to the template matching in the task of face
deOur method OpenCV NCC template tection. We took the ﬁrst 5 subjects
as test IOU ¿ 0.5 97% 97% 93% 78% subjects and the rest as training. We
can lo# evaluations O(c) O(whs) O(whs) O(whs) Table 1: Face localization
accuracy. w: image width; calize with 97% accuracy 3(IOU ¿ 0.5) ush: image
image scales; c: number of inference ing our inference algorithm .
height; s:
In comparison, a near state-of-the-art face detection system steps used.
from
OpenCV 2.4.9 obtains the same 97% accuracy. It uses Haar Cascades, which is a
form of AdaBoost4 . Normalized Cross Correlation [31] obtained 93% accuracy,
while Euclidean distance template matching achieved an accuracy of only 78%.
However, note that our algorithm looks at a constant number of windows while
the other baselines are all based on scanning windows. 6.2

Generative learning without labels
The main advantage of our model is that it can learn on large images of
faces without localization label information (no manual cropping required). To
demonstrate, we use both the Caltech and the CMU faces Table 2: Variational
lower-bound estimates on the log-density of the dataset. For the CMU faces, a
Gaussian DBNs (higher is better). subset of 2526 frontal faces with ground truth
labels are used. We split the Caltech dataset into a training and a validation
set. For the CMU faces, we ﬁrst took 10% of the images as training cases for
the ConvNet for approximate inference. This is needed due to the completely
diﬀerent backgrounds of the Caltech and CMU datasets. The remaining 90%
of the CMU faces are split into a training and validation set. We ﬁrst trained a
GDBN with 1024 h1 and 256 h2 hidden units on the Caltech training set. We

9

also trained nats No CMU training CMU w/o labels CMU w/ labels Caltech
Train 617?0.4 627?0.5 569?0.6 Caltech Valid 512?1.1 503?1.8 494?1.7 CMU Train
96?0.8 499?0.1 594?0.5 CMU Valid 85?0.5 387?0.3 503?0.7 log Z? 454.6 687.8
694.2
3
u is randomly initialized at ? 30 pixels, scale range from 0.5 to 1.5. OpenCV
detection uses pretrained model from haarcascade frontalface default.xml, scale-
Factor=1.1, minNeighbors=3 and minSize=30. 4

7
Figure 7: Left: Conditioned on diﬀerent v will result in a diﬀerent 4u. Note
that the initial u is exactly the same for two trials. Right: Additional examples.
The only diﬀerence between the top and bottom panels is the conditioned v.
Best viewed in color.

a ConvNet for approximate inference using the Caltech training set and
10% of the CMU training images. Table 2 shows the estimates of the varia-
tional lower-bounds on the average log-density (higher is better) that the GDBN
models assign to the ground-truth cropped face images from the training/test
sets under diﬀerent scenarios. In the left column, the model is only trained on
Caltech faces. Thus it gives very low probabilities to the CMU faces. Indeed,
GDBNs achieve a variational lower-bound of only 85 nats per test image. In the
middle column, we use our approximate inference to estimate the location of
the CMU training faces and further trained the GDBN on the newly localized
faces. This gives a dramatic increase of the model performance on the CMU
Validation set5 , achieving a lowerbound of 387 nats per test image. The right
column gives the best possible results if we can train with the CMU manual
localization labels. In this case, GDBNs achieve a lower-bound of 503 nats. We
used Annealed Importance Sampling (AIS) to estimate the partition function
for the top-layer RBM. Details on estimating the variational lower bound are in
the supplementary materials. Fig. 6(a) further shows samples drawn from the
Caltech trained DBN, whereas Fig. 6(b) shows samples after training with the
CMU dataset using estimated u. Observe that samples in Fig. 6(b) show a more
diverse set of faces. We trained GDBNs using a greedy, layer-wise algorithm of
[1]. For the top layer we use Fast Persistent Contrastive Divergence [32], which
substantially improved generative performance of GDBNs (see supplementary
material for more details). 6.3 Inference with ambiguity Our attentional mech-
anism can also be useful when multiple objects/faces are present in the scene.
Indeed, the posterior p(u—x, v) is conditioned on v, which means that where
to attend is a function of the canonical object v the model has in ?mind? (see
Fig. 2(b)). To explore this, we ﬁrst synthetically generate a dataset by concate-
nating together two faces from the Caltech dataset. We then train approximate
inference ConvNet as in Sec. 4.1 and test on the held-out subjects. Indeed, as
predicted, Fig. 7 shows that depending on which canonical image is conditioned,
the same exact gaze initialization leads to two very diﬀerent gaze shifts. Note
that this phenomenon is observed across diﬀerent scales and location of the ini-
tial gaze. For example, in Fig. 7, right-bottom panel, the initialized yellow box
is mostly on the female?s face to the left, but because the conditioned canonical

10

face v is that of the right male, attention is shifted to the right.

7
Conclusion
In this paper we have proposed a probabilistic graphical model framework
for learning generative models using attention. Experiments on face modeling
have shown that ConvNet based approximate inference combined with HMC
sampling is suﬃcient to explore the complicated posterior distribution. More
importantly, we can generatively learn objects of interest from novel big images.
Future work will include experimenting with faces as well as other objects in
a large scene. Currently the ConvNet approximate inference is trained in a
supervised manner, but reinforcement learning could also be used instead.

Acknowledgements The authors gratefully acknowledge the support and gen-
erosity from Samsung, Google, and ONR grant N00014-14-1-0232. 5 We note
that we still made use of labels coming from the 10% of CMU Multi-PIE training
set in order to pretrain our ConvNet. ”w/o labels” here means that no labels
for the CMU Train/Valid images are given.

8

2 References

[1] G. E. Hinton, S. Osindero, and Y. W. Teh. A fast learning algorithm for deep
belief nets. Neural Computation, 18(7):1527?1554, 2006. [2] R. Salakhutdinov
and G. Hinton. Deep Boltzmann machines. In AISTATS, 2009. [3] Geoﬀrey E.
Hinton, Peter Dayan, and Michael Revow. Modeling the manifolds of images of
handwritten digits. IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks, 8(1):65?74, 1997.
[4] Daniel Zoran and Yair Weiss. From learning models of natural image patches
to whole image restoration. In ICCV. IEEE, 2011. [5] Yoshua Bengio, Li Yao,
Guillaume Alain, and Pascal Vincent. Generalized denoising auto-encoders as
generative models. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 26,
2013.
[6] H. Lee, R. Grosse, R. Ranganath, and A. Y. Ng. Convolutional
deep belief networks for scalable unsupervised learning of hierarchical repre-
sentations. In ICML, pages 609?616, 2009.
[7] Marc?Aurelio Ranzato, Joshua
Susskind, Volodymyr Mnih, and Geoﬀrey Hinton. On Deep Generative Models
with Applications to Recognition. In CVPR, 2011.
[8] Yichuan Tang, Ruslan
Salakhutdinov, and Geoﬀrey E. Hinton. Deep mixtures of factor analysers. In
ICML. icml.cc / Omnipress, 2012. [9] M. I. Posner and C. D. Gilbert. Atten-
tion and primary visual cortex. Proc. of the National Academy of Sciences,
96(6), March 1999. [10] E. A. Buﬀalo, P. Fries, R. Landman, H. Liang, and R.
Desimone. A backward progression of attentional eﬀects in the ventral stream.
PNAS, 107(1):361?365, Jan. 2010. [11] N Kanwisher and E Wojciulik. Visual
attention: Insights from brain imaging. Nature Reviews Neuroscience, 1:91?100,
2000. [12] C. H. Anderson and D. C. Van Essen. Shifter circuits: A computa-
tional strategy for dynamic aspects of visual processing. National Academy of
Sciences, 84:6297?6301, 1987. [13] B. A. Olshausen, C. H. Anderson, and D. C.
Van Essen. A neurobiological model of visual attention and invariant pattern

11

recognition based on dynamic routing of information. The Journal of neuro-
science : the oﬃcial journal of the Society for Neuroscience, 13(11):4700?4719,
[14] Laurenz Wiskott. How does our visual system achieve shift and
1993.
size invariance?, 2004.
[15] S. Chikkerur, T. Serre, C. Tan, and T. Poggio.
What and where: a Bayesian inference theory of attention. Vision Research,
50(22):2233?2247, October 2010. [16] J. K. Tsotsos, S. M. Culhane, W. Y. K.
Wai, Y. H. Lai, N. Davis, and F. Nuﬂo. Modeling visual-attention via selec-
tive tuning. Artiﬁcial Intelligence, 78(1-2):507?545, October 1995.
[17] Hugo
Larochelle and Geoﬀrey E. Hinton. Learning to combine foveal glimpses with a
third-order boltzmann machine. In NIPS, pages 1243?1251. Curran Associates,
Inc., 2010.
[18] D. P. Reichert, P. Seri?s, and A. J. Storkey. A hierarchical
generative model of recurrent object-based attention in the visual cortex. In
ICANN (1), volume 6791, pages 18?25. Springer, 2011. [19] B. Alexe, N. Heess,
Y. W. Teh, and V. Ferrari. Searching for objects driven by context. In NIPS
2012, December 2012. [20] Marc?Aurelio Ranzato. On learning where to look.
arXiv, arXiv:1405.5488, 2014. [21] M. Denil, L. Bazzani, H. Larochelle, and N.
de Freitas. Learning where to attend with deep architectures for image tracking.
Neural Computation, 28:2151?2184, 2012. [22] G. E. Hinton and R. Salakhut-
dinov. Reducing the dimensionality of data with neural networks. Science,
[23] A. Krizhevsky. Learning multiple layers of features
313:504?507, 2006.
from tiny images, 2009.
[24] Graham W. Taylor, Rob Fergus, Yann LeCun,
and Christoph Bregler. Convolutional learning of spatiotemporal features. In
ECCV 2010. Springer, 2010. [25] A. Mohamed, G. Dahl, and G. Hinton. Acous-
tic modeling using deep belief networks. IEEE Transactions on Audio, Speech,
and Language Processing, 2011.
[26] Richard Szeliski. Computer Vision - Al-
gorithms and Applications. Texts in Computer Science. Springer, 2011. [27] S.
Duane, A. D. Kennedy, B. J Pendleton, and D. Roweth. Hybrid Monte Carlo.
Physics Letters B, 195(2):216?222, 1987. [28] R. M. Neal. MCMC using Hamil-
tonian dynamics. in Handbook of Markov Chain Monte Carlo (eds S. Brooks, A.
Gelman, G. Jones, XL Meng). Chapman and Hall/CRC Press, 2010. [29] Simon
Baker and Iain Matthews. Lucas-kanade 20 years on: A unifying framework.
International Journal of Computer Vision, 56:221?255, 2002. [30] Ralph Gross,
Iain Matthews, Jeﬀrey F. Cohn, Takeo Kanade, and Simon Baker. Multi-pie.
Image Vision Comput., 28(5):807?813, 2010. [31] J. P. Lewis. Fast normalized
cross-correlation, 1995. [32] T. Tieleman and G. E. Hinton. Using fast weights
to improve persistent contrastive divergence. In ICML, volume 382, page 130.
ACM, 2009. [33] R. Salakhutdinov and I. Murray. On the quantitative analysis
of deep belief networks. In Proceedings of the Intl. Conf. on Machine Learning,
volume 25, 2008.

9

12

