Analysis of Learning from Positive and Unlabeled

Data

Authored by:

Masashi Sugiyama

Gang Niu

Marthinus C. du Plessis

Abstract

Learning a classiﬁer from positive and unlabeled data is an important
class of classiﬁcation problems that are conceivable in many practical ap-
plications. In this paper, we ﬁrst show that this problem can be solved by
cost-sensitive learning between positive and unlabeled data. We then show
that convex surrogate loss functions such as the hinge loss may lead to a
wrong classiﬁcation boundary due to an intrinsic bias, but the problem
can be avoided by using non-convex loss functions such as the ramp loss.
We next analyze the excess risk when the class prior is estimated from
data, and show that the classiﬁcation accuracy is not sensitive to class
prior estimation if the unlabeled data is dominated by the positive data
(this is naturally satisﬁed in inlier-based outlier detection because inliers
are dominant in the unlabeled dataset). Finally, we provide generalization
error bounds and show that, for an equal number of labeled and unlabeled
samples, the generalization error of learning only from positive and unla-
beled samples is no worse than $2sqrt{2}$ times the fully supervised case.
These theoretical ﬁndings are also validated through experiments.

1 Paper Body

Let us consider the problem of learning a classiﬁer from positive and unlabeled
data (PU classiﬁcation), which is aimed at assigning labels to the unlabeled
dataset [1]. PU classiﬁcation is conceivable in various applications such as land-
cover classiﬁcation [2], where positive samples (built-up urban areas) can be
easily obtained, but negative samples (rural areas) are too diverse to be labeled.
Outlier detection in unlabeled data based on inlier data can also be regarded as
PU classiﬁcation [3, 4]. In this paper, we ﬁrst explain that, if the class prior in
the unlabeled dataset is known, PU classiﬁcation can be reduced to the problem
of cost-sensitive classiﬁcation [5] between positive and unlabeled data. Thus,
in principle, the PU classiﬁcation problem can be solved by a standard cost-
sensitive classiﬁer such as the weighted support vector machine [6]. The goal

1

of this paper is to give new insight into this PU classiﬁcation algorithm. Our
contributions are three folds: ? The use of convex surrogate loss functions such
as the hinge loss may potentially lead to a wrong classiﬁcation boundary being
selected, even when the underlying classes are completely separable. To obtain
the correct classiﬁcation boundary, the use of non-convex loss functions such as
the ramp loss is essential. 1

? When the class prior in the unlabeled dataset is estimated from data,
the classiﬁcation error is governed by what we call the eﬀective class prior that
depends both on the true class prior and the estimated class prior. In addition
to gaining intuition behind the classiﬁcation error incurred in PU classiﬁcation,
a practical outcome of this analysis is that the classiﬁcation error is not sensi-
tive to class-prior estimation error if the unlabeled data is dominated by positive
data. This would be useful in, e.g., inlier-based outlier detection scenarios where
inlier samples are dominant in the unlabeled dataset [3, 4]. This analysis can be
regarded as an extension of traditional analysis of class priors in ordinary classi-
ﬁcation scenarios [7, 8] to PU classiﬁcation. ? We establish generalization error
bounds for PU classiﬁcation. For an?equal number of positive and unlabeled
samples, the convergence rate is no worse than 2 2 times the fully supervised
case. Finally, we numerically illustrate the above theoretical ﬁndings through
experiments.

2
PU classiﬁcation as cost-sensitive classiﬁcation
In this section, we show that the problem of PU classiﬁcation can be cast as
cost-sensitive classiﬁcation. Ordinary classiﬁcation: The Bayes optimal classiﬁer
corresponds to the decision function f (X) ? {1, ?1} that minimizes the expected
misclassiﬁcation rate w.r.t. a class prior of ?: R(f ) := ?R1 (f ) + (1 ? ?)R?1 (f ),
where R?1 (f ) and R1 (f ) denote the expected false positive rate and expected
false negative rate: R?1 (f ) = P?1 (f (X) ?= ?1) and

R1 (f ) = P1 (f (X) ?= 1),
and P1 and P?1 denote the marginal probabilities of positive and negative
samples.
In the empirical risk minimization framework, the above risk is re-
placed with their empirical versions obtained from fully labeled data, leading to
practical classiﬁers [9]. Cost-sensitive classiﬁcation: A cost-sensitive classiﬁer
selects a function f (X) ? {1, ?1} in order to minimize the weighted expected
misclassiﬁcation rate: R(f ) := ?c1 R1 (f ) + (1 ? ?)c?1 R?1 (f ),

(1)
where c1 and c?1 are the per-class costs [5]. Since scaling does not matter in
(1), it is often useful to interpret the per-class costs as reweighting the problem
according to new class priors proportional to ?c1 and (1 ? ?)c?1 . PU classi-
ﬁcation: In PU classiﬁcation, a classiﬁer is learned using labeled data drawn
from the positive class P1 and unlabeled data that is a mixture of positive and
negative samples with unknown class prior ?: PX = ?P1 + (1 ? ?)P?1 . Since
negative samples are not available, let us train a classiﬁer to minimize the ex-
pected misclassiﬁcation rate between positive and unlabeled samples. Since we
do not have negative samples in the PU classiﬁcation setup, we cannot directly
estimate R?1 (f ) and thus we rewrite the risk R(f ) not to include R?1 (f ).

2

More speciﬁcally, let RX (f ) be the probability that the function f (X) gives the
positive label over PX [10]: RX (f ) = PX (f (X) = 1) = ?P1 (f (X) = 1) + (1
? ?)P?1 (f (X) = 1) = ?(1 ? R1 (f )) + (1 ? ?)R?1 (f ). 2

(2)
Then the risk R(f ) can be written as R(f ) = ?R1 (f ) + (1 ? ?)R?1 (f ) =

?R1 (f ) ? ?(1 ? R1 (f )) + RX (f ) = 2?R1 (f ) + RX (f ) ? ?.

(3)
Let ? be the proportion of samples from P1 compared to PX , which is
empirically estimated by n ? n+n? where n and n denote the numbers of positive
and unlabeled samples, respectively. The risk R(f ) can then be expressed as
R(f ) = c1 ?R1 (f ) + cX (1 ? ?)RX (f ) ? ?,

where c1 =
2? ?
and
cX =
1 . 1??
Comparing this expression with (1), we can conﬁrm that the PU classiﬁ-
cation problem is solved by cost-sensitive classiﬁcation between positive and
unlabeled data with costs c1 and cX . Some implementations of support vector
machines, such as libsvm [6], allow for assigning weights to classes. In practice,
the unknown class prior ? may be estimated by the methods proposed in [10,
1, 11]. In the following sections, we analyze this algorithm.

3 Necessity of non-convex loss functions in PU classiﬁcation In this section,
we show that solving the PU classiﬁcation problem with a convex loss function
may lead to a biased solution, and the use of a non-convex loss function is
essential to avoid this problem. Loss functions in ordinary classiﬁcation: We
ﬁrst consider ordinary classiﬁcation problems where samples from both classes
are available. Instead of a binary decision function f (X) ? {?1, 1}, a continuous
decision function g(X) ? R such that sign(g(X)) = f (X) is learned. The loss
function then becomes J0-1 (g) = ?E1 [?0-1 (g(X))] + (1 ? ?)E?1 [?0-1 (?g(X))]
, where Ey is the expectation over Py and ?0-1 (z) is the zero-one loss: { 0 z ¿
0, ?0-1 (z) = 1 z ? 0. Since the zero-one loss is hard to optimize in practice due
to its discontinuous nature, it may be replaced with a ramp loss (as illustrated
in Figure 1): ?R (z) =

1 max(0, min(2, 1 ? z)), 2
giving an objective function of JR (g) = ?E1 [?R (g(X))] + (1 ? ?)E?1 [?R

(?g(X))] .

(4)
To avoid the non-convexity of the ramp loss, the hinge loss is often preferred

in practice: ?H (z) =
1 max(1 ? z, 0), 2
giving an objective of JH (g) = ?E1 [?H (g(X))] + (1 ? ?)E?1 [?H (?g(X))] .
(5)
One practical motivation to use the convex hinge loss instead of the non-
convex ramp loss is that separability (i.e., ming JR (g) = 0) implies ?R (z) =
0 everywhere, and for all values of z for which ?R (z) = 0, we have ?H (z) =

3

0. Therefore, the convex hinge loss will give the same decision boundary as the
non-convex ramp loss in the ordinary classiﬁcation setup, under the assumption
that the positive and negative samples are non-overlapping. 3

?H (z)
?H (z) + ?H (?z)
?R (z) = 21 max(0, min(2, 1?z)) ?H (z) =
1 2
max(0, 1?z)
1
1
?R (z)
?R (z) + ?R (?z)
1 2
?1
?1
1 (a) Loss functions
1
(b) Resulting penalties
Figure 1: ?R (z) denotes the ramp loss, and ?H (z) denotes the hinge loss.
?R (z)+?R (?z) is constant but ?H (z) + ?H (?z) is not and therefore causes
a superﬂuous penalty. Ramp loss function in PU classiﬁcation: An important
question is whether the same interpretation will hold for PU classiﬁcation: can
the PU classiﬁcation problem be solved by using the convex hinge loss? As we
show below, the answer to this question is unfortunately ?no?. In PU classiﬁca-
tion, the risk is given by (3), and its ramp-loss version is given by JPU-R (g) =
2?R1 (f ) + RX (f ) ? ? = 2?E1 [?R (g(X))] + [?E1 [?R (?g(X))] + (1 ? ?)E?1
[?R (?g(X))]] ? ? = ?E1 [?R (g(X))] + ?E1 [?R (g(X)) + ?R (?g(X))] + (1 ?
?)E?1 [?R (?g(X))] ? ?,

(6) (7) (8)
where (6) comes from (3) and (7) is due to the substitution of (2). Since the
ramp loss is symmetric in the sense of ?R (?z) + ?R (z) = 1, (8) yields JPU-R
(g) = ?E1 [?R (g(X))] + (1 ? ?)E?1 [?R (?g(X))] .

(9)
(9) is essentially the same as (4), meaning that learning with the ramp loss
in the PU classiﬁcation setting will give the same classiﬁcation boundary as in
the ordinary classiﬁcation setting. For non-convex optimization with the ramp
loss, see [12, 13]. Hinge loss function in PU classiﬁcation: On the other hand,
using the hinge loss to minimize (3) for PU learning gives JPU-H (g) = 2?E1
[?H (g(X))] + [?E1 [?H (?g(X))] + (1 ? ?)E?1 [?H (?g(X))]] ? ?, (10) = ?E1 [?H
(g(X))] + (1 ? ?)E?1 [?H (?g(X))] + ?E1 [?H (g(X)) + ?H (?g(X))] ??. {z } —
{z } — Ordinary error term, cf. (5)

Superﬂuous penalty
We see that the hinge loss has a term that corresponds to (5), but it also
has a superﬂuous penalty term (see also Figure 1). This penalty term may
cause an incorrect classiﬁcation boundary to be selected. Indeed, even if g(X)

4

perfectly separates the data, it may not minimize JPU-H (g) due to the super-
ﬂuous penalty. To obtain the correct decision boundary, the loss function should
be symmetric (and therefore non-convex). Alternatively, since the superﬂuous
penalty term can be evaluated, it can be subtracted from the objective func-
tion. Note that, for the problem of label noise, an identical symmetry condition
has been obtained [14]. Illustration: We illustrate the failure of the hinge loss
on a toy PU classiﬁcation problem with class conditional densities of: ( ) ( )
p(x—y = 1) = N ?3, 12 and p(x—y = 1) = N 3, 12 , where N (?, ? 2 ) is a
normal distribution with mean ? and variance ? 2 . The hinge-loss objective
function for PU classiﬁcation, JPU-H (g), is minimized with a model of g(x) =
wx + b (the expectations in the objective function is computed via numerical
integration). The optimal decision 4

0.01
1
p(x)
0.4
0.2
Optimal Hinge Loss
Misclassiﬁcation rate
Threshold
p(x—y=1) p(x—y=?1)
0.5 0 ?0.5 ?1
0
?6
?3
0 x
3
6
0.1
0.3
0.5 ?
0.7
0.9
0.008
Optimal Hinge
0.006 0.004 0.002 0 0.1
0.3
0.5 ?
0.7
0.9
(a) Class-conditional densities of (b) Optimal threshold and threshold (c)
The misclassiﬁcation rate for the problem using the hinge loss the optimal and
hinge loss case

Figure 2: Illustration of the failure of the hinge loss for PU classiﬁcation.
The optimal threshold and the threshold estimated by the hinge loss diﬀer
signiﬁcantly (Figure 2(b)), causing a diﬀerence in the misclassiﬁcation rates

5

(Figure 2(c)). The threshold for the ramp loss agrees with the optimal threshold.
threshold and the threshold for the hinge loss is plotted in Figure 2(b) for a range
of class priors. Note that the threshold for the ramp loss will correspond to the
optimal threshold. From this ﬁgure, we note that the hinge-loss threshold diﬀers
from the optimal threshold. The diﬀerence is especially severe for larger class
priors, due to the fact that the superﬂuous penalty is weighted by the class prior.
When the class-prior is large enough, the large hinge-loss threshold causes all
samples to be positively labeled. In such a case, the false negative rate is R1 =
0 but the false positive rate is R?1 = 1. Therefore, the overall misclassiﬁcation
rate for the hinge loss will be 1 ? ?.

4
Eﬀect of inaccurate class-prior estimation
To solve the PU classiﬁcation problem by cost-sensitive learning described
in Section 2, the true class prior ? is needed. However, since it is often unknown
in practice, it needs to be estimated, e.g., by the methods proposed in [10, 1,
11]. Since many of the estimation methods are biased [1, 11], it is important to
understand the inﬂuence of inaccurate class-prior estimation on the classiﬁcation
performance. In this section, we elucidate how the error in the estimated class
prior ? b aﬀects the classiﬁcation accuracy in the PU classiﬁcation setting. Risk
with true class prior in ordinary classiﬁcation: In the ordinary classiﬁcation
scenarios with positive and negative samples, the risk for a classiﬁer f on a
dataset with class prior ? is given as follows ([8, pp. 26?29] and [7]): R(f, ?) =
?R1 (f ) + (1 ? ?)R?1 (f ). The risk for the optimal classiﬁer according to the
class prior ? is therefore, R? (?) = min R(f, ?) f ?F

Note that R? (?) is concave, since it is the minimum of a set of functions
that are linear w.r.t. ?. This is illustrated in Figure 3(a). Excess risk with class
prior estimation in ordinary classiﬁcation: Suppose we have a classiﬁer fb that
minimizes the risk for an estimated class prior ? b: fb := arg min R(f, ? b). f
?F

The risk when applying the classiﬁer fb on a dataset with true class prior
? is then on the line tangent to the concave function R? (?) at ? = ? b, as
illustrated in Figure 3(a): b R(?) = ?R1 (fb) + (1 ? ?)R?1 (fb). The function
fb is suboptimal at ?, and results in the excess risk [8]: b E? = R(?) ? R(?). 5

1 0.95 0.9
b R? (?) = R(?)
Risk
Eﬀective prior ? e
b R(?)
0.2
? = 0.95 ? = 0.9 ? = 0.7 ? = 0.5
0.8
E? 0.1
0.7 0.6 0.5 0.4 0.3 0.2 0.1
?
? e
0 0.2

6

1
0.3
0.4
Class prior
0.5 0.6 0.7 Estimated prior ? b
0.8
0.9 0.95 1
(b) The eﬀective class prior ? e vs. the estimated class prior ? b for diﬀerent

true class priors ?.

(a) Selecting a classiﬁer to minimize (11) and applying it to a dataset with

class prior ? leads to an excess risk of E? .

Figure 3: Learning in the PU framework with an estimated class prior ? b
is equivalent to selecting a classiﬁer which minimizes the risk according to an
eﬀective class prior ? e. (a) The diﬀerence between the eﬀective class prior ?
e and the true class prior ? causes an excess risk E? . (b) The eﬀective class
prior ? e depends on the true class prior ? and the estimated class prior ? b.
Excess risk with class prior estimation in PU classiﬁcation: We wish to select a
classiﬁer that minimizes the risk in (3). In practice, however, we only know an
estimated class prior ? b. Therefore, a classiﬁer is selected to minimize R(f ) =
2b ? R1 (f ) + RX (f ) ? ? b.

(11)
Expanding the above risk based on (2) gives R(f ) = 2b ? R1 (f ) + ?(1 ?
R1 (f )) + (1 ? ?)R?1 (f ) ? ? b = (2b ? ? ?) R1 (f ) + (1 ? ?)R?1 (f ) +
? ? ? b. Thus, the estimated class prior aﬀects the risk with respect to 2b ?
? ? and 1 ? ?. This result immediately shows that PU classiﬁcation cannot
be performed when the estimated class prior is less than half of the true class
prior: ? b ? 12 ?. We deﬁne the eﬀective class prior ? e so that 2b ? ? ?
and 1 ? ? are normalized to sum to one: 2b ??? 2b ??? = . 2b ???+1?? 2b
? ? 2? + 1 Figure 3(b) shows the proﬁle of the eﬀective class prior ? e for
diﬀerent ?. The graph shows that when the true class prior ? is large, ? e tends
to be ﬂat around ?. When the true class prior is known to be large (such as
the proportion of inliers in inlier-based outlier detection), a rough class-prior
estimator is suﬃcient to have a good classiﬁcation performance. On the other
hand, if the true class prior is small, PU classiﬁcation tends to be hard and an
accurate class-prior estimator is necessary. ? e=

We also see that when the true class prior is large, overestimation of the class
prior is more attenuated. This may explain why some class-prior estimation
methods [1, 11] still give a good practical performance in spite of having a
positive bias.

5 Generalization error bounds for PU classiﬁcation In this section, we analyze
the generalization error for PU classiﬁcation, when training samples are clearly
not identically distributed. More speciﬁcally, we derive error bounds for the
classiﬁcation function f (x) of form f (x) =

n ?
?
?i k(xi , x) +

7

i=1
where x1 , . . . , xn are positive training data and A=
{(?1 , . . . , ?n , ?1? , . . . , ?n? ? )
n ?
?j? k(x?j , x),
j=1
x?1 , . . . , x?n?
are positive and negative test data. Let
— x1 , . . . , xn ? p(x — y = +1), x?1 , . . . , x?n? ? p(x)} 6
be the set of all possible optimal solutions returned by the algorithm given
some training data and test data according to p(x — y = +1) and p(x). Then
deﬁne the constants C? = sup??A,x1 ,...,xn ?p(x—y=+1),x?1 ,...,x? ? ?p(x) n
)1/2 (? ?n? ? ? n n n? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? k(xi , xi? ) + 2 , x ) , ? k(x ? ? ? ? k(x
, x ) + ? ? ? ? ? i i i i j j j j j,j =1 j j i,i =1 i=1 j=1 ? Ck = supx?Rd k(x, x),
and deﬁne the function class F = {f : x 7?

n ?
?
?i k(xi , x) +
i=1
x1 , . . . , xn ? p(x — y =
n ?
?j? k(x?j , x) — ? ? A,
j=1 +1), x?1 , . . . , x?n?
Let ?? (z) be a surrogate loss for the zero-one loss ? ?0 ?? (z) = 1 ? z/? ?

1

(12)
? p(x)}.
if z ¿ ?, if 0 ¡ z ? ?, if z ? 0.
For any ? ¿ 0, ?? (z) is lower bounded by ?0-1 (z) and approaches ?0-1 (z)
as ? approaches zero. Moreover, let e (x)) = 2 ?0-1 (yf (x)) and ?e? (yf (x))
= 2 ?? (yf (x)). ?(yf y+3 y+3 Then we have the following theorems (proofs
are provided in Appendix A). Our key idea is to decompose the generalization
error as [ ] [ ] e (x)) + E p(x,y) ?(yf e (x)) , E p(x,y) [?0-1 (yf (x))] = ? ? E
p(x—y=+1) ?(f where ? ? := p(y = 1) is the true class prior of the positive
class. Theorem 1. Fix f ? F , then, for any 0 ¡ ? ¡ 1, with probability at least
1 ? ? over the repeated sampling of {x1 , .
, xn } and {(x?1 , y1? ), .
.
, (x?n? , yn? ? )} for evaluating the empirical error,1 ( ? )? n? n 1 ?e ?
.
?? ? e ? 1 ln(2/?) ? ? +? E p(x,y) [?0-1 (yf (x))] ? ? ?(yj f (xj )) ? ?(f
(xi )) + . ? n j=1 n i=1 2 2 n n (13) Theorem 2. Fix ? ¿ 0, then, for any
0 ¡ ? ¡ 1 with probability at least 1 ? ? over the repeated sampling of {x1 ,
, (x?n? , yn? ? )} for evaluating the
.
empirical error, every f ? F satisﬁes ( ? ) n? n 1 ?e ? ?? ? e ? 2 C? Ck ?
E p(x,y) [?0-1 (yf (x))] ? ? ?? (yj f (xj )) ? ?? (f (xi )) + ? + ? ? n j=1 n
i=1 ? n n ? ( ? ) 1 ln(2/?) ? ? +? . + 2 2 n n? ? ? In both theorems,
the generalization error bounds are of order O(1/ n + 1/ n? ). This order is
optimal for PU classiﬁcation where we have n i.i.d. data from a distribution

, xn } and {(x?1 , y1? ), .

.

.

.

.

.

.

8

and n? i.i.d. data from ? another distribution. The error bounds for fully ?
supervised classiﬁcation, by assuming these n + n ? data are all i.i.d., would
be of order O(1/ n + n ). However, this assumption is unreasonable ? for PU
classiﬁcation, and we cannot train fully supervised classiﬁers ? using these n +
n samples. ? ? Although the ? orders (and the ? losses) diﬀer slightly, O(1/
n + 1/ n ) for PU classiﬁcation is no worse than 2 2 times O(1/ n + n? ) for
fully supervised classiﬁcation (assuming n and n? are equal). To the best of our
knowledge, no previous work has provided such generalization error bounds for
PU classiﬁcation. 1 The empirical error that we cannot evaluate in practice is
in the left-hand side of (13), and the empirical error and conﬁdence terms that
we can evaluate in practice are in the right-hand side of (13).

7
Table 1: Misclassiﬁcation rate (in percent) for PU classiﬁcation on the USPS

dataset. The best, and equivalent by 95% t-test, is indicated in bold. ?

0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 0.9 0.95 Ramp Hinge Ramp Hinge Ramp Hinge Ramp Hinge
Ramp Hinge Ramp Hinge 3.36 4.40 4.85 4.78 5.48 5.18 4.16 4.00 2.68 9.86 1.71
4.94 5.15 6.20 6.96 8.67 7.22 8.79 5.90 14.60 4.12 9.92 2.80 4.94 3.49 5.52 4.72
8.08 5.02 8.52 4.06 16.51 2.89 9.92 2.12 4.94 1.68 2.83 2.05 4.00 2.21 3.99 2.00
3.03 1.70 9.92 1.42 4.94 5.21 7.42 7.22 11.16 7.46 12.04 6.16 19.78 4.36 9.92 3.21
4.94 11.47 11.61 19.87 19.59 22.58 22.94 15.13 19.83 8.86 9.92 5.29 4.94 1.89 3.55
2.55 4.61 2.64 3.70 2.31 2.49 1.78 9.92 1.39 4.94 3.98 5.09 4.81 7.00 4.75 6.85
3.74 11.34 2.79 9.92 2.11 4.94 1.22 2.76 1.60 3.86 1.73 3.56 1.61 2.24 1.38 9.92
1.13 4.94

0 vs 1 0 vs 2 0 vs 3 0 vs 4 0 vs 5 0 vs 6 0 vs 7 0 vs 8 0 vs 9 3
5
5
Positive loss Negative loss
5
Hinge Ramp
Positive
0
x2
x2
x2
Loss
2 0
0
1
Negative 0 ?2
?1
0 z
1
(a) Loss functions
2
?5 ?6
?4

9

?2
0 x
2
4
?5 ?6
6
1
?4
?2
0 x1
2
4
6
?5 ?6
?4
?2
0 x1
2
4
6
(b) Class prior is ? = 0.2 (c) Class prior is ? = 0.6 (d) Class prior is ? =

0.9. .

Figure 4: Examples of the classiﬁcation boundary for the ?0? vs. ?7? digits,
obtained by PU learning. The unlabeled dataset and the underlying (latent)
class labels are given. Since discriminant function for the hinge loss case is
constant 1 when ? = 0.9, no decision boundary can be drawn and all negative
samples are misclassiﬁed.

6
Experiments
In this section, the experimentally compare the performance of the ramp
loss and the hinge loss in PU classiﬁcation (weighting was performed w.r.t. the
true class prior and the ramp loss was optimized with [12]). We used the USPS
dataset, with the dimensionality reduced to 2 via principal component analy-
sis to enable illustration. 550 samples were used for the positive and mixture
datasets. From the results in Table 1, it is clear that the ramp loss gives a much
higher classiﬁcation accuracy than the hinge loss, especially for large class pri-
ors. This is due to the fact that the eﬀect of the superﬂuous penalty term in
(10) becomes larger since it scales with ?. When the class prior is large, the
classiﬁcation accuracy for the hinge loss is often close to 1 ? ?. This can be
explained by (10): collecting the terms for the positive expectation, we get an
eﬀective loss function for the positive samples (illustrated in Figure 4(a)). When
? is large enough, the positive loss is minimized, giving a constant 1. The mis-
classiﬁcation rate becomes 1 ? ? since it is a combination of the false negative
rate and the false positive rate according to the class prior. Examples of the
discrimination boundary for digits ?0? vs. ?7? are given in Figure 4. When
the class-prior is low (Figure 4(b) and Figure 4(c)) the misclassiﬁcation rate of

10

the hinge loss is slightly higher. For large class-priors (Figure 4(d)), the hinge
loss causes all samples to be classiﬁed as positive (inspection showed that w =
0 and b = 1).

7
Conclusion
In this paper we discussed the problem of learning a classiﬁer from posi-
tive and unlabeled data. We showed that PU learning can be solved using a
cost-sensitive classiﬁer if the class prior of the unlabeled dataset is known. We
showed, however, that a non-convex loss must be used in order to prevent a
superﬂuous penalty term in the objective function. In practice, the class prior
is unknown and estimated from data. We showed that the excess risk is actually
controlled by an eﬀective class prior which depends on both the estimated class
prior and the true class prior. Finally, generalization error bounds for the prob-
lem were provided. Acknowledgments MCdP is supported by the JST CREST
program, GN was supported by the 973 Program No. 2014CB340505 and MS
is supported by KAKENHI 23120004.

8

2 References

[1] C. Elkan and K. Noto. Learning classiﬁers from only positive and unlabeled
data. In Proceedings of the 14th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on
Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD2008), pages 213?220, 2008.
[2]
W. Li, Q. Guo, and C. Elkan. A positive and unlabeled learning algorithm
for one-class classiﬁcation of remote-sensing data. IEEE Transactions on Geo-
science and Remote Sensing, 49(2):717?725, 2011.
[3] S. Hido, Y. Tsuboi, H.
Kashima, M. Sugiyama, and T. Kanamori.
Inlier-based outlier detection via
direct density ratio estimation. In F. Giannotti, D. Gunopulos, F. Turini, C.
Zaniolo, N. Ramakrishnan, and X. Wu, editors, Proceedings of IEEE Interna-
tional Conference on Data Mining (ICDM2008), pages 223? 232, Pisa, Italy,
Dec. 15?19 2008. [4] C. Scott and G. Blanchard. Novelty detection: Unlabeled
data deﬁnitely help. In Proceedings of the Twelfth International Conference on
Artiﬁcial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS2009), pages 464?471, Clearwa-
ter Beach, Florida USA, Apr. 16-18 2009.
[5] C. Elkan. The foundations of
cost-sensitive learning. In Proceedings of the Seventeenth International Joint
Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence (IJCAI2001), pages 973?978, 2001. [6] C.C.
Chang and C.J. Lin. LIBSVM: A library for support vector machines. ACM
Transactions on Intelligent Systems and Technology, 2:27:1?27:27, 2011.
[7]
H.L. Van Trees. Detection, Estimation, and Modulation Theory, Part I. Detec-
tion, Estimation, and Modulation Theory. John Wiley and Sons, New York,
[8] R. Duda, P. Hart, and D. Stork. Pattern Classiﬁcation.
NY, USA, 1968.
John Wiley & Sons, 2nd edition, 2001.
[9] V. Vapnik. The Nature of Sta-
tistical Learning Theory. Springer, 2000.
[10] G. Blanchard, G. Lee, and C.
Scott. Semi-supervised novelty detection. The Journal of Machine Learning
Research, 11:2973?3009, 2010.
[11] M. C. du Plessis and M. Sugiyama. Class

11

prior estimation from positive and unlabeled data. IEICE Transactions on In-
[12] R. Collobert, F.H. Sinz,
formation and Systems, E97-D:1358?1362, 2014.
J. Weston, and L. Bottou. Trading convexity for scalability.
In Proceedings
of the 23rd International Conference on Machine learning (ICML2006), pages
201?208, 2006.
[13] S. Suzumura, K. Ogawa, M. Sugiyama, and I. Takeuchi.
Outlier path: A homotopy algorithm for robust SVM. In Proceedings of 31st
International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML2014), pages 1098? 1106,
Beijing, China, Jun. 21?26 2014. [14] A. Ghosh, N. Manwani, and P. S. Sastry.
Making risk minimization tolerant to label noise. CoRR, abs/1403.3610, 2014.
[15] M. Mohri, A. Rostamizadeh, and A. Talwalkar. Foundations of Machine
Learning. MIT Press, 2012.

9

12

