Large-Margin Convex Polytope Machine

Authored by:

Ling Huang
J. D. Tygar

Peter L. Bartlett
Alex Kantchelian

Michael C. Tschantz
Anthony D. Joseph

Abstract

We present the Convex Polytope Machine (CPM), a novel non-linear
learning algorithm for large-scale binary classiﬁcation tasks. The CPM
ﬁnds a large margin convex polytope separator which encloses one class.
We develop a stochastic gradient descent based algorithm that is amenable
to massive datasets, and augment it with a heuristic procedure to avoid
sub-optimal local minima. Our experimental evaluations of the CPM
on large-scale datasets from distinct domains (MNIST handwritten digit
recognition, text topic, and web security) demonstrate that the CPM
trains models faster, sometimes several orders of magnitude, than state-
of-the-art similar approaches and kernel-SVM methods while achieving
comparable or better classiﬁcation performance. Our empirical results
suggest that, unlike prior similar approaches, we do not need to control
the number of sub-classiﬁers (sides of the polytope) to avoid overﬁtting.

1 Paper Body

Many application domains of machine learning use massive data sets in dense
medium-dimensional or sparse high-dimensional spaces. These domains also re-
quire near real-time responses in both the prediction and the model training
phases. These applications often deal with inherent nonstationarity, thus the
models need to be constantly updated in order to catch up with drift. Today, the
de facto algorithm for binary classiﬁcation tasks at these scales is linear SVM.
Indeed, since Shalev-Shwartz et al. demonstrated both theoretically and exper-
imentally that large margin linear classiﬁers can be eﬃciently trained at scale
using stochastic gradient descent (SGD), the Pegasos [1] algorithm has become a
standard building tool for the machine learning practitioner. We propose a novel
algorithm for Convex Polytope Machine (CPM) separation exhibiting superior
empirical performance to existing algorithms, with running times on a large

1

dataset that are up to ﬁve orders of magnitude faster. We conjecture that worst
case bounds are independent of the ? number K of faces of the convex polytope
and state a theorem of loose upper bounds in terms of K. In theory, as the VC
dimension of d-dimensional linear separators is d + 1, a linear classiﬁer in very
high dimension d is expected to have a considerable expressiveness power. This
argument is often understood as ?everything is separable in high dimensional
spaces; hence linear separation is good enough?. However, in practice, deployed
systems rarely use a single naked linear separator. One explanation for this gap
between theory and practice is that while the probability of a single hyperplane
perfectly separating both classes in very high dimensions is high, the resulting
classiﬁer margin might be very small. Since the classiﬁer margin also accounts
for the generalization power, we might experience poor future classiﬁcation per-
formance in this scenario. Figure 1a provides a two-dimensional example of
a data set that has a small margin when using a single separator (solid line)
despite being linearly separable and intuitively easily classiﬁed. The intuition
that the data is easily classiﬁed comes from the data naturally separating into
three clusters 1

with two of them in the positive class. Such clusters can form due to the

positive instances being generated by a collection of diﬀerent processes.

A B + -
+ + -
2
1? 1
(a) Instances are perfectly linearly separable (solid line), although with small
margin due to positive instances (A & B) having conﬂicting patterns. We can
obtain higher margin by separately training two linear sub-classiﬁers (dashed
lines) on left and right clusters of positive instances, each against all the negative
instances, yielding a prediction value of the maximum of the sub-classiﬁers.

(b) The worst-case margin is insensitive to wiggling of sub-classiﬁers having
non-minimal margin. Sub-classiﬁer 2 has the smallest margin, and sub-classiﬁer
1 is allowed to freely move without aﬀecting ? WC . For comparison, the largest-
margin solution 10 is shown (dashed lines).

Figure 1: Positive (?) and negative (?) instances in continuous two dimen-
sional feature space. As Figure 1a shows, a way of increasing the margins is to
introduce two linear separators (dashed lines), one for each positive cluster. We
take advantage of this intuition to design a novel machine learning algorithm
that will provide larger margins than a single linear classiﬁer while still enjoying
much of the computational eﬀectiveness of a simple linear separator. Our algo-
rithm learns a bounded number of linear classiﬁers simultaneously. The global
classiﬁer will aggregate all the sub-classiﬁers decisions by taking the maximum
sub-classiﬁer score. The maximum aggregation has the eﬀect of assigning a
positive point to a unique sub-classiﬁer. The model class we have intuitively
described above corresponds to convex polytope separators. In Section 2, we
present related work in convex polytope classiﬁers and in Section 3, we deﬁne
the CPM optimization problem and derive loose upper bounds. In Section 4,
we discuss a Stochastic Gradient Descent-based algorithm for the CPM and

2

perform a comparative evaluation in Section 5.

2
Related Work
Fischer focuses on ﬁnding the optimal polygon in terms of the number of
misclassiﬁed points drawn independently from an unknown distribution using
an algorithm with a running time of more than O(n12 ) where n is the number
of sample points [2]. We instead focus on ﬁnding good, not optimal, polygons
that generalize well in practice despite having fast running times. Our focus on
generalization leads us to maximize the margin, unlike this work, which actually
minimizes it to make their proofs easier. Takacs proposes algorithms for training
convex polytope classiﬁers based on the smooth approximation of the maximum
function [3]. While his algorithms use smooth approximation during training, it
uses the original formula during prediction, which introduces a gap that could
deteriorate the accuracy. The proposed algorithms achieve similar classiﬁcation
accuracy to several nonlinear classiﬁers, including KNN, decision tree and kernel
SVM. However, the training time of the algorithms is often much longer than
those nonlinear classiﬁers (e.g., an order of magnitude longer than ID3 algorithm
and eight times longer than kernel SVM on CHESS DATASET), diminishing
the motivation to use the proposed algorithms in realistic setting. Zhang et
al. propose an Adaptive Multi-hyperplane Machine (AMM) algorithm that is
fast during both training and prediction, and capable of handling nonlinear
classiﬁcation problems [4]. They develop an iterative algorithm based on the
SGD method to search for the number of hyperplanes and train the model.
Their experiments on several large data sets show that AMM is nearly as fast
as the state-of-theart linear SVM solver, and achieves classiﬁcation accuracy
somewhere between linear and kernel 2

SVMs. Manwani and Sastry propose two methods for learning polytope
classiﬁers, one based on logistic function [5], and another based on perceptron
method [6], and propose alternating optimization algorithms to train the clas-
siﬁers. However, they only evaluate the proposed methods with a few small
datasets (with no more than 1000 samples in each), and do not compare them
to other widely used (nonlinear) classiﬁers (e.g., KNN, decision tree, SVM). It is
unclear how applicable these algorithms are to large-scale data. Our work makes
three signiﬁcant contributions over their work, including 1) deriving the formu-
lation from a large-margin argument and obtaining a regularization term which
is missing in [6], 2) safely restricting the choice of assignments to only positive
instances, leading to a training time optimization heuristic and 3) demonstrat-
ing higher performance on non-synthetic, large scale datasets, when using two
CPMs together.

3
Large-Margin Convex Polytopes
In this section, we derive and discuss several alternative optimization prob-
lems for ﬁnding a largemargin convex polytope which separates binary labeled
points of Rd . 3.1

Problem Setup and Model Space
Let D = {(xi , y i )}1?i?n be a binary labeled dataset of n instances, where

3

x ? Rd and y ? {?1, 1}. For the sake of notational brevity, we assume that
the xi include a constant unitary component corresponding to a bias term. Our
prediction problem is to ﬁnd a classiﬁer c : Rd ? {?1, 1} such that c(xi ) is a
good estimator of y i . To do so, we consider classiﬁers constructed from convex
K-faced polytope separators for a ﬁxed positive integer K. Let PK be the model
space of convex K-faced polytope separators:

K?d d
PK = f : R ? R f (x) = max (Wx)k , W ? R 1?k?K For each such function f
in PK , we can get a classiﬁer cf such that cf (x) is 1 if f (x) ¿ 0 and ?1 otherwise.
This model space corresponds to a shallow single hidden layer neural network
with a max aggregator. Note that when K = 1, P1 is simply the space of all
linear classiﬁers. Importantly, when K ? 2, elements of PK are not guaranteed
to have additive inverses in PK . As a consequence, the labels y = ?1 and y =
+1 are not interchangeable. Geometrically, the negative class remains enclosed
within the convex polytope while the positive class lives outside of it, hence the
label asymmetry. To construct a classiﬁer without label asymmetry, we can use
two polytopes, one with the negative instances on the inside the polytope to get
a classiﬁcation function f? and one with the positive instances on the inside to
get f+ . From these two polytopes, we construct the classiﬁer cf? ,f+ where
cf? ,f+ (x) is 1 if f? (x) ? f+ (x) ¿ 0 and ?1 otherwise. To better understand
the nature of the faces of a single polytope, for a given polytope W and a data
point x, we denote by zW (x) the index of the maximum sub-classiﬁer for x:
zW (x) = argmax(Wx)k 1?k?K

We call zW (x) the assigned sub-classiﬁer for instance x. When clear from
context, we drop W from zW . We also use the notation Wk to designate the
k-th row of W, which corresponds to the k-th face of the polytope, or the k-th
sub-classiﬁer. Hence, Wz(x) identiﬁes the separator assigned to x. We now
pursue a geometric large-margin based approach for formulating the concrete
optimization problem. To simplify the notations and without loss of generality,
we suppose that W is rownormalized such that ——Wk —— = 1 for all k. We
also initially suppose our dataset is perfectly separable by a K-faced convex
polytope. 3.2

Margins for Convex Polytopes
When K = 1, the problem reduces to ﬁnding a good linear classiﬁer and only
a single natural margin ? of the separator exists [7]: ?W = min y i W1 xi 1?i?n

3
Maximizing ?W yields the well known (linear) Support Vector Machine.
However, multiple notions of margin for a K-faced convex polytope with K ?
2 exist. We consider two. WC Let the worst case margin ?W be the smallest
margin of any point to the polytope. Over all the K sub-classiﬁers, we ﬁnd the
one with the minimal margin to the closest point assigned to it: WC ?W = min
y i Wz(xi ) xi = min min y i Wk xi i 1?i?n

1?k?K i:z(x )=k
The worst case margin is very similar to the linear classiﬁer margin but
suﬀers from an important drawback. Maximizing ? WC leaves K ? 1 sub-
classiﬁers wiggling while over-focusing on the subclassiﬁer with the smallest

4

margin. See Figure 1b for a geometrical intuition. Thus, we instead focus on
the total margin, which measures each sub-classiﬁer?s margin with respect T to
just its assigned points. The total margin ?W is the sum of the K sub-classiﬁers
margins: K X T ?W = min y i Wk xi i k=1

i:z(x )=k
The total margin gives the same importance to the K sub-classiﬁer margins.

3.3

Maximizing the Margin
We now turn to the question of maximizing the margin. Here, we provide an
overview of a smoothed but non-convex optimization problem for maximizing
the total margin. The appendix provides a step-by-step derivation. We would
like to optimize the margin by solving the optimization problem T max ?W
subject to kW1 k = ? ? ? = kWK k = 1 W

Introducing one additional variable ?k per classiﬁer, problem (1) is equivalent
to: K X ?k subject to ?i, ?z(xi ) ? y i Wz(xi ) xi max W,? k=1 ?1 ¿ 0, . . . ,
?K ¿ 0 kW1 k = ? ? ? = kWK k = 1 Considering the unnormalized rows Wk
/?k , we obtain the following equivalent formulation: K X 1 max subject to ?i,
1 ? y i Wz(xi ) xi W kWk k

(1)
(2)
(3)
k=1
When y = ?1 and z(xi ) satisfy the margin constraint in (3), we have that
the constraint holds for every sub-classiﬁer k since y i Wk xi is minimal at k =
z(xi ). Thus, when y = ?1, we can enforce the constraint for all k. We can also
smooth the objective into a convex, deﬁned everywhere one by minimizing the
sum of the inverse squares of the terms instead of maximizing the sum of the
terms. We obtain the following smoothed problem: K X min kWk k2 subject
to ?i : y i = ?1, ?k ? {1, . . . , K}, 1 + Wk xi ? 0 (4) W i i k=1 i ?i : y = +1,
1 ? Wz(x ) x ? 0 (5) The objective of the above program is now the familiar L2
regularization term kWk2 . The negative instances constraints (4) are convex
(linear functions), but the positive terms (5) result in non-convex constraints
because of the instance-dependent assignment z. As for the Support Vector
Machine, we can introduce n slack variables ?i and a regularization factor C ¿ 0
for the common case of noisy, non-separable data. Hence, the practical problem
becomes: n X min kWk2 + C ?i subject to ?i : y i = ?1, ?k ? {1, . . . , K}, 1
+ Wk xi ? ?i ? 0 (6) W,? i=1 ?i : y i = +1, 1 ? Wz(xi ) xi ? ?i ? 0 Following
the same steps, we obtain the following problem for maximizing the worst-case
margin. The only diﬀerence is the regularization term in the objective function
which becomes maxk kWk k2 instead of kWk2 . 4

Discussion. The goal of our relaxation is to demonstrate that our solution
involves two intuitive steps, including (1) assigning positive instances to sub-
classiﬁers, and (2) solving a collection of SVM-like sub-problems. While our
solution taken as a whole remains non-convex, this decomposition isolates the
non-convexity to a single intuitive assignment problem that is similar to clus-
tering. This isolation enables us to use intuitive heuristics or clustering-like al-

5

gorithms to handle the nonconvexity. Indeed, in our ﬁnal form of Eq. (6), if the
optimal assignment function z(xi ) of positive instances to sub-classiﬁers were
known and ﬁxed, the problem would be reduced to a collection of perfectly in-
dependent convex minimization problems. Each such sub-problem corresponds
to a classical SVM deﬁned on all negative instances and the subset of positive
instances assigned by z(xi ). It is in this sense that our approach optimizes the
total margin. 3.4

Choice of K, Generalization Bound for CPM
Assuming we can eﬃciently solve this optimization problem, we would need
to adjust the number K of faces and the degree C of regulation. The following
result gives a preliminary generalization bound for the CPM. For B1 , .
.
, Bk ? 0, let FK,B be the following subset of the set PK of convex polytope
separators:

.

.

.

.

.

.

.}, B1 , .

FK,B = f : Rd ? R f (x) = max (Wx)k , W ? RK?d , ?k, kWk k ? Bk 1?k?K
Theorem 1. There exists some constant A ¿ 0 such that for all distributions
P over X ? {?1, 1}, K in {1, 2, 3, .
, Bk ? 0, and ? ¿ 0,
with probability at least 1 ? ? over the training set (x1 , y1 ), .
, (xn ,
yn ) ? P , any f in FK,B is such that: r P n 1X ln (2/?) k Bk P (yf (x) ?
0) ? max(0, 1 ? yi f (xi )) + A ? + n i=1 2n n This is a uniform bound on
the 0-1 risk of classiﬁers in FK,B . It shows that with high probability, the risk
is bounded by the empirical hinge loss plus a capacity term that decreases in
n?1/2 ? and is P proportional to the sum of the sub-classiﬁer norms. Note that
as we have kW k ? KkWk, k k ? the capacity term is essentially equivalent to
KkWk. As a comparison, the generalization error has been previously shown to
be proportional to KkWk in [4, Thm. 2]. In practice, this bound is very loose
as it does not explain the observed absence of over ﬁtting as K gets large. We
experimentally demonstrate this phenomenon in Section 5. We conjecture that
there exists a bound that must be independent of K altogether. The proof of
Theorem 1 relies on a result due to Bartlett et al. complexities. We ﬁrst prove
that the Rademacher complexity of FK,B is in P on Rademacher ? O( k Bk /
n). We then invoke Theorem 7 of [8] to show our result. The appendix contains
the full proof.

4
SGD-based Learning
In this section, we present a Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD) based learn-
ing algorithm for approximately solving the total margin maximization problem
(6). The choice of SGD is motivated by two factors. First, we would like our
learning technique to eﬃciently scale to several million instances of sparse high
dimensional space. The sample-iterative nature of SGD makes it a very suitable
candidate to this end [9]. Second, the optimization problem we are solving is
non-convex. Hence, there are potentially many local optima which might not
result in an acceptable solution. SGD has recently been shown to work well
for such learning problems [10] where we might not be interested in a global
optimum but only a good enough local optimum from the point of view of the
learning problem. Problem (6) can be expressed as an unconstrained minimiza-
tion problem as follow: min W

6

K X X i:y i =?1 k=1
[1 + Wk xi ]+ +
X
[1 ? Wz(xi ) xi ]+ + ?kWk2
i:y i =+1
where [x]+ = max(0, x) and ? ¿ 0. This form reveals the strong similar-
ity with optimizing K unconstrained linear SVMs [1]. The diﬀerence is that
although each sub-classiﬁer is trained on 5

.

.

.

.

all the negative instances, positive instances are associated to a unique sub-
classiﬁer. From the unconstrained form, we can derive the stochastic gradient
descent Algorithm 1. For the positive instances, we isolate the task of ﬁnding the
assigned sub-classiﬁer z to a separate procedure ASSIGN. We use the Pegasos
inverse schedule ?t = 1/(?t). Because the optimization problem (6) is non-
Algorithm 1 Stochastic gradient descent alconvex, a pure SGD approach could
get stuck in a gorithm for solving problem (6).
function SGD T RAIN(D, ?,
T, (?t ), h) local optimum. We found that pure SGD gets stuck Initialize W
? RK?d , W ? 0 in low-quality local optima in practice. These opfor t ? 1,
.
, T do tima are characterized by assigning most of the posPick (x, y)
if y = ?1 then In
? D itive instances to a small number of sub-classiﬁers.
this conﬁguration, the remaining sub-classiﬁers for k ? 1, .
, K do serve
no purpose.
Intuitively, the algorithm clusif Wk x ¿ ?1 then tered the data
into large ?super-clusters? ignoring Wk ? Wk ? ?t x the more subtle sub-
clusters comprising the larger super-clusters. The large clusters represent an
apelse if y = +1 then pealing local optima since breaking one down into z ?
argmaxk Wk x sub-clusters often requires transitioning through a if Wz x ¡ 1
then patch of lower accuracy as the sub-classiﬁers realign z ? ASSIGN(W, x,
h) themselves to the new cluster boundaries. We may Wz ? Wz + ?t x view
the local optima as the algorithm underﬁtting the data by using too simple of
a model. In this case, W ? (1 ? ?t ?)W the algorithm needs encouragement
to explore more return W complex clusterings. With this intuition in mind, we
add a term encouraging the algorithm to explore higher entropy conﬁgurations
of the sub-classiﬁers. To do so, we use the entropy of the random variable Z =
argmaxk Wk x where x ? D+ , a distribution deﬁned on the set of all positive
instances as follows. Let nk be the number of positive instances assigned to
sub-classiﬁer k, and n be thetotal number of positive instances. We deﬁne D+
as the empirical distribution on nn1 , nn2 , .
, nnk . The entropy is zero
when the same classiﬁer ﬁres for all positive instances, and maximal at log2 K
when every classiﬁer ﬁres on a K ?1 fraction of the positive instances. Thus,
maximizing the entropy encourages the algorithm to break down large clusters
into smaller clusters of near equal size. We use this notion of entropy in our
heuristic procedure for assignment, described in Algorithm 2. ASSIGN takes a
predeﬁned minimum entropy level h ? 0 and compensates for disparities in how
positive instances are assigned to sub-classiﬁers, where the disparity is measured
by entropy. When the entropy is above h, there is no need to change the natural
argmaxk Wk x assignment. Conversely, if the current entropy is below h, then
we pick an assignment which is guaranteed to increase the entropy. Thus, when

.

.

7

h = 0, there is no adjustment made. It keeps a dictionary UNADJ mapping
the previous points it has encountered to the unadjusted assignment that the
natural argmax assignment would had made at the time of encountering the
point. We write UNADJ + (x, k) to denote the new dictionary U such that
U [v] is equal to k if v = x and to UNADJ[v] otherwise. Dictionary UNADJ
keeps track of the assigned positives per sub-classiﬁers, and serves to estimate
the current entropy in the conﬁguration without needing to recompute every
prior point?s assignment.

5
Evaluation
We use four data sets to evaluate the CPM: (1) an MNIST dataset consist-
ing of labeled handwritten digits encoded in 28 ? 28 gray scale pictures [11,
12] (60,000 training and 10,000 testing instances); (2) an MNIST8m dataset
consisting of 8,100,000 pictures obtained by applying various random deforma-
tions to MNIST training instances MNIST [13]; (3) a URL dataset [12] used
for malicious URL detection [14] (1.1 million training and 1.1 million testing
instances in a very large dimensional space of more than 2.3 million features);
and (4) the RCV1-bin dataset [12] corresponding to a binary classiﬁcation task
(separating corporate and economics categories from government and markets
categories [15]) deﬁned over the RCV1 dataset of news articles (20,242 training
and 677,399 testing instances). Since our main focus is on binary classiﬁcation,
for the two MNIST datasets we evaluate 6

distinguishing 2?s from any other digit, which we call MNIST-2 and MNIST8m-

2. With thirty times more testing than training data, the RCV1-bin dataset is
a good benchmark for over ﬁtting issues. 5.1

Parameter Tuning
All four datasets have well deﬁned Algorithm 2 Heuristic maximum assign-
ment algorithm. training and testing subsets and to The input is the current
weight matrix W, positive intune each algorithms meta-parameters stance x,
and the desired assignment entropy h ? 0. (? and h for the CPM, C and ? for
Initialize UNADJ? {} RBF-SVM, and ? for AMM), we ranfunction ASSIGN(W,
x, h) domly select a ﬁxed validation subset kunadj ? argmaxk Wk x from the
training set (10,000 instances if ENTROPY(UNADJ + (x, kunadj )) ? h then
for MNIST-2/MNIST8m-2; 1,000 inkadj ? kunadj stances for RCV1-bin/URL).
else For the CPM, we use a double-sided hcur ? ENTROPY(UNADJ) CPM as
described in section 3.1, where Kinc ? {k: ENTROPY(UNADJ +(x, k)) ¿ hcur
} both CPMs share the same metakadj ? argmax Wk x parameters. We start
by ﬁxing a numk?Kinc ber of iterations T and a number of UNADJ ? UNADJ
+ (x, kunadj ) hyperplanes K which will result in a return kadj reasonable ex-
ecution time, eﬀectively treating these parameters as a computational budget,
and we experimentally demonstrate that increasing either K or T always results
in a decrease of the testing error. Once these are selected, we let h = 0 and
select the best ? in {T ?1 , 10 ? T ?1 , . . . , 104 ? T ?1 }. We then choose
, log 9K/10}, eﬀectively performing a
h from {0, log K/10, log 2K/10, .
one-round coordinate descent on ?, h. To test the eﬀectiveness of our empirical
entropy-driven assignment procedure, we mute the mechanism by also testing

.

.

8

with h = 0. The AMM has three parameters to adjust (excluding T and the
equivalent of K), two of which control the weight pruning mechanism and are
left set at default values. We only adjust ?. Contrary to the CPM, we do not
observe AMM testing error to strictly decrease with the number of iterations T
. We observe erratic behavior and thus we manually select the smallest T for
which the mean validation error appears to reach a minimum. For RBF-SVM,
we use the LibSVM [16] implementation and perform the usual grid search on
the parameter space. 5.2

Performance
Unless stated otherwise, we used one core of an Intel Xeon E5 (3.2Ghz,
64GB RAM) for experiments. Table 1 presents the results of experiments and
shows that the CPM achieves comparable, and at times better, classiﬁcation
accuracy than the RBF-SVM, while working at a relatively small and constant
computational budget. For the CPM, T was up to 32 million and K ranged from
10 to 100. For AMM, T ranged from 500,000 to 36 million. Across methods,
the worst execution time is for the MNIST8m-2 task, where a 512 core parallel
implementation of RBF-SVM runs in 2 days [17], and our sequential single-core
algorithm runs in less than 5 minutes. The AMM has signiﬁcantly larger errors
and/or execution times. For small training sets such as MNIST-2 and RCV1-bin,
we were not able to achieve consistent results, regardless of how we set T and ?,
and we conjecture that this is a consequence of the weight pruning mechanism.
The results show that our empirical entropydriven assignment procedure for
the CPM leads to better solutions for all tasks. In the RCV1-bin and MNIST-
2 tasks, the improvement in accuracy from using a tuned entropy parameter
is 31% and 21%, respectively, which is statistically signiﬁcant. We use the
MNIST8m-2 task to the study the eﬀects of tuning T and K on the CPM. We
ﬁrst choose a grid of values for T, K and for a ﬁxed regularization factor C and
h = 0, we train a model for each point of the parameter grid, and evaluate its
performance on the testing set. Note that for C 1 to remain constant, we adjust
? = CT . We run each experiment 5 times and only report the mean accuracy.
Figure 2 shows how this mean error rate evolves as a function of both T and K.
We observe two phenomena. First, for any value K ¿ 1, the error rate decreases
with T . Second, for large enough values of T , the error rate decreases when K
increases. These two experimental 7

MNIST-2
CPM CPM h=0 RBF-SVM AMM
MNIST8m-2
URL
RCV1-bin
Error
Time
Error
Time
Error
0.38 ? 0.028 0.46 ? 0.026 0.35 2.83 ? 1.090
2m 2m 7m 1m

9

0.30 ? 0.023 0.35 ? 0.034 0.43? 0.38 ? 0.024
4m 4m 2d?? 1hr
1.32 ? 0.012 3m 1.35 ? 0.029 3m Timed out in 2 weeks 2.20 ? 0.067 5m
* for unadjusted parameters [17]
Time
Error
Time
2.82 ? 0.059 3.69 ? 0.156 3.7 15.40 ? 6.420
2m 2m 46m 1m
** running on 512 processors [17]
Table 1: Error rates and running times (include both training and testing
periods) for binary tasks. Means and standard deviations for 5 runs with random
shuﬄing of the training set. observations validate our treatment of both K and
T as budgeting parameters. The observation about K also provides empirical
evidence of our conjecture that large values of K do not lead to overﬁtting. 5.3

Multi-class Classiﬁcation
We performed a preliminary multiclass classiﬁcation experiment using the
MNIST/MNIST8m datasets. There are several approaches for building a multi-
class classiﬁer from a binary classiﬁer [18, 19, 20]. Weused a one-vs-one approach
where we train 10 2 = 45 one-vs-one classiﬁers and classify by a majority vote
rule with random tie breaking. While this approach is not optimal, it provides
an approximation of achievable performance. For MNIST, comparing CPM to
RBF-SVM, we achieve a testing error of 1.61 ? 0.019 and for the CPM and of
1.47 for RBF-SVM, with running times of 7m20s and 6m43s, respectively. On
MNIST8m we achieve an error of 1.03 ? 0.074 for CPM (2h3m) and Figure
2: Error rate on MNIST8m-2 as a function of 0.67 (8 days) for RBF-SVM as
reported of K, T . C = 0.01 and h = 0 are ﬁxed. by [13].

6
Conclusion
We propose a novel algorithm for Convex Polytope Machine (CPM) separa-
tion that provides larger margins than a single linear classiﬁer, while still enjoy-
ing the computational eﬀectiveness of a simple linear separator. Our algorithm
learns a bounded number of linear classiﬁers simultaneously. On large datasets,
the CPM outperforms RBF-SVM and AMM, both in terms of running times
and error rates. Furthermore, by not pruning the number of sub-classiﬁers used,
CPM is algorithmically simpler than AMM. CPM avoids such complications by
having little tendency to overﬁt the data as the number K of sub-classiﬁers
increases, shown empirically in Section 5.2.

2 References

[1] Shai Shalev-Shwartz, Yoram Singer, and Nathan Srebro. Pegasos: Primal
Estimated subGrAdient SOlver for SVM. In Proceedings of the 24th Interna-
tional Conference on Machine Learning, ICML ?07, pages 807?814, New York,

10

NY, USA, 2007. ACM. [2] Paul Fischer. More or less eﬃcient agnostic learn-
ing of convex polygons.
In Proceedings of the Eighth Annual Conference on
Computational Learning Theory, COLT ?95, pages 337?344, New York, NY,
USA, 1995. ACM. [3] Gabor Takacs. Smooth maximum based algorithms for
classiﬁcation, regression, and collaborative ﬁltering. Acta Technica Jaurinensis,
3(1), 2010. [4] Zhuang Wang, Nemanja Djuric, Koby Crammer, and Slobodan
Vucetic. Trading representability for scalability: adaptive multi-hyperplane ma-
chine for nonlinear classiﬁcation. In Proceed8

ing of the 17th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge dis-
covery and data mining (KDD 2011), 2011.
[5] Naresh Manwani and P. S.
Sastry. Learning polyhedral classiﬁers using logistic function. In Proceedings of
the 2nd Asian Conference on Machine Learning (ACML 2010), Tokyo, Japan,
2010. [6] Naresh Manwani and P. S. Sastry. arXiv:1107.1564, 2013.

Polyceptron:
A polyhedral learning algorithm.
[7] Corinna Cortes and Vladimir Vapnik. Support-vector networks. Machine
learning, 20(3):273? 297, 1995.
[8] Peter L. Bartlett and Shahar Mendelson.
Rademacher and Gaussian complexities: Risk bounds and structural results.
J. Mach. Learn. Res., 3:463?482, March 2003.
[9] L?eon Bottou. Large-scale
machine learning with stochastic gradient descent. In Proceedings of COMP-
STAT?2010, pages 177?186. Springer, 2010. [10] Geoﬀrey E Hinton. A practical
guide to training restricted Boltzmann machines. In Neural Networks: Tricks
of the Trade, pages 599?619. Springer, 2012. [11] Yann LeCun, Corinna Cortes,
and Christopher J.C. Burges. MNIST dataset, 1998.
[12] LibSVM datasets.
datasets/.

http://www.csie.ntu.edu.tw/?cjlin/libsvmtools/
[13] St?ephane Canu and Leon Bottou. Training invariant support vector
In Large Scale Kernel Machines, pages
machines using selective sampling.
301?320. MIT, 2007.
[14] Justin Ma, Lawrence K. Saul, Stefan Savage, and
Geoﬀrey M. Voelker. Beyond blacklists: Learning to detect malicious web sites
from suspicious URLs.
In Proceedings of the 15th ACM SIGKDD Interna-
tional Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, KDD ?09, pages
1245?1254, New York, NY, USA, 2009. ACM. [15] David D. Lewis, Yiming
Yang, Tony G. Rose, and Fan Li. RCV1: A new benchmark collection for text
categorization research. J. Mach. Learn. Res., 5:361?397, December 2004. [16]
Chih-Chung Chang and Chih-Jen Lin. Libsvm: A library for support vector
machines. ACM Trans.
Intell. Syst. Technol., 2(3):27:1?27:27, May 2011.
[17] Zeyuan Allen Zhu, Weizhu Chen, Gang Wang, Chenguang Zhu, and Zheng
Chen. P-packSVM: Parallel primal gradient descent kernel SVM. In Data Min-
ing, 2009. ICDM?09. Ninth IEEE International Conference on, pages 677?686.
IEEE, 2009.
[18] Alina Beygelzimer, John Langford, Yuri Lifshits, Gregory
Sorkin, and Alex Strehl. Conditional probability tree estimation analysis and
algorithms.
In Proceedings of the Twenty-Fifth Conference on Uncertainty
in Artiﬁcial Intelligence, UAI ?09, pages 51?58, Arlington, Virginia, United
States, 2009. AUAI Press. [19] Alina Beygelzimer, John Langford, and Bianca
Zadrozny. Weighted one-against-all. In Proceedings of the 20th National Con-

11

ference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence - Volume 2, AAAI?05, pages 720?725. AAAI
Press, 2005.
[20] Thomas G. Dietterich and Ghulum Bakiri. Solving multi-
class learning problems via errorcorrecting output codes. J. Artif. Int. Res.,
2(1):263?286, January 1995.

9

12

