Recursive Training of 2D-3D Convolutional
Networks for Neuronal Boundary Prediction

Authored by:

H. Sebastian Seung

Kisuk Lee

Aleksandar Zlateski

Vishwanathan Ashwin

Abstract

Eﬀorts to automate the reconstruction of neural circuits from 3D elec-
tron microscopic (EM) brain images are critical for the ﬁeld of connec-
tomics. An important computation for reconstruction is the detection of
neuronal boundaries. Images acquired by serial section EM, a leading 3D
EM technique, are highly anisotropic, with inferior quality along the third
dimension. For such images, the 2D max-pooling convolutional network
has set the standard for performance at boundary detection. Here we
achieve a substantial gain in accuracy through three innovations. Follow-
ing the trend towards deeper networks for object recognition, we use a
much deeper network than previously employed for boundary detection.
Second, we incorporate 3D as well as 2D ﬁlters, to enable computations
that use 3D context. Finally, we adopt a recursively trained architec-
ture in which a ﬁrst network generates a preliminary boundary map that
is provided as input along with the original image to a second network
that generates a ﬁnal boundary map. Backpropagation training is accel-
erated by ZNN, a new implementation of 3D convolutional networks that
uses multicore CPU parallelism for speed. Our hybrid 2D-3D architecture
could be more generally applicable to other types of anisotropic 3D im-
ages, including video, and our recursive framework for any image labeling
problem.

1 Paper Body

Neural circuits can be reconstructed by analyzing 3D brain images from elec-
tron microscopy (EM). Image analysis has been accelerated by semiautomated
systems that use computer vision to reduce the amount of human labor required
[1, 2, 3]. However, analysis of large image datasets is still laborious [4], so it
is critical to increase automation by improving the accuracy of computer vi-
sion algorithms. A variety of machine learning approaches have been explored

1

for the 3D reconstruction of neurons, a problem that can be formulated as im-
age segmentation or boundary detection [5, 6]. This paper focuses on neuronal
boundary detection in images from serial section EM, the most widespread kind
of 3D EM [7]. The technique starts by cutting and collecting ultrathin (30 to
100 nm) sections of brain tissue. A 2D image is acquired from each section,
and then the 2D images are aligned. The spatial resolution of the resulting 3D
image stack along the z direction (perpendicular to the cutting plane) is set by
the thickness of the sections. This is generally much worse than the resolution
that EM yields in the xy plane. In addition, alignment errors may corrupt the
image along the z direction. Due to these issues with the z direction of the image
stack [6, 8], most existing analysis pipelines begin with 2D processing and only
later transition to 3D. The stages are: (1) neuronal boundary detection within
each 2D image, (2) segmentation of neuron cross sections within each 2D image,
and (3) 3D reconstruction of individual neurons by linking across multiple 2D
images [1, 9]. 1

Boundary detection in serial section EM images is done by a variety of algo-
rithms. Many algorithms were compared in the ISBI?12 2D EM segmentation
challenge, a publicly available dataset and benchmark [10]. The winning sub-
mission was an ensemble of max-pooling convolutional networks (ConvNets)
created by IDSIA [11]. One of the ConvNet architectures shown in Figure 1
(N4) is the largest architecture from [11], and serves as a performance baseline
for the research reported here. We improve upon N4 by adding several new
elements (Fig. 1): Increased depth Our VD2D architecture is deeper than N4
(Figure 1), and borrows other nowstandard practices from the literature, such
as rectiﬁed linear units (ReLUs), small ﬁlter sizes, and multiple convolution
layers between pooling layers. VD2D already outperforms N4, without any use
of 3D context. VD2D is motivated by the principle ?the deeper, the better,?
which has become popular for ConvNets applied to object recognition [12, 13].
3D as well as 2D When human experts detect boundaries in EM images, they
use 3D context to disambiguate certain locations. VD2D3D is also able to use
3D context, because it contains 3D ﬁlters in its later layers. ConvNets with 3D
ﬁlters were previously applied to block face EM images [2, 3, 14]. Block face
EM is another class of 3D EM techniques, and produces nearly isotropic images,
unlike serial section EM. VD2D3D also contains 2D ﬁlters in its earlier layers.
This novel hybrid use of 2D and 3D ﬁlters is suited for the highly anisotropic
nature of serial section EM images. Recursive training of ConvNets VD2D and
VD2D3D are concatenated to create an extremely deep network. The output of
VD2D is a preliminary boundary map, which is provided as input to VD2D3D
in addition to the original image (Fig. 1). Based on these two inputs, VD2D3D
is trained to compute the ﬁnal boundary map. Such ?recursive? training has
previously been applied to neural networks for boundary detection [8, 15, 16],
but not to ConvNets. ZNN for 3D deep learning Very deep ConvNets with 3D
ﬁlters are computationally expensive, so an eﬃcient software implementation
is critical. We trained our networks with ZNN (https: //github.com/seung-
lab/znn-release, [17]), which uses multicore CPU parallelism for speed. ZNN is
one of the few deep learning implementations that is well-optimized for 3D.

2

2D 2DConvNet ConvNet VD2D VD2D
1st input 193x193x5
boundary prediction 1x1x1
2D-3D ConvNet VD2D3D 2nd input 85x85x5
initialize with learned 2D representations
1st stage
tanh Pool1 tanh Pool2 tanh 48 2x2x1 48 2x2x1 48 Conv1 Conv2 Conv3

4x4x1 5x5x1 4x4x1

N4
Input 95x95x1
VD2D
Input 109x109x1
Conv1a 3x3x1
Conv1b 3x3x1
Conv1c 2x2x1
Input 85x85x5
Conv1a 3x3x1
Conv1b 3x3x1
Conv1c 2x2x1
VD2D3D
recursive input 85x85x5
ReLU 24
ReLU 24
tanh 24
Pool1 2x2x1
Pool3 tanh Pool4 2x2x1 48 2x2x1 Conv4 4x4x1
Conv2a 3x3x1
Conv2b 3x3x1
Conv2a 3x3x1
Conv2b 3x3x1
ReLU 36
tanh 36
Pool2 2x2x1
2nd stage
tanh 200 Conv5 3x3x1
Softmax 2
Conv3a 3x3x1
Conv3b 3x3x1
Pool3 ReLU 2x2x1 60 Conv4a 3x3x1
Conv3a 3x3x1
Conv3b 3x3x1
Conv4a 3x3x2
ReLU 48
Output 1x1x1
tanh 48
Pool3 2x2x2

3

ReLU 60
tanh Pool4 ReLU 2x2x1 200 60 Conv4b Conv5 3x3x1 3x3x1
Conv4b Conv4c 3x3x2 3x3x2 ReLU 60
ReLU 100
Softmax 2 Output 1x1x1
Output 1x1x1
Softmax 2
Figure 1: An overview of our proposed framework (top) and model archi-
tectures (bottom). The number of trainable parameters in each model is 220K
(N4), 230K (VD2D), 310K (VD2D3D). 2

While we have applied the above elements to serial section EM images, they
are likely to be generally useful for other types of images. The hybrid use of
2D and 3D ﬁlters may be useful for video, which can also be viewed as an
anisotropic 3D image. Previous 3D ConvNets applied to video processing [18,
19] have used 3D ﬁlters exclusively. Recursively trained ConvNets are poten-
tially useful for any image labeling problem. The approach is very similar to re-
current ConvNets [20], which iterate the same ConvNet. The recursive approach
uses diﬀerent ConvNets for the successive iterations. The recursive approach
has been justiﬁed in several ways. In MRF/CRF image labeling, it is viewed as
the sequential reﬁnement of the posterior probability of a pixel being assigned
a label, given both an input image and recursive input from the previous step
[21]. Another viewpoint on recursive training is that statistical dependencies
in label (category) space can be directly modeled from the recursive input [15].
From the neurobiological viewpoint, using a preliminary boundary map for an
image to guide the computation of a better boundary map for the image can
be interpreted as employing a top-down or attentional mechanism. We expect
ZNN to have applications far beyond the one considered in this paper. ZNN
can train very large networks, because CPUs can access more memory than
GPUs. Task parallelism, rather than the SIMD parallelism of GPUs, allows for
eﬃcient training of ConvNets with arbitrary topology. A self-tuning capability
automatically optimizes each layer by choosing between direct and FFT-based
convolution. FFT convolution may be more eﬃcient for wider layers or larger
ﬁlter size [22, 23]. Finally, ZNN may incur less software development cost, owing
to the relative ease of the generalpurpose CPU programming model. Finally, we
applied our ConvNets to images from a new serial section EM dataset from the
mouse piriform cortex. This dataset is important to us, because we are inter-
ested in conducting neuroscience research concerning this brain region. Even to
those with no interest in piriform cortex, the dataset could be useful for research
on image segmentation algorithms. Therefore we make the annotated dataset
publicly available (http://seunglab.org/data/).

2
Dataset and evaluation
Images of mouse piriform cortex The datasets described here were acquired
from the piriform cortex of an adult mouse prepared with aldehyde ﬁxation and
reduced osmium staining [24]. The tissue was sectioned using the automatic tape
collecting ultramicrotome (ATUM) [25] and sections were imaged on a Zeiss ﬁeld

4

emission scanning electron microscope [26]. The 2D images were assembled into
3D stacks using custom MATLAB routines and TrakEM2, and each stack was
manually annotated using VAST (https://software.rc.fas.harvard.edu/ lichtman/vast/,
[25]) (Figure 2). Then each stack was checked and corrected by another anno-
tator. The properties of the four image stacks are detailed in Table 1. It should
be noted that image quality varies across the stacks, due to aging of the ﬁeld
emission source in the microscope. In all experiments we used stack1 for test-
ing, stack2 and stack3 for training, and stack4 as an additional training data
for recursive training.

Figure 2: Example dataset (stack1, Table 1) and results of each architecture

on stack1. 3

Name Resolution (nm3 ) Dimension (voxel3 ) # samples Usage
Table 1: Piriform cortex datasets stack1 stack2 stack3 7 ? 7 ? 40 7 ? 7 ?
40 7 ? 7 ? 40 255 ? 255 ? 168 512 ? 512 ? 170 512 ? 512 ? 169 10.9M 44.6 M
44.3 M Test Training Training

stack4 10 ? 10 ? 40 256 ? 256 ? 121 7.9 M Training (extra)
Pixel error We use softmax activation in the output layer of our networks to
produce per-pixel real-valued outputs between 0 and 1, each of which is inter-
preted as the probability of an output pixel being boundary, or vice versa. This
real-valued ?boundary map? can be thresholded to generate a binary bound-
ary map, from which the pixel-wise classiﬁcation error is computed. We report
the best classiﬁcation error obtained by optimizing the binarization threshold
with line search. Rand score We evaluate 2D segmentation performance with
the Rand scoring system [27, 28]. Let nij denote the number of pixels simulta-
neously in the ith segment of the proposal segmentation and the j th segment
of the ground truth segmentation. The Rand merge score and the Rand split
score P 2 P 2 ij nij ij nij Rand Rand Vmerge = P P , Vsplit = P P . 2 2 i(
j( j nij ) i nij ) are closer to one when there are fewer merge and split errors,
respectively. The Rand F-score is the Rand Rand and Vsplit . harmonic mean
of Vmerge To compute the Rand scores, we need to ﬁrst obtain 2D neuronal
segmentation based on the realvalued boundary map. To this end, we apply
two segmentation algorithms with diﬀerent levels of sophistication: (1) simple
thresholding followed by computing 2D connected components, and (2) mod-
iﬁed graph-based watershed algorithm [29]. We report the best Rand F-score
obtained by optimizing parameters for each algorithm with line search, as well
as the precision-recall curve for the Rand scores.

3
Training with ZNN
ZNN [17] was built for 3D ConvNets. 2D convolution is regarded as a special
case of 3D convolution, in which one of the three ﬁlter dimensions has size 1.
For the details on how ZNN implements task parallelism on multicore CPUs, we
refer interested readers to [17]. Here we describe only aspects of ZNN that are
helpful for understanding how it was used to implement the ConvNets of this
paper. Dense output with maximum ﬁltering In object recognition, a ConvNet
is commonly applied to produce a single output value for an entire input image.
However, there are many applications in which ?dense output? is required, i.e.,

5

the ConvNet should produce an output image with the same resolution as the
original input image. Such applications include boundary detection [11], image
labeling [30], and object localization [31]. ZNN was built from the ground up
for dense output and also for dense feature maps.1 ZNN employs max-ﬁltering,
which slides a window across the image and applies the maximum operation
to the window (Figure 3). Max-ﬁltering is the dense variant of max-pooling.
Consequently all feature maps remain intact as dense 3D volumes during both
forward and backward passes, making them straightforward for visualization
and manipulation. On the other hand, all ﬁltering operations are sparse, in
the sense that the sliding window samples sparsely from a regularly spaced set
of voxels in the image (Figure 3). ZNN can control the spacing/sparsity of
any ﬁltering operation, either convolution or max-ﬁltering. ZNN can eﬃciently
compute the dense output of a sliding window max-pooling ConvNet by making
ﬁlter sparsity depend on the number of prior max-ﬁlterings. More speciﬁcally,
each max-ﬁltering 1 Feature maps with the same resolution as the original input
image. See Figure 5 for example. Note that the feature maps shown in Figure
5 keep the original resolution even after a couple of max-pooling layers.

4
Convolution
Max-Pool
Convolution
Convolution
Max-Filter
Sparse Convolution
Figure 3: Sliding window max-pooling ConvNet (left) applied on three color-
coded adjacent input windows producing three outputs. Equivalent outputs
produced by a max-ﬁltering ConvNet with sparse ﬁlters (right) applied on a
larger window. Computation is minimized by reusing the intermediate values
for computing multiple outputs (as color coded).

increases the sparsity of all subsequent ﬁlterings by a factor equal to the size
of the max-pooling window. This approach, which we employ for the paper, is
also called ?skip-kernels? [31] or ?ﬁlter rarefaction? [30], and is equivalent in
its results to ?max-fragmentation-pooling? [32, 33]. Note however that ZNN
is more general, as the sparsity of ﬁlters need not depend on max-ﬁltering, but
can be controlled independently. Output patch training Training in ZNN is
based on loss computed over a dense output patch of arbitrary size. The patch
can be arbitrarily large, limited only by memory. This includes the case of a
patch that spans the entire image [30, 33]. Although large patch sizes reduce
the computational cost per output pixel, neighboring pixels in the patch may
provide redundant information. In practice, we choose an intermediate output
patch size.

4
Network architecture
N4 As a baseline for performance comparisons, we adopted the largest 2D
ConvNet architecture (named N4) from Cires?an et al. [11] (Figure 1). VD2D
The architecture of VD2D (?Very Deep 2D?) is shown in Figure 1. Multiple

6

convolution layers are between each max-pooling layer. All convolution ﬁlters
are 3?3?1, except that Conv1c uses a 2 ? 2 ? 1 ﬁlter to make the ?ﬁeld of
view? or ?receptive ﬁeld? for a single output pixel have an odd-numbered size
and therefore centerable around the output pixel. Due to the use of smaller
ﬁlters, the number of trainable parameters in VD2D (230K) is roughly the
same as in the shallower N4 (220K). VD2D3D The architecture of VD2D3D
(?Very Deep 2D-3D?) is initially identical to VD2D (Figure 1), except that
later convolution layers switch to 3 ? 3 ? 2 ﬁlters. This causes the number
of trainable parameters to increase, so we compensate by trimming the size of
Conv4c to just 100 feature maps. The 3D ﬁlters in the later layers should enable
the network to use 3D context to detect neuronal boundaries. The use of 2D
ﬁlters in the initial layers makes the network faster to run and train. Recursive
training It is possible to apply VD2D3D by itself to boundary detection, giving
the raw image as the only input. However, we use a recursive approach in which
VD2D3D receives an extra input, the output of VD2D. As we will see below,
this produces a signiﬁcant improvement in performance. It should be noted that
instead of providing the recursive input directly to VD2D3D, we added new
layers 2 dedicated to processing it. This separate, parallel processing stream for
recursive input joins the main stream at Conv1c, allowing for more complex,
highly nonlinear interaction between the low-level features and the contextual
information in the recursive input. 2

These layers are identical to Conv1a, Conv1b, and Conv1c.
5
5
Training procedures
Networks were trained using backpropagation with the cross-entropy loss
function. We ﬁrst trained VD2D, and then trained VD2D3D. The 2D layers of
VD2D3D were initialized using trained weights from VD2D. This initialization
meant that our recursive approach bore some similarity to recurrent ConvNets,
in which the ﬁrst and second stage networks are constrained to be identical [20].
However, we did not enforce exact weight sharing, but ﬁne-tuned the weights
of VD2D3D. Output patch As mentioned earlier, training with ZNN is done by
dense output patch-based gradient update with per-pixel loss. During training,
an output patch of speciﬁed size is randomly drawn from the training stacks at
the beginning of each forward pass. Class rebalancing In dense output patch-
based training, imbalance between the number of training samples in diﬀerent
classes (e.g. boundary/non-boundary) can be handled by either sampling a
balanced number of pixels from an output patch, or by diﬀerentially weighting
the per-pixel loss [30]. In our experiment, we adopted the latter approach (loss
weighting) to deal with the high imbalance between boundary and non-boundary
pixels. Data augmentation We used the same data augmentation method used
in [11], randomly rotating and ﬂipping 2D image patches. Hyperparameter We
always used the ﬁxed learning rate of 0.01 with the momentum of 0.9. When
updating weights we divided the gradient by the total number of pixels in an
output patch, similar to the typical minibatch averaging. We ﬁrst trained N4
with an output patch of size 200 ? 200 ? 1 for 90K gradient updates. Next,

7

we trained VD2D with 150 ? 150 ? 1 output patches, reﬂecting the increased
size of model compared to N4. After 60K updates, we evaluated the trained
VD2D on the training stacks to obtain preliminary boundary maps, and started
training VD2D3D with 100?100?1 output patches, again reﬂecting the increased
model complexity. We trained VD2D3D for 90K updates.
In this recursive
training stage we additionally used stack4 to prevent VD2D3D from being overly
dependent on the good-quality boundary maps for training stacks. It should
be noted that stack4 has slightly lower xy-resolution than other stacks (Table
1), which we think is helpful in terms of learning multi-scale representation.
Our proposed recursive framework is diﬀerent from the training of recurrent
ConvNets [20] in that recursive input is not dynamically produced by the ﬁrst
ConvNet during training, but evaluated before and being ﬁxed throughout the
recursive training stage. However, it is also possible to further train the ﬁrst
ConvNet even after evaluating its preliminary output as recursive input to the
second ConvNet. We further trained VD2D for another 30K updates while
VD2D3D is being trained. We report the ﬁnal performance of VD2D after a
total of 90K updates. We also replaced the initial VD2D boundary map with
the ﬁnal one when evaluating VD2D3D results. With ZNN, it took two days to
train both N4 and VD2D for 90K updates, and three days to train VD2D3D
for 90K updates.

6
Results
In this section, we show both quantitative and qualitative results obtained
by the three architectures shown in Figure 1, namely N4, VD2D, and VD2D3D.
The pixel-wise classiﬁcation error of each model on test set was 10.63% (N4),
9.77% (VD2D), and 8.76% (VD2D3D). Quantitative comparison Figure 4 com-
pares the result of each architecture on test set (stack1), both quantitatively
and qualitatively. The leftmost bar graph shows the best 2D Rand F-score of
each model obtained by 2D segmentation with (1) simpler connected compo-
nent clustering and (2) more sophisticated watershed-based segmentation. The
middle and rightmost graphs show the precision-recall curve of each model for
the Rand scores obtained with the connected component and watershed-based
segmentation, respectively. We observe that VD2D performs signiﬁcantly bet-
ter than N4, and also VD2D3D outperforms VD2D by a signiﬁcant margin in
terms of both best Rand F-score and overall precision-recall curve. Qualitative
comparison Figure 2 shows the visualization of boundary detection results of
each model on test set, along with the original EM images and ground truth
boundary map. We observe that false detection of boundary on intracellular
regions was signiﬁcantly reduced in VD2D3D, 6

Rand score (connected component)
0.7
Connected component
image data
Watershed
0.6 0.6
ground-truth

8

Rand score (watershed)
0.8
0.8
0.85
1 0.9
0.9
0.9
0.8
1
Rand merge score
Rand F-score
0.95
Best Rand F-score N4 VD2D VD2D3D
Rand merge score
1
0.7
N4 VD2D VD2D3D
0.7
0.8
0.9
Rand split score
N4
1
0.6 0.6
VD2D
N4 VD2D VD2D3D
0.7
0.8
0.9
Rand split score
1
VD2D3D
Figure 4: Quantitative (top) and qualitative (middle and bottom) evaluation

of results.

which demonstrates the eﬀectiveness of the proposed 2D-3D ConvNet com-
bined with recursive approach. The middle and bottom rows in Figure 4 show
some example locations in test set where both 2D models (N4 and VD2D)
failed to correctly detect the boundary, or erroneously detected false boundaries,
whereas VD2D3D correctly predicted on those ambiguous locations. Visual
analysis on the boundary detection results of each model again demonstrates
the superior performance of the proposed recursively trained 2D-3D ConvNet
over 2D models.

7
Discussion
Biologically-inspired recursive framework Our proposed recursive framework
is greatly inspired by the work of Chen et al. [34]. In this work, they examined

9

the close interplay between neurons in the primary and higher visual cortical
areas (V1 and V4, respectively) of monkeys performing contour detection tasks.
In this task, monkeys were trained to detect a global contour pattern that
consists of multiple collinearly aligned bars in a cluttered background. The
main discovery of their work is as follows:
initially, V4 neurons responded to
the global contour pattern. After a short time delay (?40 ms), the activity
of V1 neurons responding to each bar composing the global contour pattern
was greatly enhanced, whereas those responding to the background was largely
suppressed, despite the fact that those ?foreground? and ?background? V1
neurons have similar response properties. They referred to it as ?push-pull
response mode? of V1 neurons between foreground and background, which is
attributable to the top-down inﬂuence from the higher level V4 neurons. This
process is also referred to as ?countercurrent disambiguating process? [34].
This experimental result readily suggests a mechanistic interpretation on the
recursive training of deep ConvNets for neuronal boundary detection. We can
roughly think of V1 responses as lower level feature maps in a deep ConvNet,
and V4 responses as higher level feature maps or output activations. Once
the overall ?contour? of neuonal boundaries is detected by the feedforward
processing of VD2D, this preliminary boundary map can then be recursively
fed to VD2D3D. This process 7

VD2D Conv2a
VD2D Conv3b
VD2D3D Conv2a
VD2D3D Conv3b
Figure 5: Visualization of the eﬀect of recursive training. Left: an exam-
ple feature map from the lower layer Conv2a in VD2D, and its corresponding
feature map in VD2D3D. Right: an example feature map from the higher layer
Conv3b in VD2D, and its corresponding feature map in VD2D3D. Note that
recursive training greatly enhances the signal-to-noise ratio of boundary repre-
sentations. can be thought of as corresponding to the initial detection of global
contour patterns by V4 and its top-down inﬂuence on V1. During recursive
training, VD2D3D will learn how to integrate the pixel-level contextual infor-
mation in the recursive input with the low-level features, presumably in such a
way that feature activations on the boundary location are enhanced, whereas
activations unrelated to the neuronal boundary (intracellular space, mitochon-
dria, etc.) are suppressed. Here the recursive input can also be viewed as the
modulatory ?gate? through which only the signals relevant to the given task
of neuronal boundary detection can pass. This is convincingly demonstrated
by visualizing and comparing the feature maps of VD2D and VD2D3D. In Fig-
ure 5, the noisy representations of oriented boundary segments in VD2D (ﬁrst
and third volumes) are greatly enhanced in VD2D3D (second and fourth vol-
umes), with signals near boundary being preserved or ampliﬁed, and noises in
the background being largely suppressed. This is exactly what we expected from
the proposed interpretation of our recursive framework. Potential of ZNN We
have shown that ZNN can serve as a viable alternative to the mainstream GPU-
based deep learning frameworks, especially when processing 3D volume data

10

with 3D ConvNets. ZNN?s unique features including the large output patch-
based training and the dense computation of feature maps can be further utilized
for additional computations to better perform the given task. In theory, we can
perform any kind of computation on the dense output prediction between each
forward and backward passes. For instance, objective functions that consider
topological constraints (e.g. MALIS [35]) or sampling of topologically relevant
locations (e.g. LED weighting [15]) can be applied to the dense output patch, in
addition to loss computation, before each backward pass. Dense feature maps
also enable the straighforward implementation of multi-level feature integration
for ﬁne-grained segmentation. Long et al.
[30] resorted to upsampling of the
higher level features with lower resolution in order to integrate them with the
lower level features with higher resolution. Since ZNN maintains every feature
map at the original resolution of input, it is straighforward enough to combine
feature maps from any level, removing the need for upsampling. Acknowledg-
ments We thank Juan C. Tapia, Gloria Choi and Dan Stettler for initial help
with tissue handling and Jeﬀ Lichtman and Richard Schalek with help in setting
up tape collection. Kisuk Lee was supported by a Samsung Scholarship. The
recursive approach proposed in this paper was partially motivated by Matthew
J. Greene?s preliminary experiments. We are grateful for funding from the
Mathers Foundation, Keating Fund for Innovation, Simons Center for the So-
cial Brain, DARPA (HR001114-2-0004), and ARO (W911NF-12-1-0594).

2 References

[1] S. Takemura et al. A visual motion detection circuit suggested by Drosophila
connectomics. Nature, 500:175-181, 2013.

8
[2] M. Helmstaedter, K. L. Briggman, S. C. Turaga, V. Jain, H. S. Seung,
and W. Denk. Connectomic reconstruction of the inner plexiform layer in the
mouse retina. Nature, 500:168-174, 2013. [3] J. S. Kim et al. Space-time wiring
speciﬁcity supports direction selectivity in the retina. Nature, 509:331336, 2014.
[4] M. Helmstaedter. Cellular-resolution connectomics: challenges of dense neu-
ral circuit reconstruction. Nature Methods, 10(6):501-507, 2013.
[5] V. Jain,
H. S. Seung, and S. C. Turaga. Machines that learn to segment images: a cru-
cial technology for connectomics. Current Opinion in Neurobiology, 20:653-666,
2010. [6] T. Tasdizen et al. Image segmentation for connectomics using machine
learning. In Computational Intelligence in Biomedical Imaging, pp. 237-278,
ed. K. Suzuki, Springer New York, 2014. [7] K. L. Briggman and D. D. Bock.
Volume electron microscopy for neuronal circuit reconstruction. Current Opin-
ion in Neurobiology, 22(1):154-61, 2012. [8] E. Jurrus et al. Detection of neuron
membranes in electron microscopy images using a serial neural network archi-
tecture. Medical Image Analysis, 14(6):770-783, 2010. [9] T. Liu, C. Jones, M.
Seyedhosseini, and T. Tasdizen. A modular hierarchical approach to 3D elec-
tron microscopy image segmentation. Journal of Neuroscience Methods, 26:88-
102, 2014.
[10] Segmentation of neuronal structures in EM stacks challenge -

11

In NIPS, 2012.

[11] D. C. Cires?an, A.
ISBI 2012. http://brainiac2.mit. edu/isbi challenge/.
Giusti, L. M. Gambardella, and J. Schmidhuber. Deep neural networks segment
neuronal membranes in electron microscopy images.
[12] A.
Krizhevsky, I. Sutskever, and G. Hinton. Imagenet classiﬁcation with deep con-
volutional neural networks. In NIPS, 2012. [13] K. Simonyan and A. Zisserman.
Very deep convolutional networks for large-scale image recognition. In ICLR,
2015.
[14] S. C. Turaga et al. Convolutional networks can learn to generate
aﬃnity graphs for image segmentation. Neural Computation, 22:511-538, 2010.
[15] G. B. Huang and V. Jain. Deep and wide multiscale recursive networks for
robust image labeling. In ICLR, 2014. [16] M. Seyedhosseini and T. Tasdizen.
Multi-class multi-scale series contextual model for image segmentation. Image
Processing, IEEE Transactions on, 22(11):4486-4496, 2013. [17] A. Zlateski, K.
Lee, and H. S. Seung. ZNN - A fast and scalable algorithm for training 3D
convolutional networks on multi-core and many-core shared memory machines.
arXiv:1510.06706, 2015.
[18] D. Tran, L. Bourdev, R. Fergus, L. Torresani,
and M. Paluri. Learning Spatiotemporal Features with 3D Convolutional Net-
works. arXiv:1412.0767, 2014.
[19] L. Yao, A. Torabi, K. Cho, N. Ballas, C.
Pal, H. Larochelle, and A. Courville. Describing Videos by Exploiting Temporal
[20] P. O. Pinheiro and R. Collobert. Re-
Structure. arXiv:1502.08029, 2015.
current convolutional neural networks for scene labeling. In ICML, 2014.
[21]
Z. Tu. Auto-context and its application to high-level vision tasks. In CVPR,
2008.
[22] M. Mathieu, M. Henaﬀ, and Y. LeCun. Fast training of convolu-
tional networks through FFTs. In ICLR, 2014.
[23] N. Vasilache, J. Johnson,
M. Mathieu, S. Chintala, S. Piantino, and Y. LeCun. Fast convolutional nets
with fbﬀt: a GPU performance evaluation. In ICLR, 2015. [24] J. C. Tapia et
al. High-contrast en bloc staining of neuronal tissue for ﬁeld emission scanning
electron microscopy. Nature Protocols, 7(2):193-206, 2012.
[25] N. Kasthuri
et al. Saturated reconstruction of a volume of neocortex. Cell 162, 648-61,
2015. [26] K. J. Hayworth et al. Imaging ATUM ultrathin section libraries with
WaferMapper: a multi-scale approach to EM reconstruction of neural circuits.
Frontiers in Neural Circuits, 8, 2014.
[27] W. M. Rand. Objective criteria for
the evaluation of clustering methods. Journal of the American Statistical As-
sociation, 66(336):847-850, 1971.
[28] R. Unnikrishnan, C. Pantofaru, and M.
Hebert. Toward objective evaluation of image segmentation algorithms. Pattern
Analysis and Machine Intelligence, IEEE Transactions on, 29(6):929-944, 2007.
[29] A. Zlateski and H. S. Seung. Image segmentation by size-dependent single
linkage clustering of a watershed basin graph. arXiv:1505.00249, 2015.
[30] J.
Long, E. Shelhamer, and T. Darrell. Fully convolutional networks for semantic
segmentation. In CVPR, 2015. [31] P. Sermanet, D. Eigen, X. Zhang, M. Math-
ieu, R. Fergus, and Y. LeCun. OverFeat: Integrated recognition, localization
and detection using convolutional networks. In ICLR, 2014. [32] A. Giusti, D.
C. Cires?an, J. Masci, L. M. Gambardella, and J. Schmidhuber. Fast image
scanning with deep max-pooling convolutional neural networks. In ICIP, 2013.
[33] J. Masci, A. Giusti, D. C. Cires?an, G. Fricout, and J. Schmidhuber. A
fast learning algorithm for image segmentation with max-pooling convolutional
networks. In ICIP, 2013.
[34] M. Chen, Y. Yan, X. Gong, C. D. Gilbert, H.

12

Liang, and W. Li. Incremental integration of global contours through interplay
between visual cortical areas. Neuron, 82(3):682-694, 2014.
[35] S. C. Turaga
et al. Maximin aﬃnity learning of image segmentation. In NIPS, 2009.

9

13

