Data Generation as Sequential Decision Making

Authored by:

Doina Precup

Philip Bachman

Abstract

We connect a broad class of generative models through their shared
reliance on sequential decision making. Motivated by this view, we develop
extensions to an existing model, and then explore the idea further in the
context of data imputation – perhaps the simplest setting in which to
investigate the relation between unconditional and conditional generative
modelling. We formulate data imputation as an MDP and develop models
capable of representing eﬀective policies for it. We construct the models
using neural networks and train them using a form of guided policy search.
Our models generate predictions through an iterative process of feedback
and reﬁnement. We show that this approach can learn eﬀective policies
for imputation problems of varying diﬃculty and across multiple datasets.

1 Paper Body

Directed generative models are naturally interpreted as specifying sequential
procedures for generating data. We traditionally think of this process as sam-
pling, but one could also view it as making sequences of decisions for how to
set the variables at each node in a model, conditioned on the settings of its
parents, thereby generating data from the model. The large body of existing
work on reinforcement learning provides powerful tools for addressing such se-
quential decision making problems. We encourage the use of these tools to
understand and improve the extended processes currently driving advances in
generative modelling. We show how sequential decision making can be applied
to general prediction tasks by developing models which construct predictions by
iteratively reﬁning a working hypothesis under guidance from exogenous input
and endogenous feedback. We begin this paper by reinterpreting several re-
cent generative models as sequential decision making processes, and then show
how changes inspired by this point of view can improve the performance of the
LSTM-based model introduced in [3]. Next, we explore the connections between
directed generative models and reinforcement learning more fully by developing
an approach to training policies for sequential data imputation. We base our
approach on formulating imputation as a ﬁnitehorizon Markov Decision Process

1

which one can also interpret as a deep, directed graphical model. We propose
two policy representations for the imputation MDP. One extends the model in
[3] by inserting an explicit feedback loop into the generative process, and the
other addresses the MDP more directly. We train our models/policies using
techniques motivated by guided policy pearch [9, 10, 11, 8]. We examine their
qualitative and quantitative performance across imputation problems covering
a range of diﬃculties (i.e. diﬀerent amounts of data to impute and diﬀerent
?missingness mechanisms?), and across multiple datasets. Given the relative
paucity of existing approaches to the general imputation problem, we compare
our models to each other and to two simple baselines. We also test how our
policies perform when they use fewer/more steps to reﬁne their predictions. As
imputation encompasses both classiﬁcation and standard (i.e. unconditional)
generative modelling, our work suggests that further study of models for the
general imputation problem is worthwhile. The performance of our models
suggests that sequential stochastic construction of predictions, guided by both
input and feedback, should prove useful for a wide range of problems. Training
these models can be challenging, but lessons from reinforcement learning may
bring some relief. 1

2
Directed Generative Models as Sequential Decision Processes
Directed generative models have grown in popularity relative to their undi-
rected counter-parts [6, 14, 12, 4, 5, 16, 15] (etc.). Reasons include: the devel-
opment of eﬃcient methods for training them, the ease of sampling from them,
and the tractability of bounds on their log-likelihoods. Growth in available
computing power compounds these beneﬁts. One can interpret the (ancestral)
sampling process in a directed model as repeatedly setting subsets of the latent
variables to particular values, in a sequence of decisions conditioned on preced-
ing decisions. Each subsequent decision restricts the set of potential outcomes
for the overall sequence. Intuitively, these models encode stochastic procedures
for constructing plausible observations. This section formally explores this per-
spective. 2.1

Deep AutoRegressive Networks
The deep autoregressive networks investigated in [4] deﬁne distributions of
the following form: T X Y p(x) = p(x—z)p(z), with p(z) = p0 (z0 ) pt (zt —z0
, ..., zt?1 ) (1) z

t=1
in which x indicates a generated observation and z0 , ..., zT represent latent
variables in the model. The distribution p(x—z) may be factored similarly to
p(z). The form of p(z) in Eqn. 1 can represent arbitrary distributions over
the latent variables, and the work work in [4] mainly concerned approaches to
parameterizing the conditionals pt (zt —z0 , ..., zt?1 ) that restricted represen-
tational power in exchange for computational tractability. To appreciate the
generality of Eqn. 1, consider using zt that are univariate, multivariate, struc-
tured, etc. One can interpret any model based on this sequential factorization
of p(z) as a non-stationary policy pt (zt —st ) for selecting each action zt in a
state st , with each st determined by all zt0 for t0 ¡ t, and train it using some

2

form of policy search. 2.2

Generalized Guided Policy Search
We adopt a broader interpretation of guided policy search than one might
initially take from, e.g., [9, 10, 11, 8]. We provide a review of guided policy
search in the supplementary material. Our expanded deﬁnition of guided policy
search includes any optimization of the general form:

minimize E E E [‘(?, iq , ip )] + ? div (q(? —iq , ip ), p(? —ip )) (2) p,q
iq ?Iq ip ?Ip (?—iq ) ? ?q(? —iq ,ip )
in which p indicates the primary policy, q indicates the guide policy, Iq
indicates a distribution over information available only to q, Ip indicates a dis-
tribution over information available to both p and q, ‘(?, iq , ip ) computes the
cost of trajectory ? in the context of iq /ip , and div(q(? —iq , ip ), p(? —ip ))
measures dissimilarity between the trajectory distributions generated by p/q.
As ? ¿ 0 goes to inﬁnity, Eqn. 2 enforces the constraint p(? —ip ) = q(? —iq
, ip ), ??, ip , iq . Terms for controlling, e.g., the entropy of p/q can also be
added. The power of the objective in Eq. 2 stems from two main points: the
guide policy q can use information iq that is unavailable to the primary policy
p, and the primary policy need only be trained to minimize the dissimilarity
term div(q(? —iq , ip ), p(? —ip )). For example, a directed model structured
as in Eqn. 1 can be interpreted as specifying a policy for a ﬁnite-horizon MDP
whose terminal state distribution encodes p(x). In this MDP, the state at time
1 ? t ? T +1 is determined by {z0 , ..., zt?1 }. The policy picks an action
zt ? Zt at time 1 ? t ? T , and picks an action x ? X at time t = T +
1. I.e., the policy can be written as pt (zt —z0 , ..., zt?1 ) for 1 ? t ? T ,
and as p(x—z0 , ..., zT ) for t = T + 1. The initial state z0 ? Z0 is drawn
from p0 (z0 ). Executing the policy for a single trial produces a trajectory ?
, {z0 , ..., zT , x}, and the distribution over xs from these trajectories is just
p(x) in the corresponding directed generative model. The authors of [4] train
deep autoregressive networks by maximizing a variational lower bound on the
training set log-likelihood. To do this, they introduce a variational distribution
q which provides q0 (z0 —x? ) and qt (zt —z0 , ..., zt?1 , x? ) for 1 ? t ? T ,
with the ﬁnal step q(x—z0 , ..., zT , x? ) given by a Dirac-delta at x? . Given
these deﬁnitions, the training in [4] can be interpreted as guided policy search
for the MDP described in the previous paragraph. Speciﬁcally, the variational
distribution q provides a guide policy q(? —x? ) over trajectories ? , {z0 , ...,
zT , x? }: T Y q(? —x? ) , q(x—z0 , ..., zT , x? )q0 (z0 —x? ) qt (zt —z0 ,
..., zt?1 , x? ) (3) t=1

2
The primary policy p generates trajectories distributed according to: T Y

p(? ) , p(x—z0 , ..., zT )p0 (z0 ) pt (zt —z0 , ..., zt?1 )

(4)
t=1
which does not depend on x? . In this case, x? corresponds to the guide-only
information iq ? Iq in Eqn. 2. We now rewrite the variational optimization as:

minimize ? E E ? [‘(?, x? )] + KL(q(? —x? ) —— p(? )) (5) p,q
x ?DX

3

? ?q(? —x )
?
where ‘(?, x ) , 0 and DX indicates the target distribution for the terminal
state of the primary policy p.1 When expanded, the KL term in Eqn. 5 becomes:
KL(q(? —x? ) —— p(? )) = (6) # ” T q0 (z0 —x? ) X qt (zt —z0 , ...,
zt?1 , x? ) E ? log + ? log p(x? —z0 , ..., zT ) log p0 (z0 ) p (z —z , ...,
z ) ? ?q(? —x ) t t 0 t?1 t=1 Thus, the variational approach used in [4] for
training directed generative models can be interpreted as a form of generalized
guided policy search. As the form in Eqn. 1 can represent any ﬁnite directed
generative model, the preceding derivation extends to all models we discuss in
this paper.2 2.3

Time-reversible Stochastic Processes
One can simplify Eqn. 1 by assuming suitable forms for X and Z0 , ..., ZT .
E.g., the authors of [16] proposed a model in which Zt ? X for all t and p0 (x0
) was Gaussian. We can write their model as: p(xT ) =

X
pT (xT —xT ?1 )p0 (x0 )
x0 ,...,xT ?1
TY ?1
pt (xt —xt?1 )
(7)
t=1
where p(xT ) indicates the terminal state distribution of the non-stationary,
ﬁnite-horizon Markov process determined by {p0 (x0 ), p1 (x1 —x0 ), ..., pT
(xT —xT ?1 )}. Note that, throughout this paper, we (ab)use sums over latent
variables and trajectories which could/should be written as integrals. The au-
thors of [16] observed that, for any reasonably smooth target distribution DX
and suﬃciently large T , one can deﬁne a ?reverse-time? stochastic process qt
(xt?1 —xt ) with simple, time-invariant dynamics that transforms q(xT ) , DX
into the Gaussian distribution p0 (x0 ). This q is given by: q0 (x0 ) =

X
q1 (x0 —x1 )DX (xT )
x1 ,...,xT
T Y
qt (xt?1 —xt ) ? p0 (x0 )
(8)
t=2
Next, we deﬁne q(? ) as the distribution over trajectories ? , {x0 , ..., xT }
generated by the reversetime process determined by {q1 (x0 —x1 ), ..., qT (xT
?1 —xT ), DX (xT )}. We deﬁne p(? ) as the distribution over trajectories
generated by the ?forward-time? process in Eqn. 7. The training in [16] is
equivalent to guided policy search using guide trajectories sampled from q, i.e.
it uses the objective: ” # T ?1 q1 (x0 —x1 ) X DX (xT ) qt+1 (xt —xt+1
) minimize E log + + log (9) log p,q p0 (x0 ) pt (xt —xt?1 ) pT (xT —xT
?1 ) ? ?q(? )
If the
log-densities in Eqn. 9 are tractable, then this minimization can be done using

t=1 which corresponds to minimizing KL(q —— p).

4

basic Monte-Carlo.h If, as in [16], the reverse-time processi q is not PT trained,
then Eqn. 9 simpliﬁes to: minimizep Eq(? ) ? log p0 (x0 ) ? t=1 log pt (xt
—xt?1 ) . This trick for generating guide trajectories exhibiting a particular
distribution over terminal states xT ? i.e. running dynamics backwards in time
starting from xT ? DX ? may prove useful in settings other than those considered
in [16]. E.g., the LapGAN model in [1] learns to approximately invert a ﬁxed
(and information destroying) reverse-time process. The supplementary material
expands on the content of this subsection, including a derivation of Eqn. 9 as
a bound on Ex?DX [? log p(x)]. We could pull the ? log p(x? —z0 , ..., zT )
term from the KL and put it in the cost ‘(?, x? ), but we prefer the ?path-wise
KL? formulation for its elegance. We abuse notation using KL(?(x = x? ) ——
p(x)) , ? log p(x? ). 2 This also includes all generative models implemented
and executed on an actual computer. 1

3
2.4
Learning Generative Stochastic Processes with LSTMs
The authors of [3] introduced a model for sequentially-deep generative pro-
cesses. We interpret their model as a primary policy p which generates trajec-
tories ? , {z0 , ..., zT , x} with distribution: p(? ) , p(x—s? (?¡x ))p0 (z0
)

T Y
pt (zt ), with ?¡x , {z0 , ..., zT }
(10)
t=1
in which ?¡x indicates a latent trajectory and s? (?¡x ) indicates a state
trajectory {s0 , ..., sT } computed recursively from ?¡x using the update st ? f?
(st?1 , zt ) for t ? 1. The initial state s0 is given by a trainable constant. Each
state st , [ht ; vt ] represents the joint hidden/visible state ht /vt of an LSTM
and f? (state, input) computes a standard LSTM update.3 The authors of [3]
deﬁned all pt (zt ) as isotropic Gaussians and deﬁned the output distribution
p(x—s? (?¡x )) as p(x—cT ), where PT cT , c0 + t=1 ?? (vt ). Here, c0 is a
trainable constant and ?? (vt ) is, e.g., an aﬃne transform of vt . Intuitively, ??
(vt ) transforms vt into a reﬁnement of the ?working hypothesis? ct?1 , which
gets updated to ct = ct?1 + ?? (vt ). p is governed by parameters ? which
aﬀect f? , ?? , s0 , and c0 . The supplementary material provides pseudo-code
and an illustration for this model. To train p, the authors of [3] introduced a
guide policy q with trajectory distribution: q(? —x? ) , q(x—s? (?¡x ), x? )q0
(z0 —x? )

T Y
qt (zt —? st , x? ), with ?¡x , {z0 , ..., zT }
(11)
t=1
in which s? (?¡x ) indicates a state trajectory {? s0 , ..., s?T } computed
recursively from ?¡x using the guide policy?s state update s?t ? f? (? st?1 , g?
(s? (?¡t ), x? )). In this update s?t?1 is the previous guide state and g? (s?
(?¡t ), x? ) is a deterministic function of x? and the partial (primary) state

5

trajectory s? (?¡t ) , {s0 , ..., st?1 }, which is computed recursively from ?¡t , {z0
, ..., zt?1 } using the state update st ? f? (st?1 , zt ). The output distribution
q(x—s? (?¡x ), x? ) is deﬁned as a Dirac-delta at x? .4 Each qt (zt —? st , x?
) is a diagonal Gaussian distribution with means and log-variances given by an
aﬃne function L? (? vt ) of v?t . q0 (z0 ) is deﬁned as identical to p0 (z0 ). q
is governed by parameters ? which aﬀect the state updates f? (? st?1 , g? (s?
(?¡t ), x? )) and the step distributions qt (zt —? st , x? ). ? g? (s? (?¡t ), x
) corresponds to the ?read? operation of the encoder network in [3]. Using our
deﬁnitions for p/q, the training objective in [3] is given by: ” T # X qt (zt —?
st , x? ) ? minimize ? E E log ? log p(x —s(?¡x )) p,q x ?DX ? ?q(? —x? ) pt
(zt ) t=1

(12)
which can be written more succinctly as Ex? ?DX KL(q(? —x? ) —— p(?
)). This objective upper-bounds P Ex? ?DX [? log p(x? )], where p(x) , ?¡x
p(x—s? (?¡x ))p(?¡x ). 2.5

Extending the LSTM-based Generative Model
QT We propose changing p in Eqn. 10 to: p(? )

, p(x—s? (?¡x ))p0
(z0 ) t=1 pt (zt —st?1 ). We deﬁne pt (zt —st?1 ) as a diagonal Gaussian
distribution with means and log-variances given by an aﬃne function L? (vt?1
) of vt?1 (remember that st , [ht ; vt ]), and we deﬁne p0 (z0 ) as an isotropic
Gaussian. We set s0 using s0 ? f? (z0 ), where f? is a trainable function
(e.g. a neural network). Intuitively, our changes make the model more like a
typical policy by conditioning its ?action? zt on its state st?1 , and upgrade
the model to an inﬁnite mixture by placing a distribution over its initial state
s0 . We also consider using ct , L? (ht ), which transforms the hidden part
of the LSTM state st directly into an observation. This makes ht a working
memory in which to construct an observation. The supplementary material
provides pseudo-code and an illustration for this model. We train this model
by optimizing the objective: # ” T qt (zt —? st , x? ) q0 (z0 —x? ) X ? +
log ? log p(x —s(?¡x )) minimize ? E E log p,q x ?DX ? ?q(? —x? ) p0 (z0 )
pt (zt —st?1 ) t=1

(13)
3 For those unfamiliar with LSTMs, a good introduction can be found in [2].
We use LSTMs including input gates, forget gates, output gates, and peephole
connections for all tests presented in this chapter. 4 It may be useful to relax
this assumption.

4
where we now have to deal with pt (zt —st?1 ), p0 (z0 ), and q0 (z0 —x?
), which could be treated as constants in the model from [3]. We deﬁne q0 (z0
—x? ) as a diagonal Gaussian distribution whose means and log-variances are
given by a trainable function g? (x? ). When trained for the binarized MNIST
benchmark used in [3], our extended model scored a negative log-likelihood of
85.5 on the test set.5 For comparison, the score reported in [3] was 87.4.6 After
ﬁnetuning the variational distribution (i.e. q) on the test set, our model?s score
improved to 84.8, which is quite strong considering it is an upper bound. For
comparison, see the best upper bound reported for this benchmark in [15], which

6

was 85.1. When the model used the alternate cT , L? (hT ), the raw/ﬁnetuned
test scores were 85.9/85.3. Fig. 1 shows samples from the model. Model/test
code is available at http://github.com/Philip-Bachman/ Sequential-Generation.
3
Figure 1: The left block shows ?(ct ) for t ? {1, 3, 5, 9, 16}, for a policy p
with ct , c0 + Pt 0 t0 =1 L? (vt ). The right block is analogous, for a model
using ct , L? (ht ).

Developing Models for Sequential Imputation
The goal of imputation is to estimate p(xu —xk ), where x , [xu ; xk ] indi-
cates a complete observation with known values xk and missing values xu . We
deﬁne a mask m ? M as a (disjoint) partition of x into xu /xk . By expanding xu
to include all of x, one recovers standard generative modelling. By shrinking xu
to include a single element of x, one recovers standard classiﬁcation/regression.
Given distribution DM over m ? M and distribution DX over x ? X , the
objective for imputation is:

minimize E E ? log p(xu —xk ) (14) p
x?DX m?DM
We now describe a ﬁnite-horizon MDP for which guided policy search min-
imizes a bound on the objective in Eqn. 14. The MDP is deﬁned by mask
distribution DM , complete observation distribution DX , and the state spaces
{Z0 , ..., ZT } associated with each of T steps. Together, DM and DX deﬁne
a joint distribution over initial states and rewards in the MDP. For the trial
determined by x ? DX and m ? DM , the initial state z0 ? p(z0 —xk ) is
selected by the policy p based on the known values xk . The cost ‘(?, xu , xk )
suﬀered by trajectory ? , {z0 , ..., zT } in the context (x, m) is given by ? log
p(xu —?, xk ), i.e. the negative log-likelihood of p guessing the missing values
xu after following trajectory ? , while seeing the known values xk . QT We
consider a policy p with trajectory distribution p(? —xk ) , p(z0 —xk ) t=1
p(zt —z0 , ..., zt?1 , xk ), where xk is determined by x/m for the current trial
and p can?t observe the missing values xu . With these deﬁnitions, we can ﬁnd
an approximately optimal imputation policy by solving:

minimize E E E ? log p(xu —?, xk ) (15) p
x?DX m?DM ? ?p(? —xk )
I.e. the expected negative log-likelihood of making a correct imputation on
any given trial. This is a valid, but loose, upper bound on the imputation
objective in Eq. 14 (from Jensen?s inequality). We can tighten the bound
by introducing a guide policy (i.e. a variational distribution). As with the
unconditional generative models in Sec. 2, we train p to imitate a guide policy
q shaped by additional information (here it?s xu ). This q generates trajectories
with distribution q(? —xu , xk ) , QT q(z0 —xu , xk ) t=1 q(zt —z0 , ..., zt?1
, xu , xk ). Given this p and q, guided policy search solves:

u minimize E E E [? log q(x —?, iq , ip )] + KL(q(? —iq , ip ) —— p(?

—ip )) (16) p,q

x?DX m?DM
? ?q(? —iq ,ip )
where we deﬁne iq , xu , ip , xk , and q(xu —?, iq , ip ) , p(xu —?, ip ). 5 6

7

Data splits from: http://www.cs.toronto.edu/?larocheh/public/datasets/binarized mnist

The model in [3] signiﬁcantly improves its score to 80.97 when using an image-
speciﬁc architecture.

5
3.1
A Direct Representation for Sequential Imputation Policies
We deﬁne an imputation trajectory as c? , {c0 , ..., cT }, where each partial
imputation ct ? X is computed from a partial step trajectory ?¡t , {z1 , ..., zt }.
A partial imputation ct?1 encodes the policy?s guess for the missing values xu
immediately prior to selecting step zt , and cT gives the policy?s ﬁnal guess. At
each step of iterative reﬁnement, the policy selects a zt based on ct?1 and the
known values xk , and then updates its guesses to ct based on ct?1 and zt . By
iteratively reﬁning its guesses based on feedback from earlier guesses and the
known values, the policy can construct complexly structured distributions over
its ﬁnal guess cT after just a few steps. This happens naturally, without any
post-hoc MRFs/CRFs (as in many approaches to structured prediction), and
without sampling values in cT one at a time (as required by existing NADE-type
models [7]). This property of our approach should prove useful for many tasks.
We consider two ways of updating the guesses in ct , mirroring those described
in Sec. 2. The ﬁrst way sets ct ? ct?1 + ?? (zt ), where ?? (zt ) is a trainable
function. We set c0 , [cu0 ; ck0 ] using a trainable bias. The second way sets ct ?
?? (zt ). We indicate models using the ﬁrst type of update with the suﬃx -add,
and models using the second type of update with -jump. Our primary policy
p? selects zt at each step 1 ? t ? T using p? (zt —ct?1 , xk ), which we restrict
to be a diagonal Gaussian. This is a simple, stationary policy. Together, the
step selector p? (zt —ct?1 , xk ) and the imputation constructor ?? (zt ) fully
determine the behaviour of the primary policy. The supplementary material
provides pseudo-code and an illustration for this model. We construct a guide
policy q similarly to p. The guide policy shares the imputation constructor
?? (zt ) with the primary policy. The guide policy incorporates additional
information x , [xu ; xk ], i.e. the complete observation for which the primary
policy must reconstruct some missing values. The guide policy chooses steps
using q? (zt —ct?1 , x), which we restrict to be a diagonal Gaussian. We train
the primary/guide policy components ?? , p? , and q? simultaneously on the
objective:

u u u k k minimize E E E [? log q(x —cT )] + KL(q(? —x , x ) —— p(?

—x )) (17) ?,?

x?DX m?DM
? ?q? (? —xu ,xk )
where q(xu —cuT ) , p(xu —cuT ). We train our models using Monte-Carlo
roll-outs of q, and stochastic backpropagation as in [6, 14]. Full implementations
and test code are available from http:// github.com/Philip-Bachman/Sequential-
Generation. 3.2

Representing Sequential Imputation Policies using LSTMs
To make it useful for imputation, which requires conditioning on the exoge-
nous information xk , we modify the LSTM-based model from Sec. 2.5 to include

8

a ?read? operation in its primary policy p. We incorporate a read operation by
spreading p over two LSTMs, pr and pw , which respectively ?read? and ?write?
an imputation trajectory c? , {c0 , ..., cT }. Conveniently, the guide policy q for
this model takes the same form as the primary policy?s reader pr . This model
also includes an ?inﬁnite mixture? initialization step, as used in Sec. 2.5, but
modiﬁed to incorporate conditioning on x and m. The supplementary material
provides pseudo-code and an illustration for this model. Following the inﬁnite
mixture initialization step, a single full step of execution for p involves several k
substeps: ﬁrst p updates the reader state using srt ? f?r (srt?1 , ??r (ct?1 , sw
t?1 , x )), then p selects a r w w w step zt ? p? (zt —vt ), then p updates the
writer state using st ? f? (st?1 , zt ), and ﬁnally p updates r,w r,w its guesses
by setting ct ? ct?1 + ??w (vtw ) (or ct ? ??w (hw , [hr,w t ; vt ] t )). In
these updates, st r,w refer to the states of the (r)reader and (w)writer LSTMs.
The LSTM updates f? and the read/write operations ??r,w are governed by the
policy parameters ?. We train p to imitate trajectories sampled from a guide
policy q. The guide policy shares the primary policy?s writer updates f?w and
write operation ??w , but has its own reader updates f?q and read operation
??q . At each step, the guide policy: updates the guide state sqt ? f?q (sqt?1
, ??q (ct?1 , sw t?1 , x)), w w then selects zt ? q? (zt —vtq ), then updates
the writer state sw ? f (s , z ), and ﬁnally updates t t?1 t ? its guesses ct ?
ct?1 + ??w (vtw ) (or ct ? ??w (hw )). As in Sec. 3.1, the guide policy?s read
opt eration ??q gets to see the complete observation x, while the primary policy
only gets to see the known values xk . We restrict the step distributions p? /q?
to be diagonal Gaussians whose means and log-variances are aﬃne functions of
vtr /vtq . The training objective has the same form as Eq. 17. 6

350 300 250 200
Imputation NLL vs. Available Information
88
TM-orc TM-hon VAE-imp GPSI-add GPSI-jump LSTM-add LSTM-jump
86 84 82
Imputation NLL vs. Available Information
98
GPSI-add GPSI-jump LSTM-add LSTM-jump
94 92 90
78 88
76
86
74 100
84
72 0.60
0.65
GPSI-add GPSI-jump
80
150
50 0.55
The Eﬀect of Increased Reﬁnement Steps

9

96
0.70 0.75 0.80 Mask Probability
0.85
0.90
0.95
70 0.55
(a)
0.60
0.65
0.70 0.75 0.80 Mask Probability
0.85
0.90
0.95
(b)
82 0
2
4
6 8 10 Reﬁnement Steps
12
14
16
(c)
Figure 2: (a) Comparing the performance of our imputation models against
several baselines, using MNIST digits. The x-axis indicates the % of pixels
which were dropped completely at random, and the scores are normalized by
the number of imputed pixels. (b) A closer view of results from (a), just for
our models. (c) The eﬀect of increased iterative reﬁnement steps for our GPSI
models.

4
Experiments
We tested the performance of our sequential imputation models on three
datasets: MNIST (28x28), SVHN (cropped, 32x32) [13], and TFD (48x48) [17].
We converted images to grayscale and shift/scaled them to be in the range
[0...1] prior to training/testing. We measured the imputation log-likelihood log
q(xu —cuT ) using the true missing values xu and the models? guesses given
by ?(cuT ). We report negative log-likelihoods, so lower scores are better in
all of our tests. We refer to variants of the model from Sec. 3.1 as GPSI-add
and GPSI-jump, and to variants of the model from Sec. 3.2 as LSTM-add
and LSTM-jump. Except where noted, the GPSI models used 6 reﬁnement
steps and the LSTM models used 16.7 We tested imputation under two types of
data masking: missing completely at random (MCAR) and missing at random
(MAR). In MCAR, we masked pixels uniformly at random from the source
images, and indicate removal of d% of the pixels by MCAR-d.
In MAR, we
masked square regions, with the occlusions located uniformly at random within
the borders of the source image. We indicate occlusion of a d ? d square by

10

MAR-d. On MNIST, we tested MCAR-d for d ? {50, 60, 70, 80, 90}. MCAR-
100 corresponds to unconditional generation. On TFD and SVHN we tested
MCAR-80. On MNIST, we tested MAR-d for d ? {14, 16}. On TFD we
tested MAR-25 and on SVHN we tested MAR-17. For test trials we sampled
masks from the same distribution used in training, and we sampled complete
observations from a held-out test set. Fig. 2 and Tab. 1 present quantitative
results from these tests. Fig. 2(c) shows the behavior of our GPSI models when
we allowed them fewer/more reﬁnement steps.

LSTM-add LSTM-jump GPSI-add GPSI-jump VAE-imp
MNIST MAR-14 MAR-16 170 167 172 169 177 175 183 177 374 394
TFD MCAR-80 MAR-25 1381 1377 ? ? 1390 1380 1394 1384 1416 1399
SVHN MCAR-80 MAR-17 525 568 ? ? 531 569 540 572 567 624
Table 1: Imputation performance in various settings. Details of the tests are
provided in the main text. Lower scores are better. Due to time constraints, we
did not test LSTM-jump on TFD or SVHN. These scores are normalized for the
number of imputed pixels. We tested our models against three baselines. The
baselines were ?variational auto-encoder imputation?, honest template match-
ing, and oracular template matching. VAE imputation ran multiple steps of
VAE reconstruction, with the known values held ﬁxed and the missing val-
ues re-estimated with each reconstruction step.8 After 16 reﬁnement steps, we
scored the VAE based on its best 7 GPSI stands for ?Guided Policy Search
Imputer?. The tag ?-add? refers to additive guess updates, and ?-jump? refers
to updates that fully replace the guesses. 8 We discuss some deﬁciencies of VAE
imputation in the supplementary material.

7
(a)
(b)
(c)
Figure 3: This ﬁgure illustrates the policies learned by our models. (a): mod-
els trained for (MNIST, MAR-16). From top?bottom the models are: GPSI-add,
GPSI-jump, LSTM-add, LSTM-jump. (b): models trained for (TFD, MAR-25),
with models in the same order as (a) ? but without LSTMjump. (c): models
trained for (SVHN, MAR-17), with models arranged as for (b). guesses. Hon-
est template matching guessed the missing values based on the training image
which best matched the test image?s known values. Oracular template match-
ing was like honest template matching, but matched directly on the missing
values. Our models signiﬁcantly outperformed the baselines.
In general, the
LSTM-based models outperformed the more direct GPSI models. We evalu-
ated the log-likelihood of imputations produced by our models using the lower
bounds provided by the variational objectives with respect to which they were
trained. Evaluating the template-based imputations was straightforward. For
VAE imputation, we used the expected log-likelihood of the imputations sam-
pled from multiple runs of the 16-step imputation process. This provides a
valid, but loose, lower bound on their log-likelihood. As shown in Fig. 3,
the imputations produced by our models appear promising. The imputations
are generally of high quality, and the models are capable of capturing strongly

11

multi-modal reconstruction distributions (see subﬁgure (a)). The behavior of
GPSI models changed intriguingly when we swapped the imputation construc-
tor. Using the -jump imputation constructor, the imputation policy learned by
the direct model was rather inscrutable. Fig. 2(c) shows that additive guess up-
dates extracted more value from using more reﬁnement steps. When trained on
the binarized MNIST benchmark discussed in Sec. 2.5, i.e. with binarized im-
ages and subject to MCAR-100, the LSTMadd model produced raw/ﬁne-tuned
scores of 86.2/85.7. The LSTM-jump model scored 87.1/86.3. Anecdotally, on
this task, these ?closed-loop? models seemed more prone to overﬁtting than the
?open-loop? models in Sec. 2.5. The supplementary material provides further
qualitative results.

5
Discussion
We presented a point of view which links methods for training directed gen-
erative models with policy search in reinforcement learning. We showed how our
perspective can guide improvements to existing models. The importance of these
connections will only grow as generative models rapidly increase in structural
complexity and eﬀective decision depth. We introduced the notion of imputa-
tion as a natural generalization of standard, unconditional generative modelling.
Depending on the relation between the data-to-generate and the available in-
formation, imputation spans from full unconditional generative modelling to
classiﬁcation/regression. We showed how to successfully train sequential impu-
tation policies comprising millions of parameters using an approach based on
guided policy search [9]. Our approach outperforms the baselines quantitatively
and appears qualitatively promising. Incorporating, e.g., the local read/write
mechanisms from [3] should provide further improvements. 8

2 References

[1] Emily L Denton, Soumith Chintala, Arthur Szlam, and Robert Fergus.
Deep generative models using a laplacian pyramid of adversarial networks.
[2] Alex Graves. Generating sequences with
arXiv:1506.05751 [cs.CV], 2015.
recurrent neural networks. arXiv:1308.0850 [cs.NE], 2013.
[3] Karol Gregor,
Ivo Danihelka, Alex Graves, and Daan Wierstra. Draw: A recurrent neural
network for image generation. In International Conference on Machine Learn-
ing (ICML), 2015.
[4] Karol Gregor, Ivo Danihelka, Andriy Mnih, Charles
Blundell, and Daan Wierstra. Deep autoregressive networks. In International
Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2014. [5] Diederik P Kingma, Danilo
J Rezende, Shakir Mohamed, and Max Welling. Semi-supervised learning with
deep generative models. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems
(NIPS), 2014. [6] Diederik P Kingma and Max Welling. Auto-encoding varia-
tional bayes. In International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR),
2014.
[7] Hugo Larochelle and Iain Murray. The neural autoregressive distri-
bution estimator. In International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML),
2011.
[8] Sergey Levine and Pieter Abbeel. Learning neural network policies

12

In Advances in Neural
with guided policy search under unknown dynamics.
Information Processing Systems (NIPS), 2014.
[9] Sergey Levine and Vladlen
Koltun. Guided policy search. In International Conference on Machine Learn-
ing (ICML), 2013.
[10] Sergey Levine and Vladlen Koltun. Variational policy
search via trajectory optimization. In Advances in Neural Information Process-
ing Systems (NIPS), 2013.
[11] Sergey Levine and Vladlen Koltun. Learning
complex neural network policies with trajectory optimization. In International
Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2014.
[12] Andriy Mnih and Karol
Gregor. Neural variational inference and learning in belief networks. In Inter-
national Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2014. [13] Yuval Netzer, Tao
Wang, Adam Coates, Alessandro Bissacco, Bo Wu, and Andrew Y Ng. Reading
digits in natural images with unsupervised feature learning. NIPS Workshop on
Deep Learning and Unsupervised Feature Learning, 2011. [14] Danilo Rezende,
Shakir Mohamed, and Daan Wierstra. Stochastic backpropagation and ap-
proximate inference in deep generative models. In International Conference on
Machine Learning (ICML), 2014. [15] Danilo J Rezende and Shakir Mohamed.
Variational inference with normalizing ﬂows.
In International Conference on
Machine Learning (ICML), 2015.
[16] Jascha Sohl-Dickstein, Eric A. Weiss,
Niru Maheswaranathan, and Surya Ganguli. Deep unsupervised learning us-
ing nonequilibrium thermodynamics. In International Conference on Machine
Learning (ICML), 2015.
[17] Joshua Susskind, Adam Anderson, and Geoﬀrey
E Hinton. The toronto face database. 2010.

9

13

