Learning Theory and Algorithms for Forecasting

Non-stationary Time Series

Authored by:

Mehryar Mohri
Vitaly Kuznetsov

Abstract

We present data-dependent learning bounds for the general scenario
of non-stationary non-mixing stochastic processes. Our learning guaran-
tees are expressed in terms of a data-dependent measure of sequential
complexity and a discrepancy measure that can be estimated from data
under some mild assumptions. We use our learning bounds to devise new
algorithms for non-stationary time series forecasting for which we report
some preliminary experimental results.

1 Paper Body

Time series forecasting plays a crucial role in a number of domains ranging from
weather forecasting and earthquake prediction to applications in economics and
ﬁnance. The classical statistical approaches to time series analysis are based on
generative models such as the autoregressive moving average (ARMA) models,
or their integrated versions (ARIMA) and several other extensions [Engle, 1982,
Bollerslev, 1986, Brockwell and Davis, 1986, Box and Jenkins, 1990, Hamilton,
1994]. Most of these models rely on strong assumptions about the noise terms,
often assumed to be i.i.d. random variables sampled from a Gaussian distri-
bution, and the guarantees provided in their support are only asymptotic. An
alternative non-parametric approach to time series analysis consists of extend-
ing the standard i.i.d. statistical learning theory framework to that of stochastic
processes. In much of this work, the process is assumed to be stationary and suit-
ably mixing [Doukhan, 1994]. Early work along this approach consisted of the
VC-dimension bounds for binary classiﬁcation given by Yu [1994] under the as-
sumption of stationarity and -mixing. Under the same assumptions, Meir [2000]
presented bounds in terms of covering numbers for regression losses and Mohri
and Rostamizadeh [2009] proved general data-dependent Rademacher complex-
ity learning bounds. Vidyasagar [1997] showed that PAC learning algorithms in
the i.i.d. setting preserve their PAC learning property in the -mixing station-
ary scenario. A similar result was proven by Shalizi and Kontorovitch [2013] for

1

mixtures of -mixing processes and by Berti and Rigo [1997] and Pestov [2010] for
exchangeable random variables. Alquier and Wintenberger [2010] and Alquier
et al. [2014] also established PAC-Bayesian learning guarantees under weak de-
pendence and stationarity. A number of algorithm-dependent bounds have also
been derived for the stationary mixing setting. Lozano et al. [2006] studied the
convergence of regularized boosting. Mohri and Rostamizadeh [2010] gave data-
dependent generalization bounds for stable algorithms for ’-mixing and -mixing
stationary processes. Steinwart and Christmann [2009] proved fast learning
rates for regularized algorithms with ?-mixing stationary sequences and Modha
and Masry [1998] gave guarantees for certain classes of models under the same
assumptions. However, stationarity and mixing are often not valid assumptions.
For example, even for Markov chains, which are among the most widely used
types of stochastic processes in applications, stationarity does not hold unless
the Markov chain is started with an equilibrium distribution. Similarly, 1

long memory models such as ARFIMA, may not be mixing or mixing may
be arbitrarily slow [Baillie, 1996]. In fact, it is possible to construct ﬁrst order
autoregressive processes that are not mixing [Andrews, 1983]. Additionally, the
mixing assumption is deﬁned only in terms of the distribution of the under-
lying stochastic process and ignores the loss function and the hypothesis set
used. This suggests that mixing may not be the right property to characterize
learning in the setting of stochastic processes. A number of attempts have been
made to relax the assumptions of stationarity and mixing. Adams and Nobel
[2010] proved asymptotic guarantees for stationary ergodic sequences. Agar-
wal and Duchi [2013] gave generalization bounds for asymptotically stationary
(mixing) processes in the case of stable on-line learning algorithms. Kuznetsov
and Mohri [2014] established learning guarantees for fully non-stationary - and
’-mixing processes. In this paper, we consider the general case of non-stationary
non-mixing processes. We are not aware of any prior work providing general-
ization bounds in this setting.
In fact, our bounds appear to be novel even
when the process is stationary (but not mixing). The learning guarantees that
we present hold for both bounded and unbounded memory models. Deriving
generalization bounds for unbounded memory models even in the stationary
mixing case was an open question prior to our work [Meir, 2000]. Our guar-
antees cover the majority of approaches used in practice, including various au-
toregressive and state space models. The key ingredients of our generalization
bounds are a data-dependent measure of sequential complexity (expected se-
quential covering number or sequential Rademacher complexity [Rakhlin et al.,
2010]) and a measure of discrepancy between the sample and target distribu-
tions. Kuznetsov and Mohri [2014] also give generalization bounds in terms of
discrepancy. However, unlike the result of Kuznetsov and Mohri [2014], our
analysis does not require any mixing assumptions which are hard to verify in
practice. More importantly, under some additional mild assumption, the dis-
crepancy measure that we propose can be estimated from data, which leads to
data-dependent learning guarantees for non-stationary non-mixing case. We de-
vise new algorithms for non-stationary time series forecasting that beneﬁt from
our datadependent guarantees. The parameters of generative models such as

2

ARIMA are typically estimated via the maximum likelihood technique, which
often leads to non-convex optimization problems.
In contrast, our objective
is convex and leads to an optimization problem with a unique global solution
that can be found eﬃciently. Another issue with standard generative models is
that they address nonstationarity in the data via a diﬀerencing transformation
which does not always lead to a stationary process. In contrast, we address the
problem of non-stationarity in a principled way using our learning guarantees.
The rest of this paper is organized as follows. The formal deﬁnition of the time
series forecasting learning scenario as well as that of several key concepts is
given in Section 2. In Section 3, we introduce and prove our new generalization
bounds.
In Section 4, we give data-dependent learning bounds based on the
empirical discrepancy. These results, combined with a novel analysis of kernel-
based hypotheses for time series forecasting (Appendix B), are used to devise
new forecasting algorithms in Section 5. In Appendix C, we report the results
of preliminary experiments using these algorithms.

2
Preliminaries
We consider the following general time series prediction setting where the
learner receives a realization (X1 , Y1 ), . . . , (XT , YT ) of some stochastic
process, with (Xt , Yt ) 2 Z = X ? Y. The objective of the learner is to select out
of a speciﬁed family H a hypothesis h : X ! Y that achieves a small generalization
error E[L(h(XT +1 ), YT +1 )—Z1 , .
, ZT ] conditioned on observed
data, where L : Y ? Y ! [0, 1) is a given loss function. The path-dependent
generalization error that we consider in this work is a ﬁner measure of the
generalization ability than the averaged generalization error E[L(h(XT +1 ),
YT +1 )] = E[E[L(h(XT +1 ), YT +1 )—Z1 , . . . , ZT ]] since it only takes
into consideration the realized history of the stochastic process and does not
average over the set of all possible histories. The results that we present in this
paper also apply to the setting where the time parameter t can take non-integer
values and prediction lag is an arbitrary number l 0. That is, the error is deﬁned
by E[L(h(XT +l ), YT +l )—Z1 , . . . , ZT ] but for notational simplicity we
set l = 1. 2

.

.

Our setup covers a larger number of scenarios commonly used in practice.
The case X = Y p p corresponds to a large class of autoregressive models.
Taking X = [1 p=1 Y leads to growing memory models which, in particular,
include state space models. More generally, X may contain both the history of
the process {Yt } and some additional side information.

To simplify the notation, in the rest of the paper, we will use the shorter
notation f (z) = L(h(x), y), for any z = (x, y) 2 Z and introduce the family F
= {(x, y) ! L(h(x), y) : h 2 H} containing such functions f . We will assume a
bounded loss function, that is —f — ? M for all f 2 F for some M 2 R+ . Finally,
we will use the shorthand Zba to denote a sequence of random variables Za ,
Za+1 , . . . , Zb . The key quantity of interest in the analysis of generalization
is the following supremum of the empirical process deﬁned as follows: (ZT1 )

= sup f 2F
E[f (ZT +1 )—ZT1 ]

3

T X
!
qt f (Zt ) ,
t=1
(1)
where q1 , .

.

.

.

, qT are real numbers, which in the standard learning
scenarios are chosen to be uniform. In our general setting, diﬀerent Zt s may
follow diﬀerent distributions, thus distinct weights could be assigned to the
errors made on diﬀerent sample points depending on their relevance to fore-
casting the future ZT +1 . The generalization bounds that we present below
are for an arbitrary sequence q = (q1 , .
. qT ) which, in particular, cov-
ers the case of uniform weights. Remarkably, our bounds do not even require
the non-negativity of q. Our generalization bounds are expressed in terms of
data-dependent measures of sequential complexity such as expected sequential
covering number or sequential Rademacher complexity [Rakhlin et al., 2010].
We give a brief overview of the notion of sequential covering number and refer
the reader to the aforementioned reference for further details. We adopt the
following deﬁnition of a complete binary tree: a Z-valued complete binary tree
, zT ) of T mappings zt : {?1}t 1 ! Z, t 2 [1, T ].
z is a sequence (z1 , .
A path in the tree is = ( 1 , .
, T 1 ). To simplify the notation we will
write zt ( ) instead of zt ( 1 , . . . , t 1 ), even though zt depends only on the
ﬁrst t 1 elements of . The following deﬁnition generalizes the classical notion of
covering numbers to sequential setting. A set V of R-valued trees of depth T is
a sequential ?-cover (with respect to q-weighted ‘p norm) of a function class G
on a tree z of depth T if for all g 2 G and all 2 {?}T , there is v 2 V such that
T X

.

.

.

.

vt ( )
g(zt ( ))
t=1
p
! p1
? kqkq 1 ?,
where k ? kq is the dual norm. The (sequential) covering number Np (?, G,
z) of a function class G on a given tree z is deﬁned to be the size of the minimal
sequential cover. The maximal covering number is then taken to be Np (?, G)
= supz Np (?, G, z). One can check that in the case of uniform weights this
deﬁnition coincides with the standard deﬁnition of sequential covering numbers.
Note that this is a purely combinatorial notion of complexity which ignores the
distribution of the process in the given learning problem. Data-dependent se-
quential covering numbers can be deﬁned as follows. Given a stochastic process
distributed according to the distribution p with pt (?—zt1 1 ) denoting the
conditional distribution at time t, we sample a Z ? Z-valued tree of depth T
according to the following procedure. Draw two independent samples Z1 , Z10
from p1 :
in the left child of the root draw Z2 , Z20 according to p2 (?—Z1
) and in the right child according to p2 (?—Z20 ). More generally, for a node
that can be reached by a path ( 1 , .
, t ), we draw Zt , Zt0 according to

.

.

4

pt (?—S1 ( 1 ), . . . , St 1 ( t 1 )), where St (1) = Zt and St ( 1) = Zt0 . Let
z denote the tree formed using Zt s and deﬁne the expected covering number
to be Ez?T (p) [Np (?, G, z)], where T (p) denotes the distribution of z. In a
similar manner, one can deﬁne other measures of complexity such as sequential
Rademacher complexity and the Littlestone dimension [Rakhlin et al., 2015] as
well as their data-dependent counterparts [Rakhlin et al., 2011]. 3

The ﬁnal ingredient needed for expressing our learning guarantees is the
notion of discrepancy between target distribution and the distribution of the
sample: ? ? T X = sup E[f (ZT +1 )—ZT1 ] qt E[f (Zt )—Zt1 1 ] . (2) f 2F

t=1
The discrepancy is a natural measure of the non-stationarity of the stochastic
process Z with respect to both the loss function L and the hypothesis set H. In
particular, note that if the process Z is i.i.d., then we simply have = 0 provided
that qt s form a probability distribution. It is also possible to give bounds on in
terms of other natural distances between distribution. For instance, Pinsker?s
inequality yields r ? ? PT PT t 1 T ? M PT +1 (?—Z1 ) ? 12 D PT +1
(?—ZT1 ) k t=1 qt Pt (?—Zt1 1 ) , t=1 qt Pt (?—Z1 ) TV

where k ? kTV is the total variation distance and D(? k ?) the relative
entropy, Pt+1 (?—Zt1 ) the condiPT tional distribution of Zt+1 , and t=1 qt
Pt (?—Zt1 1 ) the mixture of the sample marginals. Alternatively, if the target
distribution at lag l, P = PT +l is a stationary distribution of an asymptotically
stationary process Z [Agarwal and Duchi, 2013, Kuznetsov and Mohri, 2014],
then for qt = 1/T we have ?

T MX kP T t=1
Pt+l (?—Zt
1 )kTV
?
(l),
where (l) = sups supz [kP Pl+s (?—zs 1 )kTV ] is the coeﬃcient of asymp-
totic stationarity. The process is asymptotically stationary if liml!1 (l) = 0.
However, the most important property of the discrepancy is that, as shown
later in Section 4, it can be estimated from data under some additional mild
assumptions. [Kuznetsov and Mohri, 2014] also give generalization bounds for
non-stationary mixing processes in terms of a related notion of discrepancy. It
is not known if the discrepancy measure used in [Kuznetsov and Mohri, 2014]
can be estimated from data.

3
Generalization Bounds
In this section, we prove new generalization bounds for forecasting non-
stationary time series. The ﬁrst step consists of using decoupled tangent se-
quences to establish concentration results for the supremum of the empirical
process (ZT1 ). Given a sequence of random variables ZT1 we say that T Z0
1 is a decoupled tangent sequence if Zt0 is distributed according to P(?—Zt1 1
) and is independent of Z1 na and Gin?e, t . It is always possible to construct
such a sequence of random variables [De la Pe? 1999]. The next theorem is
the main result of this section. Theorem 1. Let ZT1 be a sequence of random

5

variables distributed according to p. Fix ? ¿ 2? ¿ 0. Then, the following holds:
? ? ? ? (? 2?)2 T P (Z1 ) ? ? E N1 (?, F, v) exp . 2M 2 kqk22 v?T (p) Proof.
The ﬁrst step is to observe that, since the diﬀerence of the suprema is upper
bounded by the supremum of the diﬀerence, it suﬃces to bound the probability
of the following event ( ! ) T X sup qt (E[f (Zt )—Zt1 1 ] f (Zt )) ? . f 2F

By Markov?s inequality, for any P
sup f 2F
? exp(
T X t=1
t=1
¿ 0, the following inequality holds: ! !
qt (E[f (Zt )—Zt1 1 ] ”
?) E exp
sup f 2F
f (Zt ))
T X t=1
4
?
qt (E[f (Zt )—Zt1 1 ]
!!#
f (Zt ))
.
T
Since Z0 1 is a tangent sequence the following equalities hold: E[f (Zt )—Zt1
1 ] = E[f (Zt0 )—Zt1 1 ] = E[f (Zt0 )—ZT1 ]. Using these equalities and Jensen?s
inequality, we obtain the following: ? T ? ? X E exp sup qt E[f (Zt )—Zt1 1 ] f
(Zt ) f 2F t=1

? T ? hX = E exp sup E qt f (Zt0 ) f 2F
?
? E exp
?
sup
t=1
T X
f 2F t=1
qt f (Zt0 )
f (Zt ) —ZT1 ?
f (Zt )
i?
, T
where the last expectation is taken over the joint measure of ZT1 and Z0 1
. Applying Lemma 5 (Appendix A), we can further bound this expectation by
? ? T ? ?? X 0 E E exp sup f (zt ( )) t qt f (z t ( )) 0 (z,z )?T (p)

? ? =
E 0
(z,z )?T (p)

6

?
f 2F t=1
E exp
E
z?T (p)
?
?
sup
T X
f 2F t=1
0 t qt f (z t ( )) +
sup
? T X 0 E 0 E exp 2 sup + t qt f (z t ( ))
1 2 (z,z )
?
?
?
f 2F t=1
? q f (z ( )) t t t
T X
f 2F t=1 1 E0 E 2 (z,z )
? T X E exp 2 sup , t qt f (zt ( ))
?
?
exp 2 sup
T X
f 2F t=1
? t qt f (zt ( ))
f 2F t=1
where for the second inequality we used Young?s inequality and for the last
equality we used symmetry. Given z let C denote the minimal ?-cover with
respect to the q-weighted ‘1 -norm of F on z. Then, the following bound holds
sup

T X
f 2F t=1
t qt f (zt (
)) ? max c2C
T X
t q t ct (
) + ?.
t=1
By the monotonicity of the exponential function, ? ? ? ? ? T T X X E exp

2 sup ? exp(2 ?) E exp 2 max t qt f (zt ( )) c2C

f 2F t=1
? exp(2 ?)
X

7

c2C
?
?
E exp 2
t=1
T X t=1
Since ct ( ) depends only on 1 , . . . , T 1 , by Hoeﬀding?s bound, ? ? X ?

? ? TX1 ? ? ? T E exp 2 q c ( ) = E exp 2 q c ( ) E exp 2 t t t t t t t=1

?
?
? E exp 2
T
t=1
T X1
t q t ct (
t=1
? ) exp(2
? t q t ct ( )
? . t q t ct ( )
? q c ( ) T T T
v?T (p)
Optimizing over
completes the proof.
An immediate consequence of Theorem 1 is the following result. 5
1
2 2 qT M 2 )
and iterating this inequality and using the union bound, we obtain the fol-
lowing: ? ? T ? X P sup qt (E[f (Zt )—Zt1 1 ] f (Zt )) ? ? E [N1 (?, G, v)] exp
(? 2?)+2 f 2F t=1

T 1
2
? M 2 kqk22 .
Corollary 2. For any
¿ 0, with probability at least 1
E[f (ZT +1 )—ZT1 ] ?
T X
qt f (Zt ) +
t=1
, for all f 2 F and all ? ¿ 0, r Ev?T (P) [N1 (?, G, v)] + 2? + M kqk2 2 log .
We are not aware of other ﬁnite sample bounds in a non-stationary non-
mixing case.
In fact, our bounds appear to be novel even in the stationary
non-mixing case. Using chaining techniques bounds, Theorem 1 and Corollary
2 can be further improved and we will present these results in the full version
of this paper. While Rakhlin et al.
[2015] give high probability bounds for a
diﬀerent quantity than the quantity of interest in time series prediction, ! T X
t 1 sup qt (E[f (Zt )—Z1 ] f (Zt )) , (3) f 2F

8

t=1
their analysis of this quantity can also be used in our context to derive
high probability bounds for (ZT1 ) . However, this approach results in bounds
that are in terms of purely combinatorial notions such as maximal sequential
covering numbers N1 (?, F). While at ﬁrst sight, this may seem as a minor
technical detail, the distinction is crucial in the setting of time series prediction.
Consider the following example. Let Z1 be drawn from a uniform distribution
on {0, 1} and Zt ? p(?—Zt 1 ) with p(?—y) being a distribution over {0, 1}
such that p(x—y) = 2/3 if x = y and 1/3 otherwise. Let G be deﬁned by G
= {g(x) = 1x ? : ? 2 [0, 1]}. Then, one can check that Ev?T (P) [N1 (?,
G, v)] = 2, while N1 (?, G) 2T . The data-dependent bounds of Theorem 1
and Corollary 2 highlight the fact that the task of time series prediction lies
in between the familiar i.i.d. scenario and adversarial on-line learning setting.
However, the key component of our learning guarantees is the discrepancy term
. Note that in the general non-stationary case, the bounds of Theorem 1 may
not converge to zero due to the discrepancy between the target and sample
distributions. This is also consistent with the lower bounds of Barve and Long
[1996] that we discuss in more detail in Section 4. However, convergence can
be established in some special cases. In the i.i.d. case our bounds reduce to the
standard covering numbers learning guarantees. In the drifting scenario, with
ZT1 being a sequence of independent random variables, our discrepancy measure
coincides with the one used and studied in [Mohri and Mu?noz Medina, 2012].
Convergence can also be established in asymptotically stationary and stationary
mixing cases. However, as we show in Section 4, the most important advantage
of our bounds is that the discrepancy measure we use can be estimated from
data.
4
Estimating Discrepancy
In Section 3, we showed that the discrepancy is crucial for forecasting non-
stationary time series. In particular, if we could select a distribution q over the
sample ZT1 that would minimize the discrepancy and use it to weight training
points, then we would have a better learning guarantee for an algorithm trained
on this weighted sample. In some special cases, the discrepancy can be computed
analytically. However, in general, we do not have access to the distribution of
ZT1 and hence we need to estimate the discrepancy from the data. Furthermore,
in practice, we never observe ZT +1 and it is not possible to estimate without
some further assumptions. One natural assumption is that the distribution Pt
of Zt does not change drastically with t on average. Under this assumption the
last s observations ZTT s+1 are eﬀectively drawn from the distribution close to
PT +1 . More precisely, we can write ? ? T T X 1 X t 1 t 1 ? sup E[f (Zt
)—Z1 ] qt E[f (Zt )—Z1 ] s f 2F t=1 t=T

+ sup f 2F
?
s+1
1 s
E[f (ZT +1 )—ZT1 ]

9

T X
t=T
s+1
?
E[f (Zt )—Zt1 1 ]
.
We will assume that the second term, denoted by s , is suﬃciently small and
will show that the ﬁrst term can be estimated from data. But, we ﬁrst note
that our assumption is necessary for learning in 6

this setting. Observe that ? sup E[ZT +1 —ZT1 ]
E[f (Zr )—Zr1
f 2F
1
T ? X ? ] ? sup E[f (Zt+1 )—Zt1 ] t=r f 2F
?M for all r = T
T X t=r
kPt+1 (?—Zt1 )
? E[f (Zt )—Zt1 1 ]
Pt (?—Zt1 1 )kTV ,
s + 1, . . . , T . Therefore, we must have ? ? s+1 1 X sup E[ZT +1 —ZT1

] E[f (Zt )—Zt1 ] ? M , s ? s 2 f 2F t=T

s+1
1
= supt kPt+1 (?—Zt1 )
where Pt (?—Zt1 1 )kTV . Barve and Long [1996] showed that [VC-dim(H)
] 3 is a lower bound on the generalization error in the setting of binary classiﬁ-
cation where ZT1 is a sequence of independent but not identically distributed
random variables (drifting). This setting is a special case of the more general
scenario that we are considering. The following result shows that we can esti-
mate the ﬁrst term in the upper bound on . Theorem 3. Let ZT1 be a sequence
of random variables. Then, for any ¿ 0, with probability at least 1 , the following
holds for all ? ¿ 0: ! ! T T X X t 1 sup (pt qt ) E[f (Zt )—Z1 ] ? sup (pt qt )f
(Zt ) + B, f 2F

t=1
q pk2 2 log
where B = 2? + M kq the last s points.
f 2F
Ez?T (p) [N1 (?,G,z)]
t=1
and where p is the uniform distribution over
The proof of this result is given in Appendix A. Theorem 1 and Theorem
3 combined with the union bound yield the following result. Corollary 4. Let
ZT1 be a sequence of random variables. Then, for any ¿ 0, with probability at
least 1 , the following holds for all f 2 F and all ? ¿ 0: E[f (ZT +1 )—ZT1 ] ?
T X t=1

qt f (Zt ) + e +

10

where e = supf 2F
5
Algorithms
?P
T t=1 (pt
s
? + 4? + M kqk2 + kq
? qt )f (Zt ) .
pk2
q ? 2 log
2 Ev?T (p) [N1 (?,G,z)]
,
In this section, we use our learning guarantees to devise algorithms for fore-
casting non-stationary time series. We consider a broad family of kernel-based
hypothesis classes with regression losses. We present the full analysis of this
setting in Appendix B including novel bounds on the sequential Rademacher
complexity. The learning bounds 1 can be generalized q ? of Theorem ? to
hold uniformly 1 over q at the price of an additional term in O kq uk1 log2
log2 kq uk1 . We prove this result in Theorem 8 (Appendix B). Suppose L
is the squared loss and H = {x ! w ? (x) : kwkH ? ?}, where : X ! H is a
feature mapping from X to a Hilbert space H. By Lemma 6 (Appendix B), we
can bound the complexity term in our generalization bounds by ? ? ?r O (log3
T ) p + (log3 T )kq uk1 , T where K is a PDS kernel associated with H such
that supx K(x, x) ? r and u is the uniform distribution over the sample. Then,
we can formulate a joint optimization problem over both q and w based on the
learning guarantee of Theorem 8, which holds uniformly over all q: ?X T T X
min qt (w ? (xt ) yt )2 + 1 dt qt + 2 kwk2H + 3 kq uk1 . (4) 0?q?1,w

t=1
t=1
7
PT Here, we have upper bounded the empirical discrepancy term by t=1 dt
qt with each dt deﬁned PT by supw0 ?? — s=1 ps (w0 ? (xs ) ys )2 (w0 ? (xt
) yt )2 —. Each dt can be precomputed using DC-programming. For general
loss functions, the DC-programming approach only guarantees convergence to
a stationary point. However, for the squared loss, our problem can be cast as
an instance of the trust region problem, which can be solved globally using the
DCA algorithm of Tao and An [1998]. Note that problem (4) is not jointly
convex in q and w. However, using the dual problem associated to w yields the
following equivalent problem, it can be rewritten as follows: min

0?q?1
?
max ?
n
2
T X ?2
?T K? + 2

11

t
qt
t=1
T 2? Y
o
+
1 (d?q)
+
3 kq
uk1 ,
(5)
where d = (d1 , . . . , dT )T , K is the kernel matrix and Y = (y1 , . . .
, yT )T . We use the change of variables rt = 1/qt and further upper bound 3
kq uk1 by 03 kr T 2 uk2 , which follows from —qt ut — = —qt ut (rt T )—
and H?older?s inequality. Then, this yields the following optimization problem:
min r2D

?
max ?
n
2
T X
?T K? + 2
rt ?t2
t=1
o T ? Y + 2
1
T X dt t=1
+
rt
3 kr
T 2 uk22 ,
(6)
where D = {r : rt 1, t 2 [1, T ]}. The optimization problem (6) is con-
vex since D is a convex set, the ﬁrst term in (6) is convex as a maximum of
convex (linear) functions of r. This problem can be solved using standard de-
scent methods, where, at each iteration, we solve a standard QP in ?, which
admits a closed-form solution. Parameters 1 , 2 , and 3 are selected through
cross-validation. An alternative simpler algorithm based on the data-dependent
bounds of Corollary 4 consists of ﬁrst ﬁnding a distribution q minimizing the
(regularized) discrepancy and then using that to ﬁnd a hypothesis minimizing
the (regularized) weighted empirical risk. This leads to the following twostage
procedure. First, we ﬁnd a solution q? of the following convex optimization
problem: min q 0

?
sup
w0 ??

12

T ?X
(pt
t=1
qt )(w0 ? (xt )
? yt )2 +
1 kq
uk1 ,
(7)
where 1 and ? are parameters that can be selected via cross-validation. Our
generalization bounds hold for arbitrary weights q but we restrict them to being
positive sequences. Note that other regularization terms such as kqk22 and kq
pk22 from the bound of Corollary 4 can be incorporated in the optimization
problem, but we discard them to minimize the number of parameters. This
problem can be solved using standard descent optimization methods, where,
at each step, we use DC-programming to evaluate the supremum over w0 .
Alternatively, one can upper bound the suprePT mum by t=1 qt dt and then
solve the resulting optimization problem. The solution q? of (7) is then used to
solve the following (weighted) kernel ridge regression problem: min w

?X T t=1
qt? (w ? (xt )
yt )2 +
2 2 kwkH
Note that, in order to guarantee the convexity of this problem, we require

q?

6
(8)
. 0.
Conclusion
We presented a general theoretical analysis of learning in the broad sce-
nario of non-stationary nonmixing processes, the realistic setting for a variety
of applications. We discussed in detail several algorithms beneﬁtting from the
learning guarantees presented. Our theory can also provide a ﬁner analysis of
several existing algorithms and help devise alternative principled learning al-
gorithms. Acknowledgments This work was partly funded by NSF IIS-1117591
and CCF-1535987, and the NSERC PGS D3. 8

2 References

T. M. Adams and A. B. Nobel. Uniform convergence of Vapnik-Chervonenkis
classes under ergodic sampling. The Annals of Probability, 38(4):1345?1367,
2010. A. Agarwal and J. Duchi. The generalization ability of online algorithms
for dependent data. Information Theory, IEEE Transactions on, 59(1):573?587,
2013. P. Alquier and O. Wintenberger. Model selection for weakly depen-
dent time series forecasting. Technical Report 2010-39, Centre de Recherche
en Economie et Statistique, 2010. P. Alquier, X. Li, and O. Wintenberger.

13

Prediction of time series by statistical learning: general losses and fast rates.
Dependence Modelling, 1:65?93, 2014. D. Andrews. First order autoregressive
processes and strong mixing. Cowles Foundation Discussion Papers 664, Cowles
Foundation for Research in Economics, Yale University, 1983. R. Baillie. Long
memory processes and fractional integration in econometrics. Journal of Econo-
metrics, 73 (1):5?59, 1996. R. D. Barve and P. M. Long. On the complexity
of learning from drifting distributions. In COLT, 1996. P. Berti and P. Rigo.
A Glivenko-Cantelli theorem for exchangeable random variables. Statistics &
Probability Letters, 32(4):385 ? 391, 1997. T. Bollerslev. Generalized autore-
gressive conditional heteroskedasticity. J Econometrics, 1986. G. E. P. Box
and G. Jenkins. Time Series Analysis, Forecasting and Control. Holden-Day,
Incorporated, 1990. P. J. Brockwell and R. A. Davis. Time Series: Theory and
Methods. Springer-Verlag, New York, 1986. V. H. De la Pe?na and E. Gin?e.
Decoupling:
from dependence to independence: randomly stopped processes,
U-statistics and processes, martingales and beyond. Probability and its appli-
cations. Springer, NY, 1999. P. Doukhan. Mixing: properties and examples.
Lecture notes in statistics. Springer-Verlag, New York, 1994. R. Engle. Autore-
gressive conditional heteroscedasticity with estimates of the variance of United
Kingdom inﬂation. Econometrica, 50(4):987?1007, 1982. J. D. Hamilton. Time
series analysis. Princeton, 1994. V. Kuznetsov and M. Mohri. Generalization
bounds for time series prediction with non-stationary processes. In ALT, 2014.
A. C. Lozano, S. R. Kulkarni, and R. E. Schapire. Convergence and consis-
tency of regularized boosting algorithms with stationary -mixing observations.
In NIPS, pages 819?826, 2006. R. Meir. Nonparametric time series prediction
through adaptive model selection. Machine Learning, pages 5?34, 2000. D.
Modha and E. Masry. Memory-universal prediction of stationary random pro-
cesses. Information Theory, IEEE Transactions on, 44(1):117?133, Jan 1998.
M. Mohri and A. Mu?noz Medina. New analysis and algorithm for learning
In ALT, 2012. M. Mohri and A. Rostamizadeh.
with drifting distributions.
Rademacher complexity bounds for non-i.i.d. processes.
In NIPS, 2009. M.
Mohri and A. Rostamizadeh. Stability bounds for stationary ’-mixing and -
mixing processes. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 11:789?814, 2010. V.
Pestov. Predictive PAC learnability: A paradigm for learning from exchange-
able input data.
In GRC, 2010. A. Rakhlin, K. Sridharan, and A. Tewari.
Online learning: Random averages, combinatorial parameters, and learnability.
In NIPS, 2010. A. Rakhlin, K. Sridharan, and A. Tewari. Online learning:
Stochastic, constrained, and smoothed adversaries. In NIPS, 2011. A. Rakhlin,
K. Sridharan, and A. Tewari. Sequential complexities and uniform martin-
gale laws of large numbers. Probability Theory and Related Fields, 2015. C.
Shalizi and A. Kontorovitch. Predictive PAC learning and process decompo-
sitions. In NIPS, 2013. I. Steinwart and A. Christmann. Fast learning from
non-i.i.d. observations. In NIPS, 2009. P. D. Tao and L. T. H. An. A D.C.
optimization algorithm for solving the trust-region subproblem. SIAM Journal
on Optimization, 8(2):476?505, 1998. M. Vidyasagar. A Theory of Learning
and Generalization: With Applications to Neural Networks and Control Sys-
tems. Springer-Verlag New York, Inc., 1997. B. Yu. Rates of convergence for

14

empirical processes of stationary mixing sequences. The Annals of Probability,
22(1):94?116, 1994.

9

15

