Collaborative Filtering with Graph Information:

Consistency and Scalable Methods

Authored by:

Pradeep K. Ravikumar

Inderjit S. Dhillon

Nikhil Rao

Hsiang-Fu Yu

Abstract

Low rank matrix completion plays a fundamental role in collabora-
tive ﬁltering applications, the key idea being that the variables lie in a
smaller subspace than the ambient space. Often, additional information
about the variables is known, and it is reasonable to assume that incor-
porating this information will lead to better predictions. We tackle the
problem of matrix completion when pairwise relationships among vari-
ables are known, via a graph. We formulate and derive a highly eﬃcient,
conjugate gradient based alternating minimization scheme that solves op-
timizations with over 55 million observations up to 2 orders of magnitude
faster than state-of-the-art (stochastic) gradient-descent based methods.
On the theoretical front, we show that such methods generalize weighted
nuclear norm formulations, and derive statistical consistency guarantees.
We validate our results on both real and synthetic datasets.

1 Paper Body

Low rank matrix completion approaches are among the most widely used col-
laborative ﬁltering methods, where a partially observed matrix is available to
the practitioner, who needs to impute the missing entries. Speciﬁcally, suppose
there exists a ratings matrix Y 2 Rm?n , and we only observe a subset of the
entries Yij , 8(i, j) 2 ?, —?— = N ? mn. The goal is to estimate Yi,j , 8(i, j) 2
/ ?. To this end, one typically looks to solve one of the following (equivalent)
programs: 1 Z? = arg min kP? (Y Z 2 ? ,H ? = arg min 1 kP? (Y W W,H 2

Z)k2F +
(1)
z kZk?
W H T )k2F +
w

1

2
kW k2F +
h
2
kHk2F
(2)
where the nuclear norm kZk? , given by the sum of singular values, is a
tight convex relaxation of the non convex rank penalty, and is equivalent to the
regularizer in (2). P? (?) is the projection operator that only retains those
entries of the matrix that lie in the set ?. In many cases however, one not only
has the partially observed ratings matrix, but also has access to additional in-
formation about the relationships between the variables involved. For example,
one might have access to a social network of users. Similarly, one might have
access to attributes of items, movies, etc. The nature of the attributes can be
fairly arbitrary, but it is reasonable to assume that ?similar? users/items share
?similar? attributes. A natural question to ask then, is if one can take advan-
tage of this additional information to make better predictions. In this paper,
we assume that the row and column variables lie on graphs. The graphs may
naturally be part of the data (social networks, product co-purchasing graphs) or
they can be constructed from available features. The idea then is to incorporate
this additional structural information into the matrix completion setting. 1

We not only require the resulting optimization program to enforce addi-
tional constraints on Z, but we also require it to admit eﬃcient optimization
algorithms. We show in the sections that follow that this in fact is indeed the
case. We also perform a theoretical analysis of our problem when the observed
entries of Y are corrupted by additive white Gaussian noise. To summarize, the
contributions of our paper are as follows: ? We provide a scalable algorithm for
matrix completion graph with structural information. Our method relies on ef-
ﬁcient Hessian-vector multiplication schemes, and is orders of magnitude faster
than (stochastic) gradient descent based approaches. ? We make connections
with other structured matrix factorization frameworks. Notably, we show that
our method generalizes the weighted nuclear norm [21], and methods based on
Gaussian generative models [27]. ? We derive consistency guarantees for graph
regularized matrix completion, and empirically show that our bound is smaller
than that of traditional matrix completion, where graph information is ignored.
? We empirically validate our claims, and show that our method achieves com-
parable error rates to other methods, while being signiﬁcantly more scalable.
Related Work and Key Diﬀerences For convex methods for matrix factoriza-
tion, Haeﬀele et al.
[9] provided a framework to use regularizers with norms
other than the Euclidean norm in (2). Abernethy et al. [1] considered a kernel
based embedding of the data, and showed that the resulting problem can be
expressed as a norm minimization scheme. Srebro and Salakhutdinov [21] in-
troduced a weighted nuclear norm, and showed that the method enjoys superior
performance as compared to standard matrix completion under a non-uniform
sampling scheme. We show that the graph based framework considered in this
paper is in fact a generalization of the weighted nuclear norm problem, with

2

non-diagonal weight matrices. In the context of matrix factorization with graph
structural information, [5] considered a graph regularized nonnegative matrix
factorization framework and proposed a gradient descent based method to solve
the problem. In the context of recommendation systems in social networks, Ma
et al. [14] modeled the weight of a graph edge1 explicitly in a re-weighted regu-
larization framework. Li and Yeung [13] considered a similar setting to ours, but
a key point of diﬀerence between all the aforementioned methods and our paper
is that we consider the partially observed ratings case. There are some works
developing algorithms for the situation with partially observations [12, 26, 27];
however, none of them provides statistical guarantees. Weighted norm mini-
mization has been considered before ([16, 21]) in the context of low rank matrix
completion. The thrust of these methods has been to show that despite subopti-
mal conditions (correlated data, non-uniform sampling), the sample complexity
does not change. None of these methods use graph information. We are in-
terested in a complementary question: Given variables conforming to graph
information, can we obtain better guarantees under uniform sampling to those
achieved by traditional methods?

2
Graph-Structured Matrix Factorization
Assume that the ?true? target matrix can be factorized as Z ? = W ? (H
? )T , and there exist a graph (V w , E w ) whose adjacency matrix encodes
the relationships between the m rows of W ? and a graph (V h , E h ) for n
rows of H ? . In particular, two rows (or columns) connected by an edge in the
graph are ?close? to each other in the Euclidean distance. In the context of
graph-based embedding, [3, 4] proposed a smoothing term of the form 1X w E
(wi 2 i,j ij

wj )2 = tr(W T Lap(E w )W )
(3)
where Lap(E w ) :=PDw E w is the graph Laplacian for (V w , E w ),
where Dw is the diagonal w w matrix with Dii = j?i Eij . Adding (3) into the
minimization problem (2) encourages solutions w where wi ? wj when Eij is
large. A similar argument holds for H ? and the associated graph Laplacian
Lap(E h ). 1

The authors call this the ?trust? between links in a social network
2
We would thus not only want the target matrix to be low rank, but also
want the variables W, H to be faithful to the underlying graph structure. To
this end, we consider the following problem: 1 L min kP? Y W H T k2F +
{tr(W T Lap(E w )W ) + tr(H T Lap(E h )H)}+ (4) W,H 2 2 w

2
kW k2F +
h
2
kHk2F
1 1 kP? Y W H T k2F + tr(W T Lw W ) + tr(H T Lh H) (5) 2 2 where Lw
:= L Lap(E w ) + w Im , and Lh is deﬁned similarly. Note that we subsume

3

the regularization parameters in the deﬁnition of Lw , Lh . Note that kW k2F
= tr(W T Im W ). ? min W,H

The regularizer in (5) encourages solutions that are smooth with respect
to the corresponding graphs. However, the Laplacian matrix can be replaced
by other (positive, semi-deﬁnite) matrices that encourage structure by diﬀer-
ent means.
Indeed, a very general class of Laplacian based regularizers was
considered in [20], where one can replace Lw by a function: hx, ? (Lap(E))xi

where
? (Lap(E)) ?
—V — X
? ( i )qi qiT ,
i=1
where {( i , qi )} constitute the eigen-system of Lap(E) and ? ( i ) is a
scalar function of the eigenvalues. Our case corresponds to ? (?) being the
identity function. We brieﬂy summarize other schemes that ﬁt neatly into (5),
apart from the graph regularizer we consider: Covariance matrices for variables:
[27] proposed a kernelized probabilistic matrix factorization (KPMF), which is
a generative model to incorporate covariance information of the variables into
matrix factorization. They assumed that each row of W ? , H ? is generated
according to a multivariate Gaussian, and solving the corresponding MAP esti-
mation procedure yields exactly (5), with Lw = Cw 1 and Lh = Ch 1 , where
Cw , Ch are the associated covariance matrices. Feature matrices for variables:
Assume that there is a feature matrix X 2 Rm?d for objects associated rows.
For such X, one can construct a graph (and hence a Laplacian) using various
methods such as k-nearest neighbors, ?-nearest neighbors etc. Moreover, one
can assume that there exists a kernel k(xi , xj ) that encodes pairwise relations,
and we can use the Kernel Gram matrix as a Laplacian. We can thus see that
problem (5) is a very general scheme, and can incorporate information avail-
able in many diﬀerent forms. In the sequel, we assume the matrices Lw , Lh
are given. In the theoretical analysis in Section 5, for ease of exposition, we
further assume that the minimum eigenvalues of Lw , Lh are unity. A general
(nonzero) minimum eigenvalue will merely introduce multiplicative constants in
our bounds.

3
GRALS: Graph Regularized Alternating Least Squares
In this section, we propose eﬃcient algorithms for (5), which is convex with
respect to W or H separately. This allows us to employ alternating minimization
methods [25] to solve the problem. When Y is fully observed, Li and Yeung [13]
propose an alternating minimization scheme using block steepest descent. We
deal with the partially observed setting, and propose to apply conjugate gradient
(CG), which is known to converge faster than steepest descent, to solve each
subproblem. We propose a very eﬃcient Hessian-vector multiplication routine
that results in the algorithm being highly scalable, compared to the (stochastic)
gradient descent approaches in [14, 27]. We assume that Y 2 Rm?n , W 2 Rm?k
and H 2 Rn?k . When optimizing H with W ﬁxed, we obtain the following
sub-problem. 1 1 min f (H) = kP? Y W H T k2F + tr(H T Lh H). (6) H 2 2

4

Optimizing W while H ﬁxed is similar, and thus we only show the details for
solving (6). Since Lh is nonsingular, (6) is strongly convex.2 We ﬁrst present
our algorithm for the fully observed case, since it sets the groundwork for the
partially observed setting. 2

In fact, a nonsingular Lh can be handled using proximal updates, and our

algorithm will still apply

3
Algorithm 2 Hv-Multiplication for g? (s) ? Given: Matrices Lh , W, ? ?
Multiplication: r2 g(s0 )s: 1 Input: S 2 Rk?n s.t. s = vec(S) 2 Compute P K =
[kT1 , . . . , kn ] s.t. kj i2?j (wi sj )wi 3 A K + SLh 4 Return: vec(A)

Algorithm 1 Hv-Multiplication for g(s) ? Given: Matrices Lh , W ? Initial-
ization: G = W T W ? Multiplication: r2 g(s0 )s: 1 Input: S 2 Rn?k s.t. s =
vec(S) 2 A SG + Lh S 3 Return: vec(A)

3.1 Fully Observed Case As in [5, 13] among others, there may be scenarios
where Y is completely observed, and the goal is to ﬁnd the row/column embed-
dings that conform to the corresponding graphs. In this case, the loss term in
(6) is simply kY W H T k2F . Thus, setting rf (H) = 0 is equivalent to solving
the following Sylvester equation for an n ? k matrix H: HW T W + Lh H = Y
T W.
(7)
(7) admits a closed form solution. However the standard Bartels-Stewart
algorithm for the Sylvester equation requires transforming both W T W and Lh
into Schur form (diagonal in our case where W T W and Lh are symmetric) by
the QR algorithm, which is time consuming for a large Lh . Thus, we consider
applying conjugate gradient (CG) to minimize f (H) directly. We deﬁne the
following quadratic function: 1 T g(s) := sT M s vec Y T W s, s 2 Rnk , M = Ik
? Lh + (W T W ) ? In 2 It is not hard to show that f (H) = g(vec(H)) and so we
apply CG to minimize g(s). The most crucial step in CG is the Hessian-vector
multiplication. Using the identity (B T ? A) vec(X) = vec(AXB), it follows that
(Ik ? Lh ) s = vec(Lh S) , and

(W T W ) ? In s = vec SW T W ,
where vec(S) = s. Thus the Hessian-vector multiplication can be imple-
mented by a series of matrix multiplications as follows. M s = vec Lh S + S(W
T W ) , where W T W can be pre-computed and stored in O(k 2 ) space. The
details are presented in Algorithm 1. The time complexity for a single CG iter-
ation is O(nnz(Lh )k + nk 2 ), where nnz(?) is the number of non zeros. Since
in most practical applications k is generally small, the complexity is essentially
O(nnz(Lh )k) as long as nk ? nnz(Lh ). 3.2 Partially Observed Case P In this
case, the loss term of (6) becomes (i,j)2? (Yij wiT hj )2 , where wiT is the i-th
row of W and hj is the j-th column of H T . Similar to the fully observed case,
we can deﬁne:

1 T T s M? s vec W T Y s, 2 ? + Lh ? Ik , B ? 2 Rnk?nk is a block diagonal
matrix with n diagonal blocks where M? = B P T Bj 2 Rk?k . Bj = i2?j wi wi
, where ?j = {i : (i, j) 2 ?}. Again, we can see f (H) = g? (vec H T ). Note that
the transpose H T is used here instead of H, which is used in the fully observed
case. g? (s) :=

5

For a given s, let S = [s1 , . . . sj , . . . sn ] be a matrix such that vec(S)
,
= s and K = ? = vec(K). Note that since n can be very large in [k1 , .
kj , .
, kn ] with kj = Bj sj . Then Bs practice, it may not be feasible to
compute and store all Bj in the beginning. Alternatively, Bj sj can be computed
in O(—?j —k) time as follows. X B j sj = (wiT sj )wi . i2?j

.

.

.

.

4
? can be computed in O(—?—k) time, and the Hessian-vector multiplication
M? s can be Thus Bs done in O (—?—k + nnz(Lh )k) time. See Algorithm 2
for a detailed procedure. As a result, each CG iteration for minimizing g? (s)
is also very cheap. Remark on Convergence. In [2], it is shown that any local
minimizer of (5) is a global minimizer of (5) if k is larger than the true rank
of the underlying matrix.3 From [25], the alternating minimization procedure
is guaranteed to globally converge to a block coordinate-wise minimum4 of (5).
The converged point might not be a local minimizer, but it still yields good
performance in practice. Most importantly, since the updates are cheap to
perform, our algorithm scales well to large datasets.

4
Convex Connection via Generalized Weighted Nuclear Norm
We now show that the regularizer in (5) can be cast as a generalized version
of the weighted nuclear norm. The weights in our case will correspond to the
scaling factors introduced on the matrices W, H due to the eigenvalues of the
shifted graph Laplacians Lw , Lh respectively. 4.1

A weighted atomic norm:
From [7], we know that the nuclear norm is the gauge function induced by
the atomic set: A? = {wi hTi : kwi k = khi k = 1}. Note that all rank one
.
matrices in A? have unit Frobenius norm. 1/2 Now, assume P = [p1 , .
, pm ] 2 Rm?m is a basis of Rm and Sp is a diagonal matrix with 1/2 (Sp
)ii 0 encoding the ?preference? over the space spanned by pi . The more the
preference, 1/2 the larger the value. Similarly, consider the basis Q and the
preference Sq for Rn . Let A = 1/2 1/2 P Sp and B = QSq , and consider the
following ?preferential? atomic set: A := {

.

i
= wi hTi : wi = Aui , hi = Bvi , kui k = kvi k = 1}.
(8)
Clearly, each atom in A has non-unit Frobenius norm. This atomic set
allows for biasing of the solutions towards certain atoms. We then deﬁne a
corresponding atomic norm: X X kZkA = inf —ci — s.t. Z = ci i . (9) i 2A

i 2A
It is not hard to verify that kZkA is a norm and {Z : kZkA ? ? } is closed

and convex. 4.2

Equivalence to Graph Regularization
The graph regularization (5) can be shown to be a special case of the atomic
norm (9), as a consequence of the following result: Theorem 1. For any A = P
Sp kZkA = inf

W,H
1/2

6

, B = QSq
1 {kA 2
1
1/2
, and corresponding weighted atomic set A ,
W k2F + kB
1
Hk2F }
Z = W HT .
s.t.
We prove this result in Appendix A. Theorem 1 immediately leads us to the
following equivalence result: Corollary 1. Let Lw = Uw Sw UwT and Lh = Uh
Sh UhT be the eigen decomposition for Lw and Lh . We have Tr W T Lw W
= kA 1 W k2F , and Tr H T Lh H = kB 1 Hk2F , 1/2

1/2
1/2
where A = Uw Sw and B = Uh Sh . As a result, kM kA with the preference
pair (Uw , Sw ) 1/2 for the column space and the preference pair (Uh , Sh )
for row space is a weighted atomic norm equivalent for the graph regularization
using Lw and Lh . The results above allow us to obtain the dual weighted
atomic norm for a matrix Z 1

1
kZk?A = kAT ZB k = kSw 2 UwT ZUh Sh 2 k 3 4
The authors actually show this for a more general class of regularizers. Nash

equilibrium is used in [25].

5
(10)
which is a weighted spectral norm. An elementary proof of this result can

be found in Appendix B. Note that we can then write kZkA = kA

1
ZB
T
1
1
k? = kSw2 Uw 1 ZUh T Sh2 k?
(11)
In [21], the authors consider a norm similar to (11), but with A, B being
diagonal matrices. In the spirit of their nomenclature, we refer to the norm in
(11) as the generalized weighted nuclear norm.

5
Statistical Consistency in the Presence of Noisy Measurements
In this section, we derive theoretical guarantees for the graph regularized
low rank matrix estimators. We ﬁrst introduce some additional notation. We
assume that there is a m ? n matrix Z ? of rank k with kZ ? kF = 1, and N
= —?— entries of Z ? are uniformly sampled5 and revealed to us (i.e., Y = P?
(Z ? )). We further assume an one-to-one mapping between the set of observed

7

indices ? and {1, 2, . . . , N } so that the tth measurement is given by yt =
Yi(t),j(t) = hei(t) eTj(t) , Z ? i + p

mn
(12)
?t ? N (0, 1).
?t
where h?, ?i denotes the matrix trace inner product, and i(t), j(t) is a ran-
domly selected coordinate pair from [m]?[n]. Let A, B are corresponding matri-
ces deﬁned in Corollary 1 for the given Lw , Lh . W.L.O.G, we assume that the
minimum singular value of both Lw and Lh is 1. We then deﬁne the following
graph based complexity measures: ?g (Z) :=

p
mn
kA 1 ZB kA 1 ZB
T
k1 , Tk F
g (Z)
:=
kA 1 ZB kA 1 ZB
T
k? Tk F
(13)
where k ? k1 is the element-wise ‘1 norm. Finally, we assume that the true
matrix Z ? can be expressed as a linear combination of atoms from (8) (we deﬁne
?? := ?g (Z ? )): Z ? = AU ? (V ? )T B T , U ? 2 Rm?k , V ? 2 Rn?k ,

(14)
Our goal in this section will be to characterize the solution to the following
convex program, where the constraint set precludes selection of overly complex
matrices in the sense of (13): s ( ) 1 N 2 Z? = arg min kP? (Y Z)kF + kZkA
where C := Z : ?g (Z) g (Z) ? c?0 , Z2C N log(m + n) (15) where c?0 is a
constant depending on ?? . A quick note on solving (15): since k ? kA is a
weighted nuclear norm, one can resort to proximal point methods [6], or greedy
methods developed speciﬁcally for atomic norm constrained minimization [18,
22]. The latter are particularly attractive, since the greedy step reduces to
computing the maximum singular vectors which can be eﬃciently computed
using power methods. However, such methods will ﬁrst involve computing the
eigen decompositions of the graph Laplacians, and then storing the large, dense
matrices A, B. We refrain from resorting to such methods in Section 6, and
instead use the eﬃcient framework derived in Section 3. We now state our main
theoretical result: Theorem 2. Suppose we observe N entries of the form (12)
from a matrix Z ? 2 Rm?n , with ? ?? := ?g (Z ? ) and which can be represented
q using at most k atoms from (8). Let Z be the minimizer of the convex problem
(15) with kZ?

C1
(m+n) log(m+n) . N
Z ? k2F ? C??2 max 1,

8

2
Then, with high probability, we have
k(m + n) log(m + n) +O N
where C, C1 are positive constants. See Appendix C for the detailed proof.

A proof sketch is as follows: 5

Our results can be generalized to non uniform sampling schemes as well.
6
?
??2 N
?
Proof Sketch: There are three major portions of the proof: ? Using the fact
that Z ? has unit Frobeniusp norm and can be expressed as a combination of at
most k atoms, we can show kZ ? kA ? k (Appendix C.1) ? Using (10), we can
derive a bound for the dual norm of the gradient of the loss L(Z), given 1

1
by krL(Z)k?A = kSw 2 UwT rL(Z)Uh Sh 2 k. (Appendix C.2) ? Finally,
using (13), we deﬁne a notion of restricted strong convexity (RSC) that the
?error? matrices Z ? Z? lie in. The proof follows closely along the lines of the
equivalent result in [16], with appropriate modiﬁcations to accommodate our
generalized weighted nuclear norm. (Appendix C.3). 5.1

Comparison to Standard Matrix Completion:
It is instructive to consider our result in the context of noisy matrix comple-
tion with uniform samples. In this case, one would replace Lw , Lh by identity
matrices, eﬀectively ignoring graph information p 1 available. Speciﬁcally, the
?standard? notion of spikiness (?n := mn kZk kZkF ) deﬁned in [16] will apply,
and the corresponding error bound (Theorem 2) will have ?? replaced by ?n (Z
? ). In general, it is hard to quantify the relationship between ?g and ?n , and a
detailed comparison is an interesting topic for future work. However, we show
below using simulations for various scenarios that the former is much smaller
than the latter. We generate m ? m matrices of rank k = 10, M = U ?V T
with U, V being random orthonormal matrices and ? having diagonal elements
picked from a uniform[0, 1] distribution. We generate graphs at random using
the schemes discussed below, and set Z = AM B T , with A, B as deﬁned in
Corollary 1. We then compute ?n , ?g for various m. Comparing ?g to ?n :
Most real world graphs exhibit a power law degree distribution. We generated
graphs with the ith node having degree (m ? ip ) with varying negative p values.
Figure 1(a) shows that as p ! 0 from below, the gains received from using our
norm is clear compared to the standard nuclear norm. We also observe that in
general the weighted formulation is never worse then unweighted (The dotted
magenta line is ?n /?g = 1). The same applies for random graphs, where there
is an edge between each (i, j) with varying probability p (Figure 1(b)). ?4

25
5
m = 100 m = 200 m = 300
20
4

9

6
m = 100 m = 200 m = 300
x 10
GWNN NN
5
10
MSE
?n / ?g
?n / ?g
4
15
3
3 2
2
5 0 ?0.1
1
?0.2
?0.5
?1
?1.5
p
?2
1 0.1
0.15
(a) Power Law
0.2
0.25
0.5
p
(b) Random
1
0 0
1
2 3 # measurements x 1000
4
(c) Sample Complexity
Figure 1: (a), (b): Ratio of spikiness measures for traditional matrix com-
pletion and our formulation. (c): Sample complexity for the nuclear norm (NN)
and generalized weighted nuclear norm (GWNN) Sample Complexity: We tested
the sample complexity needed to recover a m = n = 200, k = 20 matrix, gen-
erated from a power law distributed graph with p = 0.5. Figure 1(c) again
outlines that the atomic formulation requires fewer examples to get an accurate
recovery. We average the results over 10 independent runs, and we used [18] to
solve the atomic norm constrained problem.

6
Experiments on Real Datasets

10

Comparison to Related Formulations: We compare GRALS to other meth-
ods that incorporate side information for matrix completion: the ADMM method
of [12] that regularizes the entire target matrix; using known features (IMC)
[10, 24]; and standard matrix completion (MC). We use the MOVIELENS 100k
dataset,6 that has user/movie features along with the ratings matrix. The
dataset contains user features (such as age (numeric), gender (binary), and oc-
cupation), which we map 6

http://grouplens.org/datasets/movielens/
7
1.25
Method IMC Global mean User mean Movie mean ADMM MC GRALS
ADMM MC GRALS
1.2
RMSE
1.15 1.1 1.05 1 0.95 0.9 ?4
?2
0
2 log10(time) (s)
4
6
8
Figure 2: Time comparison of diﬀerent methods on MOVIELENS 100k

Dataset Flixster ([11]) Douban ([14]) YahooMusic ([8])

RMSE 1.653 1.154 1.063 1.033 0.996 0.973 0.945
Table 1: RMSE on the MOVIELENS dataset
Table 2: Data statistics. # users # items # ratings 147,612 48,794 8,196,077

129,490 58,541 16,830,839 249,012 296,111 55,749,965

# links 2,538,746 1,711,802 57,248,136
rank used 10 10 20
into a 22 dimensional feature vector per user. We then construct a 10-nearest
neighbor graph using the euclidean distance metric. We do the same for the
movies, except in this case we have an 18 dimensional feature vector per movie.
For IMC, we use the feature vectors directly. We trained a model of rank 10,
and chose optimal parameters by cross validation. Table 1 shows the RMSE
obtained for the methods considered. Figure 2 shows that the ADMM method,
while obtaining a reasonable RMSE does not scale well, since one has to com-
pute an SVD at each iteration. Scalability of GRALS: We now demonstrate
that the proposed GRALS method is more eﬃcient than other state-of-the-art
methods for solving the graph-regularized matrix factorization problem (5). We
compare GRALS to the SGD method in [27], and GD: ALS with simple gradient
descent. We consider three large-scale real-world collaborate ﬁltering datasets
with graph information: see Table 2 for details.7 We randomly select 90% of
ratings as the training set and use the remaining 10% as the test set. All the
experiments are performed on an Intel machine with Xeon CPU E52680 v2 Ivy
Bridge and enough RAM. Figure 3 shows orders of magnitude improvement in

11

time compared to SGD. More experimental results are provided in the supple-
mentary material.

(a) Flixster
(b) Douban
(c) YahooMusic
Figure 3: Comparison of GRALS, GD, and SGD. The x-axis is the compu-

tation time in log-scale.

7
Discussion
In this paper, we have considered the problem of collaborative ﬁltering with
graph information for users and/or items, and showed that it can be cast as
a generalized weighted nuclear norm problem. We derived statistical consis-
tency guarantees for our method, and developed a highly scalable alternating
minimization method. Experiments on large real world datasets show that our
method achieves ? 2 orders of magnitude speedups over competing approaches.

Acknowledgments
This research was supported by NSF grant CCF-1320746. H.-F. Yu acknowl-
edges support from an Intel PhD fellowship. NR was supported by an ICES
fellowship. 7

See more details in Appendix D.
8

2 References

[1] Jacob Abernethy, Francis Bach, Theodoros Evgeniou, and Jean-Philippe
Vert. Low-rank matrix factorization with attributes. arXiv preprint cs/0611124,
[2] Francis Bach, Julien Mairal, and Jean Ponce. Convex sparse matrix
2006.
factorizations. CoRR, abs/0812.1869, 2008.
[3] Mikhail Belkin and Partha
Niyogi. Laplacian eigenmaps and spectral techniques for embedding and clus-
tering. In NIPS, volume 14, pages 585?591, 2001. [4] Mikhail Belkin and Partha
Niyogi. Laplacian eigenmaps for dimensionality reduction and data represen-
tation. Neural computation, 15(6):1373?1396, 2003. [5] Deng Cai, Xiaofei He,
Jiawei Han, and Thomas S Huang. Graph regularized nonnegative matrix fac-
torization for data representation. Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence,
IEEE Transactions on, 33(8): 1548?1560, 2011.
[6] Jian-Feng Cai, Emmanuel
J Cand‘es, and Zuowei Shen. A singular value thresholding algorithm for ma-
trix completion. SIAM Journal on Optimization, 20(4):1956?1982, 2010.
[7]
Venkat Chandrasekaran, Benjamin Recht, Pablo A Parrilo, and Alan S Willsky.
The convex geometry of linear inverse problems. Foundations of Computational
Mathematics, 12(6):805?849, 2012. [8] Gideon Dror, Noam Koenigstein, Yehuda
Koren, and Markus Weimer. The yahoo! music dataset and kdd-cup?11. In
KDD Cup, pages 8?18, 2012.
[9] Benjamin Haeﬀele, Eric Young, and Rene
Vidal. Structured low-rank matrix factorization: Optimality, algorithm, and
applications to image processing. In Proceedings of the 31st International Con-
ference on Machine Learning (ICML-14), pages 2007?2015, 2014.
[10] Pra-

12

teek Jain and Inderjit S Dhillon. Provable inductive matrix completion. arXiv
preprint arXiv:1306.0626, 2013. [11] Mohsen Jamali and Martin Ester. A ma-
trix factorization technique with trust propagation for recommendation in social
networks. In Proceedings of the Fourth ACM Conference on Recommender Sys-
tems, RecSys ?10, pages 135?142, 2010. [12] Vassilis Kalofolias, Xavier Bresson,
Michael Bronstein, and Pierre Vandergheynst. Matrix completion on graphs.
(EPFL-CONF-203064), 2014.
[13] Wu-Jun Li and Dit-Yan Yeung. Relation
regularized matrix factorization. In 21st International Joint Conference on Ar-
tiﬁcial Intelligence, 2009. [14] Hao Ma, Dengyong Zhou, Chao Liu, Michael R.
Lyu, and Irwin King. Recommender systems with social regularization. In Pro-
ceedings of the fourth ACM international conference on Web search and data
mining, WSDM ?11, pages 287?296, Hong Kong, China, 2011. [15] Paolo Massa
and Paolo Avesani. Trust-aware bootstrapping of recommender systems. ECAI
Workshop on Recommender Systems, pages 29?33, 2006.
[16] Sahand Negah-
ban and Martin J Wainwright. Restricted strong convexity and weighted matrix
completion: Optimal bounds with noise. The Journal of Machine Learning Re-
search, 13(1):1665?1697, 2012. [17] Sahand N Negahban, Pradeep Ravikumar,
Martin J Wainwright, and Bin Yu. A uniﬁed framework for high-dimensional
analysis of m-estimators with decomposable regularizers. Statistical Science,
27(4): 538?557, 2012.
[18] Nikhil Rao, Parikshit Shah, and Stephen Wright.
Conditional gradient with enhancement and truncation for atomic-norm regu-
larization. NIPS workshop on Greedy Algorithms, 2013. [19] Benjamin Recht.
A simpler approach to matrix completion. The Journal of Machine Learning
Research, 12:3413?3430, 2011. [20] Alexander J Smola and Risi Kondor. Ker-
In Learning theory and kernel machines,
nels and regularization on graphs.
pages 144?158. Springer, 2003.
[21] Nathan Srebro and Ruslan R Salakhutdi-
nov. Collaborative ﬁltering in a non-uniform world: Learning with the weighted
In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages
trace norm.
2056?2064, 2010.
[22] Ambuj Tewari, Pradeep K Ravikumar, and Inderjit S
Dhillon. Greedy algorithms for structurally constrained high dimensional prob-
lems. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 882? 890,
2011. [23] Roman Vershynin. A note on sums of independent random matrices
after ahlswede-winter. Lecture notes, 2009. [24] Miao Xu, Rong Jin, and Zhi-
Hua Zhou. Speedup matrix completion with side information: Application to
multi-label learning. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems,
pages 2301?2309, 2013. [25] Yangyang. Xu and Wotao Yin. A block coordinate
descent method for regularized multiconvex optimization with applications to
nonnegative tensor factorization and completion. SIAM Journal on Imaging
Sciences, 6(3):1758?1789, 2013. [26] Zhou Zhao, Lijun Zhang, Xiaofei He, and
Wilfred Ng. Expert ﬁnding for question answering via graph regularized matrix
completion. Knowledge and Data Engineering, IEEE Transactions on, PP(99),
2014.
[27] Tinghui Zhou, Hanhuai Shan, Arindam Banerjee, and Guillermo
Sapiro. Kernelized probabilistic matrix factorization: Exploiting graphs and
side information. In SDM, volume 12, pages 403?414. SIAM, 2012.

9

13

