A Probabilistic Programming Approach To

Probabilistic Data Analysis

Authored by:

Vikash K. Mansinghka

Feras Saad

Abstract

Probabilistic techniques are central to data analysis, but diﬀerent ap-
proaches can be challenging to apply, combine, and compare. This paper
introduces composable generative population models (CGPMs), a com-
putational abstraction that extends directed graphical models and can be
used to describe and compose a broad class of probabilistic data analysis
techniques. Examples include discriminative machine learning, hierarchi-
cal Bayesian models, multivariate kernel methods, clustering algorithms,
and arbitrary probabilistic programs. We demonstrate the integration
of CGPMs into BayesDB, a probabilistic programming platform that can
express data analysis tasks using a modeling deﬁnition language and struc-
tured query language. The practical value is illustrated in two ways. First,
the paper describes an analysis on a database of Earth satellites, which
identiﬁes records that probably violate Kepler?s Third Law by composing
causal probabilistic programs with non-parametric Bayes in 50 lines of
probabilistic code. Second, it reports the lines of code and accuracy of
CGPMs compared with baseline solutions from standard machine learning
libraries.

1 Paper Body

Probabilistic techniques are central to data analysis, but can be diﬃcult to ap-
ply, combine, and compare. Such diﬃculties arise because families of approaches
such as parametric statistical modeling, machine learning and probabilistic pro-
gramming are each associated with diﬀerent formalisms and assumptions. The
contributions of this paper are (i) a way to address these challenges by deﬁning
CGPMs, a new family of composable probabilistic models; (ii) an integration of
this family into BayesDB [10], a probabilistic programming platform for data
analysis; and (iii) empirical illustrations of the eﬃcacy of the framework for
analyzing a real-world database of Earth satellites. We introduce composable
generative population models (CGPMs), a computational formalism that gener-
alizes directed graphical models. CGPMs specify a table of observable random

1

variables with a ﬁnite number of columns and countably inﬁnitely many rows.
They support complex intra-row dependencies among the observables, as well
as inter-row dependencies among a ﬁeld of latent random variables. CGPMs are
described by a computational interface for generating samples and evaluating
densities for random variables derived from the base table by conditioning and
marginalization. This paper shows how to package discriminative statistical
learning techniques, dimensionality reduction methods, arbitrary probabilistic
programs, and their combinations, as CGPMs. We also describe algorithms and
illustrate new syntaxes in the probabilistic Metamodeling Language for building
composite CGPMs that can interoperate with BayesDB. The practical value is
illustrated in two ways. First, we describe a 50-line analysis that identiﬁes satel-
lite data records that probably violate their theoretical orbital characteristics.
The BayesDB script builds models that combine non-parametric Bayesian struc-
ture learning with a causal probabilistic program that implements a stochastic
variant of Kepler?s Third Law. Second, we illustrate coverage and conciseness
of the CGPM abstraction by quantifying the improvement in accuracy and re-
duction in lines of code achieved on a representative data analysis task. 30th
Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2016), Barcelona,
Spain.

2
Composable Generative Population Models
A composable generative population model represents a data generating pro-
cess for an exchangeable sequence of random vectors (x1 , x2 , . . . ), called a
population. Each member xr is T -dimensional, and element x[r,t] takes values
in an observation space Xt , for t ? [T ] and r ? N. A CGPM G is formally
represented by a collection of variables that characterize the data generating
process: G = (?, ?, Z = {zr : r ? N}, X = {xr : r ? N}, Y = {yr : r ?
N}). ? ?: Known, ﬁxed quantities about the population, such as metadata and
hyperparameters. ? ?: Population-level latent variables relevant to all members
of the population. ? zr = (z[r,1] , . . . z[r,L] ): Member-speciﬁc latent variables
that govern only member r directly. ? xr = (x[r,1] , . . . x[r,T ] ): Observable
output variables for member r. A subset of these variables may be observed
and recorded in a dataset D. ? yr = (y[r,1] , . . . y[r,I] ): Input variables, such
as ?feature vectors? in a purely discriminative model. A CGPM is required
to satisfy the following conditional independence constraint: ?r 6= r0 ? N, ?t,
t0 ? [T ] : x[r,t] ?? x[r0 ,t0 ] — {?, ?, zr , zr0 }. (1) Eq (1) formalizes the
notion that all dependencies across members r ? N are completely mediated
by the population parameters ? and member-speciﬁc variables zr . However,
elements x[r,i] and x[r,j] within a member are generally free to assume any de-
pendence structure. Similarly, the memberspeciﬁc latents in Z may be either
uncoupled or highly-coupled given population parameters ?. CGPMs diﬀer from
the standard mathematical deﬁnition of a joint density in that they are deﬁned
in terms of a computational interface (Listing 1). As computational objects,
they explicitly distinguish between the sampler for the random variables from
their joint distribution, and the assessor of their joint density. In particular, a
CGPM is required to sample/assess the joint distribution of a subset of output

2

variables x[r,Q] conditioned on another subset x[r,E] , and marginalizing over
x[r,[T ](Q?E)] . Listing 1 Computational interface for composable generative
population models. ? s ? simulate (G, member: r, query: Q = {qk }, evidence
: x[r,E] , input : yr ) Generate a sample from the distribution s ?G x[r,Q]
—{x[r,E] , yr , D}. ? c ? logpdf (G, member: r, query : x[r,Q] , evidence :
x[r,E] , input : yr ) Evaluate the log density log pG (x[r,Q] —{x[r,E] , yr , D}).
? G 0 ? incorporate (G, measurement : x[r,t] or yr ) Record a measurement
x[r,t] ? Xt (or yr ) into the dataset D. ? G 0 ? unincorporate (G, member : r)
Eliminate all measurements of input and output variables for member r. ? G 0
? infer (G, program : T ) Adjust internal latent state in accordance with the
learning procedure speciﬁed by program T .

2.1
Primitive univariate CGPMs and their statistical data types
The statistical data type (Figure 1) of a population variable xt generated
by a CGPM provides a more reﬁned taxonomy than its ?observation space? Xt
. The (parameterized) support of a statistical type is the set in which samples
from simulate take values. Each statistical type is also associated with a base
measure which ensures logpdf is well-deﬁned. In high-dimensional populations
with heterogeneous types, logpdf is taken against the product measure of these
base measures. The statistical type also identiﬁes invariants that the variable
maintains. For instance, the values of a NOMINAL variable are permutation-
invariant. Figure 1 shows statistical data types provided by the Metamodeling
Language from BayesDB. The ﬁnal column shows some examples of primitive
CGPMs that are compatible with each statistical type; they implement logpdf
directly using univariate probability density functions, and algorithms for sim-
ulate are well known [4]. For infer their parameters may be ﬁxed, or learned
from data using, e.g., maximum likelihood [2, Chapter 7] or Bayesian priors [5].
We refer to an extended version of this paper [14, Section 3] for using these
primitives to implement CGPMs for a broad collection of model classes, in-
cluding non-parametric Bayes, nearest neighbors, PCA, discriminative machine
learning, and multivariate kernel methods. 2

Statistical Data Type BINARY NOMINAL COUNT/RATE CYCLIC MAG-

NITUDE NUMERICAL NUMERICAL-RANGED Nominal

Parameters symbols: S base: b period: p ? ? low: l, high:h Count
Measure/?-Algebra
{0, 1} {0 .

. S?1} {0, 1b , 2b , .

.} (0, p) (0, ?) (??, ?) (l, h) ? R

.

.

Magnitude

Poisson Geometric
{0,1}
(#, 2 ) (#, 2[S] ) (#, 2N ) (?, B(R)) (?, B(R)) (?, B(R)) (?, B(R))
BERNOULLI CATEGORICAL POISSON, GEOMETRIC VON-MISES LOG-

NORMAL, EXPON NORMAL BETA, NORMAL-TRUNC

Cyclic
Numerical
Von-Mises
Lognormal Exponential

3

Primitive CGPM
Numerical-Ranged
Normal
NormalTrunc Beta
Frequency
Categorical
Support
Figure 1: Statistical data types for population variables generated by CGPMs
available in the BayesDB Metamodeling Language, and samples from their
marginal distributions. 2.2

Implementing general CGPMs as probabilistic programs in VentureScript
In this section, we show how to implement simulate and logpdf (Listing 1)
for composable generative models written in VentureScript [8], a probabilistic
programming language with programmable inference. For simplicity, this sec-
tion assumes a stronger conditional independence constraint, ?l, l0 ? [L] such
that (r, t) 6= (r0 , t0 ) =? x[r,t] ?? x[r0 ,t0 ] — {?, ?, z[r,l] , z[r0 ,l0 ] , yr , yr0
}.

(2)
In words, for every observable element x[r,t] , there exists a latent variable
z[r,l] which (in addition to ?) mediates all coupling with other variables in the
population. The member latents Z may still exhibit arbitrary dependencies.
The approach for simulate and logpdf described below is based on approximate
inference in tagged subparts of the Venture trace, which carries a full realization
of all random choices (population and member-speciﬁc latent variables) made by
the program. The runtime system carries a set of K traces {(? k , Z k )}K k=1
sampled from an approximate posterior pG (?, Z—D). These traces are assigned
weights depending on the user-speciﬁed evidence x[r,E] in the simulate/logpdf
function call. G represents the CGPM as a probabilistic program, and the
input yr and latent variables Z k are treated as ambient quantities in ? k . The
distribution of interest is Z pG (x[r,Q] —x[r,E] , D) = pG (x[r,Q] —x[r,E] , ?,
D)pG (?—x[r,E] , D)d? ?

Z pG (x[r,E] —?, D)pG (?—D) = pG (x[r,Q] —x[r,E] , ?, D) d? (3) pG

(x[r,E] —D) ? ? PK

K X
1
k k=1 w
pG (x[r,Q] —x[r,E] , ? k , D)wk
where ? k ?G —D. (4)
k=1
The weight wk = pG (x[r,E] —? k , D) of trace ? k is the likelihood of the
evidence. The weighting scheme (4) is a computational trade-oﬀ avoiding the
requirement to run posterior inference on population parameters ? for a query
about member r. It suﬃces to derive the distribution for only ? k , Z pG (x[r,Q]
—x[r,E] , ? k , D) = pG (x[r,Q] , zrk —x[r,E] , ? k , D)dzrk (5) zrk

Z =
Y

4

zrk q?Q
J
1X Y pG (x[r,q] —zrk , ? k ) pG (zrk —x[r,E] , ? k , D)dzrk ? pG (x[r,q]

—zrk,j , ? k ), J j=1

(6)
q?Q
where zrk,j ?G —{x[r,E] , ? k , D}. Eq (5) suggests that simulate can be
implemented by sampling (x[r,Q] , zrk ) ?G —{x[r,E] , ? k , D} from the joint
local posterior, then returning elements x[r,Q] . Eq (6) shows that logpdf can
be implemented by ﬁrst sampling the member latents zrk ?G —{x[r,E] , ? k ,
D} from the local posterior; using the conditional independence constraint (2),
the query x[r,Q] then factors into a product of density terms for each element
x[r,q] . 3
To aggregate over {? k }K k=1 , for simulate the runtime obtains the queried
sample by ﬁrst drawing k ? C ATEGORICAL({w1 , . . . , wK }), then returns
the sample x[r,Q] drawn from trace ? k . Similarly, logpdf is computed using
the weighted Monte Carlo estimator (6). Algorithms 2a and 2b summarize
implementations of simulate and logpdf in a general probabilistic programming
environment. Algorithm 2a simulate for CGPMs in a probabilistic programming
environment. 1: function S IMULATE(G, r, Q, x[r,E] , yr ) 2: for k = 1, . . .
, K do 3: if zrk ? 6 Z k then k 4: zr ?G —{? k , Z k , D} Q k 5: w ? e?E pG
(x[r,e] —? k , zrk ) 6: k ? C ATEGORICAL ({w1 , . . . , wk }) 7: {x[r,Q] ,
zrk } ?G —{? k , Z k , D ? {yr , x[r,E] }} 8: return x[r,Q]

. for each trace k . if member r has unknown local latents . sample them from
the prior . weight the trace by likelihood of evidence .
importance resample
the traces . run a transition operator leaving target invariant . select query
variables from the resampled trace

Algorithm 2b logpdf for CGPMs in a probabilistic programming environ-
ment. 1: function L OG P DF(G, r, x[r,Q] , x[r,E] , yr ) 2: for k = 1, .
,
.
K do 3: Run steps 2 through 5 from Algorithm 2a 4: for j = 1, . . . , J do 5:
zrk,j ?G —{? k , Z k , D ? {yr , x[r,E] }} Q 6: hk,j ? q?Q pG (x[r,q] —? k ,
zrk,j ) P 7: rk ? J1 Jj=1 hk,j k k 8: q k ? r w

.

P
PK K k k 9: return log ? log k=1 q k=1 w
2.3
. for each trace k . retrieve the trace weight . obtain J samples of latents
in scope of member r .
run a transition operator leaving target invariant .
compute the density estimate . aggregate density estimates by simple Monte
Carlo .
importance weight the estimate . weighted importance sampling over
all traces

Inference in a composite network of CGPMs
This section shows how CGPMs are composed by applying the output of one
to the input of another. This allows us to build complex probabilistic models
out of simpler primitives directly as software. Section 3 demonstrates surface-
level syntaxes in the Metamodeling Language for constructing these composite
structures. We report experiments including up to three layers of composed

5

CGPMs. Let G a be a CGPM with output xa? and input y?a , and G b have
output xb? and input y?b (the symbol ? a indexes all members r ? N). The
composition GBb ? GA applies the subset of outputs xa[?,A] of G a to b the
inputs y[?,B] of G b , where —A— = —B— and the variables are type-matched
(Figure 1). This operation b results in a new CGPM G c with output xa?
? xb? and input y?a ? y[?,B] . In general, a collection k {G : k ? [K]} of
CGPMs can be organized into a generalized directed graph G [K] , which itself
is a CGPM. Node k is an ?internal? CGPM G k , and the labeled edge aA ?
bB denotes the composition a GA ? GBb . The directed acyclic edge structure
applies only to edges between elements of diﬀerent CGPMs in the network;
elements xk[?,i] , xk[?,j] within G k may satisfy the more general constraint
(1). Algorithms 3a and 3b show sampling-importance-resampling and ratio-
likelihood weighting algorithms that combine simulate and logpdf from each
individual G k to compute queries against network G [K] . The symbol ? k =
{(p, t) : xp[?,t] ? y?k } refers to the set of all output elements from upstream
CGPMs connected to the inputs of G k , so that {? k : k ? [K]} encodes
the graph adjacency matrix. Subroutine 3c generates a full realization of all
unconstrained variables, and weights forward samples from the network by the
likelihood of constraints. Algorithm 3b is based on ratio-likelihood weighting
(both terms in line 6 are computed by unnormalized importance sampling) and
admits an analysis with known error bounds when logpdf and simulate of each G
k are exact [7]. Algorithm 3a simulate in a directed acyclic network of CGPMs.
1: function S IMULATE(G k , r, Qk , xk[r,E k ] , yrk , for k ? [K]) 2: for j =
1, . . . , J do 3: (sj , wj ) ? W EIGHTED -S AMPLE ({xk[r,E k ] : k ? [K]})
4: 5:
m ? C ATEGORICAL ({w1 , . . . , wJ }) return {xk[r,Qk ] ? sm : k ? [K]}
. generate J importance samples . retrieve jth weighted sample
. resample by importance weights . return query variables from the selected

sample

4
Algorithm 3b logpdf in a directed acyclic network of CGPMs. 1: function S
IMULATE(G k , r, xkQ , xk[r,E k ] , yrk , for k ? [K]) 2: for j = 1, . . . , J do
3: (sj , wj ) ? W EIGHTED -S AMPLE ({xk[r,Qk ?E k ] : k ? [K]}) 4: 5: 6:

. generate J importance samples . joint density of query/evidence
for j = 1, . . . , J 0 do . generate J 0 importance samples (s0j , w0j ) ? W
EIGHTED -S AMPLE ({xk[r,E k ] : k ? [K]}) . marginal density of evidence P
j P 0j 0 return log ? log(J/J ) . return likelihood ratio importance estimate

[J] w / [J 0 ] w

Algorithm 3c Weighted forward sampling in a directed acyclic network of
CGPMs. 1: function W EIGHTED -S AMPLE (constraints: xk[r,C k ] , for k
? [K]) 2: (s, log w) ? (?, 0) . initialize empty sample with zero weight 3: for k
? T OPO S ORT ({? 1 , . . . , ? K }) do . topologically sort CGPMs using
adjacency matrix 4: y?rk ? yrk ? {xp[r,t] ? s : (p, t) ? ? k } . retrieve required
inputs at node k 5:
log w ? log w + logpdf (G k , r, xk[r,C k ] , ?, y?rk ) .
update weight by likelihood of constraint 6: xk[r,C k ] ? simulate (G k , r, C k
, xk[r,C k ] , y?rk ) . simulate unconstrained nodes 7: s ? s ? xk[r,C k ?C k ] .

6

append all node values to sample 8:

3
return (s, w)
. return the overall sample and its weight
Analyzing satellites using CGPMs built from causal probabilistic programs,

discriminative machine learning, and Bayesian non-parametrics

This section outlines a case study applying CGPMs to a database of 1163
satellites maintained by the Union of Concerned Scientists [12]. The dataset
contains 23 numerical and categorical features of each satellite such as its ma-
terial, functional, physical, orbital and economic characteristics. The list of
variables and examples of three representative satellites are shown in Table 1.
A detailed study of this database using BayesDB provided in [10]. Here, we com-
pose the baseline CGPM in BayesDB, CrossCat [9], a non-parametric Bayesian
structure learner for high dimensional data tables, with several CGPMs: a clas-
sical physics model written in VentureScript, a random forest classiﬁer, factor
analysis, and an ordinary least squares regressor. These composite models allow
us to identify satellites that probably violate their orbital mechanics (Figure 2),
as well as accurately infer the anticipated lifetimes of new satellites (Figure 3).
We refer to [14, Section 6] for several more experiments on a broader set of
data analysis tasks, as well as comparisons to baseline machine learning solu-
tions. Name Country of Operator Operator Owner Users Purpose Class of Orbit
Type of Orbit Perigee km Apogee km Eccentricity Period minutes Launch Mass
kg Dry Mass kg Power watts Date of Launch Anticipated Lifetime Contrac-
tor Country of Contractor Launch Site Launch Vehicle Source Used for Orbital
Data longitude radians of geo Inclination radians

International Space Station Multinational NASA/Multinational Government
Scientiﬁc Research LEO Intermediate 401 422 0.00155 92.8 NaN NaN NaN
36119 30 Boeing Satellite Systems/Multinational Multinational Baikonur Cos-
modrome Proton www.satellitedebris.net 12/12 NaN 0.9005899

AAUSat-3 Denmark Aalborg University Civil Technology Development LEO
NaN 770 787 0.00119 100.42 0.8 NaN NaN 41330 1 Aalborg University Denmark
Satish Dhawan Space Center PSLV SC - ASCR NaN 1.721418241

Advanced Orion 5 (NRO L-32, USA 223) USA National Reconnaissance
Oﬃce (NRO) Military Electronic Surveillance GEO NaN 35500 35500 0 NaN
5000 NaN NaN 40503 NaN National Reconnaissance Laboratory USA Cape
Canaveral Delta 4 Heavy SC - ASCR 1.761037215 0

Table 1: Variables in the satellite population, and three representative satel-
lites. The records are multivariate, heterogeneously typed, and contain arbitrary
patterns of missing data.

5
CREATE TABLE satellites ucs FROM ’satellites.csv’; CREATE POPULA-
TION satellites FOR satellites ucs WITH SCHEMA ( GUESS STATTYPES
FOR (*) );

1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28

29 30 31 32 33 34 35 36 37 38 39 40 41 42 43 44 45 46 47 48 49 50

7

CREATE METAMODEL satellites hybrid FOR satellites WITH BASE-
LINE CROSSCAT ( OVERRIDE GENERATIVE MODEL FOR type of orbit
GIVEN apogee km, perigee km, period minutes, users, class of orbit USING
RANDOM FOREST (num categories = 7); OVERRIDE GENERATIVE MODEL
FOR launch mass kg, dry mass kg, power watts, perigee km, apogee km US-
ING FACTOR ANALYSIS (dimensionality = 2); OVERRIDE GENERATIVE
MODEL FOR period minutes AND EXPOSE kepler cluster id CATEGORI-
CAL, kepler noise NUMERICAL GIVEN apogee km, perigee km USING VEN-
TURESCRIPT (program = ’ deﬁne dpmm kepler = () -¿ { // Deﬁnition of
DPMM Kepler model program. assume keplers law = (apogee, perigee) -¿ {
(GM, earth radius) = (398600, 6378); a = .5*(abs(apogee) + abs(perigee)) +
earth radius; 2 * pi * sqrt(a**3 / GM) / 60 }; // Latent variable priors. assume
crp alpha = gamma(1,1); assume cluster id sampler = make crp(crp alpha); as-
sume noise sampler = mem((cluster) -¿ make nig normal(1, 1, 1, 1)); // Simula-
tor for latent variables (kepler cluster id and kepler noise). assume sim cluster id
= mem((rowid, apogee, perigee) -¿ { cluster id sampler() #rowid:1 }); assume
sim noise = mem((rowid, apogee, perigee) -¿ { cluster id = sim cluster id(rowid,
apogee, perigee); noise sampler(cluster id)() #rowid:2 }); // Simulator for ob-
servable variable (period minutes). assume sim period = mem((rowid, apogee,
perigee) -¿ { keplers law(apogee, perigee) + sim noise(rowid, apogee, perigee)
}); assume outputs = [sim period, sim cluster id, sim noise]; // List of out-
put variables. }; // Procedures for observing the output variables. deﬁne
label) -¿ { $label: observe
obs cluster id = (rowid, apogee, perigee, value,
sim cluster id( $rowid, $apogee, $perigee) = atom(value); }; deﬁne obs noise
= (rowid, apogee, perigee, value, label) -¿ { $label: observe sim noise( $rowid,
$apogee, $perigee) = value; }; deﬁne obs period = (rowid, apogee, perigee,
value, label) -¿ { theoretical period = run(sample keplers law($apogee, $perigee));
obs noise( rowid, apogee, perigee, value - theoretical period, label); }; deﬁne
observers = [obs period, obs cluster id, obs noise]; // List of observer proce-
dures. deﬁne inputs = [”apogee”, ”perigee”]; // List of input variables. de-
ﬁne transition = (N) -¿ { default markov chain(N) }; // Transition opera-
tor.
’)); INITIALIZE 10 MODELS FOR satellites hybrid; ANALYZE satel-
lites hybrid FOR 100 ITERATIONS; INFER name, apogee km, perigee km,
period minutes, kepler cluster id, kepler noise FROM satellites; Clusters Iden-
tiﬁed by Kepler CGPM

Period [mins]
4000
Geotail
3000
28
Cluster 1 Cluster 2 Cluster 3 Cluster 4 Theoretically Feasible Orbits
26
2000 Amos5 NavStar
1000 Meridian4
20000 30000 Perigee [km]
Geotail

8

Negligible Noticeable Large Extreme
24 23
Amos5
Meridian4 Orion6
21
0 10000
25
22 Orion6
0
Empirical Distribution of Orbital Deviations
27
Number of Satellites
5000
20 1e-10
40000
1e-5 1e0 1e5 Magntiude of Deviation from Keplers? Law [mins2 ]
1e10
Figure 2: A session in BayesDB to detect satellites whose orbits are likely
violations of Kepler?s Third Law using a causal composable generative popula-
tion model written in VentureScript. The dpmm kepler CGPM (line 17) learns
a DPMM on the residuals of each satellite?s deviation from its theoretical orbit.
Both the cluster identity and inferred noise are exposed latent variables (line
14). Each dot in the scatter plot (left) is a satellite in the population, and its
color represents the latent cluster assignment learned by dpmm kepler. The
histogram (right) shows that each of the four detected clusters roughly trans-
lates to a qualitative description of the deviation: yellow (negligible), magenta
(noticeable), green (large), and blue (extreme). 6

1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 27 28

29 30 31 32

CREATE TABLE data train FROM ’sat train.csv’; .nullify data train ’NaN’;
def dummy code categoricals(frame, maximum=10): def dummy code categoricals(series):

categories = pd.get dummies( series, dummy na=1) if len(categories.columns) ¿
maximum-1: return None if sum(categories[np.nan]) == 0: del categories[np.nan]
categories.drop( categories.columns[-1], axis=1, inplace=1) return categories

CREATE POPULATION satellites FOR data train WITH SCHEMA( GUESS

STATTYPES FOR (*) ); CREATE METAMODEL crosscat ols FOR satel-
lites WITH BASELINE CROSSCAT( OVERRIDE GENERATIVE MODEL
FOR anticipated lifetime GIVEN type of orbit, perigee km, apogee km, pe-
riod minutes, date of launch, launch mass kg USING LINEAR REGRESSION
);

def append frames(base, right): for col in right.columns: base[col] = pd.DataFrame(right[col])

numerical = frame.select dtypes([ﬂoat]) categorical = frame.select dtypes([object])

INITIALIZE 4 MODELS FOR crosscat ols; ANALYZE crosscat ols FOR

100 ITERATION WAIT;

categorical coded = ﬁlter( lambda s: s is not None, [dummy code categoricals(categorical[c])

for c in categorical.columns])

9

CREATE TABLE data test FROM ’sat test.csv’; .nullify data test ’NaN’;

.sql INSERT INTO data train SELECT * FROM data test;

joined = numerical
CREATE TABLE predicted lifetime AS INFER EXPLICIT PREDICT an-

ticipated lifetime CONFIDENCE prediction conﬁdence FROM satellites WHERE
rowid ¿ 1000;

for sub frame in categorical coded: append frames(joined, sub frame) return

joined

(a) Full session in BayesDB which loads the training and test sets, creates a

hybrid CGPM, and runs the regression using CrossCat+OLS.

(b) Ad-hoc Python routine (used by baselines) for coding nominal predictors

in a dataframe with missing values and mixed data types.

Mean Squared Error
102
101
ridge ols lasso kernel forest bayesdb(crosscat+ols) bayesdb(crosscat)
100 1 10
102 Lines of Code
Figure 3: In a high-dimensional regression problem with mixed data types
and missing data, the composite CGPM improves prediction accuracy over
purely generative and purely discriminative baselines. The task is to infer the
anticipated lifetime of a held-out satellite given categorical and numerical fea-
tures such as type of orbit, launch mass, and orbital period. As feature vectors
in the test set have missing entries, purely discriminative models (ridge, lasso,
OLS) either heuristically impute missing features, or ignore the features and
predict the anticipated lifetime using the mean in the training set. The purely
generative model (CrossCat) can impute missing features from their joint distri-
bution, but only indirectly mediates dependencies between the predictors and
response through latent variables. The composite CGPM (CrossCat+OLS) in
panel (a) combines advantages of both approaches; statistical imputation fol-
lowed by regression on the features leads to improved predictive accuracy. The
reduced code size is a result of using SQL, BQL, & MML, for preprocessing,
model-building and predictive querying, as opposed to collections of ad-hoc
scripts such as panel (b). Figure 2 shows the MML program for constructing
the hybrid CGPM on the satellites population. In terms of the compositional
formalism from Section 2.3, the CrossCat CGPM (speciﬁed by the MML BASE-
LINE keyword) learns the joint distribution of variables at the ?root? of the
network (i.e., all variables from Table 1 which do not appear as arguments to
an MML OVERRIDE command). The dpmm kepler CGPM in line 16 of the
top panel in Figure 2 accepts apogee km and perigee km as input variables y =
(A, P ), and produces as output the period minutes x = (T ). These variables
characterize the ellipticalporbit of a satellite and are constrained by the rela-
tionships e = (A ? P )/(A + P ) and T = 2? ((A + P )/2))3 /GM where e is
the eccentricity and GM 7

is a physical constant. The program speciﬁes a stochastic version of Ke-
pler?s Law using a Dirichlet process mixture model for the distribution over

10

errors (between the theoretical and observed period), P ? DP(?, N ORMAL -I
NVERSE -G AMMA(m, V, a, b)),

(?r , ?r2 )—P ? P
r —{?r , ?r2 , yr } ? N ORMAL(?—?r , ?r2 ), where r := Tr ? K EPLER(Ar
, Pr ). The lower panels of Figure 2 illustrate how the dpmm kepler CGPM
clusters satellites based on the magnitude of the deviation from their theoretical
orbits; the variables (deviation, cluster identity, etc) in these ﬁgures are obtained
from the BQL query on line 50. For instance, the satellite Orion6 shown in the
right panel of Figure 2, belongs to a component with ?extreme? deviation.
Further investigation reveals that Orion6 has a recorded period 23.94 minutes,
most likely a data entry error for the true period of 24 hours (1440 minutes); we
have reported such errors to the maintainers of the database. The data analysis
task in Figure 3 is to infer the anticipated lifetime xr of a new satellite, given
a set of features yr such as its type of orbit and perigee km. A simple OLS
regressor with normal errors is used for the response pG ols (xr —yr ). The
CrossCat baseline learns a joint generative model for the covariates pG crosscat
(yr ). The composite CGPM crosscat ols built Figure 3 (left panel) thus carries
the full joint distribution over the predictors and response pG (xr , yr ), leading
to more accurate predictions. Advantages of this hybrid approach are further
discussed in the ﬁgure.

4
Related Work and Discussion
This paper has shown that it is possible to use a computational formal-
ism in probabilistic programming to uniformly apply, combine, and compare a
broad class of probabilistic data analysis techniques. By integrating CGPMs
into BayesDB [10] and expressing their compositions in the Metamodeling Lan-
guage, we have shown it is possible to combine CGPMs synthesized by auto-
matic model discovery [9] with custom probabilistic programs, which accept
and produce multivariate inputs and outputs, into coherent joint probabilistic
models. Advantages of this hybrid approach to modeling and inference include
combining the strengths of both generative and discriminative techniques, as
well as savings in code complexity from the uniformity of the CGPM inter-
face. While our experiments have constructed CGPMs using VentureScript
and Python implementations, the general probabilistic programming interface
of CGPMs makes it possible for BayesDB to interact with a variety systems
such as BUGS [15], Stan [1], BLOG [11], Figaro [13], and others. Each of these
systems provides varying levels of model expressiveness and inference capabil-
ities, and can be used to be construct domain-speciﬁc CGPMs with diﬀerent
performance properties based on the data analysis task on hand. Moreover,
by expressing the data analysis tasks in BayesDB using the model-independent
Bayesian Query Language [10, Section 3], CGPMs can be queried without nec-
essarily exposing their internal structures to end users. Taken together, these
characteristics help illustrate the broad utility of the BayesDB probabilistic pro-
gramming platform and architecture [14, Section 5], which in principle can be
used to create and query novel combinations of black-box machine learning,
statistical modeling, computer simulation, and probabilistic generative models.

11

Our applications have so far focused on CGPMs for analyzing populations from
standard multivariate statistics. A promising area for future work is extending
the computational abstraction of CGPMs, as well as the Metamodeling and
Bayesian Query Languages, to cover analysis tasks in other domains such lon-
gitudinal populations [3], statistical relational settings [6], or natural language
processing and computer vision. Another extension, important in practice, is
developing alternative compositional algorithms for querying CGPMs (Section
2.3). The importance sampling strategy used for compositional simulate and
logpdf may only be feasible when the networks are shallow and the constituent
CGPMs are fairly noisy; better Monte Carlo strategies or perhaps even varia-
tional strategies may be needed for deeper networks. Additional future work for
composite CGPMs include (i) algorithms for jointly learning the internal param-
eters of each individual CGPM, using, e.g., imputations from its parents, and
(ii) new meta-algorithms for structure learning among a collection of compatible
CGPMs, in a similar spirit to the non-parametric divide-and-conquer method
from [9]. We hope the formalisms in this paper lead to practical, unifying tools
for data analysis that integrate these ideas, and provide abstractions that en-
able the probabilistic programming community to collaboratively explore these
research directions. 8

2 References

[1] B. Carpenter, A. Gelman, M. Hoﬀman, D. Lee, B. Goodrich, M. Betancourt,
M. A. Brubaker, J. Guo, P. Li, and A. Riddell. Stan: A probabilistic program-
ming language. J Stat Softw, 2016.
[2] G. Casella and R. Berger. Statistical
Inference. Duxbury advanced series in statistics and decision sciences. Thom-
[3] M. Davidian and D. M. Giltinan. Nonlinear models
son Learning, 2002.
for repeated measurement data, volume 62. CRC press, 1995.
[4] L. Devroye.
Sample-based non-uniform random variate generation.
In Proceedings of the
18th conference on Winter simulation, pages 260?265. ACM, 1986. [5] D. Fink.
A compendium of conjugate priors. 1997. [6] N. Friedman, L. Getoor, D. Koller,
and A. Pfeﬀer. Learning probabilistic relational models. In Proceedings of the
Sixteenth International Joint Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence, IJCAI 99,
Stockholm, Sweden, July 31 - August 6, 1999. 2 Volumes, 1450 pages, pages
1300?1309, 1999. [7] D. Koller and N. Friedman. Probabilistic graphical mod-
els: principles and techniques. MIT press, 2009. [8] V. Mansinghka, D. Selsam,
and Y. Perov. Venture: a higher-order probabilistic programming platform with
programmable inference. CoRR, abs/1404.0099, 2014.
[9] V. Mansinghka, P.
Shafto, E. Jonas, C. Petschulat, M. Gasner, and J. B. Tenenbaum. Crosscat:
A fully bayesian nonparametric method for analyzing heterogeneous, high di-
mensional data. arXiv preprint arXiv:1512.01272, 2015.
[10] V. Mansinghka,
R. Tibbetts, J. Baxter, P. Shafto, and B. Eaves. Bayesdb: A probabilistic pro-
gramming system for querying the probable implications of data. arXiv preprint
arXiv:1512.05006, 2015. [11] B. Milch, B. Marthi, S. Russell, D. Sontag, D. L.
Ong, and A. Kolobov. 1 blog: Probabilistic models with unknown objects.

12

Statistical relational learning, page 373, 2007. [12] U. of Concerned Scientists.
UCS Satellite Database, 2015.
[13] A. Pfeﬀer. Figaro: An object-oriented
probabilistic programming language. Charles River Analytics Technical Re-
[14] F. Saad and V. Mansinghka. Probabilistic data analysis
port, 137, 2009.
with probabilistic programming. arXiv preprint arXiv:1608.05347, 2016.
[15]
D. J. Spiegelhalter, A. Thomas, N. G. Best, W. Gilks, and D. Lunn. Bugs:
Bayesian inference using gibbs sampling. Version 0.5,(version ii) http://www.
mrc-bsu. cam. ac. uk/bugs, 19, 1996.

9

13

