Automatic Neuron Detection in Calcium Imaging

Data Using Convolutional Networks

Authored by:

H. Sebastian Seung

Noah Apthorpe

Alexander Riordan

Robert Aguilar

Jan Homann

Yi Gu

David Tank

Abstract

Calcium imaging is an important technique for monitoring the activ-
ity of thousands of neurons simultaneously. As calcium imaging datasets
grow in size, automated detection of individual neurons is becoming im-
portant. Here we apply a supervised learning approach to this problem
and show that convolutional networks can achieve near-human accuracy
and superhuman speed. Accuracy is superior to the popular PCA/ICA
method based on precision and recall relative to ground truth annotation
by a human expert. These results suggest that convolutional networks are
an eﬃcient and ﬂexible tool for the analysis of large-scale calcium imaging
data.

1 Paper Body

Two-photon calcium imaging is a powerful technique for monitoring the activity
of thousands of individual neurons simultaneously in awake, behaving animals
[1, 2]. Action potentials cause transient changes in the intracellular concentra-
tion of calcium ions. Such changes are detected by observing the ﬂuorescence
of calcium indicator molecules, typically using two-photon microscopy in the
mammalian brain [3]. Repeatedly scanning a single image plane yields a time
series of 2D images. This is eﬀectively a video in which neurons blink whenever
they are active [4, 5]. In the traditional workﬂow for extracting neural activ-
ities from the video, a human expert manually annotates regions of interest
(ROIs) corresponding to individual neurons [5, 1, 2]. Within each ROI, pixel
values are summed for each frame of the video, which yields the calcium signal
of the corresponding neuron versus time. A subsequent step may deconvolve

1

the temporal ﬁltering of the intracellular calcium dynamics for an estimate of
neural activity with better time resolution. The traditional workﬂow has the
deﬁciency that manual annotation becomes laborious and timeconsuming for
very large datasets. Furthermore, manual annotation does not de-mix the sig-
nals from spatially overlapping neurons. Unsupervised basis learning methods
(PCA/ICA [6], CNMF [7], dictionary learning [8], and sparse space-time decon-
volution [9]) express the video as a time-varying superposition of basis images.
The basis images play a similar role as ROIs in the traditional workﬂow, and
their time-varying coeﬃcients are intended to correspond to neural activities.
While basis learning methods are useful for ﬁnding active neurons, they do not
detect low-activity cells?making these methods inappropriate for studies involv-
ing neurons that may be temporarily inactive depending on context or learning
[10]. Such subtle diﬃculties may explain the lasting popularity of manual an-
notation. At ﬁrst glance, the videos produced by calcium imaging seem simple
(neurons blinking on and oﬀ). Yet automating image analysis has not been
trivial. One diﬃculty is that images are corrupted by noise and artifacts due to
brain motion. Another diﬃculty is variability in the appearance of cell bodies,
which vary 30th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS
2016), Barcelona, Spain.

in shape, size, spacing, and resting-level ﬂuorescence. Additionally, diﬀerent
neuroscience studies may require diﬀering ROI selection criteria. Some may
require only cell bodies [5, 11], while others involve dendrites [6]. Some may
require only active cells, while others necessitate both active and inactive cells
[10]. Some neuroscientists may wish to reject slightly out-of-focus neurons. For
all of these reasons, a neuroscientist may spend hours or days tuning the pa-
rameters of nominally automated methods, or may never succeed in ﬁnding a
set of parameters that produces satisfactory results. As a way of dealing with
these diﬃculties, we focus here on a supervised learning approach to automated
ROI detection. An automated ROI detector could be used to replace man-
ual ROI detection by a human expert in the traditional workﬂow, or could be
used to make the basis learning algorithms more reliable by providing good
initial conditions for basis images. However, the usability of an automated al-
gorithm strongly depends on it attaining high accuracy. A supervised learning
method can adapt to diﬀerent ROI selection criteria and generalize them to new
datasets. Supervised learning has become the dominant approach for attaining
high accuracy in many computer vision problems [12]. We assemble ground
truth datasets consisting of calcium imaging videos along with ROIs drawn by
human experts and employ a precision-recall formalism for quantifying accuracy.
We train a sliding window convolutional network (ConvNet) to take a calcium
video as input and output a 2D image that matches the human-drawn ROIs as
well as possible. The ConvNet achieves near-human accuracy and exceeds that
of PCA/ICA [6]. The prior work most similar to ours used supervised learning
based on boosting with hand-designed features [13]. Other previous attempts
to automate ROI detection did not employ supervised machine learning. For
example, hand-designed ﬁltering operations [14] and normalized cuts [15] were
applied to image pixel correlations. The major cost of supervised learning is the

2

human eﬀort required to create the training set. As a rough guide, our results
suggest that on the order of 10 hours of eﬀort or 1000 annotated cells are suf-
ﬁcient to yield a ConvNet with usable accuracy. This initial time investment,
however, is more than repaid by the speed of a ConvNet at classifying new data.
Furthermore, the marginal eﬀort required to create a training set is essentially
zero for those neuroscientists who already have annotated data. Neuroscientists
can also agree to use the same trained ConvNets for uniformity of ROI selec-
tion across labs. From the deep learning perspective, an interesting aspect of
our work is that a ConvNet that processes a spatiotemporal (2+1)D image is
trained using only spatial (2D) annotations. Full spatiotemporal annotations
(spatial locations and times of activation) would have been more laborious to
collect. The use of purely spatial annotations is possible because the neurons
in our videos are stationary (apart from motion artifacts). This makes our task
simpler than other applications of ConvNets to video processing [16].

2
Neuron detection benchmark
We use a precision-recall framework to quantify accuracy of neuron detec-
tion. Predicted ROIs are classiﬁed as false positives (FP), false negatives (FN),
and true positives (TP) relative to ground truth ROIs. Precision and recall are
deﬁned by TP TP precision = recall = (1) TP + FP TP + FN Both measures
would be equal to 1 if predictions were perfectly accurate, i.e. higher numbers
are better.
If a single measure of accuracy is required, we use the harmonic
mean of precision and recall, 1/F1 = (1/precision + 1/recall) /2. The F1 score
favors neither precision nor recall, but in practice a neuroscientist may care
more about one measure than the other. For example, some neuroscientists
may be satisﬁed if the algorithm fails to detect many neurons (low recall) so
long as it produces few false positives (high precision). Other neuroscientists
may want the algorithm to ﬁnd as many neurons as possible (high recall) even
if there are many false positives (low precision). For computing precision and
recall, it is helpful to deﬁne the overlap between two ROIs R1 and R2 as the
Jaccard similarity coeﬃcient —R1 ? R2 —/—R1 ? R2 — where —R— denotes
the number of pixels in R. For each predicted ROI, we ﬁnd the ground truth
ROI with maximal overlap. The ground truth ROIs with overlap greater than
0.5 are assigned to the predicted ROIs with which they overlap the most. These
assignments are true positives. Leftover ROIs are the false positives and false
negatives. 2

We prefer the precision-recall framework over the receiver operating charac-
teristic (ROC), which was previously used as a quantitative measure of neuron
detection accuracy [13]. This is because precision and recall do not depend on
true negatives, which are less well-deﬁned. (The ROC depends on true negatives
through the false positive rate.) Ground truth generation by human annotation
The quantitative measures of accuracy proposed above depend on the existence
of ground truth. For the vast majority of calcium imaging datasets, no objec-
tively deﬁned ground truth exists, and we must rely on subjective evaluation
by human experts. For a dataset with low noise in which the desired ROIs are
cell bodies, human experts are typically conﬁdent about most of their ROIs,

3

though some are borderline cases that may be ambiguous. Therefore our mea-
sures of accuracy should be able to distinguish between algorithms that diﬀer
widely in their performance but may not be adequate to distinguish between
algorithms that are very similar. Two-photon calcium imaging data were gath-
ered from both the primary visual cortex (V1) and medial entorhinal cortex
(MEC) from awake-behaving mice (Supplementary Methods). All experiments
were performed according to the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Ani-
mals, and procedures were approved by Princeton University?s Animal Care and
Use Committee. Each time series of calcium images was corrected for motion
artifacts (Supplementary Methods), average-pooled over time with stride 167,
and then max-pooled over time with stride 6. This downsampling in time was
arbitrarily chosen to reduce noise and make the dataset into a more manageable
size. Human experts then annotated ROIs using the ImageJ Cell Magic Wand
Tool [17], which automatically generates a region of interest (ROI) based on a
single mouse click. The human experts found 4006 neurons in the V1 dataset
with an average of 148 neurons per image series and 538 neurons in the MEC
dataset with an average of 54 neurons per image series. Human experts used
the following criteria to select neurons: 1. the soma was in the focal plane of
the image?apparent as a light doughnut-like ring (the soma cytosol) surround-
ing a dark area (the nucleus), or 2.
the area showed signiﬁcantly changing
brightness distinguishable from background and had the same general size and
shape expected from a neuron in the given brain region. After motion correc-
tion, downsampling, and human labeling, the V1 dataset consisted of 27 16-bit
grayscale multi-page TIFF image series ranging from 28 to 142 frames per series
with 512 ? 512 pixels per frame. The MEC dataset consisted of 10 image series
ranging from 5 to 28 frames in the same format. Human annotation time was
estimated at one hour per image series for the V1 dataset and 40 minutes per
images series for the MEC dataset. Each human-labeled ROI was represented
as a 512 ? 512 pixel binary mask.

3
Convolutional network
Preprocessing of images and ground truth ROIs. Microscopy image series
from the V1 and MEC datasets were preprocessed prior to network training
(Figure 1). Image contrast was enhanced by clipping all pixel values above the
99th percentile and below the 3rd percentile. Pixel values were then normalized
to [0, 1]. We divided the V1 series into 60% training, 20% validation, and 20%
test sets and the MEC series into 50% training, 20% validation, and 30% test
sets. Neighboring ground truth ROIs often touched or even overlapped with
each other. For the purpose of ConvNet training, we shrank the ground truth
ROIs by replacing each one with a 4-pixel radius disk located at the centroid
of the ROI. The shrinkage was intended to encourage the ConvNets to separate
neighboring neurons. Convolutional network architecture and training. The
architecture of the (2+1)D ConvNet is depicted in Figure 2. The input is an
image stack containing T time slices. There are four convolutional layers, a max
pooling over all time slices, and then two pixelwise fully connected layers. This
yields two 2D grayscale images as output, which together represent the softmax

4

probability of each pixel being inside an ROI centroid. The convolutional layers
were chosen to contain only 2D kernels, because the temporal downsampling
used in the preprocessing (?2) caused most neural activity to last for only a
single time frame. Each output pixel depended on a 37 ? 37 ? T pixel ﬁeld
of view in the input, where T is the number of frames in the input image
stack?governed by the length of the imaging experiment and the imaging 3

Initial#Image
Contrast#Enhancement
Human#Labeled#ROIs
ROI#Centroids
V1#Dataset
20?m
MEC#Dataset
Figure 1: Preprocessing steps for calcium images and human-labeled ROIs.
Col 1) Calcium imaging stacks were motion-corrected and downsampled in time.
Col 2) Image contrast was enhanced by clipping pixel intensities below the 3rd
and above the 99th percentile then linearly rescaling pixel intensities between
these new bounds. Col 3) Human-labeled ROIs were converted into binary
masks. Col 4) Networks were trained to detect 4-pixel radius circular centroids
of human-labeled ROIs. Primary visual cortex (V1, Row 1) and medial entorhi-
nal cortex (MEC, Row 2) datasets were preprocessed identically. sampling rate.
T was equalized to 50 for all image stacks in the V1 dataset and 5 for all image
stacks in the MEC dataset using averaging and bicubic interpolation. In the
future, we will consider less temporal downsampling and the use of 3D kernels
in the convolutional layers. The ConvNet was applied in a 37 ? 37 ? T window,
sliding in two dimensions over the input image stack to produce an output pixel
for every location of the window fully contained within the image bounds. For
comparison, we also trained a 2D ConvNet that took as input the time-averaged
image stack and did no temporal computation (Figure 2). We used ZNN, an
open-source sliding window ConvNet package with multi-core CPU parallelism
and FFT-based convolution [18]. ZNN automatically augmented training sets
by random rotations (multiples of 90 degrees) and reﬂections of image patches
to facilitate ConvNet learning of invariances. The training sets were also rebal-
anced by the fraction of pixels in human-labeled ROIs to the total number of
pixels. See Supplementary Methods for further details. The (2+1)D network
was trained with softmax loss and output patches of size 120 ? 120. The learning
rate parameter was annealed by hand from 0.01 to 0.002, and the momentum
parameter was annealed by hand from 0.9 to 0.5. The network was trained for
16800 stochastic gradient descent (SGD) updates for the V1 dataset, which took
approximately 1.2 seconds/update (? 5.5hrs) on an Amazon EC2 c4.8xlarge in-
stance (Supplementary Figure 1). The network was trained for 200000 SGD
updates for the MEC dataset, which took approximately 0.1 seconds/update (?
5.5hrs). The 2D network training omitted annealing of the learning rate and
momentum parameters. The 2D network was trained for 14000 SGD updates
for the V1 dataset, which took approximately 0.9 seconds/update (? 3.75hrs)
on an Amazon EC2 c4.8xlarge instance (Supplementary Figure 1). We per-

5

formed early stopping on the network after 10200 SGD updates based on the
validation loss. Network output postprocessing. Network outputs were con-
verted into individual ROIs by: 1. Thresholding out pixels with low probability
values, 2. Removing small connected components, 3. Weighting resulting pixels
with a normalized distance transform, 4. Performing marker-based watershed
labeling with local max markers, 5. Merging small watershed regions, and 6.
Automatically applying the ImageJ Cell Magic Wand tool to the original im-
ages at the centroids of the watershed regions. Thresholding and minimum
size values were optimized using the validation sets (Supplementary Methods).
Source code. A ready-to-use pipeline, including pre- and postprocessing, Con-
vNet training, and precision-recall scoring, will be publicly available for com-
munity use (https://github.com/ NoahApthorpe/ConvnetCellDetection). 4

A. conv 10x10x1
conv 10x10x1
conv conv max’ﬁlter’ conv 1x1x1 10x10x1 10x10x1 1x1xT 2D’output’ image
3D’image’ input
20’unit’FC’ layer
10’units/conv layer
B. conv 3x3
conv max’ﬁlter’ conv 3x3 2x2 3x3
conv max’ﬁlter’ conv 3x3 2x2 3x3
conv 1x1 2D’image’ output
2D’image’ input
24 units
48
48
72
96
96
120
50’unit’FC’ layer
Figure 2: A) Schematic of the (2+1)D network architecture. The (2+1)D
network transforms 3D calcium imaging stacks ? stacks of 2D calcium images
changing over time ? into 2D images of predicted neuron locations. All con-
volutional ﬁlters are 2D except for the 1x1xT max ﬁlter layer, where T is the
number of frames in the image stack. B) The 2D network architecture. The
2D network takes as input calcium imaging stacks that are mean projected over
time down to two dimensions.

4
Results
ConvNets successfully detect cells in calcium images. A sample image from
the V1 test set and ConvNet output is shown in Figure 4. Postprocessing of
the ConvNet output yielded predicted ROIs, many of which are the same as
the human ROIs (Figure 4c). As described in Section 2, we quantiﬁed agree-
ment between ConvNet and human using the precision-recall formalism. Both
(2+1)D and 2D networks attained the same F1 score (0.71). Full precision-recall

6

curves are given in Supplementary Figure 1. Inspection of the ConvNet-human
disagreements suggested that some were not actually ConvNet errors. To inves-
tigate this hypothesis, the original human expert reevaluated all disagreements
with the (2+1)D network. After reevaluation, 131 false positives became true
positives, and 30 false negatives became true negatives (Figure 4D). Some of
these reversals appeared to involve unambiguous human errors in the original
annotation, while others were ambiguous cases (Figure 4E? G). After reevalua-
tion, the F1 score of the (2+1)D network increased to 0.82. The F1 score of the
human expert?s reevaluation relative to his original annotation was 0.89. These
results indicate that the ConvNet is nearing human performance. (2+1)D ver-
sus 2D network. The (2+1)D and 2D networks achieved similar precision, recall,
and F1 scores on the V1 dataset; however, the (2+1)D network produced raw
output with less noise than the 2D network (Figure 3). Qualitative inspection
also indicates that the (2+1)D network ﬁnds transiently active and transiently
in focus neurons missed by the 2D network (Figure 3). Although such neurons
occurred infrequently in the V1 dataset and did not noticeably aﬀect network
scores, these results suggest that datasets with larger populations of transiently
active or variably focused cells will particularly beneﬁt from (2+1)D network
architectures. ConvNet segmentation outperforms PCA/ICA. The (2+1)D net-
work was also able to successfully locate neurons in the MEC dataset (Figure
5). For comparison, we also implemented and applied PCA/ICA as described
by Ref. [6]. The (2+1)D network achieved an F1 score of 0.51, while PCA/ICA
achieved 0.27. Precision and recall numbers are given in Figure 5. 5

A.
Transiently’active’neuron (2+1)D network 2D’network Overlay 20?m
Neuron’falls’in’and’out’of’focus
20?m
(2+1)D network
2D’network
2
number pixels in image
C.
B.
#10
4
(2+1)D network 2D network
1.5 1 0.5 0
0
0.2
0.4
0.6
0.8
1
pixel intensity
Figure 3: A) The (2+1)D network detected neurons that the 2D network
failed to locate. The sequence of greyscale images shows a patch of V1 neurons

7

over time. Both transiently active neurons and neurons that wane in and out of
the focal plane are visible. The color image shows the output of both networks.
The (2+1)D network detects these transiently visible neurons, whereas the 2D
network is unable to ﬁnd these cells using only the mean-ﬂattened image. B) The
raw outputs of the (2+1)D and 2D networks. C) Representative histogram of
output pixel intensities. The (2+1)D network output has more values clustered
around 0 and 1 compared to the 2D network. This suggests that (2+1)D network
output has a higher signal to noise ratio than 2D network output.

ConvNet accuracy was lower on the MEC dataset than the V1 dataset,
probably because the former has more noise and larger motion artifacts. The
amount of training data for the MEC dataset was also much smaller. PCA/ICA
accuracy was numerically worse, but this result should be interpreted cautiously.
PCA/ICA is intended to identify active neurons, while the ground truth included
both active and inactive neurons. Furthermore, the ground truth depends on
the human expert?s selection criteria, which are not accessible to PCA/ICA.
Training and post-processing optimization for ConvNet segmentation took ?6
hours with a forward pass taking ?1.2 seconds per image series. Parameter
optimization for PCA/ICA performed by a human expert took ?2.5 hours with a
forward pass taking ?40 minutes. This amounted to ?6 hours total computation
time for the ConvNet and ?9 hours for the PCA/ICA algorithm. This suggests
that ConvNet segmentation is faster than PCA/ICA for all but the smallest
datasets.

5
Discussion
The lack of quantitative diﬀerence between (2+1)D and 2D ConvNet accu-
racy (same F1 score on the V1 dataset) may be due to limitations of our study,
such as imperfect ground truth and temporal downsampling in preprocessing. It
may also be because the vast majority of neurons in the V1 dataset are clearly
visible in the time-averaged image. We do have qualitative evidence that the
(2+1)D architecture may turn out to be superior for other datasets, because its
output looks cleaner, and it is able to detect transiently active or transiently
in-focus cells (Figure 3). The (2+1)D ConvNet outperformed PCA/ICA in the
precision-recall metrics. We are presently working to compare against recently
released basis learning methods [7]. ConvNets readily locate inactive neurons
and process new images rapidly once trained. ConvNets adapt to the selection
criteria of the neuroscientist if they are implicitly contained in the training set.
They do not depend on hand-designed features and so require little expertise
in computer vision. ConvNet speed could enable novel applications involving
online ROI detection, such as computer-guided single-cell optogenetics [11] or
real-time neural feedback experiments. 6

B.
A.
20?m
C.
D.
Human

8

(2+1)D&network
Added&by&human&relabeling& Removed&by&human&relabeling&
Human&&&(2+1)D&network&overlay B. F.
C. G.
H.
F1&Score
A. E.
2D Original Labels
20?m
(2+1)D Temporal Original Labels
2D Relabeled
(2+1)D Temporal Relabeled
Human Original to Relabeled
Figure 4: The (2+1)D network successfully detected neurons in the V1 test
set with near-human accuracy. A) Slice from preprocessed calcium imaging stack
input to network. B) Network softmax probability output. Brighter regions are
considered by the network to have higher probability of being a neuron. C)
ROIs found by the (2+1)D network after post-processing, overlaid with human
labels. Network output is shown by green outlines, whereas human labels are
red. Regions of agreement are indicated by yellow overlays. D) ROI labels added
by human reevaluation are shown in blue. ROI labels removed by reevaluation
are shown in magenta. Post hoc assessment of network output revealed a sizable
portion of ROIs that were initially missed by human labeling. E) Examples of
formerly negative ROIs that were reevaluated as positive. F) Initial positive
labels that were reevaluated to be false. G) Examples of ROIs that remained
negative even after reevaluation. H) F1 scores for (2+1)D and 2D networks
before and after ROI reevaluation. Human labels before and after reevaluation
were also compared to assess human labeling variability. Boxplots depict the
variability of F1 scores around the median score across test images.

7
A.
B.
20?m
C.
D.
Human
(2+1)D)network
PCA/ICA
Human)&)(2+1)D)network)overlay
E.
(2+1)D Temporal network
PCA/ PCA ICA
(2+1)D Temporal network
PCA/ PCA ICA
(2+1)D Temporal network
PCA/ PCA ICA

9

Figure 5: The (2+1)D network successfully detected neurons in the MEC
test set with higher precision and recall than PCA/ICA. A) Slice from prepro-
cessed calcium imaging stack that was input to network. B) Network output,
normalized by softmax. C) ROIs found by the (2+1)D network after postpro-
cessing, overlaid with ROIs previously labeled by a human. Network output is
shown by red outlines, whereas human labels are green. Regions of agreement
are indicated by yellow overlays. D) The ROIs found by PCA/ICA are over-
laid in blue. E) Quantitative comparison of F1 score, precision, and recall for
(2+1)D network and PCA/ICA on human-labeled MEC data.

8
Acknowledgments We thank Kisuk Lee, Jingpeng Wu, Nicholas Turner, and
Jeﬀrey Gauthier for technical assistance. We also thank Sue Ann Koay, Niran-
jani Prasad, Cyril Zhang, and Hussein Nagree for discussions. This work was
supported by IARPA D16PC00005 (HSS), the Mathers Foundation (HSS), NIH
R01 MH083686 (DWT), NIH U01 NS090541 (DWT, HSS), NIH U01 NS090562
(HSS), Simons Foundation SCGB (DWT), and U.S. Army Research Oﬃce
W911NF-12-1-0594 (HSS).

2 References

[1] Daniel Huber, DA Gutnisky, S Peron, DH O?connor, JS Wiegert, Lin Tian,
TG Oertner, LL Looger, and K Svoboda. Multiple dynamic representations
in the motor cortex during sensorimotor learning. Nature, 484(7395):473?478,
[2] Daniel A Dombeck, Anton N Khabbaz, Forrest Collman, Thomas
2012.
L Adelman, and David W Tank.
Imaging large-scale neural activity with
cellular resolution in awake, mobile mice. Neuron, 56(1):43?57, 2007.
[3]
Winfried Denk, James H Strickler, Watt W Webb, et al. Two-photon laser
scanning ﬂuorescence microscopy. Science, 248(4951):73?76, 1990.
[4] Tsai-
Wen Chen, Trevor J Wardill, Yi Sun, Stefan R Pulver, Sabine L Renninger,
Amy Baohan, Eric R Schreiter, Rex A Kerr, Michael B Orger, Vivek Ja-
yaraman, et al. Ultrasensitive ﬂuorescent proteins for imaging neuronal ac-
tivity. Nature, 499(7458):295?300, 2013.
[5] Christopher D Harvey, Philip
Coen, and David W Tank. Choice-speciﬁc sequences in parietal cortex dur-
ing a virtual-navigation decision task. Nature, 484(7392):62?68, 2012. [6] Eran
A Mukamel, Axel Nimmerjahn, and Mark J Schnitzer. Automated analysis of
cellular signals from large-scale calcium imaging data. Neuron, 63(6):747?760,
2009.
[7] Eftychios A Pnevmatikakis, Daniel Soudry, Yuanjun Gao, Timothy
A Machado, Josh Merel, David Pfau, Thomas Reardon, Yu Mu, Clay Lace-
ﬁeld, Weijian Yang, et al. Simultaneous denoising, deconvolution, and demix-
ing of calcium imaging data. Neuron, 89(2):285?299, 2016.
[8] Marius Pachi-
tariu, Adam M Packer, Noah Pettit, Henry Dalgleish, Michael Hausser, and
Maneesh Sahani. Extracting regions of interest from biological images with
In Advances in Neural Information Pro-
convolutional sparse block coding.
cessing Systems, pages 1745?1753, 2013.
[9] Ferran Diego Andilla and Fred
A Hamprecht. Sparse space-time deconvolution for calcium image analysis.

10

In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 64?72, 2014.
[10] David S Greenberg, Arthur R Houweling, and Jason ND Kerr. Pop-
ulation imaging of ongoing neuronal activity in the visual cortex of awake
rats. Nature neuroscience, 11(7):749?751, 2008.
[11] John Peter Rickgauer,
Karl Deisseroth, and David W Tank. Simultaneous cellular-resolution opti-
cal perturbation and imaging of place cell ﬁring ﬁelds. Nature neuroscience,
17(12):1816?1824, 2014. [12] Yann LeCun, Koray Kavukcuoglu, Cl?ment Fara-
bet, et al. Convolutional networks and applications in vision. In ISCAS, pages
253?256, 2010. [13] Ilya Valmianski, Andy Y Shih, Jonathan D Driscoll, David
W Matthews, Yoav Freund, and David Kleinfeld. Automatic identiﬁcation of
ﬂuorescently labeled brain cells for rapid functional imaging. Journal of neuro-
physiology, 104(3):1803?1811, 2010. [14] Spencer L Smith and Michael H?usser.
Parallel processing of visual space by neighboring neurons in mouse visual cor-
tex. Nature neuroscience, 13(9):1144?1149, 2010. [15] Patrick Kaifosh, Jeﬀrey D
Zaremba, Nathan B Danielson, and Attila Losonczy. Sima: Python software for
analysis of dynamic ﬂuorescence imaging data. Frontiers in neuroinformatics, 8,
2014. [16] Andrej Karpathy, George Toderici, Sanketh Shetty, Thomas Leung,
Rahul Sukthankar, and Li Fei-Fei. Large-scale video classiﬁcation with convo-
lutional neural networks. In Proceedings of the IEEE conference on Computer
Vision and Pattern Recognition, pages 1725?1732, 2014.
[17] Theo Walker.
Cell magic wand tool. http://www.maxplanckﬂorida.org/ﬁtzpatricklab/ soft-
ware/cellMagicWand/index.html. 2014.
[18] Aleksandar Zlateski, Kisuk Lee,
and H Sebastian Seung. ZNN ? a fast and scalable algorithm for training 3d
convolutional networks on multi-core and many-core shared memory machines.
arXiv:1510.06706, 2015.

9

11

