Unsupervised Domain Adaptation with Residual

Transfer Networks

Authored by:

Michael I. Jordan
Mingsheng Long

Han Zhu

Jianmin Wang

Abstract

The recent success of deep neural networks relies on massive amounts
of labeled data. For a target task where labeled data is unavailable, do-
main adaptation can transfer a learner from a diﬀerent source domain.
In this paper, we propose a new approach to domain adaptation in deep
networks that can jointly learn adaptive classiﬁers and transferable fea-
tures from labeled data in the source domain and unlabeled data in the
target domain. We relax a shared-classiﬁer assumption made by previous
methods and assume that the source classiﬁer and target classiﬁer diﬀer
by a residual function. We enable classiﬁer adaptation by plugging several
layers into deep network to explicitly learn the residual function with refer-
ence to the target classiﬁer. We fuse features of multiple layers with tensor
product and embed them into reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces to match
distributions for feature adaptation. The adaptation can be achieved in
most feed-forward models by extending them with new residual layers and
loss functions, which can be trained eﬃciently via back-propagation. Em-
pirical evidence shows that the new approach outperforms state of the art
methods on standard domain adaptation benchmarks.

1 Paper Body

Deep networks have signiﬁcantly improved the state of the art for a wide variety
of machine-learning problems and applications. Unfortunately, these impressive
gains in performance come only when massive amounts of labeled data are avail-
able for supervised training. Since manual labeling of suﬃcient training data for
diverse application domains on-the-ﬂy is often prohibitive, for problems short of
labeled data, there is strong incentive to establishing eﬀective algorithms to re-
duce the labeling consumption, typically by leveraging oﬀ-the-shelf labeled data
from a diﬀerent but related source domain. However, this learning paradigm
suﬀers from the shift in data distributions across diﬀerent domains, which poses

1

a major obstacle in adapting predictive models for the target task [1]. Domain
adaptation [1] is machine learning under the shift between training and test
distributions. A rich line of approaches to domain adaptation aim to bridge
the source and target domains by learning domain-invariant feature representa-
tions without using target labels, so that the classiﬁer learned from the source
domain can be applied to the target domain. Recent studies have shown that
deep networks can learn more transferable features for domain adaptation [2,
3], by disentangling explanatory factors of variations behind domains. Latest
advances have been achieved by embedding domain adaptation in the pipeline
of deep feature learning which can extract domain-invariant representations [4,
5, 6, 7]. The previous deep domain adaptation methods work under the assump-
tion that the source classiﬁer can be directly transferred to the target domain
upon the learned domain-invariant feature representations. This assumption is
rather strong as in practical applications, it is often infeasible to check whether
the source classiﬁer and target classiﬁer can be shared or not. Hence we fo-
cus in this paper on a more general, and safe, domain adaptation scenario in
which the source classiﬁer and target classiﬁer diﬀer 30th Conference on Neural
Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2016), Barcelona, Spain.

by a small perturbation function. The goal of this paper is to simultane-
ously learn adaptive classiﬁers and transferable features from labeled data in the
source domain and unlabeled data in the target domain by embedding the adap-
tations of both classiﬁers and features in a uniﬁed deep architecture. Motivated
by the state of the art deep residual learning [8], winner of the ImageNet ILSVRC
2015 challenge, we propose a new Residual Transfer Network (RTN) approach
to domain adaptation in deep networks which can simultaneously learn adaptive
classiﬁers and transferable features. We relax the shared-classiﬁer assumption
made by previous methods and assume that the source and target classiﬁers
diﬀer by a small residual function. We enable classiﬁer adaptation by plugging
several layers into deep networks to explicitly learn the residual function with
reference to the target classiﬁer. In this way, the source classiﬁer and target
classiﬁer can be bridged tightly in the back-propagation procedure. The tar-
get classiﬁer is tailored to the target data better by exploiting the low-density
separation criterion. We fuse features of multiple layers with tensor product
and embed them into reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces to match distributions
for feature adaptation. The adaptation can be achieved in most feed-forward
models by extending them with new residual layers and loss functions, and
can be trained eﬃciently using standard back-propagation. Extensive evidence
suggests that the RTN approach outperforms several state of art methods on
standard domain adaptation benchmarks.

2
Related Work
Domain adaptation [1] builds models that can bridge diﬀerent domains or
tasks, which mitigates the burden of manual labeling for machine learning [9, 10,
11, 12], computer vision [13, 14, 15] and natural language processing [16]. The
main technical problem of domain adaptation is that the domain discrepancy in
probability distributions of diﬀerent domains should be formally reduced. Deep

2

neural networks can learn abstract representations that disentangle diﬀerent ex-
planatory factors of variations behind data samples [17] and manifest invariant
factors underlying diﬀerent populations that transfer well from original tasks to
similar novel tasks [3]. Thus deep neural networks have been explored for do-
main adaptation [18, 19, 15], multimodal and multi-task learning [16, 20], where
signiﬁcant performance gains have been witnessed relative to prior shallow trans-
fer learning methods. However, recent advances show that deep networks can
learn abstract feature representations that can only reduce, but not remove, the
cross-domain discrepancy [18, 4]. Dataset shift has posed a bottleneck to the
transferability of deep features, resulting in statistically unbounded risk for tar-
get tasks [21, 22]. Some recent work addresses the aforementioned problem by
deep domain adaptation, which bridges the two worlds of deep learning and do-
main adaptation [4, 5, 6, 7]. They extend deep convolutional networks (CNNs)
to domain adaptation either by adding one or multiple adaptation layers through
which the mean embeddings of distributions are matched [4, 5], or by adding a
fully connected subnetwork as a domain discriminator whilst the deep features
are learned to confuse the domain discriminator in a domain-adversarial train-
ing paradigm [6, 7]. While performance was signiﬁcantly improved, these state
of the art methods may be restricted by the assumption that under the learned
domain-invariant feature representations, the source classiﬁer can be directly
transferred to the target domain. In particular, this assumption may not hold
when the source classiﬁer and target classiﬁer cannot be shared. As theoreti-
cally studied in [22], when the combined error of the ideal joint hypothesis is
large, then there is no single classiﬁer that performs well on both source and
target domains, so we cannot ﬁnd a good target classiﬁer by directly transferring
from the source domain. This work is primarily motivated by He et al. [8], the
winner of the ImageNet ILSVRC 2015 challenge. They present deep residual
learning to ease the training of very deep networks (hundreds of layers), termed
residual nets. The residual nets explicitly reformulate the layers as learning
residual functions ?F (x) with reference to the layer inputs x, instead of directly
learning the unreferenced functions F (x) = ?F (x) + x. The method focuses
on standard deep learning in which training data and test data are drawn from
identical distributions, hence it cannot be directly applied to domain adapta-
tion. In this paper, we propose to bridge the source classiﬁer fS (x) and target
classiﬁer fT (x) by the residual layers such that the classiﬁer mismatch across
domains can be explicitly modeled by the residual functions ?F (x) in a deep
learning architecture. Although the idea of adapting source classiﬁer to target
domain by adding a perturbation function has been studied by [23, 24, 25], these
methods require target labeled data to learn the perturbation function, which
cannot be applied to unsupervised domain adaptation, the focus of this study.
Another distinction is that their perturbation function is deﬁned in the input
space x, while the input to our residual function is the target classiﬁer fT (x),
which can capture the connection between the source and target classiﬁers more
eﬀectively. 2

3
Residual Transfer Networks

3

s In unsupervised domain adaptation problem, we are given a source domain
Ds = {(xsi , yis )}ni=1 of ns t labeled examples and a target domain Dt = {xtj
}nj=1 of nt unlabeled examples. The source domain and target domain are
sampled from diﬀerent probability distributions p and q respectively, and p
6= q. The goal of this paper is to design a deep neural network that enables
learning of transfer classiﬁers y = fs (x) and y = ft (x) to close the source-target
discrepancy, such that the expected target risk Rt (ft ) = E(x,y)?q [ft (x) 6= y]
can be bounded by leveraging the source domain supervised data.

The challenge of unsupervised domain adaptation arises in that the target
domain has no labeled data, while the source classiﬁer fs trained on source
domain Ds cannot be directly applied to the target domain Dt due to the distri-
bution discrepancy p(x, y) 6= q(x, y). The distribution discrepancy may give
rise to mismatches in both features and classiﬁers, i.e. p(x) 6= q(x) and fs (x)
6= ft (x). Both mismatches should be ﬁxed by joint adaptation of features and
classiﬁers to enable eﬀective domain adaptation. Classiﬁer adaptation is more
diﬃcult than feature adaptation because it is directly related to the labels but
the target domain is fully unlabeled. Note that the state of the art deep fea-
ture adaptation methods [5, 6, 7] generally assume classiﬁers can be shared on
adapted deep features. This paper assumes fs 6= ft and presents an end-to-end
deep learning framework for classiﬁer adaptation. Deep networks [17] can learn
distributed, compositional, and abstract representations for natural data such as
image and text. This paper addresses unsupervised domain adaptation within
deep networks for jointly learning transferable features and adaptive classiﬁers.
We extend deep convolutional networks (CNNs), i.e. AlexNet [26], to novel
residual transfer networks (RTNs) as shown in Figure 1. Denote by fs (x) the
source classiﬁer, and the empirical error of CNN on source domain data Ds is
min fs

ns 1 X L (fs (xsi ) , yis ), ns i=1
(1)
where L(?, ?) is the cross-entropy loss function. Based on the quantiﬁcation
study of feature transferability in deep convolutional networks [3], convolutional
layers can learn generic features that are transferable across domains [3]. Hence
we opt to ﬁne-tune, instead of directly adapt, the features of convolutional
layers when transferring pre-trained deep models from source domain to target
domain. 3.1

Feature Adaptation
Deep features learned by CNNs can disentangle explanatory factors of vari-
ations behind data distributions to boost knowledge transfer [19, 17]. However,
the latest literature ﬁndings reveal that deep features can reduce, but not re-
move, the cross-domain distribution discrepancy [3], which motivates the state
of the art deep feature adaptation methods [5, 6, 7]. Deep features in standard
CNNs must eventually transition from general to speciﬁc along the network, and
the transferability of features and classiﬁers will decrease when the cross-domain
discrepancy increases [3]. In other words, the shifts in the data distributions
linger even after multilayer feature abstractions. In this paper, we perform fea-
ture adaptation by matching the feature distributions of multiple layers ‘ ? L

4

across domains. We reduce feature dimensions by adding a bottleneck layer f
cb on top of the last feature layer of CNNs, and then ﬁne-tune CNNs on source
labeled examples such that the feature distributions of the source and target are
made similar under new feature representations in multiple layers L = {f cb, f
cc}, as shown in Figure 1. To adapt multiple feature layers eﬀectively, we pro-
pose the tensor product between features of multiple layers to perform lossless
multi-layer feature fusion, i.e. zsi , ¿?L xs‘ i and ztj , ¿?L xt‘ . We then perform
feature adaptation by minimizing the Maximum Mean Discrepancy j (MMD)
[27] between source and target domains using the fusion features (dubbed tensor
MMD) as

ns X ns ns X nt nt X nt X X X k zsi , zsj k zsi , ztj k zti , ztj min DL (Ds ,

Dt ) = + ?2 , (2) fs ,ft n2s n2t ns nt i=1 j=1 i=1 j=1 i=1 j=1 0

2
where the characteristic kernel k(z, z0 ) = e?kvec(z)?vec(z )k /b is the Gaus-
sian kernel function deﬁned on the vectorization of tensors z and z0 with band-
width parameter b. Diﬀerent from DAN [5] that adapts multiple feature layers
using multiple MMD penalties, this paper adapts multiple feature layers by ﬁrst
fusing them and then adapting the fused features. The advantage of our method
against DAN [5] is that our method can capture full interactions across multi-
layer features and facilitate easier model selection, while DAN [5] needs —L—
independent MMD penalties for adapting —L— layers. 3

Xs
fcb AlexNet, ResNet?
Xt
fcb
?
fcc
fc2
fT ( x )
MMD
?
fc1
?f ( x )
fS ( x ) = fT ( x ) + ?f ( x ) fcc
?f
S
(x)
Ys
fcb
Xs
?
fcc
Xs
Zs
weight layer ?F ( x ) x
MMD

5

fT ( x )
entropy minimization
Yt
fcb
Xt
Zt
?
weight layer
fcc
Xt
F (x) =
+
?F ( x ) + x
Figure 1: (left) Residual Transfer Network (RTN) for domain adaptation,
based on well-established architectures. Due to dataset shift, (1) the last-layer
features are tailored to domain-speciﬁc structures that are not safely transfer-
able, hence we add a bottleneck layer f cb that is adapted jointly with the
classiﬁer layer f cc by the tensor MMD module; (2) Supervised classiﬁers are
not safely transferable, hence we bridge them by the residual layers f c1?f c2 so
that fS (x) = fT (x)+?f (x). (middle) The tensor MMD module for multi-layer
feature adaptation. (right) The building block for deep residual learning; In-
stead of using the residual block to model feature mappings, we use it to bridge
the source classiﬁer fS (x) and target classiﬁer fT (x) with x , fT (x), F (x) , fS
(x), and ?F (x) , ?f (x). 3.2

Classiﬁer Adaptation
As feature adaptation cannot remove the mismatch in classiﬁcation models,
we further perform classiﬁer adaptation to learn transfer classiﬁers that make
domain adaptation more eﬀective. Although the source classiﬁer fs (x) and
target classiﬁer ft (x) are diﬀerent, fs (x) 6= ft (x), they should be related to
ensure the feasibility of domain adaptation. It is reasonable to assume that fs
(x) and ft (x) diﬀer only by a small perturbation function ?f (x). Prior work
on classiﬁer adaptation [23, 24, 25] assumes that ft (x) = fs (x) + ?f (x), where
the perturbation ?f (x) is a function of input feature x. However, these methods
require target labeled data to learn the perturbation function, which cannot be
applied to unsupervised domain adaptation where target domain has no labeled
data. How to bridge fs (x) and ft (x) in a framework is a key challenge of
unsupervised domain adaptation. We postulate that the perturbation function
?f (x) can be learned jointly from the source labeled data and target unlabeled
data, given that the source classiﬁer and target classiﬁer are properly connected.
To enable classiﬁer adaptation, consider ﬁtting F (x) as an original mapping by
a few stacked layers (convolutional or fully connected layers) in Figure 1 (right),
where x denotes the inputs to the ﬁrst of these layers [8]. If one hypothesizes that
multiple nonlinear layers can asymptotically approximate complicated functions,
then it is equivalent to hypothesize that they can asymptotically approximate
the residual functions, i.e. F (x) ? x. Rather than expecting stacked layers
to approximate F (x), one explicitly lets these layers approximate a residual

6

function ?F (x) , F (x) ? x, with the original function being ?F (x) + x. The
operation ?F (x) + x is performed by a shortcut connection and an element-
wise addition, while the residual function is parameterized by residual layers
within each residual block. Although both forms are able to asymptotically
approximate the desired functions, the ease of learning is diﬀerent. In reality, it
is unlikely that identity mappings are optimal, but it should be easier to ﬁnd the
perturbations with reference to an identity mapping, than to learn the function
as new. The residual learning is the key to the successful training of very deep
networks. The deep residual network (ResNet) framework [8] bridges the inputs
and outputs of the residual layers by the shortcut connection (identity mapping)
such that F (x) = ?F (x) + x, which eases the learning of residual function ?F
(x) (similar to the perturbation function across the source and target classiﬁers).
Based on this key observation, we extend the CNN architectures (Figure 1, left)
by plugging in the residual block (Figure 1, right). We reformulate the residual
block to bridge the source classiﬁer fS (x) and target classiﬁer fT (x) by letting x
, fT (x), F (x) , fS (x), and ?F (x) , ?f (x). Note that fS (x) is the outputs of the
element-wise addition operator and fT (x) is the outputs of the targetclassiﬁer
layer f cc, both before softmax activation ?(?), fs (x) , ? (fS (x)) , ft (x) ,
? (fT (x)). We can connect the source classiﬁer and target classiﬁer (before
activation) by the residual block as fS (x) = fT (x) + ?f (x) ,

(3)
where we use functions fS and fT before softmax for residual block to ensure
that the ﬁnal classiﬁers fs and ft will output probabilities. Residual layers f
c1?f c2 are fully-connected layers with c ? c units, where c is the number of
classes. We set the source classiﬁer fS as the outputs of the residual block to
make it better trainable from the source-labeled data by deep residual learning
[8]. In other words, if we set fT as the outputs of the residual block, then we
may be unable to learn it successfully as we do not have target labeled data
and thus standard back-propagation will not work. Deep residual learning [8]
ensures to output valid classiﬁers —?f (x)— —fT (x)— ? —fS (x)—, and more
importantly, 4

makes the perturbation function ?f (x) dependent on both the target classiﬁer
fT (x) (due to the functional dependency) as well as the source classiﬁer fS
(x) (due to the back-propagation pipeline). Although we successfully cast the
classiﬁer adaptation into the residual learning framework while the residual
learning framework tends to make the target classiﬁer ft (x) not deviate much
from the source classiﬁer fs (x), we still cannot guarantee that ft (x) will ﬁt
the target-speciﬁc structures well. To address this problem, we further exploit
the entropy minimization principle [28] for reﬁning the classiﬁer adaptation,
which encourages the low-density separation between classes by minimizing the
entropy of class-conditional distribution fjt (xti ) = p(yit = j—xti ; ft ) on target
domain data Dt as min ft

nt
1 X H ft xti , nt i=1
(4)
t t where Pc H(?) is the entropy function of class-conditional distribution

7

ft (xi ) deﬁned as H (ft (xi )) = ? j=1 fjt (xti ) log fjt (xti ), c is the number
of classes, and fjt (xti ) is the probability of predicting point xti to class j.
By minimizing entropy penalty (4), the target classiﬁer ft (x) is made directly
accessible to target-unlabeled data and will amend itself to pass through the
target low-density regions.

3.3
Residual Transfer Network
To enable eﬀective unsupervised domain adaptation, we propose Residual
Transfer Network (RTN), which jointly learns transferable features and adaptive
classiﬁers by integrating deep feature learning (1), feature adaptation (2), and
classiﬁer adaptation (3)?(4) in an end-to-end deep learning framework, min

fS =fT +?f
+
ns 1 X L (fs (xsi ) , yis ) ns i=1 nt
? X H ft xti nt i=1
(5)
+ ? DL (Ds , Dt ), where ? and ? are the tradeoﬀ parameters for the
tensor MMD penalty (2) and entropy penalty (4) respectively. The proposed
RTN model (5) is enabled to learn both transferable features and adaptive clas-
siﬁers. As classiﬁer adaptation proposed in this paper and feature adaptation
studied in [5, 6] are tailored to adapt diﬀerent layers of deep networks, they can
complement each other to establish better performance. Since training deep
CNNs requires a large amount of labeled data that is prohibitive for many do-
main adaptation applications, we start with the CNN models pre-trained on
ImageNet 2012 data and ﬁne-tune it as [5]. The training of RTN mainly follows
standard back-propagation, with the residual transfer layers for classiﬁer adap-
tation as [8]. Note that, the optimization of tensor MMD penalty (2) requires
carefully-designed algorithm to establish linear-time training, as detailed in [5].
We also adopt bilinear pooling [29] to reduce the dimensions of fusion features
in tensor MMD (2).

4
Experiments
We evaluate the residual transfer network against state of the art transfer
learning and deep learning methods. Codes and datasets will be available at
https://github.com/thuml/transfer-caﬀe. 4.1

Setup
Oﬃce-31 [13] is a benchmark for domain adaptation, comprising 4,110 im-
ages in 31 classes collected from three distinct domains: Amazon (A), which
contains images downloaded from amazon.com, Webcam (W) and DSLR (D),
which contain images taken by web camera and digital SLR camera with dif-
ferent photographical settings, respectively. To enable unbiased evaluation, we
evaluate all methods on all six transfer tasks A ? W, D ? W, W ? D, A ? D,
D ? A and W ? A as in [5, 7]. Oﬃce-Caltech [14] is built by selecting the 10
common categories shared by Oﬃce-31 and Caltech256 (C), and is widely used
by previous methods [14, 30]. We can build 12 transfer tasks: A ? W, D ? W,
W ? D, A ? D, D ? A, W ? A, A ? C, W ? C, D ? C, C ? A, C ? W, and C ? D.

8

While Oﬃce-31 has more categories and is more diﬃcult for domain adaptation
algorithms, 5

Oﬃce-Caltech provides more transfer tasks to enable an unbiased look at
dataset bias [31]. We adopt DeCAF7 [2] features for shallow transfer meth-
ods and original images for deep adaptation methods. We compare with both
conventional and the state of the art transfer learning and deep learning meth-
ods: Transfer Component Analysis (TCA) [9], Geodesic Flow Kernel (GFK)
[14], Deep Convolutional Neural Network (AlexNet [26]), Deep Domain Con-
fusion (DDC) [4], Deep Adaptation Network (DAN) [5], and Reverse Gradient
(RevGrad) [6]. TCA is a conventional transfer learning method based on MMD-
regularized Kernel PCA. GFK is a manifold learning method that interpolates
across an inﬁnite number of intermediate subspaces to bridge domains. DDC
is the ﬁrst method that maximizes domain invariance by adding to AlexNet
an adaptation layer using linear-kernel MMD [27]. DAN learns more trans-
ferable features by embedding deep features of multiple task-speciﬁc layers to
reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces (RKHSs) and matching diﬀerent distributions
optimally using multi-kernel MMD. RevGrad improves domain adaptation by
making the source and target domains indistinguishable for a discriminative
domain classiﬁer via an adversarial training paradigm. To go deeper with the
eﬃcacy of classiﬁer adaptation (residual transfer block) and feature adaptation
(tensor MMD module), we perform ablation study by evaluating several vari-
ants of RTN: (1) RTN (mmd), which adds the tensor MMD module to AlexNet;
(2) RTN (mmd+ent), which further adds the entropy penalty to AlexNet; (3)
RTN (mmd+ent+res), which further adds the residual module to AlexNet. Note
that RTN (mmd) improves DAN [5] by replacing the multiple MMD penalties in
DAN by a single tensor MMD penalty in RTN (mmd), which facilitates much
easier parameter selection. We follow standard protocols and use all labeled
source data and all unlabeled target data for domain adaptation [5]. We com-
pare average classiﬁcation accuracy of each transfer task using three random
experiments. For MMD-based methods (TCA, DDC, DAN, and RTN), we use
Gaussian kernel with bandwidth b set to median pairwise squared distances on
training data, i.e. median heuristic [27]. As there are no target labeled data
in unsupervised domain adaptation, model selection proves diﬃcult. For all
methods, we perform cross-valuation on labeled source data to select candidate
parameters, then conduct validation on transfer task A ? W by requiring one
labeled example per category from target domain W as the validation set, and
ﬁx the selected parameters throughout all transfer tasks. We implement all
deep methods based on the Caﬀe deep-learning framework, and ﬁne-tune from
Caﬀe-provided models of AlexNet [26] pre-trained on ImageNet. For RTN, We
ﬁne-tune all the feature layers, train bottleneck layer f cb, classiﬁer layer f cc
and residual layers f c1?f c2, all through standard back-propagation. Since these
new layers are trained from scratch, we set their learning rate to be 10 times
that of the other layers. We use mini-batch stochastic gradient descent (SGD)
with momentum of 0.9 and the learning rate annealing strategy implemented in
RevGrad [6]: the learning rate is not selected through a grid search due to high
computational cost?it is adjusted during SGD ?0 using the following formula:

9

?p = (1+?p) ? , where p is the training progress linearly changing from 0 to
1, ?0 = 0.01, ? = 10 and ? = 0.75, which is optimized for low error on the
source domain. As RTN can work stably across diﬀerent transfer tasks, the
MMD penalty parameter ? and entropy penalty ? are ﬁrst selected on A ? W
and then ﬁxed as ? = 0.3, ? = 0.3 for all other transfer tasks. 4.2

Results
The classiﬁcation accuracy results on the six transfer tasks of Oﬃce-31 are
shown in Table 1, and the results on the twelve transfer tasks of Oﬃce-Caltech
are shown in Table 2. The RTN model based on AlexNet (Figure 1) outperforms
all comparison methods on most transfer tasks. In particular, RTN substantially
improves the accuracy on hard transfer tasks, e.g. A ? W and C ? W, where the
source and target domains are very diﬀerent, and achieves comparable accuracy
on easy transfer tasks, D ? W and W ? D, where source and target domains
are similar [13]. These results suggest that RTN is able to learn more adaptive
classiﬁers and transferable features for safer domain adaptation. From the re-
sults, we can make interesting observations. (1) Standard deep-learning methods
(AlexNet) perform comparably with traditional shallow transfer-learning meth-
ods with deep DeCAF7 features as input (TCA and GFK). The only diﬀerence
between these two sets of methods is that AlexNet can take the advantage of
supervised ﬁne-tuning on the source-labeled data, while TCA and GFK can
take beneﬁts of their domain adaptation procedures. This result conﬁrms the
current practice that supervised ﬁne-tuning is important for transferring source
classiﬁer to target domain [19], and sustains the recent discovery that deep neu-
ral networks learn abstract feature representation, which can only reduce, but
not remove, the cross-domain discrepancy [3]. This reveals that the two worlds
of deep 6

Table 1: Accuracy on Oﬃce-31 dataset using standard protocol [5] for un-
supervised adaptation. Method TCA [9] GFK [14] AlexNet [26] DDC [4] DAN
[5] RevGrad [6] RTN (mmd) RTN (mmd+ent) RTN (mmd+ent+res)

A?W 59.0?0.0 58.4?0.0 60.6?0.4 61.0?0.5 68.5?0.3 73.0?0.6 70.0?0.4 71.2?0.3

73.3?0.3

D?W 90.2?0.0 93.6?0.0 95.4?0.2 95.0?0.3 96.0?0.1 96.4?0.4 96.1?0.3 96.4?0.2

96.8?0.2

W?D 88.2?0.0 91.0?0.0 99.0?0.1 98.5?0.3 99.0?0.1 99.2?0.3 99.2?0.3 99.2?0.1

99.6?0.1

A?D 57.8?0.0 58.6?0.0 64.2?0.3 64.9?0.4 66.8?0.2 67.6?0.4 69.8?0.2 71.0?0.2
D?A 51.6?0.0 52.4?0.0 45.5?0.5 47.2?0.5 50.0?0.4 49.8?0.4 50.2?0.3 50.5?0.3
W?A 47.9?0.0 46.1?0.0 48.3?0.5 49.4?0.6 49.8?0.3 50.0?0.3 50.7?0.2 51.0?0.1
Avg 65.8 66.7 68.8 69.3 71.7 72.1 72.9 73.7
Table 2: Accuracy on Oﬃce-Caltech dataset using standard protocol [5] for
unsupervised adaptation. Method A?W D?W W?D A?D D?A W?A A?C W?C
D?C C?A C?W C?D Avg TCA [9] 84.4 96.9 99.4 82.8 90.4 85.6 81.2 75.5 79.6
92.1 88.1 87.9 87.0 GFK [14] 89.5 97.0 98.1 86.0 89.8 88.5 76.2 77.1 77.9 90.7
78.0 77.1 85.5 AlexNet [26] 79.5 97.7 100.0 87.4 87.1 83.8 83.0 73.0 79.0 91.9
83.7 87.1 86.1 DDC [4] 83.1 98.1 100.0 88.4 89.0 84.9 83.5 73.4 79.2 91.9 85.4
88.8 87.1 DAN [5] 91.8 98.5 100.0 91.7 90.0 92.1 84.1 81.2 80.3 92.0 90.6 89.3

10

90.1 RTN (mmd) 93.2 98.5 100.0 91.7 88.0 90.7 84.0 81.3 80.4 91.0 89.8 90.4
90.0 RTN (mmd+ent) 93.8 98.6 100.0 92.9 93.6 92.7 87.8 84.8 83.4 93.2 96.6
93.9 92.6 RTN (mmd+ent+res) 95.2 99.2 100.0 95.5 93.8 92.5 88.1 86.6 84.6
93.7 96.9 94.2 93.4

learning and domain adaptation cannot reinforce each other substantially
in the two-step pipeline, which motivates carefully-designed deep adaptation
architectures to unify them. (2) Deep-transfer learning methods that reduce
the domain discrepancy by domain-adaptive deep networks (DDC, DAN and
RevGrad) substantially outperform standard deep learning methods (AlexNet)
and traditional shallow transfer-learning methods with deep features as the
input (TCA and GFK). This conﬁrms that incorporating domain-adaptation
modules into deep networks can improve domain adaptation performance. By
adapting source-target distributions in multiple task-speciﬁc layers using opti-
mal multi-kernel two-sample matching, DAN performs the best in general among
the prior deep-transfer learning methods. (3) The proposed residual transfer
network (RTN) performs the best and sets up a new state of the art result on
these benchmark datasets. Diﬀerent from all the previous deep-transfer learn-
ing methods that only adapt the feature layers of deep neural networks to learn
more transferable features, RTN further adapts the classiﬁer layers to bridge the
source and target classiﬁers in an end-to-end residual learning framework, which
can correct the classiﬁer mismatch more eﬀectively. To go deeper into diﬀerent
modules of RTN, we show the results of RTN variants in Tables 1 and 2. (1) RTN
(mmd) slightly outperforms DAN, but RTN (mmd) has only one MMD penalty
parameter while DAN has two or three. Thus the proposed tensor MMD mod-
ule is eﬀective for adapting multiple feature layers using a single MMD penalty,
which is important for easy model selection. (2) RTN (mmd+ent) performs sub-
stantially better than RTN (mmd). This highlights the importance of entropy
minimization for low-density separation, which exploits the cluster structure of
target-unlabeled data such that the target-classiﬁer can be better adapted to
the target data. (3) RTN (mmd+ent+res) performs the best across all vari-
ants. This highlights the importance of residual transfer of classiﬁer layers for
learning more adaptive classiﬁers. This is critical as in practical applications,
there is no guarantee that the source classiﬁer and target classiﬁer can be safely
shared. It is worth noting that, the entropy penalty and the residual module
should be used together, otherwise the residual function tends to learn useless
zero mapping such that the source and target classiﬁers are nearly identical [8].
4.3

Discussion
Predictions Visualization: We respectively visualize in Figures 2(a)?2(d) the
t-SNE embeddings [2] of the predictions by DAN and RTN on transfer task A ?
W. We can make the following observations. (1) The predictions made by DAN
in Figure 2(a)?2(b) show that the target categories are not well discriminated
by the source classiﬁer, which implies that target data is not well compatible
with the source classiﬁer. Hence the source and target classiﬁers should not
be assumed to be identical, which has been a common assumption made by all
prior deep domain adaptation methods [4, 5, 6, 7]. (2) The predictions made by

11

RTN in Figures 2(c)?2(d) show that the target categories are discriminated 7

(a) DAN: Source=A
(b) DAN: Target=W
(c) RTN: Source=A
(d) RTN: Target=W
6
f S (x )
f T (x )
?f(x )
4 2 0
mean
deviation
Statistics
(a) Layer Responses
-0.5
-1 fs
-1.5
10
ft
20
Class
(b) Classiﬁer Shift
30
Average Accuracy (%)
Layer Responses
8
Weight Parameters
Figure 2: Visualization: (a)-(b) t-SNE of DAN predictions; (c)-(d) t-SNE of

RTN predictions. 100 90 80 70 60

A ?W
50 0.01 0.04 0.07 0.1
C?W
0.4
0.7
1
?
(c) Accuracy w.r.t. ?
Figure 3: (a) layer responses; (b) classiﬁer shift; (c) sensitivity of ? (dashed
lines show best baselines). better by the target classiﬁer (larger class-to-class
distances), which suggests that residual transfer of classiﬁers is a reasonable
extension to previous deep feature adaptation methods. RTN simultaneously
learns more adaptive classiﬁers and more transferable features to enable eﬀec-
tive domain adaptation. Layer Responses: We show in Figure 3(a) the means
and standard deviations of the layer responses [8], which are the outputs of fT
(x) (f cc layer), ?f (x) (f c2 layer), and fS (x) (after element-wise sum opera-
tor), respectively. This exposes the response strength of the residual functions.

12

The results show that the residual function ?f (x) have generally much smaller
responses than the shortcut function fT (x). These results support our moti-
vation that the residual functions are generally smaller than the non-residual
functions, as they characterize the small gap between the source classiﬁer and
target classiﬁer. The small residual function can be learned eﬀectively via deep
residual learning [8]. Classiﬁer Shift: To justify that there exists a classiﬁer
shift between source classiﬁer fs and target classiﬁer ft , we train fs on source
domain and ft on target domain, both provided with labeled data. By taking A
as source domain and W as target domain, the weight parameters of the classi-
ﬁers (e.g. softmax regression) are shown in Figure 3(b), which shows that fs and
ft are substantially diﬀerent. Parameter Sensitivity: We check the sensitivity
of entropy parameter ? on transfer tasks A ? W (31 classes) and C ? W (10
classes) by varying the parameter in {0.01, 0.04, 0.07, 0.1, 0.4, 0.7, 1.0}. The
results are shown in Figures 3(c), with the best results of the baselines shown as
dashed lines. The accuracy of RTN ﬁrst increases and then decreases as ? varies
and demonstrates a desirable bell-shaped curve. This justiﬁes our motivation of
jointly learning transferable features and adaptive classiﬁers by the RTN model,
as a good trade-oﬀ between them can promote transfer performance.

5
Conclusion
This paper presented a novel approach to unsupervised domain adaptation
in deep networks, which enables end-to-end learning of adaptive classiﬁers and
transferable features. Similar to many prior domain adaptation techniques, fea-
ture adaptation is achieved by matching the distributions of features across
domains. However, unlike previous work, the proposed approach also supports
classiﬁer adaptation, which is implemented through a new residual transfer mod-
ule that bridges the source classiﬁer and target classiﬁer. This makes the ap-
proach a good complement to existing techniques. The approach can be trained
by standard back-propagation, which is scalable and can be implemented by
most deep learning package. Future work constitutes semi-supervised domain
adaptation extensions.

Acknowledgments This work was supported by the National Natural Science
Foundation of China (61502265, 61325008), National Key R&D Program of
China (2016YFB1000701, 2015BAF32B01), and TNList Key Project. 8

2 References

[1] S. J. Pan and Q. Yang. A survey on transfer learning. TKDE, 22(10):1345?1359,
2010. [2] J. Donahue, Y. Jia, O. Vinyals, J. Hoﬀman, N. Zhang, E. Tzeng, and
T. Darrell. Decaf: A deep convolutional activation feature for generic visual
recognition. In ICML, 2014.
[3] J. Yosinski, J. Clune, Y. Bengio, and H. Lip-
son. How transferable are features in deep neural networks? In NIPS, 2014. [4]
E. Tzeng, J. Hoﬀman, N. Zhang, K. Saenko, and T. Darrell. Deep domain con-
fusion: Maximizing for domain invariance. 2014. [5] M. Long, Y. Cao, J. Wang,
and M. I. Jordan. Learning transferable features with deep adaptation net-

13

In ICCV, 2015.

works. In ICML, 2015. [6] Y. Ganin and V. Lempitsky. Unsupervised domain
adaptation by backpropagation. In ICML, 2015. [7] E. Tzeng, J. Hoﬀman, N.
Zhang, K. Saenko, and T. Darrell. Simultaneous deep transfer across domains
[8] K. He, X. Zhang, S. Ren, and J. Sun. Deep
and tasks.
residual learning for image recognition. In CVPR, 2016.
[9] S. J. Pan, I. W.
Tsang, J. T. Kwok, and Q. Yang. Domain adaptation via transfer component
analysis. TNNLS, 22(2):199?210, 2011. [10] L. Duan, I. W. Tsang, and D. Xu.
Domain transfer multiple kernel learning. TPAMI, 34(3):465?479, 2012.
[11]
K. Zhang, B. Sch?lkopf, K. Muandet, and Z. Wang. Domain adaptation under
target and conditional shift. In ICML, 2013.
[12] X. Wang and J. Schneider.
Flexible transfer learning under support and model shift. In NIPS, 2014. [13] K.
Saenko, B. Kulis, M. Fritz, and T. Darrell. Adapting visual category models to
new domains. In ECCV, 2010. [14] B. Gong, Y. Shi, F. Sha, and K. Grauman.
Geodesic ﬂow kernel for unsupervised domain adaptation. In CVPR, 2012. [15]
J. Hoﬀman, S. Guadarrama, E. Tzeng, R. Hu, J. Donahue, R. Girshick, T. Dar-
rell, and K. Saenko. LSDA: Large scale detection through adaptation. In NIPS,
2014.
[16] R. Collobert, J. Weston, L. Bottou, M. Karlen, K. Kavukcuoglu,
and P. Kuksa. Natural language processing (almost) from scratch. JMLR,
12:2493?2537, 2011. [17] Y. Bengio, A. Courville, and P. Vincent. Representa-
tion learning: A review and new perspectives. TPAMI, 35(8):1798?1828, 2013.
[18] X. Glorot, A. Bordes, and Y. Bengio. Domain adaptation for large-scale sen-
timent classiﬁcation: A deep learning approach. In ICML, 2011. [19] M. Oquab,
L. Bottou, I. Laptev, and J. Sivic. Learning and transferring mid-level image
representations using convolutional neural networks. In CVPR, June 2013. [20]
J. Ngiam, A. Khosla, M. Kim, J. Nam, H. Lee, and A. Y. Ng. Multimodal deep
learning. In ICML, 2011.
[21] Y. Mansour, M. Mohri, and A. Rostamizadeh.
Domain adaptation: Learning bounds and algorithms. In COLT, 2009. [22] S.
Ben-David, J. Blitzer, K. Crammer, A. Kulesza, F. Pereira, and J. W. Vaughan.
A theory of learning from diﬀerent domains. MLJ, 79(1-2):151?175, 2010. [23]
J. Yang, R. Yan, and A. G. Hauptmann. Cross-domain video concept detection
using adaptive svms. In MM, pages 188?197. ACM, 2007.
[24] Lixin Duan,
Ivor W Tsang, Dong Xu, and Tat-Seng Chua. Domain adaptation from multi-
ple sources via auxiliary classiﬁers. In ICML, pages 289?296. ACM, 2009. [25]
L. Duan, D. Xu, I. W. Tsang, and J. Luo. Visual event recognition in videos by
learning from web data. TPAMI, 34(9):1667?1680, 2012. [26] A. Krizhevsky, I.
Sutskever, and G. E. Hinton. Imagenet classiﬁcation with deep convolutional
neural networks. In NIPS, 2012. [27] A. Gretton, K. Borgwardt, M. Rasch, B.
Sch?lkopf, and A. Smola. A kernel two-sample test. JMLR, 13:723?773, March
2012. [28] Y. Grandvalet and Y. Bengio. Semi-supervised learning by entropy
[29] Tsung-Yu Lin, Aruni RoyChowdhury, and
minimization. In NIPS, 2004.
Subhransu Maji. Bilinear cnn models for ﬁne-grained visual recognition.
In
CVPR, pages 1449?1457, 2015. [30] B. Sun, J. Feng, and K. Saenko. Return of
frustratingly easy domain adaptation. In AAAI, 2016. [31] A. Torralba and A.
A. Efros. Unbiased look at dataset bias. In CVPR, 2011.

9

14

