A Minimax Approach to Supervised Learning

Authored by:

Farzan Farnia

David Tse

Abstract

Given a task of predicting Y from X, a loss function L, and a set of
probability distributions Gamma on (X,Y), what is the optimal decision
rule minimizing the worst-case expected loss over Gamma? In this paper,
we address this question by introducing a generalization of the maximum
entropy principle. Applying this principle to sets of distributions with
marginal on X constrained to be the empirical marginal, we provide a
minimax interpretation of the maximum likelihood problem over gener-
alized linear models as well as some popular regularization schemes. For
quadratic and logarithmic loss functions we revisit well-known linear and
logistic regression models. Moreover, for the 0-1 loss we derive a classiﬁer
which we call the minimax SVM. The minimax SVM minimizes the worst-
case expected 0-1 loss over the proposed Gamma by solving a tractable
optimization problem. We perform several numerical experiments to show
the power of the minimax SVM in outperforming the SVM.

1 Paper Body

.

.

Supervised learning, the task of inferring a function that predicts a target Y
from a feature vector X = (X1 , . . . , Xd ) by using n labeled training sam-
ples {(x1 , y1 ), .
, (xn , yn )}, has been a problem of central interest
in machine learning. Given the underlying distribution P?X,Y , the optimal
prediction rules had long been studied and formulated in the statistics litera-
ture. However, the advent of highdimensional problems raised this important
question: What would be a good prediction rule when we do not have enough
samples to estimate the underlying distribution? To understand the diﬃculty
of learning in high-dimensional settings, consider a genome-based classiﬁcation
task where we seek to predict a binary trait of interest Y from an observation of
3, 000, 000 SNPs, each of which can be considered as a discrete variable Xi ? {0,
1, 2}. Hence, to estimate the underlying distribution we need O(33,000,000 )
samples. With no possibility of estimating the underlying P? in such problems,
several approaches have been proposed to deal with high-dimensional settings.
The standard approach in statistical learning theory is empirical risk minimiza-
tion (ERM) [1]. ERM learns the prediction rule by minimizing an approximated

1

loss under the empirical distribution of samples. However, to avoid overﬁtting,
ERM restricts the set of allowable decision rules to a class of functions with
limited complexity measured through its VC-dimension. This paper focuses on
a complementary approach to ERM where one can learn the prediction rule
through minimizing a decision rule?s worst-case loss over a larger set of dis-
tributions ?(P? ) centered at the empirical distribution P? . In other words,
instead of restricting the class of decision rules, we consider and evaluate all
possible decision rules, but based on a more stringent criterion that they will
have to perform well over all distributions in ?(P? ). As seen in Figure 1, this
minimax approach can be broken into three main steps: 1. We compute the
empirical distribution P? from the data, ?

Department of Electrical Engineering, Stanford University, Stanford, CA

94305.

30th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2016),

Barcelona, Spain.

Figure 1: Minimax Approach
Figure 2: Minimax-hinge Loss
2. We form a distribution set ?(P? ) based on P? , 3. We learn a prediction
rule ? ? that minimizes the worst-case expected loss over ?(P? ). Some spe-
cial cases of this minimax approach, which are based on learning a prediction
rule from low-order marginal/moments, have been addressed in the literature:
[2] solves a robust minimax classiﬁcation problem for continuous settings with
ﬁxed ﬁrst and second-order moments; [3] develops a classiﬁcation approach by
minimizing the worst-case hinge loss subject to ﬁxed low-order marginals; [4]
ﬁts a model minimizing the maximal correlation under ﬁxed pairwise marginals
to design a robust classiﬁcation scheme. In this paper, we develop a general
minimax approach for supervised learning problems with arbitrary loss func-
tions. To formulate Step 3 in Figure 1, given a general loss function L and set
of distribution ?(P? ) we generalize the problem formulation discussed at [3] to

argmin max E L Y, ?(X) . (1) ???
P ??(P? )
Here, ? is the space of all decision rules. Notice the diﬀerence with the ERM
problem where ? was restricted to smaller function classes while ?(P? ) = {P? }.
If we have to predict Y with no access to X, (1) will reduce to the formulation
studied at [5]. There, the authors propose to use the principle of maximum
entropy [6], for a generalized deﬁnition of entropy, to ﬁnd the optimal prediction
rule minimizing the worst-case expected loss. By the principle of maximum
entropy, we should predict based on a distribution in ?(P? ) that maximizes the
entropy function. How can we use the principle of maximum entropy to solve
(1) when we observe X as well? A natural idea is to apply the maximum entropy
principle to the conditional PY —X=x instead of the marginal PY . This idea
motivates a generalized version of the principle of maximum entropy, which we
call the principle of maximum conditional entropy. In fact, this principle breaks
Step 3 into two smaller steps: 3a. We search for P ? the distribution maximizing
the conditional entropy over ?(P? ), 3b. We ﬁnd ? ? the optimal decision rule for
P ? . Although the principle of maximum conditional entropy characterizes the

2

solution to (1), computing the maximizing distribution is hard in general. In [7],
the authors propose a conditional version of the principle of maximum entropy,
for the speciﬁc case of Shannon entropy, and draw the principle?s connection
to (1). They call it the principle of minimum mutual information, by which
one should predict based on the distribution minimizing mutual information
among X and Y . However, they develop their theory targeting a broad class of
distribution sets, which results in a convex problem, yet the number of variables
is exponential in the dimension of the problem. To overcome this issue, we
propose a speciﬁc structure for the distribution set by matching the marginal
PX of all the joint distributions PX,Y in ?(P? ) to the empirical marginal P?X
while matching only the cross-moments between X and Y with those of the
empirical distribution P?X,Y . We show that this choice of ?(P? ) has two key
advantages: 1) the minimax decision rule ? ? can be computed eﬃciently; 2) the
minimax generalization error can be controlled by allowing a level of uncertainty
in the matching of the cross-moments, which can be viewed as regularization
in the minimax framework. Our solution is achieved through convex duality.
For some loss functions, the dual problem turns out to be equivalent to the
maximum likelihood problem for generalized linear models. For example, 2

under quadratic and logarithmic loss functions this minimax approach re-
visits the linear and logistic regression models respectively. On the other hand,
for 0-1 loss, the minimax approach leads to a new randomized linear classiﬁer
which we call the minimax SVM. The minimax SVM minimizes the worst-case
expected 0-1 loss over ?(P? ) by solving a tractable optimization problem. In
contrast, the classic ERM formulation of minimizing the 0-1 loss over linear
classiﬁers is well-known to be NP-hard [8]. Interestingly, the dual problem for
the 0-1 loss minimax problem corresponds also to an ERM problem for linear
classiﬁers, but with a loss function diﬀerent from 0-1 loss. This loss function,
which we call the minimax-hinge loss, is also diﬀerent from the classic hinge
loss (Figure 2). We emphasize that while the hinge loss is an adhoc surrogate
loss function chosen to convexify the 0-1 loss ERM problem, the minimax-hinge
loss emerges from the minimax formulation. We also perform several numerical
experiments to demonstrate the power of the minimax SVM in outperforming
the standard SVM which minimizes the surrogate hinge loss.

2
Principle of Maximum Conditional Entropy
In this section, we provide a conditional version of the key deﬁnitions and
results developed in [5]. We propose the principle of maximum conditional en-
tropy to break Step 3 into 3a and 3b in Figure 1. We also deﬁne and characterize
Bayes decision rules for diﬀerent loss functions to address Step 3b. 2.1

Decision Problems, Bayes Decision Rules, Conditional Entropy
Consider a decision problem. Here the decision maker observes X ? X from
which she predicts a random target variable Y ? Y using an action a ? A. Let
PX,Y = (PX , PY —X ) be the underlying distribution for the random pair (X,
Y ). Given a loss function L : Y ? A ? [0, ?], L(y, a) indicates the loss suﬀered
by the decision maker by deciding action a when Y = y. The decision maker
uses a decision rule ? : X ? A to select an action a = ?(x) from A based on an

3

observation x ? X . We will in general allow the decision rules to be random,
i.e. ? is random. The main purpose of extending to the space of randomized
decision rules is to form a convex set of decision rules. Later in Theorem 1,
this convexity is used to prove a saddle-point theorem. We call a (randomized)
decision rule ?Bayes a Bayes decision rule if for all decision rules ? and for all
x ? X : E[L(Y, ?Bayes (X))—X = x] ? E[L(Y, ?(X))—X = x]. It should be
noted that ?Bayes depends only on PY —X , i.e.
it remains a Bayes decision
rule under a diﬀerent PX . The (unconditional) entropy of Y is deﬁned as [5]
H(Y ) := inf E[L(Y, a)]. a?A

(2)
Similarly, we can deﬁne conditional entropy of Y given X = x as H(Y —X

= x) := inf E[L(Y, ?(X))—X = x], ?

and the conditional entropy of Y given X as X H(Y —X) := PX (x)H(Y —X

= x) = inf E[L(Y, ?(X))]. ?

x
(3)
(4)
Note that H(Y —X = x) and H(Y — X) are both concave in PY —X .
Applying Jensen?s inequality, this concavity implies that H(Y —X) ? H(Y ),
which motivates the following deﬁnition for the information that X carries about
Y , I(X; Y ) := H(Y ) ? H(Y —X),

(5)
i.e. the reduction of expected loss in predicting Y by observing X. In [9], the
author has deﬁned the same concept to which he calls a coherent dependence
measure. It can be seen that I(X; Y ) = EPX [ D(PY —X , PY ) ] where D is the
divergence measure corresponding to the loss L, deﬁned for any two probability
distributions PY , QY with Bayes actions aP , aQ as [5] D(PY , QY ) := EP
[L(Y, aQ )] ? EP [L(Y, aP )] = EP [L(Y, aQ )] ? HP (Y ). 3

(6)
2.2 2.2.1
Examples Logarithmic loss
For an outcome y ? Y and distribution QY , deﬁne logarithmic loss as Llog
(y, QY ) = ? log QY (y). It can be seen Hlog (Y ), Hlog (Y —X), Ilog (X; Y
) are the well-known unconditional, conditional Shannon entropy and mutual
information [10]. Also, the Bayes decision rule for a distribution PX,Y is given
by ?Bayes (x) = PY —X (?—x). 2.2.2

0-1 loss
The 0-1 loss function is deﬁned for any y, y? ? Y as L0-1 (y, y?) = I(? y
6= y). Then, we can show X H0-1 (Y ) = 1 ? max PY (y), H0-1 (Y —X) = 1
? max PX,Y (x, y). y?Y

x?X
y?Y
The Bayes decision rule for a distribution PX,Y is the well-known maximum

a posteriori (MAP) rule, i.e. ?Bayes (x) = argmaxy?Y PY —X (y—x). 2.2.3

Quadratic loss

4

The quadratic loss function is deﬁned as L2 (y, y?) = (y ? y?)2 . It can be

seen H2 (Y ) = Var(Y ),

H2 (Y —X) = E [Var(Y —X)],
I2 (X; Y ) = Var (E[Y —X]) .
The Bayes decision rule for any PX,Y is the well-known minimum mean-

square error (MMSE) estimator that is ?Bayes (x) = E[Y —X = x]. 2.3

Principle of Maximum Conditional Entropy & Robust Bayes decision rules
Given a distribution set ?, consider the following minimax problem to ﬁnd
a decision rule minimizing the worst-case expected loss over ? argmin max EP
[L(Y, ?(X))], ???

P ??
(7)
where ? is the space of all randomized mappings from X to A and EP denotes
the expected value over distribution P . We call any solution ? ? to the above
problem a robust Bayes decision rule against ?. The following results motivate a
generalization of the maximum entropy principle to ﬁnd a robust Bayes decision
rule. Refer to the supplementary material for the proofs. Theorem 1.A. (Weak
Version) Suppose ? is convex and closed, and let L be a bounded loss function.
Assume X , Y are ﬁnite and that the risk set S = { [L(y, a)]y?Y : a ? A } is
closed. Then there exists a robust Bayes decision rule ? ? against ?, which
is a Bayes decision rule for a distribution P ? that maximizes the conditional
entropy H(Y —X) over ?. Theorem 1.B. (Strong Version) Suppose ? is convex
and that under any P ? ? there exists a Bayes decision rule. We also assume the
continuity in Bayes decision rules for distributions in ? (See the supplementary
material for the exact condition). Then, if P ? maximizes H(Y —X) over ?, any
Bayes decision rule for P ? is a robust Bayes decision rule against ?. Principle of
Maximum Conditional Entropy: Given a set of distributions ?, predict Y based
on a distribution in ? that maximizes the conditional entropy of Y given X, i.e.
argmax H(Y —X)

(8)
P ??
Note that while the weak version of Theorem 1 guarantees only the existence
of a saddle point for (7), the strong version further guarantees that any Bayes
decision rule of the maximizing distribution results in a robust Bayes decision
rule. However, the continuity in Bayes decision rules does not hold for the
discontinuous 0-1 loss, which requires considering the weak version of Theorem
1 to address this issue. 4

3
Prediction via Maximum Conditional Entropy Principle
Consider a prediction task with target variable Y and feature vector X = (X1
, . . . , Xd ). We do not require the variables to be discrete. As discussed earlier,
the maximum conditional entropy principle reduces (7) to (8), which formulate
steps 3 and 3a in Figure 1, respectively. However, a general formulation of (8)
in terms of the joint distribution PX,Y leads to an exponential computational
complexity in the feature dimension d. The key question is therefore under
what structures of ?(P? ) in Step 2 we can solve (8) eﬃciently. In this section,

5

we propose a speciﬁc structure for ?(P? ), under which we provide an eﬃcient
solution to Steps 3a and 3b in Figure 1.
In addition, we prove a bound on
the excess worst-case risk for the proposed ?(P? ). To describe this structure,
consider a set of distributions ?(Q) centered around a given distribution QX,Y
, where for a given norm k ? k, mapping vector ?(Y )t?1 , ?(Q) = { PX,Y : PX
= QX , ? 1 ? i ? t : k EP [?i (Y )X] ? EQ [?i (Y )X] k ? i }.

(9)
Here ? encodes Y with t-dimensional ?(Y ), and ?i (Y ) denotes the ith entry
of ?(Y ). The ﬁrst constraint in the deﬁnition of ?(Q) requires all distributions
in ?(Q) to share the same marginal on X as Q; the second imposes constraints
on the cross-moments between X and Y , allowing for some uncertainty in
estimation. When applied to the supervised learning problem, we will choose
Q to be the empirical distribution P? and select ? appropriately based on the
loss function L. However, for now we will consider the problem of solving (8)
over ?(Q) for general Q and ?. To that end, we use a similar technique as in
the Fenchel?s duality theorem, also used at [11, 12, 13] to address divergence
minimization problems. However, we consider a diﬀerent version of convex
conjugate for ?H, which is deﬁned with respect to ?. Considering PY as the set
of all probability distributions for the variable Y , we deﬁne F? : Rt ? R as the
convex conjugate of ?H(Y ) with respect to the mapping ?, F? (z) := max H(Y
) + E[?(Y )]T z.

(10)
P ?PY
Theorem 2. Deﬁne ?(Q), F? as given by (9), (10). Then the following duality

holds max H(Y —X) = min

P ??(Q)
A?Rt?d
t
X EQ F? (AX) ? ?(Y )T AX + i kAi k? ,
(11)
i=1
where kAi k? denotes k ? k?s dual norm of the A?s ith row. Furthermore,

for the optimal P ? and A? EP ? [ ?(Y ) — X = x ] = ?F? (A? x).

(12)
Proof. Refer to the the supplementary material for the proof. When applying
Theorem 2 on a supervised learning problem with a speciﬁc loss function, ? will
be chosen such that EP ? [ ?(Y ) — X = x ] provides suﬃcient information to
compute the Bayes decision rule ?? for P ? . This enables the direct computation
of ? ? , i.e. step 3 of Figure 1, without the need to explicitly compute P ? itself.
For the loss functions discussed at Subsection 2.2, we choose the identity ?(Y )
= Y for the quadratic loss and the one-hot encoding ?(Y ) = [ I(Y = i) ]ti=1
for the logarithmic and 0-1 loss functions. Later in this section, we will discuss
how this theorem applies to these loss functions. 3.1

Generalization Bounds for the Worst-case Risk
By establishing the objective?s Lipschitzness and boundedness through ap-
propriate assumptions, we can bound the rate of uniform convergence for the

6

problem in the RHS of (11) [14]. Here we consider the uniform convergence of
the empirical averages, when Q = P?n is the empirical distribution of n samples
drawn i.i.d. from the underlying distribution P? , to their expectations when Q
= P? . In the supplementary material, we prove the following theorem which
bounds the excess worst-case risk. Here ??n and ?? denote the robust Bayes
decision rules against ?(P?n ) and ?(P? ), respectively. 5

Figure 3: Duality of Maximum Conditional Entropy/Maximum Likelihood
in GLMs As explained earlier, by the maximum conditional entropy principle
we can learn ??n by solving the RHS of (11) for the empirical distribution of
samples and then applying (12). Theorem 3. Consider a loss function L with
the entropy function H and suppose ?(Y ) includes only one element, i.e. t = 1.
Let M = maxP ?PY H(Y ) be the maximum entropy value over PY . Also, take
k ? k/k ? k? to be the ‘p /‘q pair where p1 + 1q = 1, 1 ? q ? 2. Given that
kXk2 ? B and —?(Y )— ? L, for any ? ¿ 0 with probability at least 1 ? ? r

4BLM 9 log(4/?) ? ? ? max E[L(Y, ?n (X))] ? max E[L(Y, ?(X))] ? 1+ . (13)
8 n P ??(P? ) P ??(P? ) Theorem 3 states that though we learn the prediction
rule ??n by solving the maximum conditional problem for the empirical case, we
can bound the excess ?-based worst-case risk. This result justiﬁes the speciﬁc
constraint of ﬁxing the marginal PX across the proposed ?(Q) and explains the
role of the uncertainty parameter in bounding the excess worst-case risk. 3.2

A Minimax Interpretation of Generalized Linear Models
We make the key observation that if F? is the log-partition function of an
expoenetial-family distribution, the problem in the RHS of (11), when i = 0
for all i?s, is equivalent to minimizing the negative log-likelihood for ﬁtting a
generalized linear model [15] given by

? An exponential-family distribution p(y—?) = h(y) exp ? T ?(y) ? F? (?)
with the log-partition function F? and the suﬃcient statistic ?(Y ), ? A linear
predictor, ?(X) = AX, ? A mean function, E[ ?(Y )—X = x] = ?F? (?(x)).
Therefore, Theorem 2 reveals a duality between the maximum conditional en-
tropy problem over ?(Q) and the regularized maximum likelihood problem for
the speciﬁed generalized linear model. As a geometric interpretation of this
duality, by solving the regularized maximum likelihood problem in the RHS of
(11), we in fact minimize a regularized KL-divergence argmin EQX [ DKL ( QY
—X —— PY —X ) ] +

PY —X ?SF
t X
i kAi (PY —X )k? ,
(14)
i=1
where SF = {PY —X (y—x) = h(y) exp( ?(y)T Ax?F? (Ax) — A ? Rt?s
} is the set of all exponentialfamily conditional distributions for the speciﬁed
generalized linear model. This can be viewed as projecting Q onto (QX , SF
) (See Figure 3). Furthermore, for a label-invariant entropy H(Y ) the Bayes
act for the uniform distribution UY leads to the same expected loss under any
distribution on Y . Based on the divergence D?s deﬁnition in (6), maximizing
H(Y —X) over ?(Q) in the LHS of (11) is therefore equivalent to the following

7

divergence minimization problem argmin EQX [ D(PY —X , UY —X ) ]. (15)
PY —X : (QX ,PY —X )??(Q)

6
Here UY —X denotes the uniform conditional distribution over Y given any
x ? X . This can be interpreted as projecting the joint distribution (QX , UY
—X ) onto ?(Q) (See Figure 3). Then, the duality shown in Theorem 2 implies
the following corollary. Corollary 1. Given a label-invariant H, the solution to
(14) also minimizes (15), i.e. (14) ? (15). 3.3

Examples
3.3.1
Logarithmic Loss: Logistic Regression
To gain suﬃcient information for the Bayes decision rule under the logarith-
mic loss, for Y ? Y = {1, . . . , t + 1}, let ?(Y ) be the one-hot encoding of Y
, i.e. ? i (Y ) = I(Y = i) for 1 ? i ? t. Here, Pt we exclude i = t + 1 as I(Y =
t + 1) = 1 ? i=1 I(Y = i). Then F? (z) = log 1 +

t X
exp(zj ) ,
t X
?F? (z) i = exp (zi ) / 1 + exp(zj ) , (16)
?1 ? i ? t :
j=1
j=1
which is the logistic regression model [16]. Also, the RHS of (11) will be the
regularized maximum likelihood problem for logistic regression. This particular
result is well-studied in the literature and straightforward using the duality
shown in [17]. 3.3.2

0-1 Loss: Minimax SVM
To get suﬃcient information for the Bayes decision rule under the 0-1 loss,
we again consider the one-hot encoding ? described for the logarithmic loss. We
show in the supplementary material that if ? = (z, 0) and z?(i) denotes the ith
largest element of z ?, z Pk k ? 1 + j=1 z?(j) F? (z) = max . (17) 1?k?t+1 k In
particular, if Y ? Y = {?1, 1} is binary the dual problem (11) for learning the
optimal linear predictor ?? given n samples (xi , yi )ni=1 will be

n 1 ? yi ?T xi 1X min max 0 , , ?yi ?T xi + k?k? . (18) ? n i=1 2 The
ﬁrst term is the empirical risk of a linear classiﬁer over the minimax-hinge loss
max{0, 1?z 2 , ?z} as shown in Figure 2.
In contrast, the standard SVM is
formulated using the hinge loss max{0, 1 ? z}: n

min ?
1X max 0 , 1 ? yi ?T xi + k?k? , n i=1
(19)
We therefore call this classiﬁcation approach the minimax SVM. However,
unlike the standard SVM, the minimax SVM is naturally extended to multi-
class classiﬁcation. Using Theorem 1.A2 , we prove that for 0-1 loss the robust
Bayes decision rule exists and is randomized ? = (A? x, 0) randomly predicts
a label according in general, where given the optimal linear predictor z ?-based
distribution on labels to the following z ? Pkmax ? 1 ? j=1 z?(j) ? if ?(i) ?

8

kmax , ? 1 ? i ? t + 1 : p?(i) = z?(i) + (20) kmax ? ?0 Otherwise. ? in
the ascending order, i.e. z??(i) = z?(i) , and kmax is the largest Here ? is the
permutation sorting z Pk ?(k) ] ¡ 1. For example, in the binary case discussed,
the minimax z(i) ? z index k satisfying i=1 [? SVM ﬁrst solves ?? and then
predicts label y = 1 vs. label y = ?1 with (18) to ﬁnd the optimal T ? probability
min 1 , max{0 , (1 + x ? )/2} . 2

We show that given the speciﬁc structure of ?(Q) Theorem 1.A holds whether

X is ﬁnite or inﬁnite.

7
Dataset adult credit kr-vs-kp promoters votes hepatitis
mmSVM 17 12 4 5 3 17
SVM 22 16 3 9 5 20
DCC 18 14 10 5 3 19
MPM 22 13 5 6 4 18
TAN 17 17 7 44 8 17
DRC 17 13 5 6 3 17
Table 1: Methods Performance (error in %) 3.3.3
Quadratic Loss: Linear Regression
Based on the Bayes decision rule for the quadratic loss, we choose ?(Y ) = Y
. To derive F? , note that if we let PY in (10) include all possible distributions,
the maximized entropy (variance for quadratic loss) and thus the value of F?
would be inﬁnity. Therefore, given a parameter ?, we restrict the second moment
of distributions in PY = {PY : E[Y 2 ] ? ?2 } and then apply (10). We show in
the supplementary material that an adjusted version of Theorem 2 holds after
this change, and 2 z /4 if —z/2— ? ? 2 F? (z) ? ? = (21) ?(—z— ? ?) if
—z/2— ¿ ?, which is the Huber function [18]. Given the samples of a supervised
learning task if we choose the parameter ? large enough, by solving the RHS of
(11) when F? (z) is replaced with z 2 /4 and set ? greater than maxi —A? xi
—, we can equivalently take F? (z) = z 2 /4 + ?2 . Then, by (12) we derive the
linear regression model and the RHS of (11) is equivalent to ? ? ? ?

4
Least squares when = 0. Lasso [19, 20] when k ? k/k ? k? is the ‘? /‘1 pair.
Ridge regression [21] when k ? k is the ‘2 -norm. (overlapping) Group lasso [22,
23] with the ‘1,p penalty when ?GL (Q) is deﬁned, given subsets I1 , . . . Ik of
{1, . . . , d} and 1/p + 1/q = 1, as ?GL (Q) = { PX,Y : PX = QX , (22)

? 1 ? j ? k : k EP Y XIj ? EQ Y XIj kq ? j }.
Numerical Experiments
We evaluated the performance of the minimax SVM on six binary classiﬁ-
cation datasets from the UCI repository, compared to these ﬁve benchmarks:
Support Vector Machines (SVM) [24], Discrete Chebyshev Classiﬁers (DCC)
[3], Minimax Probabilistic Machine (MPM) [2], Tree Augmented Naive Bayes
(TAN) [25], and Discrete R?nyi Classiﬁers (DRC) [4]. The results are summa-
rized in Table 1 where the numbers indicate the percentage of error in the clas-
siﬁcation task. We implemented the minimax SVM by applying the subgradient
descent to (18) with the regularizer ?k?k22 . We determined the parameters by
cross validation, where we used a randomly-selected 70% of the training set for

9

.

.

training and the rest 30% for testing. We tested the values in {2?10 , .
,
210 }. Using the tuned parameters, we trained the algorithm over all the train-
ing set and then evaluated the error rate over the test set. We performed this
procedure in 1000 Monte Carlo runs each training on 70% of the data points
and testing on the rest 30% and averaged the results. As seen in the table,
the minimax SVM results in the best performance for ﬁve of the six datasets.
To compare these methods in high-dimensional problems, we ran an experiment
over synthetic data with n = 200 samples and d = 10000 features. We generated
features by i.i.d. Bernoulli with P (Xi = 1) = 0.7, and considered y = sign(?
T x + z) where z ? N (0, 1). Using the above procedure, we evaluated 19.3%
for the mmSVM, 19.5% error rate for SVM, 19.6% error rate for DRC, which
indicates the mmSVM can outperform SVM and DRC in high-dimensional set-
tings as well. Also, the average training time for training mmSVM was 0.085
seconds, faster than the training time for the SVM (using Matlab?s SVM com-
mand) with the average 0.105 seconds. Acknowledgments: We are grateful to
Stanford University providing a Stanford Graduate Fellowship, and the Center
for Science of Information (CSoI), an NSF Science and Technology Center under
grant agreement CCF-0939370 , for the support during this research. 8

2 References

[1] Vladimir Vapnik. The nature of statistical learning theory. Springer Science
& Business Media, 2013. [2] Gert RG Lanckriet, Laurent El Ghaoui, Chiranjib
Bhattacharyya, and Michael I Jordan. A robust minimax approach to clas-
siﬁcation. The Journal of Machine Learning Research, 3:555?582, 2003.
[3]
Elad Eban, Elad Mezuman, and Amir Globerson. Discrete chebyshev classi-
ﬁers. In Proceedings of the 31st International Conference on Machine Learning
(ICML-14), pages 1233?1241, 2014.
[4] Meisam Razaviyayn, Farzan Farnia,
and David Tse. Discrete r?nyi classiﬁers. In Advances in Neural Information
Processing Systems 28, pages 3258?3266, 2015.
[5] Peter D. Gr?nwald and
Philip Dawid. Game theory, maximum entropy, minimum discrepancy and ro-
bust bayesian decision theory. The Annals of Statistics, 32(4):1367?1433, 2004.
[6] Edwin T Jaynes.
Information theory and statistical mechanics. Physical
review, 106(4):620, 1957.
[7] Amir Globerson and Naftali Tishby. The mini-
mum information principle for discriminative learning. In Proceedings of the
20th conference on Uncertainty in artiﬁcial intelligence, pages 193?200, 2004.
[8] Vitaly Feldman, Venkatesan Guruswami, Prasad Raghavendra, and Yi Wu.
Agnostic learning of monomials by halfspaces is hard. SIAM Journal on Com-
puting, 41(6):1558?1590, 2012.
[9] Philip Dawid. Coherent measures of dis-
crepancy, uncertainty and dependence, with applications to bayesian predictive
experimental design. Technical Report 139, University College London, 1998.
http://www.ucl.ac.uk/Stats/research/abs94.html.
[10] Thomas M Cover and
Joy A Thomas. Elements of information theory. John Wiley & Sons, 2012.
[11] Yasemin Altun and Alexander Smola. Unifying divergence minimisation
and statistical inference via convex duality. In Learning Theory: Conference on

10

In AISTATS, pages 209?216, 2010.

[18] Peter J Huber. Robust Statistics. Wiley, 1981.

Learning Theory COLT 2006, Proceedings, 2006. [12] Miroslav Dud?k, Steven
J Phillips, and Robert E Schapire. Maximum entropy density estimation with
generalized regularization and an application to species distribution modeling.
Journal of Machine Learning Research, 8(6):1217?1260, 2007. [13] Ayse Erkan
and Yasemin Altun. Semi-supervised learning via generalized maximum en-
tropy.
[14] Peter L Bartlett and Shahar
Mendelson. Rademacher and gaussian complexities: Risk bounds and structural
results. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 3(Nov):463?482, 2002. [15] Pe-
ter McCullagh and John A Nelder. Generalized linear models, volume 37. CRC
press, 1989. [16] Jerome Friedman, Trevor Hastie, and Robert Tibshirani. The
elements of statistical learning, volume 1. Springer, 2001. [17] Adam L Berger,
Vincent J Della Pietra, and Stephen A Della Pietra. A maximum entropy ap-
proach to natural language processing. Computational linguistics, 22(1):39?71,
1996.
[19] Robert Tib-
shirani. Regression shrinkage and selection via the lasso. Journal of the Royal
Statistical Society. Series B (Methodological), pages 267?288, 1996. [20] Scott
Shaobing Chen, David L. Donoho, and Michael A. Saunders. Atomic decom-
position by basis pursuit. SIAM Journal on Scientiﬁc Computing, 20(1):33?61,
1998.
[21] Arthur E Hoerl and Robert W Kennard. Ridge regression: Bi-
ased estimation for nonorthogonal problems. Technometrics, 12(1):55?67, 1970.
[22] Ming Yuan and Yi Lin. Model selection and estimation in regression with
grouped variables. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Statistical
[23] Laurent Jacob, Guillaume Obozinski,
Methodology), 68(1):49?67, 2006.
and Jean-Philippe Vert. Group lasso with overlap and graph lasso.
In Pro-
ceedings of the 26th annual international conference on machine learning, pages
433?440, 2009. [24] Corinna Cortes and Vladimir Vapnik. Support-vector net-
works. Machine learning, 20(3):273?297, 1995.
[25] CK Chow and CN Liu.
Approximating discrete probability distributions with dependence trees. Infor-
mation Theory, IEEE Transactions on, 14(3):462?467, 1968.

9

11

