Deep Learning Models of the Retinal Response to

Natural Scenes

Authored by:

Surya Ganguli
Lane McIntosh

Niru Maheswaranathan

Aran Nayebi

Stephen Baccus

Abstract

A central challenge in sensory neuroscience is to understand neural
computations and circuit mechanisms that underlie the encoding of etho-
logically relevant, natural stimuli. In multilayered neural circuits, nonlin-
ear processes such as synaptic transmission and spiking dynamics present
a signiﬁcant obstacle to the creation of accurate computational models of
responses to natural stimuli. Here we demonstrate that deep convolutional
neural networks (CNNs) capture retinal responses to natural scenes nearly
to within the variability of a cell’s response, and are markedly more ac-
curate than linear-nonlinear (LN) models and Generalized Linear Models
(GLMs). Moreover, we ﬁnd two additional surprising properties of CNNs:
they are less susceptible to overﬁtting than their LN counterparts when
trained on small amounts of data, and generalize better when tested on
stimuli drawn from a diﬀerent distribution (e.g. between natural scenes
and white noise). An examination of the learned CNNs reveals several
properties. First, a richer set of feature maps is necessary for predicting
the responses to natural scenes compared to white noise. Second, tempo-
rally precise responses to slowly varying inputs originate from feedforward
inhibition, similar to known retinal mechanisms. Third, the injection of la-
tent noise sources in intermediate layers enables our model to capture the
sub-Poisson spiking variability observed in retinal ganglion cells. Fourth,
augmenting our CNNs with recurrent lateral connections enables them
to capture contrast adaptation as an emergent property of accurately de-
scribing retinal responses to natural scenes. These methods can be readily
generalized to other sensory modalities and stimulus ensembles. Overall,
this work demonstrates that CNNs not only accurately capture sensory
circuit responses to natural scenes, but also can yield information about
the circuit’s internal structure and function.

1

1 Paper Body

A fundamental goal of sensory neuroscience involves building accurate neural
encoding models that predict the response of a sensory area to a stimulus of
interest. These models have been used to shed light on circuit computations [1,
2, 3, 4], uncover novel mechanisms [5, 6], highlight gaps in our understanding [7],
and quantify theoretical predictions [8, 9]. A commonly used model for retinal
responses is a linear-nonlinear (LN) model that combines a linear spatiotemporal
ﬁlter with a single static nonlinearity. Although LN models have been used to
describe responses to artiﬁcial stimuli such as spatiotemporal white noise [10,
2], they fail to generalize to natural stimuli [7]. Furthermore, the white noise
stimuli used in previous studies are often low resolution or spatially uniform
and therefore fail to diﬀerentially activate nonlinear subunits in the ?

These authors contributed equally to this work.
30th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2016),

Barcelona, Spain.

?
responses
?
convolution
dense
convolution
time
8 subunits
16 subunits
Figure 1: A schematic of the model architecture. The stimulus was convolved
with 8 learned spatiotemporal ﬁlters whose activations were rectiﬁed. The sec-
ond convolutional layer then projected the activity of these subunits through
spatial ﬁlters onto 16 subunit types, whose activity was linearly combined and
passed through a ﬁnal soft rectifying nonlinearity to yield the predicted response.
retina, potentially simplifying the retinal response to such stimuli [11, 12, 2,
10, 13]. In contrast to the perceived linearity of the retinal response to coarse
stimuli, the retina performs a wide variety of nonlinear computations includ-
ing object motion detection [6], adaptation to complex spatiotemporal patterns
[14], encoding spatial structure as spike latency [15], and anticipation of peri-
odic stimuli [16], to name a few. However it is unclear what role these nonlinear
computational mechanisms have in generating responses to more general natural
stimuli. To better understand the visual code for natural stimuli, we modeled
retinal responses to natural image sequences with convolutional neural networks
(CNNs). CNNs have been successful at many pattern recognition and function
approximation tasks [17]. In addition, these models cascade multiple layers of
spatiotemporal ﬁltering and rectiﬁcation?exactly the elementary computational
building blocks thought to underlie complex functional responses of sensory cir-
cuits. Previous work utilized CNNs to gain insight into the neural computations
of inferotemporal cortex [18], but these models have not been applied to early

2

sensory areas where knowledge of neural circuitry can provide important val-
idation for such models. We ﬁnd that deep neural network models markedly
outperform previous models in predicting retinal responses both for white noise
and natural scenes. Moreover, these models generalize better to unseen stimu-
lus classes, and learn internal features consistent with known retinal properties,
including sub-Poisson variability, feedforward inhibition, and contrast adapta-
tion. Our ﬁndings indicate that CNNs can reveal both neural computations and
mechanisms within a multilayered neural circuit under natural stimulation.

2
Methods
The spiking activity of a population of tiger salamander retinal ganglion
cells was recorded in response to both sequences of natural images jittered with
the statistics of eye movements and high resolution spatiotemporal white noise.
Convolutional neural networks were trained to predict ganglion cell responses to
each stimulus class, simultaneously for all cells in the recorded population of a
given retina. For a comparison baseline, we also trained linear-nonlinear models
[19] and generalized linear models (GLMs) with spike history feedback [2]. More
details on the stimuli, retinal recordings, experimental structure, and division of
data for training, validation, and testing are given in the Supplemental Material.
2.1

Architecture and optimization
The convolutional neural network architecture is shown in Figure 2.1. Model
parameters were optimized to minimize a loss function corresponding to the
negative log-likelihood under Poisson spike generation. Optimization was per-
formed using ADAM [20] via the Keras and Theano software libraries [21]. The
networks were regularized with an ‘2 weight penalty at each layer and an ‘1
activity penalty at the ﬁnal layer, which helped maintain a baseline ﬁring rate
near 0 Hz. 2

We explored a variety of architectures for the CNN, varying the number of
layers, number of ﬁlters per layer, the type of layer (convolutional or dense), and
the size of the convolutional ﬁlters. Increasing the number of layers increased
prediction accuracy on held-out data up to three layers, after which perfor-
mance saturated. One implication of this architecture search is that LN-LN
cascade models ? which are equivalent to a 2-layer CNN ? would also underper-
form 3 layer CNN models. Contrary to the increasingly small ﬁlter sizes used
by many state-of-the-art object recognition networks, our networks had better
performance using ﬁlter sizes in excess of 15x15 checkers. Models were trained
over the course of 100 epochs, with early-stopping guided by a validation set.
See Supplementary Materials for details on the baseline models we used for
comparison.

3
Results
We found that convolutional neural networks were substantially better at
predicting retinal responses than either linear-nonlinear (LN) models or gen-
eralized linear models (GLMs) on both white noise and natural scene stimuli
(Figure 2). 3.1

3

Performance
B
A
C
ROC Curve for Natural Scenes
Retinal reliability
CNN
D
GLM
LN
White noise
CNN
GLM
LN
Natural scenes
LN GLM CNN 6 trials
Data Firing Rate (Hz)
E
Time (seconds)
Figure 2: Model performance. (A,B) Correlation coeﬃcients between the
data and CNN, GLM or LN models for white noise and natural scenes. Dot-
ted line indicates a measure of retinal reliability (See Methods). (C) Receiver
Operating Characteristic (ROC) curve for spike events for CNN, GLM and LN
models. (D) Spike rasters of one example retinal ganglion cell responding to
6 repeated trials of the same randomly selected segment of the natural scenes
stimulus (black) compared to the predictions of the LN (red), GLM (green), or
CNN (blue) model with Poisson spike generation used to generate model rasters.
(E) Peristimulus time histogram (PSTH) of the spike rasters in (D). 3

LN models and GLMs failed to capture retinal responses to natural scenes
(Figure 2B) consistent with previous results [7]. In addition, we also found that
LN models only captured a small fraction of the response to high resolution spa-
tiotemporal white noise, presumably because of the ﬁner resolution that were
used (Figure 2A). In contrast, CNNs approach the reliability of the retina for
both white noise and natural scenes. Using other metrics, including fraction
of explained variance, log-likelihood, and mean squared error, CNNs showed a
robust gain in performance over previously described sensory encoding models.
We investigated how model performance varied as a function of training data,
and found that LN models were more susceptible to overﬁtting than CNNs, de-
spite having fewer parameters (Figure 4A). In particular, a CNN model trained
using just 25 minutes of data had better held out performance than an LN model
ﬁt using the full 60 minute recording. We expect that both depth and convo-
lutional ﬁlters act as implicit regularizers for CNN models, thereby increasing
generalization performance. 3.2

CNN model parameters
Figure 3 shows a visualization of the model parameters learned when a con-
volutional network is trained to predict responses to either white noise or natural

4

scenes. We visualized the average feature represented by a model unit by com-
puting a response-weighted average for that unit. Models trained on white noise
learned ﬁrst layer features with small (?200 ?m) receptive ﬁeld widths (top left
box in Figure 3), whereas the natural scene model learns spatiotemporal ﬁlters
with overall lower spatial and temporal frequencies. This is likely in part due
to the abundance of low spatial frequencies present in natural images [22]. We
see a greater diversity of spatiotemporal features in the second layer receptive
ﬁelds compared to the ﬁrst (bottom panels in Figure 3). Additionally, we see
more diversity in models trained on natural scenes, compared to white noise.

Figure 3: Model parameters visualized by computing a response-weighted
average for diﬀerent model units, computed for models trained on spatiotem-
poral white noise stimuli (left) or natural image sequences (right). Top panel
(purple box): visualization of units in the ﬁrst layer. Each 3D spatiotemporal
receptive ﬁeld is displayed via a rank-one decomposition consisting of a spatial
ﬁlter (top) and temporal kernel (black traces, bottom). Bottom panel (green
box): receptive ﬁelds for the second layer units, again visualized using a rank-
one decomposition. Natural scenes models required more active second layer
units, displaying a greater diversity of spatiotemporal features. Receptive ﬁelds
are cropped to the region of space where the subunits have non-zero sensitivity.
3.3

Generalization across stimulus distributions
Historically, much of our understanding of the retina comes from ﬁtting
models to responses to artiﬁcial stimuli and then generalizing this understanding
to cases where the stimulus distribution is more natural. Due to the large
diﬀerence between artiﬁcial and natural stimulus distributions, it is unknown
what retinal encoding properties generalize to a new stimulus. 4

Figure 4: CNNs overﬁt less and generalize better across stimulus class
as compared to simpler models.
(A) Held-out performance curves for CNN
(?150,000 parameters) and GLM/LN models cropped around the cell?s recep-
tive ﬁeld (?4,000 parameters) as a function of the amount of training data. (B)
Correlation coeﬃcients between responses to natural scenes and models trained
on white noise but tested on natural scenes. See text for discussion. We ex-
plored what portion of CNN, GLM, and LN model performance is speciﬁc to a
particular stimulus distribution (white noise or natural scenes), versus what por-
tion describes characteristics of the retinal response that generalize to another
stimulus class. We found that CNNs trained on responses to one stimulus class
generalized better to a stimulus distribution that the model was not trained
on (Figure 4B). Despite LN models having fewer parameters, they nonethe-
less underperform larger convolutional neural network models when predicting
responses to stimuli not drawn from the training distribution. GLMs faired
particularly poorly when generalizing to natural scene responses, likely because
changes in mean luminance result in pathological ﬁring rates after the GLM?s
exponential nonlinearity. Compared to standard models, CNNs provide a more
accurate description of sensory responses to natural stimuli even when trained
on artiﬁcial stimuli (Figure 4B). 3.4

Capturing uncertainty of the neural response

5

In addition to describing the average response to a particular stimulus, an
accurate model should also capture the variability about the mean response.
Typical noise models assume i.i.d. Poisson noise drawn from a deterministic
mean ﬁring rate. However, the variability in retinal spiking is actually sub-
Poisson, that is, the variability scales with the mean but then increases sub-
linearly at higher mean rates [23, 24]. By training models with injected noise
[25], we provided a latent noise source in the network that models the unob-
served internal variability in the retinal population. Surprisingly, the model
learned to shape injected Gaussian noise to qualitatively match the shape of
the true retinal noise distribution, increasing with the mean response but grow-
ing sublinearly at higher mean rates (Figure 5). Notably, this relationship only
arises when noise is injected during optimization?injecting Gaussian noise in a
pre-trained network simply produced a linear scaling of the noise variance as a
function of the mean. 3.5

Feedforward inhibition shapes temporal responses in the model
To understand how a particular model response arises, we visualized the ﬂow
of signals through the network. One prominent aspect of the diﬀerence between
CNN and LN model responses is that CNNs but not LN models captured the
precise timing and short duration of ﬁring events. By examining the responses
to the internal units of CNNs in time and averaged over space (Figure 6 A-C),
we found that in both convolutional layers, diﬀerent units had either positive or
negative responses to the same stimuli, equivalent to excitation and inhibition
as found in the retina. Precise timing in CNNs arises by a timed combination
of positive and negative responses, analogous to feedforward inhibition that is
thought to generate precise timing in the retina [26, 27]. To examine network
responses in 5

Normalized Variance in Spike Count Mean Spike Count
0.1 0.1 1.0 2.0 4.0 10.0
Poisson Data
Mean Spike Count
C Variance in Spike Count
B
Variance in Spike Count
A
Poisson Data 1.0 2.0 4.0 10.0
Mean Spike Count
Figure 5: Training with added noise recovers retinal sub-Poisson noise scaling
property. (A) Variance versus mean spike count for CNNs with various strengths
of injected noise (from 0.1 to 10 standard deviations), as compared to retinal
data (black) and a Poisson distribution (dotted red). (B) The same plot as A
but with each curve normalized by the maximum variance. (C) Variance versus
mean spike count for CNN models with noise injection at test time but not
during training.

space, we selected a particular time in the experiment and visualized the acti-
vation maps in the ﬁrst (purple) and second (green) convolutional layers (Figure
6D). A given image is shown decomposed through multiple parallel channels in

6

this manner. Finally, Figure 6E highlights how the temporal autocorrelation
in the signals at diﬀerent layers varies. There is a progressive sharpening of
the response, such that by the time it reaches the model output the predicted
responses are able to mimic the statistics of the real ﬁring events (Figure 6C).
3.6

Feedback over long timescales
Retinal dynamics are known to exceed the duration of the ﬁlters that we
used (400 ms). In particular, changes in stimulus statistics such as luminance,
contrast and spatio-temporal correlations can generate adaptation lasting sec-
onds to tens of seconds [5, 28, 14]. Therefore, we additionally explored adding
feedback over longer timescales to the convolutional network. To do this, we
added a recurrent neural network (RNN) layer with a history of 10s after the
fully connected layer prior to the output layer. We experimented with diﬀer-
ent recurrent architectures (LSTMs [29], GRUs [30], and MUTs [31]) and found
that they all had similar performance to the CNN at predicting natural scene re-
sponses. Despite the similar performance, we found that the recurrent network
learned to adapt its response over the timescale of a few seconds in response to
step changes in stimulus contrast (Figure 7). This suggests that RNNs are a
promising way forward to capture dynamical processes such as adaptation over
longer timescales in an unbiased, data-driven manner.

4
Discussion
In the retina, simple models of retinal responses to spatiotemporal white
noise have greatly inﬂuenced our understanding of early sensory function. How-
ever, surprisingly few studies have addressed whether or not these simple models
can capture responses to natural stimuli. Our work applies models with rich
computational capacity to bear on the problem of understanding natural scene
responses. We ﬁnd that convolutional neural network (CNN) models, sometimes
augmented with lateral recurrent connections, well exceed the performance of
other standard retinal models including LN and GLMs. In addition, CNNs are
better at generalizing both to held-out stimuli and to entirely diﬀerent stimulus
classes, indicating that they are learning general features of the retinal response.
Moreover, CNNs capture several key features about retinal responses to natural
stimuli where LN models fail. In particular, they capture: (1) the temporal pre-
cision of ﬁring events despite employing ﬁlters with slower temporal frequencies,
(2) adaptive responses during changing stimulus statistics, and (3) biologically
realistic sub-Poisson variability in retinal responses. In this fashion, this work
provides the ﬁrst application of deep learning to understanding early sensory
systems under natural conditions. 6

Figure 6: Visualizing the internal activity of a CNN in response to a natural
scene stimulus. (A-C) Time series of the CNN activity (averaged over space) for
the ﬁrst convolutional layer (8 units, A), the second convolutional layer (16 units,
B), and the ﬁnal predicted response for an example cell (C, cyan trace). The
recorded (true) response is shown below the model prediction (C, gray trace) for
comparison. (D) Spatial activation of example CNN ﬁlters at a particular time
point. The selected stimulus frame (top, grayscale) is represented by parallel

7

pathways encoding spatial information in the ﬁrst (purple) and second (green)
convolutional layers (a subset of the activation maps is shown for brevity).
(E) Autocorrelation of the temporal activity in (A-C). The correlation in the
recorded ﬁring rates is shown in gray.

B LSTM
Full Field Flicker Stimulus Intensity
A
Firing Rate (spikes/s)
4
RNN
2
0 0
4 2 Time (s)
6
Figure 7: Recurrent neural network (RNN) layers capture response features
occurring over multiple seconds. (A) A schematic of how the architecture from
Figure 2.1 was modiﬁed to incorporate the RNN at the last layer of the CNN.
(B) Response of an RNN trained on natural scenes, showing a slowly adapting
ﬁring rate in response to a step change in contrast. To date, modeling eﬀorts in
sensory neuroscience have been most useful in the context of carefully designed
parametric stimuli, chosen to illuminate a computation or mechanism of interest
[32]. In part, this is due to the complexities of using generic natural stimuli. It
is both diﬃcult to describe the distribution of natural stimuli mathematically
(unlike white or pink noise), and diﬃcult to ﬁt models to stimuli with non-
stationary statistics when those statistics inﬂuence response properties. 7

We believe the approach taken in this paper provides a way forward for
understanding general natural scene responses. We leverage the computational
power and ﬂexibility of CNNs to provide us with a tractable, accurate model
that we can then dissect, probe, and analyze to understand what that model
captures about the retinal response. This strategy of casting a wide computa-
tional net to capture neural circuit function and then constraining it to better
understand that function will likely be useful in a variety of neural systems
in response to many complex stimuli. Acknowledgments The authors would
like to thank Ben Poole and EJ Chichilnisky for helpful discussions related to
this work. Thanks also goes to the following institutions for providing funding
and hardware grants, LM: NSF, NVIDIA Titan X Award, NM: NSF, AN and
SB: NEI grants, SG: Burroughs Wellcome, Sloan, McKnight, Simons, James S.
McDonnell Foundations and the ONR.

2 References

[1] Tim Gollisch and Markus Meister. Eye smarter than scientists believed:
neural computations in circuits of the retina. Neuron, 65(2):150?164, 2010. [2]
Jonathan W Pillow, Jonathon Shlens, Liam Paninski, Alexander Sher, Alan M
Litke, EJ Chichilnisky, and Eero P Simoncelli. Spatio-temporal correlations and

8

visual signalling in a complete neuronal population. Nature, 454(7207):995?999,
2008. [3] Nicole C Rust, Odelia Schwartz, J Anthony Movshon, and Eero P Si-
moncelli. Spatiotemporal elements of macaque v1 receptive ﬁelds. Neuron,
46(6):945?956, 2005. [4] David B Kastner and Stephen A Baccus. Coordinated
dynamic encoding in the retina using opposing forms of plasticity. Nature neu-
roscience, 14(10):1317?1322, 2011. [5] Stephen A Baccus and Markus Meister.
Fast and slow contrast adaptation in retinal circuitry. Neuron, 36(5):909?919,
2002. [6] Bence P ?lveczky, Stephen A Baccus, and Markus Meister. Segrega-
tion of object and background motion in the retina. Nature, 423(6938):401?408,
2003.
[7] Alexander Heitman, Nora Brackbill, Martin Greschner, Alexander
Sher, Alan M Litke, and EJ Chichilnisky. Testing pseudo-linear models of re-
sponses to natural scenes in primate retina. bioRxiv, page 045336, 2016.
[8]
Joseph J Atick and A Norman Redlich. Towards a theory of early visual pro-
cessing. Neural Computation, 2(3):308?320, 1990. [9] Xaq Pitkow and Markus
Meister. Decorrelation and eﬃcient coding by retinal ganglion cells. Nature
neuroscience, 15(4):628?635, 2012.
[10] Jonathan W Pillow, Liam Paninski,
Valerie J Uzzell, Eero P Simoncelli, and EJ Chichilnisky. Prediction and de-
coding of retinal ganglion cell responses with a probabilistic spiking model.
The Journal of Neuroscience, 25(47):11003?11013, 2005.
[11] S Hochstein and
RM Shapley. Linear and nonlinear spatial subunits in y cat retinal ganglion
cells. The Journal of Physiology, 262(2):265, 1976.
[12] Tim Gollisch. Fea-
tures and functions of nonlinear spatial integration by retinal ganglion cells.
Journal of Physiology-Paris, 107(5):338?348, 2013. [13] Adrienne L Fairhall, C
Andrew Burlingame, Ramesh Narasimhan, Robert A Harris, Jason L Puchalla,
and Michael J Berry. Selectivity for multiple stimulus features in retinal gan-
glion cells. Journal of neurophysiology, 96(5):2724?2738, 2006.
[14] Toshihiko
Hosoya, Stephen A Baccus, and Markus Meister. Dynamic predictive coding
by the retina. Nature, 436(7047):71?77, 2005.
[15] Tim Gollisch and Markus
Meister. Rapid neural coding in the retina with relative spike latencies. science,
319(5866):1108?1111, 2008. 8

[16] Greg Schwartz, Rob Harris, David Shrom, and Michael J Berry. De-
tection and prediction of periodic patterns by the retina. Nature neuroscience,
[17] Yann LeCun, Yoshua Bengio, and Geoﬀrey Hinton.
10(5):552?554, 2007.
Deep learning. Nature, 521(7553):436?444, 2015.
[18] Daniel L Yamins, Ha
Hong, Charles Cadieu, and James J DiCarlo. Hierarchical modular optimiza-
tion of convolutional networks achieves representations similar to macaque it
and human ventral stream. In Advances in neural information processing sys-
tems, pages 3093?3101, 2013. [19] EJ Chichilnisky. A simple white noise anal-
ysis of neuronal light responses. Network: Computation in Neural Systems,
12(2):199?213, 2001. [20] Diederik Kingma and Jimmy Ba. Adam: A method
for stochastic optimization. arXiv preprint arXiv:1412.6980, 2014. [21] Fr?d?ric
Bastien, Pascal Lamblin, Razvan Pascanu, James Bergstra, Ian Goodfellow,
Arnaud Bergeron, Nicolas Bouchard, David Warde-Farley, and Yoshua Bengio.
Theano: new features and speed improvements. arXiv preprint arXiv:1211.5590,
2012. [22] Aapo Hyv?rinen, Jarmo Hurri, and Patrick O Hoyer. Natural Image
Statistics: A Probabilistic Approach to Early Computational Vision., volume

9

39. Springer Science &amp; Business Media, 2009. [23] Michael J Berry, David
K Warland, and Markus Meister. The structure and precision of retinal spike
trains. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 94(10):5411?5416,
1997. [24] Rob R de Ruyter van Steveninck, Geoﬀrey D Lewen, Steven P Strong,
Roland Koberle, and William Bialek. Reproducibility and variability in neural
spike trains. Science, 275(5307):1805? 1808, 1997.
[25] Ben Poole, Jascha
Sohl-Dickstein, and Surya Ganguli. Analyzing noise in autoencoders and deep
networks. arXiv preprint arXiv:1406.1831, 2014. [26] Botond Roska and Frank
Werblin. Vertical interactions across ten parallel, stacked representations in
the mammalian retina. Nature, 410(6828):583?587, 2001.
[27] Botond Roska
and Frank Werblin. Rapid global shifts in natural scenes block spiking in spe-
ciﬁc ganglion cell types. Nature neuroscience, 6(6):600?608, 2003.
[28] Peter
D Calvert, Victor I Govardovskii, Vadim Y Arshavsky, and Clint L Makino.
Two temporal phases of light adaptation in retinal rods. The Journal of general
physiology, 119(2):129?146, 2002.
[29] Sepp Hochreiter and J?rgen Schmidhu-
ber. Long short-term memory. Neural Computation, 9(8):1735?1780, 1997.
[30] Kyunghyun Cho, Bart van Merrienboer, Dzmitry Bahdanau, and Yoshua
Bengio. On the properties of neural machine translation: Encoder?decoder ap-
proaches. Eighth Workshop on Syntax, Semantics and Structure in Statistical
Translation (SSST-8), pages 103?111, 2014.
[31] Rafal Jozefowicz, Wojciech
Zaremba, and Ilya Sutskever. An empirical exploration of recurrent network
architectures. Proceedings of the 32nd International Conference on Machine
Learning, 37:2342?2350, 2015. [32] Nicole C Rust and J Anthony Movshon. In
praise of artiﬁce. Nature neuroscience, 8(12):1647? 1650, 2005.

9

10

