Unsupervised Feature Extraction by

Time-Contrastive Learning and Nonlinear ICA

Authored by:

Aapo Hyvarinen
Hiroshi Morioka

Abstract

Nonlinear independent component analysis (ICA) provides an appeal-
ing framework for unsupervised feature learning, but the models proposed
so far are not identiﬁable. Here, we ﬁrst propose a new intuitive principle
of unsupervised deep learning from time series which uses the nonstation-
ary structure of the data. Our learning principle, time-contrastive learning
(TCL), ﬁnds a representation which allows optimal discrimination of time
segments (windows). Surprisingly, we show how TCL can be related to a
nonlinear ICA model, when ICA is redeﬁned to include temporal nonsta-
tionarities. In particular, we show that TCL combined with linear ICA
estimates the nonlinear ICA model up to point-wise transformations of
the sources, and this solution is unique — thus providing the ﬁrst iden-
tiﬁability result for nonlinear ICA which is rigorous, constructive, as well
as very general.

1 Paper Body

Unsupervised nonlinear feature learning, or unsupervised representation learn-
ing, is one of the biggest challenges facing machine learning. Various approaches
have been proposed, many of them in the deep learning framework. Some of
the most popular methods are multi-layer belief nets and Restricted Boltzmann
Machines [13] as well as autoencoders [14, 31, 21], which form the basis for
the ladder networks [30]. While some success has been obtained, the general
consensus is that the existing methods are lacking in scalability, theoretical
justiﬁcation, or both; more work is urgently needed to make machine learning
applicable to big unlabeled data. Better methods may be found by using the
temporal structure in time series data. One approach which has shown a great
promise recently is based on a set of methods variously called temporal coher-
ence [17] or slow feature analysis [32]. The idea is to ﬁnd features which change
as slowly as possible, originally proposed in [6] for learning invariant features.
Kernel-based methods [12, 26] and deep learning methods [23, 27, 9] have been
developed to extend this principle to the general nonlinear case. However, it

1

is not clear how one should optimally deﬁne the temporal stability criterion;
these methods typically use heuristic criteria and are not based on generative
models.
In fact, the most satisfactory solution for unsupervised deep learn-
ing would arguably be based on estimation of probabilistic generative models,
because probabilistic theory often gives optimal objectives for learning. This
has been possible in linear unsupervised learning, where sparse coding and in-
dependent component analysis (ICA) use independent, typically sparse, latent
variables that generate the data via a linear mixing. Unfortunately, at least
without temporal structure, the nonlinear ICA model is seriously unidentiﬁable
[18], which means that the original sources cannot be found. In spite of years of
research [20], no generally applicable identiﬁability conditions have been found.
Nevertheless, practical algorithms have been proposed [29, 1, 5] with the hope
that some kind of useful solution can still be found even for data with no tempo-
ral structure (that is, an i.i.d. sample). 30th Conference on Neural Information
Processing Systems (NIPS 2016), Barcelona, Spain.

1
Source signals
2
Segments: 3
T
1
23
34
T
T
1
Multinomial logistic regression: Theorem 1
n
1
Nonlinear mixture:
Observed signals
Predictions of segment labels
12
Feature values
1
m
Feature extractor:
n
Time ( )
A Generative model
B Time-contrastive learning
Figure 1: An illustration of how we combine a new generative nonlinear ICA
model with the new learning principle called time-contrastive learning (TCL).
A) The probabilistic generative model is a nonlinear version of ICA, where the
observed signals are given by a nonlinear transformation of source signals, which
are mutually independent, and have segment-wise nonstationarity. B) In TCL

2

.

.

we train a feature extractor to be sensitive to the nonstationarity of the data by
using a multinomial logistic regression which attempts to discriminate between
the segments, labelling each data point with the segment label 1, .
, T .
The feature extractor and the logistic regression together can be implemented
by a conventional multi-layer perceptron with back-propagation training. Here,
we combine a new heuristic principle for analysing temporal structure with a
rigorous treatment of a nonlinear ICA model, leading to a new identiﬁability
proof. The structure of our theory is illustrated in Figure 1. First, we propose
to learn features using the (temporal) nonstationarity of the data. The idea is
that the learned features should enable discrimination between diﬀerent time
windows; in other words, we search for features that provide maximal infor-
mation on which part of the time series a given data point comes from. This
provides a new, intuitively appealing method for feature extraction, which we
call time-contrastive learning (TCL). Second, we formulate a generative model
in which independent components have diﬀerent distributions in diﬀerent time
windows, and we observe nonlinear mixtures of the components. While a special
case of this principle, using nonstationary variances, has been very successfully
used in linear ICA [22], our extension to the nonlinear case is completely new.
Such nonstationarity of variances seems to be prominent in many kinds of data,
for example EEG/MEG [2], natural video [17], and closely related to changes in
volatility in ﬁnancial time series; but we further generalize the nonstationarity
to modulated exponential families. Finally, we show that as a special case, TCL
estimates the nonlinear part of the nonlinear ICA model, leaving only a simple
linear mixing to be determined by linear ICA, and a ﬁnal indeterminacy in terms
of a component-wise nonlinearity similar to squaring. For modulated Gaussian
sources, even the squaring can be removed and we have ?full? identiﬁability.
This gives the very ﬁrst identiﬁability proof for a high-dimensional, nonlinear,
ICA mixing model ? together with a practical method for its estimation.

2
Time-contrastive learning
TCL is a method to train a feature extractor by using a multinomial logis-
tic regression (MLR) classiﬁer which aims to discriminate all segments (time
windows) in a time series, given the segment indices as the labels of the data
points. In more detail, TCL proceeds as follows: 1. Divide a multivariate time
series xt into segments, i.e. time windows, indexed by ? = 1, .
, T . Any
temporal segmentation method can be used, e.g. simple equal-sized bins. 2.
Associate each data point with the corresponding segment index ? in which the
data point is contained; i.e. the data points in the segment ? are all given the
same segment label ? . 2

.

.

3. Learn a feature extractor h(xt ; ?) together with an MLR with a linear
regression function w?T h(xt ; ?) + b? to classify all data points with the
corresponding segment labels ? used as class labels Ct , as deﬁned above.
(For example, by ordinary deep learning with h(xt ; ?) being outputs in the last
hidden layer and ? being network weights.) The purpose of the feature extractor
is to extract a feature vector that enables the MLR to discriminate the segments.
Therefore, it seems intuitively clear that the feature extractor needs to learn a

3

useful representation of the temporal structure of the data, in particular the
diﬀerences of the distributions across segments. Thus, we are eﬀectively using
a classiﬁcation method (MLR) to accomplish unsupervised learning. Methods
such as noise-contrastive estimation [11] and generative adversarial nets [8],
see also [10], are similar in spirit, but clearly distinct from TCL which uses
the temporal structure of the data by contrasting diﬀerent time segments. In
practice, the feature extractor needs to be capable of approximating a general
nonlinear relationship between the data points and the log-odds of the classes,
and it must be easy to learn from data simultaneously with the MLR. To satisfy
these requirements, we use here a multilayer perceptron (MLP) as the feature
extractor. Essentially, we use ordinary MLP/MLR training according to very
well-known neural network theory, with the last hidden layer working as the
feature extractor. Note that the MLR is here only used as an instrument for
training the feature extractor, and has no practical meaning after the training.

3
TCL as approximator of log-pdf ratios
We next show how the combination of the optimally discriminative feature
extractor and MLR learns to model the nonstationary probability density func-
tions (pdf?s) of the data. The posterior over classes for one data point xt in the
multinomial logistic regression of TCL is given by well-known theory as p(Ct =
? —xt ; ?, W, b) =

exp(w?T h(xt ; ?) + b? ) PT 1 + j=2 exp(wjT h(xt ; ?) + bj )
(1)
where Ct is a class label of the data at time t, xt is the n-dimensional data
point at time t, ? is the parameter vector of the m-dimensional feature extractor
(MLP) denoted by h, W = [w1 , . . . , wT ] ? Rm?T , and b = [b1 , . . . , bT
]T are the weight and bias parameters of the MLR. We ﬁxed the elements of w1
and b1 to zero to avoid the well-known indeterminacy of the softmax function.
On the other hand, the true posteriors of the segment labels can be written, by
the Bayes rule, as p? (xt )p(Ct = ? ) p(Ct = ? —xt ) = PT , j=1 pj (xt )p(Ct
= j)

(2)
where p(Ct = ? ) is a prior distribution of the segment label ? , and p?
(xt ) = p(xt —Ct = ? ). Assume that the feature extractor has a universal
approximation capacity (in the sense of well-known neural network theory), and
that the amount of data is inﬁnite, so that the MLR converges to the optimal
classiﬁer. Then, we will have equality between the model posterior Eq. (1) and
the true posterior in Eq. (2) for all ? . Well-known developments, intuitively
based on equating the numerators in those equations and taking the pivot into
account, lead to the relationship w?T h(xt ; ?) + b? = log p? (xt ) ? log p1
(xt ) + log

p(Ct = ? ) , p(Ct = 1)
(3)
where the last term on the right-hand side is zero if the segments have equal
prior probability (i.e. equal length). In other words, what the feature extractor
computes after TCL training (under optimal conditions) is the log-pdf of the

4

data point in each segment (relative to that in the ﬁrst segment which was
chosen as pivot above). This gives a clear probabilistic interpretation of the
intuitive principle of TCL, and will be used below to show its connection to
nonlinear ICA.

4
Nonlinear nonstationary ICA model
In this section, seemingly unrelated to the preceding section, we deﬁne a
probabilistic generative model; the connection will be explained in the next
section. We assume, as typical in nonlinear ICA, 3

that the observed multivariate time series xt is a smooth and invertible
, sn (t)); in

nonlinear mixture of a vector of source signals st = (s1 (t), .
other words: xt = f (st ).

.

.

(4)
The components si (t) in st are assumed mutually independent over i (but
not over time t). The crucial question is how to deﬁne a suitable model for
the sources, which is general enough while allowing strong identiﬁability results.
Here, we start with the fundamental assumption that the source signals si (t) are
nonstationary, and use such nonstationarity for source separation. For example,
the variances (or similar scaling coeﬃcients) could be changing as proposed
earlier in the linear case [22, 24, 16]. We generalize that idea and propose a
generative model for nonstationary sources based on the exponential family.
Merely for mathematical convenience, we assume that the nonstationarity is
much slower than the sampling rate, so the time series can be divided into
segments in each of which the distribution is approximately constant (but the
distribution is diﬀerent in diﬀerent segments). The log-pdf of the source signal
with index i in the segment ? is then deﬁned as: log p? (si ) = qi,0 (si ) +

V X
?i,v (? )qi,v (si ) ? log Z(?i,1 (? ), . . . , ?i,V (? ))
(5)
v=1
where qi,0 is a ?stationary baseline? log-pdf of the source, and the qi,v , v
? 1 are nonlinear scalar functions deﬁning the exponential family for source i;
the index t is dropped for simplicity. The essential point is that the parameters
?i,v (? ) of the source i depend on the segment index ? , which creates non-
stationarity. The normalization constant Z disappears in all our proofs below.
A simple example would be obtained by setting qi,0 = 0, V = 1, i.e., using a
single modulated function qi,1 with qi,1 (si ) = ?s2i /2 which means that the
variance of a Gaussian source is modulated, or qi,1 (si ) = ?—si —, a modulated
Laplacian source. Another interesting option might be to use two nonlinearities
similar to ?rectiﬁed linear units? (ReLU) given by qi,1 (si ) = ? max(si , 0) and
qi,2 (si ) = ? max(?si , 0) to model both changes in scale (variance) and location
(mean). Yet another option is to use a Gaussian baseline qi,0 (si ) = ?s2i /2
with a nonquadratic function qi,1 . Our deﬁnition thus generalizes the linear
model [22, 24, 16] to the nonlinear case, as well as to very general modulated
non-Gaussian densities by allowing qi,v to be non-quadratic, using more than
one qi,v per source (i.e. we can have V ¿ 1) as well as a non-stationary baseline.

5

We emphasize that our principle of nonstationarity is clearly distinct from the
principle of linear autocorrelations previously used in the nonlinear case [12, 26].
Note further that some authors prefer to use the term blind source separation
(BSS) for generative models with temporal structure.

5
Solving nonlinear ICA by TCL
Now we consider the case where TCL as deﬁned in Section 2 is applied on
data generated by the nonlinear ICA model in Section 4. We refer again to
Figure 1 which illustrates the total system. For simplicity, we consider the case
qi,0 = 0, V = 1, i.e. the exponential family has a single modulated function
qi,1 per source, and this function is the same for all sources; we will discuss the
general case separately below. The modulated function will be simply denoted
by q := qi,1 in the following. First, we show that the nonlinear functions
q(si ), i = 1, .
, n, of the sources can be obtained as unknown linear
transformations of the outputs of the feature extractor hi trained by the TCL:
Theorem 1. Assume the following: A1. We observe data which is obtained by
generating independent sources1 according to (5), and mixing them as in (4)
with a smooth invertible f . For simplicity, we assume only a single function
deﬁning the exponential family, i.e. qi,0 = 0, V = 1 and q := qi,1 as explained
above. A2. We apply TCL on the data so that the dimension of the feature
extractor h is equal to the dimension of the data vector xt , i.e., m = n. 1

.

.

More precisely: the sources are generated independently given the ?i,v .
Depending on how the ?i,v are generated, there may or may not be marginal
dependency between the si ; see the Corollary 1 below.

4
A3. The modulation parameter matrix L with elements [L]?,i = ?i,1 (? ) ?
?i,1 (1), ? = 1, . . . , T ; i = 1, . . . , n has full column rank n. (Intuitively: the
variances of the components are modulated suﬃciently independently of each
other. Note that many segments are actually allowed to have equal distributions
since this matrix is typically very tall.) Then, in the limit of inﬁnite data, the
outputs of the feature extractor are equal to q(s) = (q(s1 ), q(s2 ), . . . , q(sn
))T up to an invertible linear transformation. In other words, q(st ) = Ah(xt ;
?) + d (6) for some constant invertible matrix A ? Rn?n and a constant vector
d ? Rn . Sketch of proof : (see Supplementary Material for full proof) The basic
idea is that after convergence we must have equality between the model of the
log-pdf in each segment given by TCL in Eq. (3) and that given by nonlinear
ICA, obtained by summing the RHS of Eq. (5) over i: n X T w? h(x; ?) ? k1
(x) = ?i,1 (? )q(si ) ? k2 (? ) (7) i=1

where k1 does not depend on ? , and k2 (? ) does not depend on x or s.
We see that the functions hi (x) and q(si ) must span the same linear subspace.
(TCL looks at diﬀerences of log-pdf?s, introducing the baseline k1 (x), but
this does not actually change the subspace). This implies that the q(si ) must
be equal to some invertible linear transformation of h(x; ?) and a constant
bias term, which gives (6). To further estimate the linear transformation A
in (6), we can simply use linear ICA, under a further independence assumption
regarding the generation of the ?i,1 : Corollary 1. Assume the ?i,1 are randomly

6

generated, independently for each i. The estimation (identiﬁcation) of the q(si
) can then be performed by ﬁrst performing TCL, and then linear ICA on the
hidden representation h(x). Proof: We only need to combine the well-known
identiﬁability proof of linear ICA [3] with Theorem 1, noting that the quantities
q(si ) are now independent, and since q has a strict upper bound (which is
necessary for integrability), q(si ) must be non-Gaussian.
In general, TCL
followed by linear ICA does not allow us to exactly recover the independent
components because the function q(?) can hardly be invertible, typically being
something like squaring or absolute values. However, for a speciﬁc class of
q including the modulated Gaussian family, we can prove a stricter form of
identiﬁability. Slightly counterintuitively, we can recover the signs of the si ,
since we also know the corresponding x and the transformation is invertible:
Corollary 2. Assume q(s) is a strictly monotonic function of —s—. Then, we
can further identify the original si , up to strictly monotonic transformations of
each source. Proof: To make p? (s) integrable, necessarily q(s) ? ?? when —s—
? ?, and q(s) must have a ﬁnite maximum, which we can set to zero without
restricting generality. For each ﬁxed i, consider the manifold deﬁned by q(gi
(x))) = 0. By invertibility of g, this divides the space of x into two halves. In one
half, deﬁne s?i = q(si ), and in the other, s?i = ?q(si ). With such s?i , we have
thus recovered the original sources, up to the strictly monotonic transformation
s?i = c sign(si )q(si ), where c is either +1 or ?1. (Note that in general, the si are
meaningfully deﬁned only up to a strictly monotonic transformation, analogue
to multiplication by an arbitrary constant in the linear case [3].) Summary of
Theory What we have proven is that in the special case of a single q(s) which
is a monotonic function of —s—, our nonlinear ICA model is identiﬁable, up
to inevitable component-wise monotonic transformations. We also provided a
practical method for the estimation of the nonlinear transformations q(si ) for
any general q, given by TCL followed by linear ICA. (The method provided for
?inverting? q in the proof of Corollary 2 may be very diﬃcult to implement in
practice.) Extensions First, allowing a stationary baseline qi,0 does not change
the Theorem at all, and a weaker form of Corollary 1 holds as well. Second,
with many qi,v (V ¿ 1), the left-hand-side of (6) will have V n entries given by
all the possible qi,v (si ), and the dimension of the feature extractor must be
equally increased; the condition of full rank on L is likewise more complicated.
Corollary 1 must then consider an independent subspace model, but it can still
be proven in the same way. (The details and the proof will be presented in a
later paper.) Third, the case of combining ICA with dimension reduction is
treated in Supplementary Material. 5

6
Simulation on artiﬁcial data
Data generation We created data from the nonlinear ICA model in Section
4, using the simpliﬁed case of the Theorem (a single function q) as follows. Non-
stationary source signals (n = 20, segment length 512) were randomly generated
by modulating Laplacian sources by ?i,1 (? ) randomly drawn so that the std?s
inside the segments have a uniform distribution in [0, 1]. As the nonlinear mix-
ing function f (s), we used an MLP (?mixing-MLP?). In order to guarantee that

7

the mixing-MLP is invertible, we used leaky ReLU?s and the same number of
units in all layers. TCL settings, training, and ﬁnal linear ICA As the feature
extractor to be trained by TCL, we adopted an MLP (?feature-MLP?). The
segmentation in TCL was the same as in the data generation, and the number of
layers was the same in the mixing-MLP and the feature-MLP. Note that when
L = 1, both the mixing-MLP and feature-MLP are a one layer model, and then
the observed signals are simply linear mixtures of the source signals as in a linear
ICA model. As in the Theorem, we set m = n. As the activation function in the
hidden layers, we used a ?maxout? unit, constructed by taking the maximum
across G = 2 aﬃne fully connected weight groups. However, the output layer
has ?absolute value? activation units exclusively. This is because the output
of the feature-MLP (i.e., h(x; ?)) should resemble q(s), based on Theorem 1,
and here we used the Laplacian distribution for generating the sources. The
initial weights of each layer were randomly drawn from a uniform distribution
for each layer, scaled as in [7]. To train the MLP, we used back-propagation
with a momentum term. To avoid overﬁtting, we used ‘2 regularization for the
feature-MLP and MLR. According to Corollary 1 above, after TCL we further
applied linear ICA (FastICA, [15]) to the h(x; ?), and used its outputs as the
ﬁnal estimates of q(si ). To evaluate the performance of source recovery, we
computed the mean correlation coeﬃcients between the true q(si ) and their
estimates. For comparison, we also applied a linear ICA method based on non-
stationarity of variance (NSVICA) [16], a kernel-based nonlinear ICA method
(kTDSEP) [12], and a denoising autoencoder (DAE) [31] to the observed data.
We took absolute values of the estimated sources to make a fair comparison with
TCL. In kTDSEP, we selected the 20 estimated components with the highest
correlations with the source signals. We initialized the DAE by the stacked DAE
scheme [31], and sigmoidal units were used in the hidden layers; we omitted the
case L ¿ 3 because of instability of training. Results Figure 2a) shows that
after training the feature-MLP by TCL, the MLR achieved higher classiﬁcation
accuracies than chance level, which implies that the feature-MLP was able to
learn a representation of the data nonstationarity. (Here, chance level denotes
the performance of the MLP with a randomly initialized feature-MLP.) We can
see that the larger the number of layers is (which means that the nonlinearity in
the mixing-MLP is stronger), the more diﬃcult it is to train the feature-MLP
and the MLR. The classiﬁcation accuracy also goes down when the number of
segments increases, since when there are more and more classes, some of them
will inevitably have very similar distributions and are thus diﬃcult to discrimi-
nate; this is why we computed the chance level as above. Figure 2b) shows that
the TCL method could reconstruct the q(si ) reasonably well even for the non-
linear mixture case (L ¿ 1), while all other methods failed (NSVICA obviously
performed very well in the linear case).The ﬁgure also shows that (1) the larger
the number of segments (amount of data) is, the higher the performance of the
TCL method is (i.e. the method seems to converge), and (2) again, more layers
makes learning more diﬃcult. To summarize, this simulation conﬁrms that TCL
is able to estimate the nonlinear ICA model based on nonstationarity. Using
more data increases performance, perhaps obviously, while making the mixing

8

more nonlinear decreases performance.

7
Experiments on real brain imaging data
To evaluate the applicability of TCL to real data, we applied it on magne-
toencephalography (MEG), i.e. measurements of the electrical activity in the
human brain. In particular, we used data measured in a resting-state session,
during which the subjects did not have any task nor were receiving any par-
ticular stimulation.
In recent years, many studies have shown the existence
of networks of brain activity in resting state, with MEG as well [2, 4]. Such
networks mean that the data is nonstationary, and thus this data provides an
excellent target for TCL. 6

a)
100 80
0.8
20
Mean correlation
Accuracy (%)
40 L=1 L=2 L=3 L=4 L=5 L=1(chance) L=2(chance) L=3(chance) L=4(chance)

L=5(chance)
10 8 4 2 1
1
b)
8
16
32 64 128 Number of segments
256
0.6 0.4 0.2 0
512
8
16
32 64 128 Number of segments
256
512
TCL(L=1) TCL(L=2) TCL(L=3) TCL(L=4) TCL(L=5) NSVICA(L=1)
NSVICA(L=2) NSVICA(L=3) NSVICA(L=4) NSVICA(L=5) kTDSEP(L=1)
kTDSEP(L=2) kTDSEP(L=3) kTDSEP(L=4) kTDSEP(L=5) DAE(L=1) DAE(L=2)
DAE(L=3)

Figure 2: Simulation on artiﬁcial data. a) Mean classiﬁcation accuracies of
the MLR in TCL, as a function of the numbers of layers and segments. (Ac-
curacies are on training data since it is not obvious how to deﬁne test data.)
Note that chance levels (dotted lines) change as a function of the number of
segments (see text). The MLR achieved higher accuracy than chance level. b)
Mean absolute correlation coeﬃcients between the true q(s) and the features
learned by TCL (solid line) and, for comparison: nonstationarity-based lin-
ear ICA (NSVICA, dashed line), kernel-based nonlinear ICA (kTDSEP, dotted
line), and denoising autoencoder (DAE, dash-dot line). TCL has much higher

9

correlations than DAE or kTDSEP, and in the nonlinear case (L ¿ 1), higher
than NSVICA. Data and preprocessing We used MEG data from an earlier neu-
roimaging study [25], graciously provided by P. Ramkumar. MEG signals were
measured from nine healthy volunteers by a Vectorview helmet-shaped neuro-
magnetometer at a sampling rate of 600 Hz with 306 channels. The experiment
consisted of two kinds of sessions, i.e., resting sessions (2 sessions of 10 min) and
task sessions (2 sessions of 12 min). In the task sessions, the subjects were ex-
posed to a sequence of 6?33 s blocks of auditory, visual and tactile stimuli, which
were interleaved with 15 s rest periods. We exclusively used the resting-session
data for the training of the network, and task-session data was only used in the
evaluation. The modality of the sensory stimulation (incl. no stimulation, i.e.
rest) provided a class label that we used in the evaluation, giving in total four
classes. We preprocessed the MEG signals by Morlet ﬁltering around the alpha
frequency band. TCL settings We used segments of equal size, of length 12.5
s or 625 data points (downsampling to 50 Hz); the length was based on prior
knowledge about the time-scale of resting-state networks. The number of layers
took the values L ? {1, 2, 3, 4}, and the number of nodes of each hidden layer
was a function of L so that we always ﬁxed the number of output layer nodes to
10, and increased gradually the number of nodes when going to earlier layer as
L = 1 : 10, L = 2 : 20 ? 10, L = 3 : 40 ? 20 ? 10, and L = 4 : 80 ? 40 ? 20 ?
10. We used ReLU?s in the middle layers, and adaptive units ?(x) = max(x, ax)
exclusively for the output layer, which is more ﬂexible than the ?absolute value?
unit used in the Simulation above. To prevent overﬁtting, we applied dropout
[28] to inputs, and batch normalization [19] to hidden layers. Since diﬀerent
subjects and sessions are likely to have uninteresting technical diﬀerences, we
used a multi-task learning scheme, with a separate top-layer MLR classiﬁer for
each measurement session and subject, but a shared feature-MLP. (In fact, if
we use the MLR to discriminate all segments of all sessions, it tends to mainly
learn such inter-subject and inter-session diﬀerences.) Otherwise, all the settings
were as in Section 6. Evaluation methods To evaluate the obtained features,
we performed classiﬁcation of the sensory stimulation categories (modalities)
by applying feature extractors trained with (unlabeled) restingsession data to
(labeled) task-session data. Classiﬁcation was performed using a linear support
vector machine (SVM) classiﬁer trained on the stimulation modality labels, and
its performance was evaluated by a session-average of session-wise one-block-
out cross-validation (CV) accuracies. The hyperparameters of the SVM were
determined by nested CV without using the test data. The average activities
of the feature extractor during each block were used as feature vectors in the
evaluation of TCL features. However, we used log-power activities for the other
(baseline) methods because the average activities had much lower performance
with those methods. We balanced the number of blocks between the four cate-
gories. We measured the CV accuracy 10 times by changing the initial values
of the feature extractor training, and showed their average performance. We
also visualized the spatial activity patterns obtained by TCL, using weighted-
averaged sensor signals; i.e., the sensor signals are averaged while weighted by
the activities of the feature extractor. 7

10

Classiﬁcation accuracy (%)
a)
L=1
L=4
b)
50 L=1
L3
L=4
L2
40
30
L1 TCL
DAE
kTDSEP NSVICA
Figure 3: Real MEG data. a) Classiﬁcation accuracies of linear SVMs newly
trained with tasksession data to predict stimulation labels in task-sessions, with
feature extractors trained in advance with resting-session data. Error bars give
standard errors of the mean across ten repetitions. For TCL and DAE, ac-
curacies are given for diﬀerent numbers of layers L. Horizontal line shows the
chance level (25%). b) Example of spatial patterns of nonstationary compo-
nents learned by TCL. Each small panel corresponds to one spatial pattern
with the measurement helmet seen from three diﬀerent angles (left, back, right);
red/yellow is positive and blue is negative. L3: approximate total spatial pat-
tern of one selected third-layer unit. L2: the patterns of the three second-layer
units maximally contributing to this L3 unit. L1: for each L2 unit, the two most
strongly contributing ﬁrst-layer units. Results Figure 3a) shows the comparison
of classiﬁcation accuracies between the diﬀerent methods, for diﬀerent numbers
of layers L = {1, 2, 3, 4}. The classiﬁcation accuracies by the TCL method
were consistently higher than those by the other (baseline) methods.2 We can
also see a superior performance of multi-layer networks (L ? 3) compared with
that of the linear case (L = 1), which indicates the importance of nonlinear
demixing in the TCL method. Figure 3b) shows an example of spatial patterns
learned by the TCL method. For simplicity of visualization, we plotted spatial
patterns for the three-layer model. We manually picked one out of the ten hid-
den nodes from the third layer, and plotted its weighted-averaged sensor signals
(Figure 3b, L3). We also visualized the most strongly contributing second- and
ﬁrst-layer nodes. We see progressive pooling of L1 units to form left temporal,
right temporal, and occipito-parietal patterns in L2, which are then all pooled
together in the L3 resulting in a bilateral temporal pattern with negative con-
tribution from the occipito-parietal region. Most of the spatial patterns in the
third layer (not shown) are actually similar to those previously reported using
functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), and MEG [2, 4]. Interestingly,
none of the hidden units seems to represent artefacts (i.e. non-brain signals), in
contrast to ordinary linear ICA of EEG or MEG.

8
Conclusion

11

We proposed a new learning principle for unsupervised feature (representa-
tion) learning.
It is based on analyzing nonstationarity in temporal data by
discriminating between time segments. The ensuing ?time-contrastive learning?
is easy to implement since it only uses ordinary neural network training: a
multi-layer perceptron with logistic regression. However, we showed that, sur-
prisingly, it can estimate independent components in a nonlinear mixing model
up to certain indeterminacies, assuming that the independent components are
nonstationary in a suitable way. The indeterminacies include a linear mix-
ing (which can be resolved by a further linear ICA step), and component-wise
nonlinearities, such as squares or absolute values. TCL also avoids the compu-
tation of the gradient of the Jacobian, which is a major problem with maximum
likelihood estimation [5]. Our developments also give by far the strongest iden-
tiﬁability proof of nonlinear ICA in the literature. The indeterminacies actually
reduce to just inevitable monotonic component-wise transformations in the case
of modulated Gaussian sources. Thus, our results pave the way for further de-
velopments in nonlinear ICA, which has so far seriously suﬀered from the lack
of almost any identiﬁability theory, and provide a new principled approach to
unsupervised deep learning. Experiments on real MEG found neuroscientiﬁcally
interesting networks. Other promising future application domains include video
data, econometric data, and biomedical data such as EMG and ECG, in which
nonstationary variances seem to play a major role.3 2

Note that classiﬁcation using the ﬁnal linear ICA is equivalent to using
whitening since ICA only makes a further orthogonal rotation. 3 This research
was supported in part by JSPS KAKENHI 16J08502 and the Academy of Fin-
land.
8

2 References

[1] L. B. Almeida. MISEP?linear and nonlinear ICA based on mutual informa-
tion. J. of Machine Learning Research, 4:1297?1318, 2003.
[2] M. J. Brookes
et al. Investigating the electrophysiological basis of resting state networks us-
ing magnetoencephalography. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci., 108(40):16783?16788,
2011.
[3] P. Comon. Independent component analysis?a new concept? Signal
Processing, 36:287?314, 1994.
[4] F. de Pasquale et al. A cortical core for dy-
namic integration of functional networks in the resting human brain. Neuron,
[5] L. Dinh, D. Krueger, and Y. Bengio. NICE: Non-
74(4):753?764, 2012.
linear independent components estimation. arXiv:1410.8516 [cs.LG], 2015.
[6]
P. F?ldi?k. Learning invariance from transformation sequences. Neural Com-
putation, 3:194?200, 1991. [7] X. Glorot and Y. Bengio. Understanding the dif-
ﬁculty of training deep feedforward neural networks. In AISTATS?10, 2010. [8]
I. Goodfellow, J. Pouget-Abadie, M. Mirza, B. Xu, D. Warde-Farley, S. Ozair,
A. Courville, and Y. Bengio. Generative adversarial nets.
In NIPS, pages
2672?2680, 2014.
[9] R. Goroshin, J. Bruna, J. Tompson, D. Eigen, and Y.
LeCun. Unsupervised feature learning from temporal data. arXiv:1504.02518,

12

[10] M. U. Gutmann, R. Dutta, S. Kaski, and J. Corander. Likelihood-
2015.
free inference via classiﬁcation. arXiv:1407.4981 [stat.CO], 2014.
[11] M. U.
Gutmann and A. Hyv?rinen. Noise-contrastive estimation of unnormalized sta-
tistical models, with applications to natural image statistics. J. of Machine
Learning Research, 13:307?361, 2012. [12] S. Harmeling, A. Ziehe, M. Kawan-
abe, and K.-R. M?ller. Kernel-based nonlinear blind source separation. Neural
[13] G. E. Hinton. Learning multiple layers
Comput., 15(5):1089?1124, 2003.
of representation. Trends Cogn. Sci., 11:428?434, 2007.
[14] G. E. Hinton
and R. S. Zemel. Autoencoders, minimum description length, and helmholtz
free energy. Adv. Neural Inf. Process. Syst., 1994.
[15] A. Hyv?rinen. Fast
and robust ﬁxed-point algorithms for independent component analysis. IEEE
Trans. Neural Netw., 10(3):626?634, 1999.
[16] A. Hyv?rinen. Blind source
separation by nonstationarity of variance: A cumulant-based approach. IEEE
Transactions on Neural Networks, 12(6):1471?1474, 2001. [17] A. Hyv?rinen, J.
Hurri, and P. O. Hoyer. Natural Image Statistics. Springer-Verlag, 2009.
[18]
A. Hyv?rinen and P. Pajunen. Nonlinear independent component analysis: Ex-
istence and uniqueness results. Neural Netw., 12(3):429?439, 1999. [19] S. Ioﬀe
and C. Szegedy. Batch normalization: Accelerating deep network training by
reducing internal covariate shift. CoRR, abs/1502.03167, 2015. [20] C. Jutten,
M. Babaie-Zadeh, and J. Karhunen. Nonlinear mixtures. Handbook of Blind
Source Separation, Independent Component Analysis and Applications, pages
549?592, 2010.
[21] D. P. Kingma and M. Welling. Auto-encoding variational
bayes. arXiv:1312.6114 [stat.ML], 2014.
[22] K. Matsuoka, M. Ohya, and M.
Kawamoto. A neural net for blind separation of nonstationary signals. Neural
Netw., 8(3):411?419, 1995. [23] H. Mobahi, R. Collobert, and J. Weston. Deep
learning from temporal coherence in video. In Proceedings of the 26th Annual
International Conference on Machine Learning, pages 737?744, 2009. [24] D.-T.
Pham and J.-F. Cardoso. Blind separation of instantaneous mixtures of non
stationary sources. IEEE Trans. Signal Processing, 49(9):1837?1848, 2001. [25]
P. Ramkumar, L. Parkkonen, R. Hari, and A. Hyv?rinen. Characterization
of neuromagnetic brain rhythms over time scales of minutes using spatial in-
dependent component analysis. Hum. Brain Mapp., 33(7):1648? 1662, 2012.
[26] H. Sprekeler, T. Zito, and L. Wiskott. An extension of slow feature anal-
ysis for nonlinear blind source separation. J. of Machine Learning Research,
[27] J. T. Springenberg and M. Riedmiller. Learning
15(1):921?947, 2014.
temporal coherent features through life-time sparsity.
In Neural Information
Processing, pages 347?356. Springer, 2012.
[28] N. Srivastava, G. Hinton, A.
Krizhevsky, I. Sutskever, and R. Salakhutdinov. Dropout: A simple way to pre-
vent neural networks from overﬁtting. J. Mach. Learn. Res., 15(1):1929?1958,
2014. [29] Y. Tan, J. Wang, and J.M. Zurada. Nonlinear blind source separation
using a radial basis function network. IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks,
12(1):124?134, 2001. [30] H. Valpola. From neural PCA to deep unsupervised
learning. In Advances in Independent Component Analysis and Learning Ma-
chines, pages 143?171. Academic Press, 2015. [31] P. Vincent, H. Larochelle, I.
Lajoie, Y. Bengio, and P.-A. Manzagol. Stacked denoising autoencoders: Learn-
ing useful representations in a deep network with a local denoising criterion. J.

13

[32] L. Wiskott and T. J. Sejnowski.
Mach. Learn. Res., 11:3371?3408, 2010.
Slow feature analysis: Unsupervised learning of invariances. Neural Comput.,
14(4):715?770, 2002.

9

14

