Learning to learn by gradient descent by gradient

descent

Authored by:

Nando de Freitas

David Pfau
Misha Denil

Matthew W. Hoﬀman

Tom Schaul

Marcin Andrychowicz

Sergio G?mez

Abstract

The move from hand-designed features to learned features in machine
learning has been wildly successful. In spite of this, optimization algo-
rithms are still designed by hand. In this paper we show how the design
of an optimization algorithm can be cast as a learning problem, allowing
the algorithm to learn to exploit structure in the problems of interest in an
automatic way. Our learned algorithms, implemented by LSTMs, outper-
form generic, hand-designed competitors on the tasks for which they are
trained, and also generalize well to new tasks with similar structure. We
demonstrate this on a number of tasks, including simple convex problems,
training neural networks, and styling images with neural art.

1 Paper Body

Frequently, tasks in machine learning can be expressed as the problem of opti-
mizing an objective function f (?) deﬁned over some domain ? 2 ?. The goal
in this case is to ﬁnd the minimizer ?? = arg min?2? f (?). While any method
capable of minimizing this objective function can be applied, the standard ap-
proach for diﬀerentiable functions is some form of gradient descent, resulting in
a sequence of updates ?t+1 = ?t

?t rf (?t ) .
The performance of vanilla gradient descent, however, is hampered by the
fact that it only makes use of gradients and ignores second-order informa-
tion. Classical optimization techniques correct this behavior by rescaling the
gradient step using curvature information, typically via the Hessian matrix of
second-order partial derivatives?although other choices such as the generalized

1

Gauss-Newton matrix or Fisher information matrix are possible. Much of the
modern work in optimization is based around designing update rules tailored
to speciﬁc classes of problems, with the types of problems of interest diﬀer-
ing between diﬀerent research communities. For example, in the deep learning
community we have seen a proliferation of optimization methods specialized for
high-dimensional, non-convex optimization problems. These include momen-
tum [Nesterov, 1983, Tseng, 1998], Rprop [Riedmiller and Braun, 1993], Ada-
grad [Duchi et al., 2011], RMSprop [Tieleman and Hinton, 2012], and ADAM
[Kingma and Ba, 2015]. More focused methods can also be applied when more
structure of the optimization problem is known [Martens and Grosse, 2015].
In contrast, communities who focus on sparsity tend to favor very diﬀerent
approaches [Donoho, 2006, Bach et al., 2012]. This is even more the case for
combinatorial optimization for which relaxations are often the norm [Nemhauser
and Wolsey, 1988]. 30th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems
(NIPS 2016), Barcelona, Spain.

This industry of optimizer design allows diﬀerameter update s par ent com-
munities to create optimization methods which exploit structure in their prob-
lems of interest at the expense of potentially poor performance on problems
outside of that scope. Moreover the No Free Lunch Theorems for Optimiza-
tion [Wolpert and Macready, 1997] show that in the setting of combinatorial
optimization, no algorithm is able to do better than a random optimizer opti-
mizee strategy in expectation. This suggests that speerror signal cialization to
a subclass of problems is in fact the only way that improved performance can
be achieved in general. Figure 1: The optimizer (left) is provided with In this
work we take a diﬀerent tack and instead performance of the optimizee (right)
and proposes propose to replace hand-designed update rules updates to increase
the optimizee?s performance. with a learned update rule, which we call the op-
[photos: Bobolas, 2009, Maley, 2011] timizer g, speciﬁed by its own set of pa-
rameters . This results in updates to the optimizee f of the form ?t+1 = ?t +
gt (rf (?t ), ) .

(1)
A high level view of this process is shown in Figure 1. In what follows we
will explicitly model the update rule g using a recurrent neural network (RNN)
which maintains its own state and hence dynamically updates as a function of
its iterates. 1.1

Transfer learning and generalization
The goal of this work is to develop a procedure for constructing a learning
algorithm which performs well on a particular class of optimization problems.
Casting algorithm design as a learning problem allows us to specify the class
of problems we are interested in through example problem instances. This is
in contrast to the ordinary approach of characterizing properties of interesting
problems analytically and using these analytical insights to design learning al-
gorithms by hand. It is informative to consider the meaning of generalization in
this framework. In ordinary statistical learning we have a particular function of
interest, whose behavior is constrained through a data set of example function
evaluations. In choosing a model we specify a set of inductive biases about how

2

we think the function of interest should behave at points we have not observed,
and generalization corresponds to the capacity to make predictions about the
behavior of the target function at novel points. In our setting the examples are
themselves problem instances, which means generalization corresponds to the
ability to transfer knowledge between diﬀerent problems. This reuse of problem
structure is commonly known as transfer learning, and is often treated as a sub-
ject in its own right. However, by taking a meta-learning perspective, we can
cast the problem of transfer learning as one of generalization, which is much
better studied in the machine learning community. One of the great success
stories of deep-learning is that we can rely on the ability of deep networks to
generalize to new examples by learning interesting sub-structures. In this work
we aim to leverage this generalization power, but also to lift it from simple
supervised learning to the more general setting of optimization. 1.2

A brief history and related work
The idea of using learning to learn or meta-learning to acquire knowledge
or inductive biases has a long history [Thrun and Pratt, 1998]. More recently,
Lake et al. [2016] have argued forcefully for its importance as a building block in
artiﬁcial intelligence. Similarly, Santoro et al. [2016] frame multi-task learning
as generalization, however unlike our approach they directly train a base learner
rather than a training algorithm. In general these ideas involve learning which
occurs at two diﬀerent time scales: rapid learning within tasks and more gradual,
meta learning across many diﬀerent tasks. Perhaps the most general approach
to meta-learning is that of Schmidhuber [1992, 1993]?building on work from
[Schmidhuber, 1987]?which considers networks that are able to modify their
own weights. Such a system is diﬀerentiable end-to-end, allowing both the
network and the learning 2

algorithm to be trained jointly by gradient descent with few restrictions.
However this generality comes at the expense of making the learning rules very
diﬃcult to train. Alternatively, the work of Schmidhuber et al.
[1997] uses
the Success Story Algorithm to modify its search strategy rather than gradient
descent; a similar approach has been recently taken in Daniel et al. [2016] which
uses reinforcement learning to train a controller for selecting step-sizes. Bengio
et al.
[1990, 1995] propose to learn updates which avoid back-propagation by
using simple parametric rules. In relation to the focus of this paper the work
of Bengio et al. could be characterized as learning to learn without gradient
descent by gradient descent. The work of Runarsson and Jonsson [2000] builds
upon this work by replacing the simple rule with a neural network. Cotter
and Conwell [1990], and later Younger et al.
[1999], also show ﬁxed-weight
recurrent neural networks can exhibit dynamic behavior without need to modify
their network weights. Similarly this has been shown in a ﬁltering context
[e.g. Feldkamp and Puskorius, 1998], which is directly related to simple multi-
timescale optimizers [Sutton, 1992, Schraudolph, 1999]. Finally, the work of
Younger et al.
[2001] connects these diﬀerent
threads of research by allowing for the output of backpropagation from one
network to feed into an additional learning network, with both networks trained
jointly. Our approach to meta-learning builds on this work by modifying the

[2001] and Hochreiter et al.

3

network architecture of the optimizer in order to scale this approach to larger
neural-network optimization problems.

2
Learning to learn with recurrent neural networks
In this work we consider directly parameterizing the optimizer. As a result,
in a slight abuse of notation we will write the ﬁnal optimizee parameters ?? (f, )
as a function of the optimizer parameters and the function in question. We can
then ask the question: What does it mean for an optimizer to be good? Given
a distribution of functions f we will write the expected loss as h i L( ) = Ef f ??
(f, ) .
(2)
As noted earlier, we will take the update steps gt to be the output of a
recurrent neural network m, parameterized by , whose state we will denote
explicitly with ht . Next, while the objective function in (2) depends only on
the ﬁnal parameter value, for training the optimizer it will be convenient to
have an objective that depends on the entire trajectory of optimization, for
some horizon T, L( ) = Ef

”
T X t=1
wt f (?t )
#
where
?
?t+1 = ?t + gt ,
(3)
gt = m(rt , ht , ) . ht+1
Here wt 2 R 0 are arbitrary weights associated with each time-step and we
will also use the notation rt = r? f (?t ). This formulation is equivalent to (2)
when wt = 1[t = T ], but later we will describe why using diﬀerent weights
can prove useful. We can minimize the value of L( ) using gradient descent
on . The gradient estimate @L( )/@ can be computed by sampling a random
function f and applying backpropagation to the computational graph in Figure
2. We allow gradients to ﬂow along the solid edges in the graph, but gradients
along the dashed edges are dropped. Ignoring gradients along the dashed edges
amounts to making the assumption that the gradients of the optimizee do not
depend on the optimizer parameters, i.e. @rt @ = 0. This assumption allows
us to avoid computing second derivatives of f . Examining the objective in (3)
we see that the gradient is non-zero only for terms where wt 6= 0. If we use
wt = 1[t = T ] to match the original problem, then gradients of trajectory
preﬁxes are zero and only the ﬁnal optimization step provides information for
training the optimizer. This renders Backpropagation Through Time (BPTT)
ineﬃcient. We solve this problem by relaxing the objective such that wt ¿ 0 at
intermediate points along the trajectory. This changes the objective function,
but allows us to train the optimizer on partial trajectories. For simplicity, in all
our experiments we use wt = 1 for every t. 3

t-2

4

ft-2
Optimizee
?t-2
t-1
ft-1
?t-1
+
ht-2
gt
?t-1
m
?t+1
+
gt-1
?t-2
Optimizer
?t
+
gt-2
t
ft
?t
m
ht-1
m
ht
ht+1
Figure 2: Computational graph used for computing the gradient of the op-

timizer.

2.1
Coordinatewise LSTM optimizer
One challenge in applying RNNs in our setting is that we want to be able
to optimize at least tens of thousands of parameters. Optimizing at this scale
with a fully connected RNN is not feasible as it would require a huge hidden
state and an enormous number of parameters. To avoid this diﬃculty we will
use an optimizer m which operates coordinatewise on the parameters of the
objective function, similar to other common update rules like RMSprop and
ADAM. This coordinatewise network architecture allows us to use a very small
network that only looks at a single coordinate to deﬁne the optimizer and share
optimizer parameters across diﬀerent parameters of the optimizee. Diﬀerent
behavior on each coordinate is achieved by using separate activations for each
objective function parameter. In addition to allowing us to use a small network
for this optimizer, this setup has the nice eﬀect of making the optimizer invariant
to the order of parameters in the network, since the same update rule is used
independently on each coordinate.

?1

5

?1
LSTMn
+
?
?n
LSTM1
?
?
? ?n
f
?
We implement the update rule for each coordinate using a two-layer Long
Short Term Memory (LSTM) network [Hochreiter and Schmidhuber, 1997], us-
ing the now-standard forget gate architecture. The network takes as input the
optimizee gradient for a single coordinate as well as the previous hidden state
and outputs the update for the corresponding optimizee parameter. We will
refer to this architecture, illustrated in Figure 3, as an LSTM optimizer.

+
The use of recurrence allows the LSTM to learn dynamic update rules which
integrate informa- Figure 3: One step of an LSTM optimizer. All tion from the
history of gradients, similar to LSTMs have shared parameters, but separate
hidmomentum. This is known to have many desir- den states. able properties
in convex optimization [see e.g. Nesterov, 1983] and in fact many recent learning
procedures?such as ADAM?use momentum in their updates.

Preprocessing and postprocessing Optimizer inputs and outputs can have
very diﬀerent magnitudes depending on the class of function being optimized,
but neural networks usually work robustly only for inputs and outputs which
are neither very small nor very large. In practice rescaling inputs and outputs
of an LSTM optimizer using suitable constants (shared across all timesteps and
functions f ) is suﬃcient to avoid this problem. In Appendix A we propose a
diﬀerent method of preprocessing inputs to the optimizer inputs which is more
robust and gives slightly better performance. 4

Figure 4: Comparisons between learned and hand-crafted optimizers per-
formance. Learned optimizers are shown with solid lines and hand-crafted
optimizers are shown with dashed lines. Units for the y axis in the MNIST
plots are logits. Left: Performance of diﬀerent optimizers on randomly sampled
10-dimensional quadratic functions. Center: the LSTM optimizer outperforms
standard methods training the base network on MNIST. Right: Learning curves
for steps 100-200 by an optimizer trained to optimize for 100 steps (continuation
of center plot).

3
Experiments
In all experiments the trained optimizers use two-layer LSTMs with 20 hid-
den units in each layer. Each optimizer is trained by minimizing Equation 3
using truncated BPTT as described in Section 2. The minimization is per-
formed using ADAM with a learning rate chosen by random search. We use

6

early stopping when training the optimizer in order to avoid overﬁtting the op-
timizer. After each epoch (some ﬁxed number of learning steps) we freeze the
optimizer parameters and evaluate its performance. We pick the best optimizer
(according to the ﬁnal validation loss) and report its average performance on a
number of freshly sampled test problems. We compare our trained optimizers
with standard optimizers used in Deep Learning: SGD, RMSprop, ADAM, and
Nesterov?s accelerated gradient (NAG). For each of these optimizer and each
problem we tuned the learning rate, and report results with the rate that gives
the best ﬁnal error for each problem. When an optimizer has more parame-
ters than just a learning rate (e.g. decay coeﬃcients for ADAM) we use the
default values from the optim package in Torch7. Initial values of all optimizee
parameters were sampled from an IID Gaussian distribution. 3.1

Quadratic functions
In this experiment we consider training an optimizer on a simple class of syn-
thetic 10-dimensional quadratic functions. In particular we consider minimizing
functions of the form f (?) = kW ?

yk22
for diﬀerent 10x10 matrices W and 10-dimensional vectors y whose elements
are drawn from an IID Gaussian distribution. Optimizers were trained by opti-
mizing random functions from this family and tested on newly sampled functions
from the same distribution. Each function was optimized for 100 steps and the
trained optimizers were unrolled for 20 steps. We have not used any prepro-
cessing, nor postprocessing. Learning curves for diﬀerent optimizers, averaged
over many functions, are shown in the left plot of Figure 4. Each curve corre-
sponds to the average performance of one optimization algorithm on many test
functions; the solid curve shows the learned optimizer performance and dashed
curves show the performance of the standard baseline optimizers. It is clear the
learned optimizers substantially outperform the baselines in this setting. 3.2

Training a small neural network on MNIST
In this experiment we test whether trainable optimizers can learn to optimize
a small neural network on MNIST, and also explore how the trained optimizers
generalize to functions beyond those they were trained on. To this end, we train
the optimizer to optimize a base network and explore a series of modiﬁcations
to the network architecture and training procedure at test time. 5

Figure 5: Comparisons between learned and hand-crafted optimizers per-
formance. Units for the y axis are logits. Left: Generalization to the diﬀerent
number of hidden units (40 instead of 20). Center: Generalization to the diﬀer-
ent number of hidden layers (2 instead of 1). This optimization problem is very
hard, because the hidden layers are very narrow. Right: Training curves for an
MLP with 20 hidden units using ReLU activations. The LSTM optimizer was
trained on an MLP with sigmoid activations.

Figure 6: Systematic study of ﬁnal MNIST performance as the optimizee
architecture is varied, using sigmoid non-linearities. The vertical dashed line
in the left-most plot denotes the architecture at which the LSTM is trained
and the horizontal line shows the ﬁnal performance of the trained optimizer in
this setting. In this setting the objective function f (?) is the cross entropy of

7

a small MLP with parameters ?. The values of f as well as the gradients @f
(?)/@? are estimated using random minibatches of 128 examples. The base
network is an MLP with one hidden layer of 20 units using a sigmoid activation
function. The only source of variability between diﬀerent runs is the initial
value ?0 and randomness in minibatch selection. Each optimization was run
for 100 steps and the trained optimizers were unrolled for 20 steps. We used
input preprocessing described in Appendix A and rescaled the outputs of the
LSTM by the factor 0.1. Learning curves for the base network using diﬀerent
optimizers are displayed in the center plot of Figure 4.
In this experiment
NAG, ADAM, and RMSprop exhibit roughly equivalent performance the LSTM
optimizer outperforms them by a signiﬁcant margin. The right plot in Figure 4
compares the performance of the LSTM optimizer if it is allowed to run for 200
steps, despite having been trained to optimize for 100 steps. In this comparison
we re-used the LSTM optimizer from the previous experiment, and here we see
that the LSTM optimizer continues to outperform the baseline optimizers on this
task. Generalization to diﬀerent architectures Figure 5 shows three examples
of applying the LSTM optimizer to train networks with diﬀerent architectures
than the base network on which it was trained. The modiﬁcations are (from left
to right) (1) an MLP with 40 hidden units instead of 20, (2) a network with two
hidden layers instead of one, and (3) a network using ReLU activations instead
of sigmoid.
In the ﬁrst two cases the LSTM optimizer generalizes well, and
continues to outperform the hand-designed baselines despite operating outside
of its training regime. However, changing the activation function to ReLU makes
the dynamics of the learning procedure suﬃciently diﬀerent that the learned
optimizer is no longer able to generalize. Finally, in Figure 6 we show the results
of systematically varying the tested architecture; for the LSTM results we again
used the optimizer trained using 1 layer of 20 units and sigmoid non-linearities.
Note that in this setting where the 6

Figure 7: Optimization performance on the CIFAR-10 dataset and subsets.
Shown on the left is the LSTM optimizer versus various baselines trained on
CIFAR-10 and tested on a held-out test set. The two plots on the right are the
performance of these optimizers on subsets of the CIFAR labels. The additional
optimizer LSTM-sub has been trained only on the heldout labels and is hence
transferring to a completely novel dataset. test-set problems are similar enough
to those in the training set we see even better generalization than the baseline
optimizers. 3.3

Training a convolutional network on CIFAR-10
Next we test the performance of the trained neural optimizers on optimiz-
ing classiﬁcation performance for the CIFAR-10 dataset [Krizhevsky, 2009]. In
these experiments we used a model with both convolutional and feed-forward
layers. In particular, the model used for these experiments includes three con-
volutional layers with max pooling followed by a fully-connected layer with 32
hidden units; all non-linearities were ReLU activations with batch normaliza-
tion. The coordinatewise network decomposition introduced in Section 2.1?and
used in the previous experiment?utilizes a single LSTM architecture with shared
weights, but separate hidden states, for each optimizee parameter. We found

8

that this decomposition was not suﬃcient for the model architecture introduced
in this section due to the diﬀerences between the fully connected and convolu-
tional layers. Instead we modify the optimizer by introducing two LSTMs: one
proposes parameter updates for the fully connected layers and the other updates
the convolutional layer parameters. Like the previous LSTM optimizer we still
utilize a coordinatewise decomposition with shared weights and individual hid-
den states, however LSTM weights are now shared only between parameters of
the same type (i.e. fully-connected vs. convolutional). The performance of this
trained optimizer compared against the baseline techniques is shown in Figure
7. The left-most plot displays the results of using the optimizer to ﬁt a clas-
siﬁer on a held-out test set. The additional two plots on the right display the
performance of the trained optimizer on modiﬁed datasets which only contain a
subset of the labels, i.e. the CIFAR-2 dataset only contains data corresponding
to 2 of the 10 labels. Additionally we include an optimizer LSTM-sub which
was only trained on the held-out labels. In all these examples we can see that
the LSTM optimizer learns much more quickly than the baseline optimizers,
with signiﬁcant boosts in performance for the CIFAR-5 and especially CIFAR-2
datsets. We also see that the optimizers trained only on a disjoint subset of
the data is hardly eﬀected by this diﬀerence and transfers well to the additional
dataset. 3.4

Neural Art
The recent work on artistic style transfer using convolutional networks, or
Neural Art [Gatys et al., 2015], gives a natural testbed for our method, since
each content and style image pair gives rise to a diﬀerent optimization problem.
Each Neural Art problem starts from a content image, c, and a style image,
s, and is given by f (?) = ?Lcontent (c, ?) + Lstyle (s, ?) + Lreg (?) The
minimizer of f is the styled image. The ﬁrst two terms try to match the content
and style of the styled image to that of their ﬁrst argument, and the third term
is a regularizer that encourages smoothness in the styled image. Details can be
found in [Gatys et al., 2015]. 7

Figure 8: Optimization curves for Neural Art. Content images come from
the test set, which was not used during the LSTM optimizer training. Note:
the y-axis is in log scale and we zoom in on the interesting portion of this plot.
Left: Applying the training style at the training resolution. Right: Applying
the test style at double the training resolution.

Figure 9: Examples of images styled using the LSTM optimizer. Each triple
consists of the content image (left), style (right) and image generated by the
LSTM optimizer (center). Left: The result of applying the training style at the
training resolution to a test image. Right: The result of applying a new style
to a test image at double the resolution on which the optimizer was trained.
We train optimizers using only 1 style and 1800 content images taken from Im-
ageNet [Deng et al., 2009]. We randomly select 100 content images for testing
and 20 content images for validation of trained optimizers. We train the opti-
mizer on 64x64 content images from ImageNet and one ﬁxed style image. We
then test how well it generalizes to a diﬀerent style image and higher resolution
(128x128). Each image was optimized for 128 steps and trained optimizers were

9

unrolled for 32 steps. Figure 9 shows the result of styling two diﬀerent images
using the LSTM optimizer. The LSTM optimizer uses inputs preprocessing de-
scribed in Appendix A and no postprocessing. See Appendix C for additional
images. Figure 8 compares the performance of the LSTM optimizer to standard
optimization algorithms. The LSTM optimizer outperforms all standard opti-
mizers if the resolution and style image are the same as the ones on which it was
trained. Moreover, it continues to perform very well when both the resolution
and style are changed at test time. Finally, in Appendix B we qualitatively
examine the behavior of the step directions generated by the learned optimizer.

4
Conclusion
We have shown how to cast the design of optimization algorithms as a learn-
ing problem, which enables us to train optimizers that are specialized to par-
ticular classes of functions. Our experiments have conﬁrmed that learned neu-
ral optimizers compare favorably against state-of-the-art optimization methods
used in deep learning. We witnessed a remarkable degree of transfer, with for
example the LSTM optimizer trained on 12,288 parameter neural art tasks being
able to generalize to tasks with 49,152 parameters, diﬀerent styles, and diﬀerent
content images all at the same time. We observed similar impressive results
when transferring to diﬀerent architectures in the MNIST task. The results
on the CIFAR image labeling task show that the LSTM optimizers outperform
handengineered optimizers when transferring to datasets drawn from the same
data distribution.

2 References

F. Bach, R. Jenatton, J. Mairal, and G. Obozinski. Optimization with sparsity-
inducing penalties. Foundations and Trends in Machine Learning, 4(1):1?106,
2012.
8
S. Bengio, Y. Bengio, and J. Cloutier. On the search for new learning rules
for ANNs. Neural Processing Letters, 2(4):26?30, 1995. Y. Bengio, S. Bengio,
and J. Cloutier. Learning a synaptic learning rule. Universit? de Montr?al,
D?partement d?informatique et de recherche op?rationnelle, 1990. F. Bobolas.
brain-neurons, 2009. URL https://www.ﬂickr.com/photos/fbobolas/3822222947.
Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 2.0 Generic. N. E. Cotter and P. R.
Conwell. Fixed-weight networks can learn. In International Joint Conference on
Neural Networks, pages 553?559, 1990. C. Daniel, J. Taylor, and S. Nowozin.
Learning step size controllers for robust neural network training. In Associa-
tion for the Advancement of Artiﬁcial Intelligence, 2016. J. Deng, W. Dong,
R. Socher, L.-J. Li, K. Li, and L. Fei-Fei. Imagenet: A large-scale hierarchical
image database. In Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, pages 248?255.
IEEE, 2009. D. L. Donoho. Compressed sensing. Transactions on Information
Theory, 52(4):1289?1306, 2006. J. Duchi, E. Hazan, and Y. Singer. Adaptive
subgradient methods for online learning and stochastic optimization. Journal

10

of Machine Learning Research, 12:2121?2159, 2011. L. A. Feldkamp and G. V.
Puskorius. A signal processing framework based on dynamic neural networks
with application to problems in adaptation, ﬁltering, and classiﬁcation. Pro-
ceedings of the IEEE, 86(11): 2259?2277, 1998. L. A. Gatys, A. S. Ecker, and
M. Bethge. A neural algorithm of artistic style. arXiv Report 1508.06576, 2015.
S. Hochreiter and J. Schmidhuber. Long short-term memory. Neural compu-
tation, 9(8):1735?1780, 1997. S. Hochreiter, A. S. Younger, and P. R. Conwell.
Learning to learn using gradient descent. In International Conference on Ar-
tiﬁcial Neural Networks, pages 87?94. Springer, 2001. D. P. Kingma and J.
Ba. Adam: A method for stochastic optimization. In International Conference
on Learning Representations, 2015. A. Krizhevsky. Learning multiple layers of
features from tiny images. Technical report, 2009. B. M. Lake, T. D. Ullman,
J. B. Tenenbaum, and S. J. Gershman. Building machines that learn and think
like people. arXiv Report 1604.00289, 2016. T. Maley. neuron, 2011. URL
https://www.ﬂickr.com/photos/taylortotz101/6280077898. Creative Commons
Attribution 2.0 Generic. J. Martens and R. Grosse. Optimizing neural networks
with Kronecker-factored approximate curvature. In International Conference on
Machine Learning, pages 2408?2417, 2015. G. L. Nemhauser and L. A. Wolsey.
Integer and combinatorial optimization. John Wiley & Sons, 1988. Y. Nesterov.
A method of solving a convex programming problem with convergence rate o
(1/k2). In Soviet Mathematics Doklady, volume 27, pages 372?376, 1983. M.
Riedmiller and H. Braun. A direct adaptive method for faster backpropagation
learning: The RPROP algorithm. In International Conference on Neural Net-
works, pages 586?591, 1993. T. P. Runarsson and M. T. Jonsson. Evolution
and design of distributed learning rules. In IEEE Symposium on Combinations
of Evolutionary Computation and Neural Networks, pages 59?63. IEEE, 2000.
A. Santoro, S. Bartunov, M. Botvinick, D. Wierstra, and T. Lillicrap. Meta-
learning with memory-augmented neural networks. In International Conference
on Machine Learning, 2016. J. Schmidhuber. Evolutionary principles in self-
referential learning; On learning how to learn: The meta-meta-... hook. PhD
thesis, Institut f.
Informatik, Tech. Univ. Munich, 1987. J. Schmidhuber.
Learning to control fast-weight memories: An alternative to dynamic recurrent
networks. Neural Computation, 4(1):131?139, 1992. J. Schmidhuber. A neural
network that embeds its own meta-levels. In International Conference on Neu-
ral Networks, pages 407?412. IEEE, 1993. J. Schmidhuber, J. Zhao, and M.
Wiering. Shifting inductive bias with success-story algorithm, adaptive levin
search, and incremental self-improvement. Machine Learning, 28(1):105?130,
1997. N. N. Schraudolph. Local gain adaptation in stochastic gradient de-
scent.
In International Conference on Artiﬁcial Neural Networks, volume 2,
pages 569?574, 1999. R. S. Sutton. Adapting bias by gradient descent: An
incremental version of delta-bar-delta. In Association for the Advancement of
Artiﬁcial Intelligence, pages 171?176, 1992. S. Thrun and L. Pratt. Learning to
learn. Springer Science & Business Media, 1998. T. Tieleman and G. Hinton.
Lecture 6.5-rmsprop: Divide the gradient by a running average of its recent
magnitude. COURSERA: Neural Networks for Machine Learning, 4:2, 2012.
P. Tseng. An incremental gradient (-projection) method with momentum term

11

and adaptive stepsize rule. Journal on Optimization, 8(2):506?531, 1998. D.
H. Wolpert and W. G. Macready. No free lunch theorems for optimization.
Transactions on Evolutionary Computation, 1(1):67?82, 1997. A. S. Younger,
P. R. Conwell, and N. E. Cotter. Fixed-weight on-line learning. Transactions
on Neural Networks, 10(2):272?283, 1999. A. S. Younger, S. Hochreiter, and
P. R. Conwell. Meta-learning with backpropagation.
In International Joint
Conference on Neural Networks, 2001.

9

12

