Blind Attacks on Machine Learners

Authored by:

Han Liu

Zhaoran Wang
Alex Beatson

Abstract

The importance of studying the robustness of learners to malicious
data is well established. While much work has been done establishing
both robust estimators and eﬀective data injection attacks when the at-
tacker is omniscient, the ability of an attacker to provably harm learning
while having access to little information is largely unstudied. We study
the potential of a ?blind attacker? to provably limit a learner?s perfor-
mance by data injection attack without observing the learner?s training
set or any parameter of the distribution from which it is drawn. We pro-
vide examples of simple yet eﬀective attacks in two settings: ﬁrstly, where
an ?informed learner? knows the strategy chosen by the attacker, and
secondly, where a ?blind learner? knows only the proportion of malicious
data and some family to which the malicious distribution chosen by the at-
tacker belongs. For each attack, we analyze minimax rates of convergence
and establish lower bounds on the learner?s minimax risk, exhibiting lim-
its on a learner?s ability to learn under data injection attack even when
the attacker is ?blind?.

1 Paper Body

As machine learning becomes more widely adopted in security and in security-
sensitive tasks, it is important to consider what happens when some aspect of
the learning process or the training data is compromised [1?4]. Examples in
network security are common and include tasks such as spam ﬁltering [5, 6]
and network intrusion detection [7, 8]; examples outside the realm of network
security include statistical fraud detection [9] and link prediction using social
network data or communications metadata for crime science and counterter-
rorism [10]. In a training set attack, an attacker either adds adversarial data
points to the training set (?data injection?) or preturbs some of the points in
the dataset so as to inﬂuence the concept learned by the learner, often with
the aim of maximizing the learner?s risk. Training-set data injection attacks
are one of the most practical means by which an attacker can inﬂuence learn-
ing, as in many settings an attacker which does not have insider access to the

1

learner or its data collection or storage systems may still be able to carry out
some activity which is monitored and the resulting data used in the learner?s
training set [2, 6]. In a network security setting, an attacker might inject data
into the training set for an anomaly detection system so that malicious traﬃc
is classiﬁed as normal, thus making a network vulnerable to attack, or so that
normal traﬃc is classiﬁed as malicious, thus harming network operation. 30th
Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2016), Barcelona,
Spain.

A growing body of research focuses on game-theoretic approaches to the
security of machine learning, analyzing both the ability of attackers to harm
learning and eﬀective strategies for learners to defend against attacks. This
work often makes strong assumptions about the knowledge of the attacker. In a
single-round game it is usually assumed that the attacker knows the algorithm
used by the learner (e.g. SVM or PCA) and has knowledge of the training set
either by observing the training data or the data-generating distribution [2, 5,
11]. This allows the construction of an optimal attack to be treated as an op-
timization problem. However, this assumption is often unrealistic as it requires
insider knowledge of the learner or for the attacker to solve the same estimation
problem the learner faces to identify the data-generating distribution.
In an
iterated-game setting it is usually assumed the attacker can query the learner
and is thus able to estimate the learner?s current hypothesis in each round
[12?14]. This assumption is reasonable in some settings, but in other scenarios
the attacker may not receive immediate feedback from the learner, making the
iterated-game setting inappropriate. We provide analysis which makes weaker
assumptions than either of these bodies of work by taking a probabilistic ap-
proach in tackling the setting where a ?blind attacker? has no knowledge of the
training set, the learner?s algorithm or the learner?s hypothesis. Another mo-
tivation is provided by the ﬁeld of privacy. Much work in the ﬁeld of statistical
privacy concerns disclosure risk: the probability that an entry in a dataset might
be identiﬁed given statistics of the dataset released. This has been formalized by
?diﬀerential privacy?, which provides bounds on the maximum disclosure risk
[15]. However, diﬀerential privacy hinges on the benevolence of an organization
to which you give your data: the privacy of individuals is preserved as long
as organizations which collect and analyze data take necessary steps to enforce
diﬀerential privacy. Many data are gathered without users? deliberate consent
or even knowledge. Organizations are also not yet under legal obligation to use
diﬀerentially-private procedures. A user might wish to take action to preserve
their own privacy without making any assumption of benevolence on the part
of those that collect data arising from the user?s actions. For example, they
may wish to prevent an online service from accurately estimating their income,
ethnicity, or medical history. The user may have to submit some quantity of
genuine data in order to gain a result from the service which addresses a speciﬁc
query, and may not even observe all the data the service collects. They may wish
to enforce the privacy of their information by also submitting fabricated data
to the service or carrying out uncharacteristic activity. This is a data injection
training set attack, and studying such attacks thus reveals the ability of a user

2

to prevent a statistician or learner from making inferences from the user?s be-
havior. In this paper we address the problem of a one-shot data injection attack
carried out by a blind attacker who does not observe the training set, the true
distribution of interest, or the learner?s algorithm. We approach this problem
from the perspective of minimax decision theory to provide an analysis of the
rate of convergence of estimators on training sets subject to such attacks. We
consider both an ?informed learner? setting where the learner is aware of the
exact distribution used by the attacker to inject malicious data, and a ?blind
learner? setting where the learner is unaware of the malicious distribution. In
both settings we suggest attacks which aim to minimize an upper bound on
the pairwise KL divergences between the distributions conditioned on particu-
lar hypotheses, and thus maximize a lower bound on the minimax risk of the
learner. We provide lower bounds on the rate of convergence of any estimator
under these attacks.

2 2.1
Setting and contributions Setting
A learner attempts to learn some parameter ? of a distribution of interest
F? with density f? and belonging to some family F = {F? , ? ? ?}, where ?
is a set of candidate hypotheses for the parameter. ?Uncorrupted? data X1 ,
..., Xn ? X are drawn i.i.d.
from F? . The attacker chooses some malicious
distribution G? with density g? and from a family G = {G? : ? ? ?}, where
? is a parameter set representing candidate attack strategies. ?Malicious? data
X10 , .., Xn0 ? X are drawn i.i.d from the malicious distribution. The observed
dataset is made up of a fraction ? of true examples and 1 ? ? of malicious
examples. The learner observes a dataset Z1 , ..., Zn ? Z, where
Xi with probability ? Zi = (1) Xi0 with probability 1 ? ?. 2
We denote the distribution of Z with P . P is clearly a mixture distribution
with density: p(z) = ?f? (z) + (1 ? ?)g? (z). The distribution of Z conditional
on X is: p(z—x) = ?1{z = x} + (1 ? ?)g? (z). We consider two distinct
settings based on the knowledge of the attacker and of the learner. First we
consider the scenario where the learner knows the malicious distribution, G?
and the fraction of inserted examples (?informed learner?). Second we consider
the scenario where the learner knows only the family G to which G? belongs
and fraction of inserted examples (?blind learner?). Our work assumes that the
attacker knows only the family of distributions F to which the true distribution
belongs (?blind attacker?). As such, the attacker designs an attack so as to
maximally lower bound the learner?s minimax risk. We leave as future work a
probabilistic treatment of the setting where the attacker knows the true F? but
not the training set drawn from it (?informed attacker?). To our knowledge,
our work is the ﬁrst to consider the problem of learning in a setting where the
training data is distributed according to a mixture of a distribution of interest
and a malicious distribution chosen by an adversary without knowledge of the
distribution of interest. 2.2

Related work
Our paper has very strong connections to several problems which have pre-
viously been studied in the minimax framework. First is the extensive literature

3

on robust statistics. Our framework is very similar to Huber?s -contamination
model, where the observed data follows the distribution: (1 ? )P? + Q. Here
controls the degree of corruption, Q is an arbitrary corruption distribution, and
the learner attempts to estimate ? robust to the contamination. A general esti-
mator which achieves the minimax optimal rate under Huber?s -contamination
model was recently proposed by Chen, Gao and Ren[16]. Our work diﬀers from
the robust estimation literature in that rather than designing optimal estima-
tors for the learner, we provide concrete examples of attack strategies which
harm the learning rate of any estimator, even those which are optimal under
Huber?s model. Unlike robust statistics, our attacker does not have complete
information on the generating distribution, and must select an attack which is
eﬀective for any data-generating distribution drawn from some set. Our work
has similar connections to the literature on minimax rates of convergence of
estimators for mixture models [17] and minimax rates for mixed regression with
multiple components [18], but diﬀers in that we consider the problem of design-
ing a corrupting distribution. There are also connections to the work on PAC
learning with contaminated data [19]. Here the key diﬀerence, beyond the fact
that we focus on strategies for a blind attacker as discussed earlier, is that we use
information-theoretic proof techniques rather than reductions to computational
hardness. This means that our bounds restrict all learning algorithms, not just
polynomial-time learning algorithms. Our work has strong connections to the
analysis of minimax lower bounds in local diﬀerential privacy. In [20] and [21],
Duchi, Wainwright and Jordan establish lower bounds in the local diﬀerential
privacy setting, where P (Zi —Xi = x), the likelihood of an observed data point
Zi given Xi takes any value x, is no more than some constant factor greater
than P (Zi —Xi = x0 ), the likelihood of Zi given Xi takes any other value x0
. Our work can be seen as an adaptation of those ideas to a new setting: we
perform very similar analysis but in a data injection attack setting rather than
local diﬀerential privacy setting. Our analysis for the blind attacker, informed
learner setting and our examples in Section 5 for both settings draw heavily
from [21].
In fact, the blind attack setting is by nature locally diﬀerentially
private with the likelihood ratio ?f (z)+(1??)g (z) upper bounded by maxz ?
(1??)g? (z)? , as in the blind attack setting only ? of the data points are drawn
from the distribution of interest F . This immediately suggests bounds on the
minimax rates of convergence according to [20]. However, the rates we obtain
by appropriate choice of G? by the attacker obtain lower bounds on the rate
of convergence which are often much slower than the bounds due to diﬀerential
privacy obtained by arbitrary choice of G? . The rest of this work proceeds as
follows. Section 3.1 formalizes our notation. Section 3.2 introduces our minimax
framework and the standard techniques of lower bounding the minimax risk by
reduction 3

from parameter estimation to testing. Sections 3.3 and 3.4 discuss the ?blind
attacker; informed learner? and ?blind attacker; blind learner? settings in this
minimax framework. Section 3.5 brieﬂy proposes how this framework could be
extended to consider an ?informed attacker? which observes the true distri-
bution of interest F? . Section 4 provides a summary of the main results. In

4

Section 5 we give examples of estimating a mean under blind attack in both
the informed and blind learner setting and performing linear regression in the
informed learner setting. In Section 6 we conclude. Proof of the main results is
presented in the appendix.

3 3.1
Problem formulation Notation
We denote the ?uncorrupted? data with the random variables X1:n . Fi
is the distribution and ﬁ the density of each Xi conditioning on ? = ?i ? ?;
F? and f? are the generic distribution and density 0 parametrized by ?. We
denote malicious data with the random variables X1:n .
In the ?informed 0
learner? setting, G is the distribution and g the density from which each Xi
is drawn.
In the ?blind learner? setting, Gj and gj are the distribution and
density of Xi0 conditioning on ? = ?j ? ?; G? and g? are the generic distribution
and density parametrized by ?. We denote the observed data Z1:n , which is
distributed according to (1). Pi is the distribution and pi the density of each
Zi , conditioning on ? = ?i and ? = ?i . P? or P?,? is the parametrized form.
We say that Pi = ?Fi + (1 ? ?)Gi , or equivalently pi (z) = ?ﬁ (z) + (1 ? ?)gi
(z), to indicate that Pi is a weighted mixture of the distributions Fi and Gi .
We assume that X, X 0 and Z have the same support, denoted Z. Mn is the
minimax risk of a learner. DKL (P1 ——P2 ) is the KL-divergence. ——P1 ?
P2 ——TV is the total variation distance. I(Z, V ) is the mutual information
between the random variables Z and V . ??n : Z n ? ? denotes an arbitrary
estimator for ? with a sample size of n; ??n : Z n ? ? denotes an arbitrary
estimator for an arbitrary parameter vector ? with a sample size of n. 3.2

Minimax framework
The minimax risk of estimating a parameter ? ? ? is equal to the risk of
the estimator ??n which achieves smallest maximal risk across all ? ? ?: Mn =
inf sup EZ1:n ?P?n L(?, ??n ). ? ??? ?

The minimax risk thus provides a strong guarantee: the population risk of
an estimator can be no worse than the minimax risk, no matter which ? ?
? happens to be the true parameter. Our analysis aims to build insight into
how the minimax risk increases when the training set is subjected to blind data
injection attacks. In the informed learner setting we ﬁx some ? and G? , and
consider ? = ?, letting L(?, ??n ) be the squared ‘2 distance ——? ? ??n
——22 . In the blind learner setting we account for there being two parameters
unknown to the learner ? and ? by letting ? = ? ? ? and considering a loss
function which depends only on the value of ? and its estimator, L(?, ??n ) =
——? ? ??n ——22 We follow the standard approach to lower bounding the
minimax risk [22], reducing the problem of estimating ? to that of testing the
hypothesis H : V = Vj for Vj ? V, where V ? U(V), a uniform distribution across
V. V ? ? is an appropriate ﬁnite packing of the parameter space. The Le Cam
method provides lower bound on the minimax risk of the learner in terms of the
KL divergence DKL (P?1 ——P?2 ) for ?1 , ?2 ? ? [22]: q i h1 1 Mn ? L(?1
, ?2 ) ? ? nDKL (P?1 ——P?2 ) . (2) 2 2 2 The Fano method provides lower
bounds on the minimax risk of the learner in terms of the mutual information
I(Z, V ) between the observed data and V chosen uniformly at random from V,

5

where L(Vi , Vj ) ? 2? ?Vi , Vj ? V [22]: h I(Z1:n ; V ) + log 2 i Mn ? ? 1 ? .
log —V— 4

(3)
The mutual information is upper bounded by the pariwise KL divergences

as n XX I(Z1:n , V ) ? DKL (PVi ——PVj ). —V—2 i j 3.3

(4)
Blind attacker, informed learner
In this setting we assume the attacker does not know F? but does know F.
The learner knows both G? and ? prior to picking an estimator. In this case, as
G? is known, we do not need to consider a distribution over possible values of
?; instead, we consider some ﬁxed p(z—x). The attacker chooses G? to attempt
to maximally lower bound the minimax risk of the learner: ?? = argmax? Mn
= argmax? inf sup EZ1:n ?P?,? L(?, ??n ), ?? ???

where L(?, ?0 ) is the learner?s loss function; in our case the squared ‘2
distance ——? ? ?0 ——22 . The attacker chooses a malicious distribution G??
which minimizes the sum of KL-divergences between the distributions indexed
by V: ?? = argmin?

X X
DKL (P?i ,? ——P?j ,? ) ?
?i ?V ?j ?V
—V—2 I(Zn ; ?), n
P?i ,? = ?F?i + (1 ? ?)G? .
where
This directly provides lower bounds on the minimax risk of the learner via

(2) and (3). 3.4

Blind attacker, blind learner
In this setting, the learner does not know the speciﬁc malicious distribution
G? used to inject points into the training set, but is allowed to know the family
G = {G? : ? ? ?} from which the attacker picks this distribution. We propose
that the minimax risk is thus with respect to the worst-case choice of both the
true parameter of interest ? and the parameter of the malicious distribution ?:
Mn = inf

sup
?? (?,?)????
EZ1:n ?P?,? L(?, ??n ).
That is, the minimax risk in this setting is taken over worst-case choice of
the parameter pair ? is with respect to only the true value of of ? and its
estimator ?. ? (?, ?) ? ? ? ?, but the loss L(?, ?) The attacker thus designs
a family of malicious distributions G = {G? : ? ? ?} so as to maximally lower
bound the minimax risk: G ? = argmax inf

sup
?? (F? ,G? )?F ?G
? EZ1:n L(?, ?).
We use the Le Cam approach (2) in this setting. To accommodate the
additional set of parameters ? we consider nature picking (?, ?)
from ???.
The loss function is L (?i , ?i ), (?j , ?j ) = ——?i ??j ——22 , and thus only

6

depends on ?. Therefore when constructing our hypothesis set we must choose
wellseparated ? but may arbitrarily pick each element ?. The problem reduces
from that of estimating ? to that of testing the hypothesis H : (?, ?) = (?,
?)j for (?, ?)j ? V, where nature chooses (?, ?) ? U(V). The attacker again
lower bounds the minimax risk by choosing G to minimize an upper bound on
the pairwise KL divergences. Unlike the informed learner setting where the KL
divergence was between the distributions indexed by ?i and ?j with ? ﬁxed, here
the KL divergence is between the distributions indexed by appropriate choice
of pairings (?i , ?i ) and (?j , ?j ): G? = argminG

X
X
DKL (P?i ,?i ——P?j ,?j ) ?
(?i ,?i )?V (?j ,?j )?V
where
P?i ,?i = ?F?i + (1 ? ?)G?i . 5
—V—2 I(Zn ; ?), n
3.5
Informed attacker
We leave this setting as future work, but brieﬂy propose a formulation for
completeness. In this setting the attacker knows F? prior to picking G? . We
assume that the learner picks some ?? which is minimax-optimal over F and G
as deﬁned in Section 1.5 and 1.6 respectively. We denote the ? The attacker
picks G? ? G so as to maximally lower bound appropriate set of such estimators
as ?. the risk for any ?? ? ?: ? = EZ ?P L(?, ??n ). R?,? (?) 1:n ?,? This is
similar to the setting in [11], with the modiﬁcation that the learner can use any
(potentially non-convex) algorithm and estimator. The attacker must therefore
identify an optimal attack using information-theoretic techniques and knowledge
of F? , rather than inverting the learner?s convex learning problem and using
convex optimization to maximize the learner?s risk.

4 4.1
Main results Informed learner, blind attacker
In the informed learner setting, the attacker chooses a single malicious dis-
tribution (known to the learner) from which to draw malicious data. Theorem 1
(Uniform attack). The attacker picks g? (z) := g uniform over Z in the informed
learner setting. We assume that Z is compact and that G Fi Fj ??i , ?j ? ?.
Then: DKL (Pi ——Pj ) + DKL (Pj ——Pi ) ?

?2 ——Fi ? Fj ——2TV Vol(Z) ??i , ?j ? ?. (1 ? ?)
The proof modiﬁes the analysis used to prove Theorem 1 in [21] and is
presented in the appendix. By applying Le Cam?s method to P1 and P2 as
described in the theorem, we ﬁnd: Corollary 1.1 (Le Cam bound with uniform
attack). Given a data injection attack as described in Theorem 1, the minimax
risk of the learner is lower bounded by s

1 1 ?2 Mn ? L(?1 , ?2 ) ? ? n——F1 ? F2 ——2TV Vol(Z) . 2 2 2 (1 ? ?)
We turn to the local Fano method. Consider the traditional setting (P? = F?
), and consider a packing set V of ? which obeys L(?i , ?j ) ? 2? ??i , ?j ? V,
and where the KL divergences are bounded such that there exists some ﬁxed ?

7

fulﬁlling DKL (Fi ——Fj ) ? ?? ??i , ?j ? V. We can use this inequality and
the bound on mutual information in (4) to rewrite the Fano bound in (3) as: h
n?? + log 2 i Mn ? ? 1 ? . log —V— If we consider the uniform attack setting
with the same packing set V of ?, then by applying Theorem 1) in addition to
the bound on mutual information in (4) to the standard fano bound in (3), we
obtain: Corollary 1.2 (Local Fano bound with uniform attack). Given a data
injection attack as described in Theorem 1, and given any packing V of ? so
such L(?i , ?j ) ? 2? ??i , ?j ? V and DKL (Fi ——Fj ) ? ?? ??i , ?j ? V, then
the minimax risk of the learner is lower bounded by

Mn ? ? 1 ?
?2 (1??) Vol(Z)n? ?
log —V —
+ log 2
.
Remarks. Comparing the two corollaries to the standard form of the Le
Cam and Fano bounds shows ?2 that a uniform attack has the eﬀect of upper-
bounding the eﬀective sample size at n (1??) Vol(Z). The range of ? for which
this bound results in a reduction in eﬀective sample size beyond the trivial
reduction to ?n depends on Vol(Z). We illustrate the consequences of these
corollaries for some classical estimation problems in Section 3. 6

4.2
Blind learner, blind attacker
We begin with a lemma that shows that for ? ? 12 the attacker can make
learning impossible beyond permutation for higher rates of injection. Similar
results have been shown in [18] among others, and this is included for complete-
ness. Lemma 1 (Impossibility of learning beyond permutation for ? ? 0.5).
Consider any hypotheses ?1 and ?2 , with F1 F2 and F2 F1 . We construct V
= {F, G}2 = {(F1 , G1 ), (F2 , G2 )}. For all ? ? 0.5, there exist choices of
G1 and G2 such that DKL (P1 ——P2 ) + DKL (P2 ——P1 ) = 0. 2 (z) The
proof progresses by considering g1 (z) = ?f (1??) + c, g2 (z) = P2 ——TV =
0. Full proof is provided in the appendix.

?f1 (z) (1??)
+ c, such that ——P1 ?
It is unnecessary to further consider values of ? less than 0.5. We proceed
with an attack where the attacker chooses a family of malicious distributions
G which mimics the family of candidate distributions of interest F, and show
that this increases the lower bound on the learner?s minimax risk for 0.5 ¡ ?
¡ 43 . Theorem 2 (Mimic attack). Consider any hypotheses ?1 and ?2 , with
F1 F2 and F2 F1 . The attacker picks G = F. We construct V = {F, G}2 =
{(F1 , G1 ), (F2 , G2 )} where G1 = F2 and G2 = F1 . Then: (2? ? 1)2 ?4
DKL (P1 ——P2 ) + DKL (P2 ——P1 ) ? ——F1 ? F2 ——TV ? 4 ——F1
? F2 ——2TV . 1?? 1?? ? The proof progresses by upper bounding — log
pp21 (z) (z) — by log 1?? , and consequently upper bounding the pairwise
KL divergence in terms of the total variation distance. It is presented in the
appendix. By applying the standard Le Cam bound with the the bound on KL
divergence provided by the theorem, we obtain: Corollary 2.1 (Le Cam bound

8

with mimic attack). Given a data injection attack as described in Theorem 2,
the minimax risk of the learner is lower bounded by r 1

1 (2? ? 1)2 Mn ? L(?1 , ?2 ) ?? n——F1 ? F2 ——2TV . 2 1?? 2
Remarks. For ? ? [0, 43 ], comparing the corollary to the standard form of

the Le Cam bound shows 2

that this attack reduces the eﬀective sample size from n to (2??1) 1?? n. We
illustrate the consequences of this corollary for estimating a mean in Section 3.
There are two main diﬀerences in the result from the bound for the uniform
attack. Firstly, the dependence on (2? ? 1)2 instead of ?2 means that the KL
divergence rapidly approaches zero as ? ? 12 , rather than as ? ? 0 as in the
uniform attack. Secondly, there is no dependence on the volume of the support
of the data.

5
Minimax rates of convergence under blind attack
We analyze the minimax risk in the settings of mean estimation and of ﬁxed-
design linear regression by showing how the blind attack forms of the Le Cam
and Fano bounds modify the lower bounds on the minimax risk for each model.
5.1

Mean estimation
In this section we address the simple problem of estimating a one-dimensional
mean when the training set is subject to a blind attack. Consider the following
family, where ? is the interval [?1, 1]: F = {F? : EF? X = ?; EF? X 2 ? 1;
? ? ?}. We apply Theorems 1 and 2 and the associated Le Cam bounds to
obtain: Proposition 1 (Mean estimation under uniform attack ? blind attacker,
informed learner). If the attacker carries out a uniform attack as presented in
theorem 1, then there exists a universal constant 0 ¡ c ¡ ? such that the minimax
risk is bounded as: h r 1 ? ?i Mn ? c min 1, 2 2 . ? n 7

The proof is direct by using the uniform-attack form of the Le Cam lower
bound on minimax risk presented in corollary 1.1 in the proof of (20) in [21]
in place of the diﬀerentially private form of the lower bound in equation (16)
of that paper. Proposition 2 (Mean estimation under mimic attack ? blind
attacker, blind learner). If the attacker carries out a mimic attack as presented
in theorem 2, then there exists a universal constant 0 ¡ c ¡ ? such that the
minimax risk is bounded as: r h 1 ? ?i 1 . Mn ? c min 1, 2 ? 4? n The
proof is direct by using the mimic-attack form of the Le Cam lower bound on
minimax risk presented in corollary 2.1 in the proof of (20) in [21] in place of
the diﬀerentially private form of the lower bound in equation (16) of that paper.
5.2

Linear regression with ﬁxed design
We now consider the minimax risk in a standard ﬁxed-design linear regression
problem. Consider a ﬁxed design matrix X ? Rn?d , and the standard linear
model Y = X?? + , where ? Rn is a vector of independent noise variables with
each entry of the noise vector upper bounded as —i — ? ? ¡ ? ?i. We assume
that the problem is appropriately scaled so that ——X——? ? 1, ——Y ——?
? 1, and so that it suﬃces to consider ?? ? ?, where ? = Sd is the d-dimensional
unit sphere. The loss function is the squared ‘2 loss with respect to ?? : L(??n

9

, ?? ) = ——??n ? ?? ——22 . It is also assumed that X is full rank to make
estimation of ? possible. Proposition 3 (Linear regression under uniform attack
- blind attacker, informed learner). If the attacker carries out a uniform attack
per Theorem 1, and si (A) is the ith singular value of A, then the minimax
risk is bounded by h ? 2 d(1 ? ?) i ? Mn ? min 1, . 2 n? s2max (X/ n)
The proof is direct by using the uniform-attack form of the Fano lower bound
on minimax risk presented in corollary 1.2 in the proof of (22) in [21] in place
of the diﬀerentially private form of the lower bound in equation (19) of that
paper, noting ? that Vol(Z) ? 1 by construction. If we consider the orthonormal
design case such that s2max (X/ n) = 1, and recall that lower bounds on 2 the
minimax risk in linear regression in traditional settings is O( ?nd ), we see a
clear reduction in 2 ? eﬀective sample size from n to 1?? n.

6
Discussion
We have approached the problem of data injection attacks on machine learn-
ers from a statistical decision theory framework, considering the setting where
the attacker does not observe the true distribution of interest or the learner?s
training set prior to choosing a distribution from which to draw malicious exam-
ples. This has applications to the theoretical analysis of both security settings,
where an attacker attempts to compromise a machine learner through data in-
jection, and privacy settings, where a user of a service aims to protect their own
privacy by sumbitting some proportion of falsiﬁed data. We identiﬁed simple
attacks in settings where the learner is and is not aware of the malicious dis-
tribution used which reduce the eﬀective sample size when considering rates of
convergence of estimators. These attacks maximize lower bounds on the min-
imax risk. These lower bounds may not be tight, and we leave as future work
thorough exploration of optimality of attacks in this setting and the establishing
of optimal estimation procedures in the presence of such attacks. Exploration
of attacks on machine learners in the minimax framework should lead to better
understanding of the inﬂuence an attacker might have over a learner in settings
where the attacker has little information.

2 References

(1)

M. Barreno, B. Nelson, R. Sears, A. D. Joseph and J. D. Tygar, ACM

Symposium on Information, computer and communications security, 2006. 8

(2) (3) (4) (5) (6) (7) (8) (9) (10) (11) (12) (13) (14) (15) (16) (17) (18) (19)

(20) (21) (22)

M. Barreno, B. Nelson, A. D. Joseph and J. Tygar, Machine Learning, 2010,
81, 121?148. P. Laskov and M. Kloft, ACM workshop on security and artiﬁcial
intelligence, 2009. P. Laskov and R. Lippmann, Machine learning, 2010, 81,
115?119. H. Xiao, H. Xiao and C. Eckert, European Conference on Artiﬁcial
Intelligence, 2012, pp. 870? 875. B. Biggio, B. Nelson and P. Laskov, arXiv
preprint arXiv:1206.6389, 2012. B. I. Rubinstein, B. Nelson, L. Huang, A. D.

10

Joseph, S.-h. Lau, N. Taft and D. Tygar, EECS Department, University of Cal-
ifornia, Berkeley, Tech. Rep. UCB/EECS-2008-73, 2008. R. Sommer and V.
Paxson, IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, 2010. R. J. Bolton and D. J.
Hand, Statistical science, 2002, 235?249. M. Al Hasan, V. Chaoji, S. Salem and
M. Zaki, SDM Workshop on Link Analysis, Counterterrorism and Security, 2006.
S. Mei and X. Zhu, Association for the Advancement of Artiﬁcial Intelligence,
2015. W. Liu and S. Chawla, IEEE International Conference on Data Min-
ing, 2009. S. Alfeld, X. Zhu and P. Barford, Association for the Advancement
of Artiﬁcial Intelligence, 2016. M. Bruckner and T. Scheﬀer, ACM SIGKDD,
2011. C. Dwork, in Automata, languages and programming, Springer, 2006,
pp. 1?12. M. Chen, C. Gao and Z. Ren, arXiv preprint arXiv:1511.04144, 2015.
M. Azizyan, A. Singh and L. Wasserman, Neural Information Processing Sys-
tems, 2013. Y. Chen, X. Yi and C. Caramanis, arXiv preprint arXiv:1312.7006,
2013. M. Kearns and M. Li, SIAM Journal on Computing, 1993, 22, 807?837.
J. Duchi, M. J. Wainwright and M. I. Jordan, Neural Information Process-
ing Systems, 2013. J. Duchi, M. Wainwright and M. Jordan, arXiv preprint
arXiv:1302.3203v4, 2014. A. B. Tsybakov, Introduction to Nonparametric Es-
timation, Springer Publishing Company, Incorporated, 1st, 2008.

9

11

