Using Social Dynamics to Make Individual
Predictions: Variational Inference with a

Stochastic Kinetic Model

Authored by:

Zhen Xu
Wen Dong

Sargur N. Srihari

Abstract

Social dynamics is concerned primarily with interactions among indi-
viduals and the resulting group behaviors, modeling the temporal evo-
lution of social systems via the interactions of individuals within these
systems. In particular, the availability of large-scale data from social net-
works and sensor networks oﬀers an unprecedented opportunity to predict
state-changing events at the individual level. Examples of such events
include disease transmission, opinion transition in elections, and rumor
propagation. Unlike previous research focusing on the collective eﬀects
of social systems, this study makes eﬃcient inferences at the individual
level. In order to cope with dynamic interactions among a large number of
individuals, we introduce the stochastic kinetic model to capture adaptive
transition probabilities and propose an eﬃcient variational inference algo-
rithm the complexity of which grows linearly ? rather than exponentially?
with the number of individuals. To validate this method, we have per-
formed epidemic-dynamics experiments on wireless sensor network data
collected from more than ten thousand people over three years. The pro-
posed algorithm was used to track disease transmission and predict the
probability of infection for each individual. Our results demonstrate that
this method is more eﬃcient than sampling while nonetheless achieving
high accuracy.

1 Paper Body

The ﬁeld of social dynamics is concerned primarily with interactions among in-
dividuals and the resulting group behaviors. Research in social dynamics models
the temporal evolution of social systems via the interactions of the individuals
within these systems [9]. For example, opinion dynamics can model the opinion
state transitions of an entire population in an election scenario [3], and epidemic

1

dynamics can predict disease outbreaks ahead of time [10]. While traditional
socialdynamics models focus primarily on the macroscopic eﬀects of social sys-
tems, often we instead wish to know the answers to more speciﬁc questions.
Given the movement and behavior history of a subject with Ebola, can we tell
how many people should be tested or quarantined? City-size quarantine is not
necessary, but family-size quarantine is insuﬃcient. We aim to model a method
to evaluate the paths of illness transmission and the risks of infection for indi-
viduals, so that limited medical resources can be most eﬃciently distributed.
The rapid growth of both social networks and sensor networks oﬀers an unprece-
dented opportunity to collect abundant data at the individual level. From these
data we can extract temporal interactions among individuals, such as meeting
or taking the same class. To take advantage of this opportunity, we model social
dynamics from an individual perspective. Although such an approach has con-
siderable potential, in practice it is diﬃcult to model the dynamic interactions
and handle the costly computations when a large number of individuals are in-
volved. In this paper, we introduce an 30th Conference on Neural Information
Processing Systems (NIPS 2016), Barcelona, Spain.

event-based model into social systems to characterize their temporal evolu-
tions and make tractable inferences on the individual level. Our research on the
temporal evolutions of social systems is related to dynamic Bayesian networks
and continuous time Bayesian networks [13, 18, 21]. Traditionally, a coupled
hidden Markov model is used to capture the interactions of components in a
system [2], but this model does not consider dynamic interactions. However,
a stochastic kinetic model is capable of successfully describing the interactions
of molecules (such as collisions) in chemical reactions [12, 22], and is widely
used in many ﬁelds such as chemistry and cell biology [1, 11]. We introduce
this model into social dynamics and use it to focus on individual behaviors. A
challenge in capturing the interactions of individuals is that in social dynam-
ics the state space grows exponentially with the number of individuals, which
makes exact inference intractable. To resolve this we must apply approximate
inference methods. One class of these involves sampling-based methods. Rao
and Teh introduce a Gibbs sampler based on local updates [20], while Murphy
and Russell introduce Rao-Blackwellized particle ﬁltering for dynamic Bayesian
networks [17]. However, sampling-based methods sometimes mix slowly and
require a large number of samples/particles. To demonstrate this issue, we oﬀer
empirical comparisons with two major sampling methods in Section 4. An al-
ternative class of approximations is based on variational inference. Opper and
Sanguinetti apply the variational mean ﬁeld approach to factor a Markov jump
process [19], and Cohn and El-Hay further improve its eﬃciency by exploiting
the structure of the target network [4]. A problem is that in an event-based
model such as a stochastic kinetic model (SKM), the variational mean ﬁeld is
not applicable when a single event changes the states of two individuals simulta-
neously. Here, we use a general expectation propagation principle [14] to design
our algorithm. This paper makes three contributions: First, we introduce the
discrete event model into social dynamics and make tractable inferences on both
individual behaviors and collective eﬀects. To this end, we apply the stochastic

2

kinetic model to deﬁne adaptive transition probabilities that characterize the
dynamic interaction patterns in social systems. Second, we design an eﬃcient
variational inference algorithm whose computation complexity grows linearly
with the number of individuals. As a result, it scales very well in large social
systems. Third, we conduct experiments on epidemic dynamics to demonstrate
that our algorithm can track the transmission of epidemics and predict the
probability of infection for each individual. Further, we demonstrate that the
proposed method is more eﬃcient than sampling while nonetheless achieving
high accuracy. The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. In Section
2, we brieﬂy review the coupled hidden Markov model and the stochastic ki-
netic model.
In Section 3, we propose applying a variational algorithm with
the stochastic kinetic model to make tractable inferences in social dynamics. In
Section 4, we detail empirical results from applying the proposed algorithm to
our epidemic data along with the proximity data collected from sensor networks.
Section 5 concludes.

2 2.1
Background Coupled Hidden Markov Model
A coupled hidden Markov model (CHMM) captures the dynamics of a dis-
crete time Markov process that joins a number of distinct hidden Markov models
(HMMs), as shown in Figure 2.1(a). xt = (1) (M ) (m) (xt , . . . , xt ) deﬁnes
the hidden states of all HMMs at time t, and xt is the hidden state of (1) (M
) (m) HMM m at time t. yt = (yt , . . . , yt ) are observations of all HMMs
at time t, and yt is the observation of HMM m at time t. P (xt —xt 1 ) are
transition probabilities, and P (yt —xt ) are emission probabilities for CHMM.
Given hidden states, all observations are independent. As such, Q (m) (m) (m)
(m) P (yt —xt ) = m P (yt —xt ), where P (yt —xt ) is the emission proba-
bility for HMM m at time t. The joint probability of CHMM can be deﬁned as
follows: P (x1,...,T , y1,...,T ) =

T Y
t=1
P (xt —xt
1 )P (yt —xt ).
(1)
For a CHMM that contains M HMMs in a binary state, the state space is 2M
, and the state transition kernel is a 2M ? 2M matrix. In order to make exact
inferences, the classic forward-backward algorithm sweeps a forward/ﬁltering
pass to compute the forward statistics ?t (xt ) = P (xt —y1,...,t ) 2

vt
HMM 1 ...
HMM 2 ...
HMM 3 ...
x1,t-1
x1,t
x1,t+1
y1,t-1
y1,t

3

y1,t+1
x2,t-1
x2,t
x2,t+1
y2,t-1
y2,t
y2,t+1
x3,t-1
x3,t
x3,t+1
y3,t-1
y3,t
y3,t+1
t-1
t
HMM 1 ...
...
...
HMM 2 ...
...
HMM 3 ...
vt+1
x1,t-1
x1,t
x1,t+1
y1,t-1
y1,t
y1,t+1
x2,t-1
x2,t
x2,t+1
y2,t-1
y2,t
y2,t+1
x3,t-1
x3,t
x3,t+1
y3,t-1
y3,t
y3,t+1
t-1
t+1
t
...
...
...

4

t+1
Time
Time
(a)
(b)
Figure 1: Illustration of (a) Coupled Hidden Markov Model, (b) Stochastic

Kinetic Model. P (y

—x )
t t+1,...,T and a backward/smoothing pass to estimate the backward statis-
tics t (xt ) = P (yt+1,...,T —y1,...,t ) . Then it can estimate the one-slice
statistics t (xt ) = P (xt —y1,...,T ) = ?t (xt ) t (xt ) and two-slice (xt —xt 1
)P (yt —xt ) t (xt ) statistics ?t (xt 1 , xt ) = P (xt 1 , xt —y1,...,T ) = ?t 1 (xt
1 )P . Its complexity P (yt —y1,...,t 1 ) grows exponentially with the number of
HMM chains. In order to make tractable inferences, certain factorizations and
approximations must be applied. In the next section, we introduce a stochastic
kinetic model to lower the dimensionality of transition probabilities.

2.2
The Stochastic Kinetic Model
A stochastic kinetic model describes the temporal evolution of a chemical
system with M species X = {X1 , X2 , ? ? ? , XM } driven by V events (or
chemical reactions) parameterized by rate constants c = (c1 , . . . , cV ). An
event (chemical reaction) k has a general form as follows: c

k r1 X 1 + ? ? ? + rM X M ! p1 X 1 + ? ? ? + pM X M . The species on
the left are called reactants, and rm is the number of mth reactant molecules
consumed during the reaction. The species on the right are called products, and
pm is the number of mth product molecules produced in the reaction. Species
involved in the reaction (rm ¿ 0) without consumption or production (rm = pm
) are called catalysts. At any speciﬁc time t, the populations of the species (1)
(M ) is xt = (xt , .
, xt ). An event k happens with rate hk (xt , ck ),
determined by the rate constant and the current population state [22]:

.

.

hk (xt , ck ) =ck gk (xt ) = ck
M Y
(m)
(m)
gk (xt
(2)
).
m=1
The form of gk (xt ) depends on the reaction. In our case, we adopt the
product form QM (m) (m) ), which represents the total number of ways that
reactant molecules can be selected m=1 gk (xt to trigger event k [22]. Event k
changes the populations by k = xt xt 1 . The probability that event k will occur
during time interval (t, t + dt] is hk (xt , ck )dt. We assume at each discrete
time step that no more than one event will occur. This assumption follows the
linearization principle in the literature [18], and is valid when the discrete time

5

step is small. We treat each discrete time step as a unit of time, so that hk (xt
, ck ) represents the probability of an event. c

i In epidemic modeling, for example, an infection event vi has the form S + I
! 2I, such that a susceptible individual (S) is infected by an infectious individual
(I) with rate constant ci . If there is only one susceptible individual (type m =
1) and one infectious individual (type m = 2) involved in this event, hi (xt , ci
) = ci , i = [ 1 1]T and P (xt xt 1 = i ) = P (xt —xt 1 , vi ) = ci .

In a traditional hidden Markov model, the transition kernel is typically ﬁxed.
In comparison, SKM is better at capturing dynamic interactions in terms of the
events with rates dependent on reactant populations, as shown in Eq.(2). 3

3
Variational Inference with the Stochastic Kinetic Model
In this section, we deﬁne the likelihood of the entire sequence of hidden states
and observations for an event-based model, and derive a variational inference
algorithm and parameter-learning algorithm. 3.1

Likelihood for Event-based Model
In social dynamics, we use a discrete time Markov model to describe the
temporal evolutions of a set of individuals x(1) , .
, x(M ) according to
a set of V events. To cope with dynamic interactions, we introduce the SKM
and express the state transition probabilities in terms of event probabilities, as
shown in Figure 2.1(b). We assume at each discrete time step that no more
than one event will occur. Let v1 , .
, vT be a sequence of events, x1 , .
. . , xT a sequence of hidden states, and y1 , . . . , yT a set of observations.
Similar to Eq.(1), the likelihood of the entire sequence is as follows: P (x1,...,T
, y1,...,T , v1,...,T ) = P (xt , vt —xt

.

.

.

.

1)
=
?
T Y
t=1
P (xt , vt —xt
1 )P (yt —xt ),
where
ck ? gk (xt 1 ) ? (xt xt 1 ? k ) P (1 xt 1 ? 0) k ck gk (xt 1 )) ? (xt
(3)
if vt = k . if vt = ;
P (xt , vt —xt 1 ) is the event-based transition kernel. (xt xt 1 ? k ) is 1 if
the previous state is xt 1 and the current state is xt = xt 1 + k , and 0 otherwise.
k is the eﬀect of event vk . ; represents an auxiliary event, meaning that there
is no event. Substituting the product form of gk , the transition kernel can be
written as follows: Y (m) (m) Y (m) (m) (m) P (xt , vt = k—xt 1 ) = ck gk
(xt 1 ) ? (xt xt 1 ? k ), (4) m

P (xt , vt = ;—xt
(m)
(m)
where (xt xt 1 ? (m) (m) state is xt = xt 1 + 3.2

6

1)
= (1
X
ck
k
Y
m (m) (m) gk (xt 1 ))
m
(m) k ) is 1 if the previous (m) k , and 0 otherwise.
?
Y
(m)
(xt
(m) 1
xt
m
? 0),
(m) 1
state of an individual m is xt
(5)
and the current
Variational Inference for Stochastic Kinetic Model
As noted in Section 2.1, exact inference in social dynamics is intractable due
to the formidable state space. However, we can approximate the posterior distri-
bution P (x1,...,T , v1,...,T —y1,...,T ) using an approximate distribution within
the exponential family. The inference algorithm minimizes the KL divergence
between these two distributions, which can be formulated as an optimization
problem [14]: Minimize: t,xt

Subject to:
X
??t (xt
1 , x t , vt )
1 ,xt ,vt
X
1 , x t , vt )
=
(m) (m) ?t (xt ),
for all
(6)
m
(m) t, m, xt ,
(m) } 1 ,{xt xt
??t (xt
1 , x t , vt )
(m) (m) 1 (xt 1 ),
= ?t

7

(m) 1,
for all t, m, xt
(m) 1 xt 1 },xt
vt ,{xt
X
??t (xt 1 , xt , vt ) P (xt , vt —xt 1 )P (yt —xt ) X Y (m) (m) Y (m) (m)

?t (xt ) log ?t (xt ) t,xt m

??t (xt
vt ,xt
X
? log
(m)
?t
(m)
(xt
) = 1, for all t, m.
(m) xt
The objective function is the Bethe free energy, composed of average energy
and Bethe entropy (m) (m) approximation [23]. ??t (xt 1 , xt , vt ) is the ap-
proximate two-slice statistics and ?t (xt ) is the approximate one-slice statistics
for each individual P m. They form the approximate distribution over which to
minimize the Bethe free energy. The t,xt 1 ,xt ,vt is an abbreviation for sum-
ming over P (m) t, xt 1 , xt , and vt . {xt x(m) } is the sum over all individuals
in xt except xt . We use similar t abbreviations below. The ﬁrst two sets of
constraints are marginalization conditions, and the third 4

is normalization conditions. To solve this constrained optimization problem,
we ﬁrst deﬁne the Lagrange function using Lagrange multipliers to weight con-
straints, then take the partial derivatives (m) (m) with respect to ??t (xt 1 , xt
, vt ), and ?t (xt ). The dual problem is to ﬁnd the approximate forward (m)
(m) (m) (m) statistics ? ? t 1 (xt 1 ) and backward statistics ?t (xt ) in order
to maximize the pseudo-likelihood function. The duality is between minimizing
Bethe free energy and maximizing pseudo-likelihood. The ﬁxed-point solution
for the primal problem is as follows1 : 1 X Q (m) (m) (m) (m) Q (m) (m) Q
(m) (m) ??t (xt 1 , xt , vt ) = P (xt ,vt —xt 1 )? m ? ? t 1 (xt 1 )? m P (yt
—xt )? m ?t (xt ). (7) Zt (m0 ) (m0 ) m0 6=m,xt

1
,xt
(m) (m) ??t (xt 1 , xt , vt )
is the two-slice statistics for an individual m, and Zt is the normalization
constant. Given the factorized form of P (xt , vt —xt 1 ) in Eqs.
(4) and
(5), everything in Eq. (7) can be written (m) (m) in a factorized form. After
reformulating the term relevant to the individual m, ??t (xt 1 , xt , vt ) can be
shown neatly as follows: 1 ? (m) (m) (m) (m) (m) (m) (m) (m) (m) (m) ??t
(xt 1 , xt , vt ) = P (xt , vt —xt 1 ) ? ? ? t 1 (xt 1 )P (yt —xt ) ?t (xt ), (8)
Zt (m) (m) where the marginalized transition kernel P? (xt , vt —xt 1 ) for the
individual m can be deﬁned as: Y (m) (m) (m) (m) (m0 ) (m) (m) (m) P? (xt

8

, vt = k—xt 1 ) = ck gk (xt 1 ) g?k,t 1 ? (xt xt 1 ? k ), (9) (m) (m) P? (xt ,
vt = ;—xt 1 ) = (1

X
m0 6=m
(m)
(m) 1)
ck gk (xt
Y
m0 6=m
k
(m0 ) 1)
g?k,t
P (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) ?t 1 (xt 1 )P (yt

—xt ) t (xt )gk (xt 1 ) 1= 0 0 0 (m ) (m ) (m ) xt x ? t 1 k

g ?k,t
P (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) ?t 1 (xt 1 )P (yt —xt )

t (xt )gk (xt 1 ) 1= (m0 ) (m0 ) xt x ?0 t 1

g ?k,t
P
(m)
(xt
(m) 1
xt
? 0),
(10)
(m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) —xt ) t (xt ) 1 (xt 1 )P (yt 0 (m ) x

?0 t 1
?t
(m0 ) xt
P
(m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) (m0 ) ?t 1 (xt 1 )P (yt —xt ) t (xt ) (m0 )

(m0 ) xt x ?0 t 1

,
,
In the above equations, we consider the mean ﬁeld eﬀect by summing over
the current and previous states of all the other individuals m0 6= m. The
marginalized transition kernel considers the probability of event k on the indi-
vidual m given the context of the temporal evolutions of the other individuals.
(m0 ) (m0 ) Comparing Eqs. (9) and (10) with Eqs. (4) and (5), instead of
multiplying gk (xt 1 ) for individual (m0 )

m0 6= m, we use the expected value of gk
with respect to the marginal probability distribution of
(m0 ) xt 1 .
Complexity Analysis: In our inference algorithm, the most computation-
intensive step is the marginalization in Eqs. (9)-(10). The complexity is O(M
S 2 ), where M is the number of individuals and S is the state space of a single

9

individual. The complexity of the entire algorithm is therefore O(M S 2 T N
), where T is the number of time steps and N is the number of iterations until
convergence. As such, the complexity of our algorithm grows only linearly with
the number of individuals; it oﬀers excellent scalability when the number of
tracked individuals becomes large. 3.3 Parameter Learning In order to learn
the rate constant ck , we maximize the expected log likelihood. In a stochastic
kinetic model, the probability of a sample path is given in Eq. (3). The expected
log likelihood over the posterior probability conditioned on the observations y1
, .
, yT takes the following form: X log P (x1,...,T , y1,...,T , v1,...,T ) =
??t (xt 1 , xt , vt ) ? log(P (xt , vt —xt 1 )P (yt —xt )). t,xt

.

.

1 ,xt ,vt
??t (xt 1 , xt , vt ) is the approximate two-slice statistics deﬁned in Eq. (6).
Maximizing this expected log likelihood by setting its partial derivative over
the rate constants to 0 gives the maximum expected log likelihood estimation
of these rate constants. P P P ? ? t,xt 1 ,xt ?t (xt 1 , xt , vt = k) t x ,x ?t (xt
1 , xt , vt = k) ck = P ? P Q Pt 1 t (m) (m) (m) (m) . (11) ? (m) ?t 1 (xt 1
)g t,xt 1 ,xt ?t (xt 1 , xt , vt = ;)gk (xt 1 ) t m k (xt 1 ) x t

1
1
The derivations for the optimization problem and its solution are shown in

the Supplemental Material.

5
As such, the rate constant for event k is the expected number of times that
this event has occurred divided by the total expected number of times this
event could have occurred. To summarize, we provide the variational inference
algorithm below. Algorithm: Variational Inference with a Stochastic Kinetic
Model (m)

Given the observations yt for k = 1, . . . , V .
(m)
for t = 1, . . . , T and m = 1, . . . , M , ﬁnd xt
, vt and rate constants ck
Latent state inference. Iterate through the following forward and backward
passes until convergence, (m) (m) where P? (xt , vt —xt 1 ) is given by Eqs.
(9) and (10). (m)

? Forward pass. For t = 1, . . . , T and m = 1, . . . , M , update ? ?t (m)
? ?t
(m)
(xt
(m)
(xt
) according to
1 X (m) (m) ? (m) (m) (m) (m) ? ? (x )P (xt , vt —xt 1 )P (yt —xt ). Zt

(m) t 1 t 1

)
xt
1 ,vt

10

(m) (m) ? Backward pass. For t = T, . . . , 1 and m = 1, . . . , M , update

?t 1 (xt 1 ) according to

1 X ?(m) (m) ? (m) (m) (m) (m) (xt )P (xt , vt —xt 1 )P (yt —xt ). Zt

(m) t

?(m) (x(m) ) t 1
t 1
xt
,vt
Parameter estimation. Iterate through the latent state inference (above) and

rate constants estimate of ck according to Eq. (11), until convergence.

4
Experiments on Epidemic Applications
In this section, we evaluate the performance of variational inference with a
stochastic kinetic model (VISKM) algorithm of epidemic dynamics, with which
we predict the transmission of diseases and the health status of each individual
based on proximity data collected from sensor networks. 4.1

Epidemic Dynamics
In epidemic dynamics, Gt = (M, Et ) is a dynamic network, where each node
m 2 M is an individual in the network, and Et = {(mi , mj )} is a set of edges
in Gt representing that individuals mi and mj have interacted at a speciﬁc time
t. There are two possible hidden states for each (m) individual m at time t, xt
2 {0, 1}, where 0 indicates the susceptible state and 1 the infectious (m) state.
yt 2 {0, 1} represents the presence or absence of symptoms for individual m at
time t. (m) (m) P (yt —xt ) represents the observation probability. We deﬁne
three types of events in epidemic c1 applications: (1) A previously infectious
individual recovers and becomes susceptible again: I ! S. c2 (2) An infectious
individual infects a susceptible individual in the network: S + I ! 2I. (3) A
c3 susceptible individual in the network is infected by an outside infectious
individual: S ! I. Based on these events, the transition kernel can be deﬁned as
follows: (m)

(m) 1 = 1) = c1 , (m) (m) P (xt = 0—xt 1 = 0) = (1
P (xt
= 0—xt
(m)
(m) 1
P (xt
= 1—xt
c3 )(1
Cm,t
c2 )
,
= 1) = 1
c1 ,
(m) (m) P (xt = 1—xt 1 = 0)
=1
(1

11

c3 )(1
c2 )Cm,t ,
P (m0 ) where Cm,t = ? 1) is the number of possible infectious sources
for m0 :(m0 ,m)2Et (xt individual m at time t. Intuitively, the probability of
a susceptible individual becoming infected is 1 minus the probability that no
infectious individuals (inside or outside the network) infected him. When (m)
(m) the probability of infection is very small, we can approximate P (xt = 1—xt
1 = 0) ? c3 +c2 ?Cm,t . 6

4.2
Experimental Results
Data Explanation: We employ two data sets of epidemic dynamics. The
real data set is collected from the Social Evolution experiment [5, 6]. This
study records ?common cold? symptoms of 65 students living in a university
residence hall from January 2009 to April 2009, tracking their locations and
proximities using mobile phones. In addition, the students took periodic sur-
veys regarding their health status and personal interactions. The synthetic
data set was collected on the Dartmouth College campus from April 2001 to
June 2004, and contains the movement history of 13,888 individuals [16]. We
synthesized disease transmission along a timeline using the popular susceptible-
infectioussusceptible (SIS) epidemiology model [15], then applied the VISKM
to calibrate performance. We selected this data set because we want to demon-
strate that our model works on data with a large number of people over a
long period of time. Evaluation Metrics and Baseline Algorithms: We select
the receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve as our performance metric
because the discrimination thresholds of diseases vary. We ﬁrst compare the
accuracy and eﬃciency of VISKM with Gibbs sampling (Gibbs) and particle
ﬁltering (PF) on the Social Evolution data set [7, 8].2 Both Gibbs sampling and
particle ﬁltering iteratively sample the infectious and susceptible latent state
sequences and the infection and recovery events conditioned on these state se-
quences. Gibbs-Prediction-10000 indicates 10,000 iterations of Gibbs sampling
with 1000 burn-in iterations for the prediction task. PF-Smoothing-1000 sim-
ilarly refers to 1000 iterations of particle ﬁltering for the smoothing task. All
experiments are performed on the same computer. Individual State Inference:
We infer the probabilities of a hidden infectious state for each individual at
diﬀerent times under diﬀerent scenarios. There are three tasks: 1. Prediction:
Given an individual?s past health and current interaction patterns, we predict
the current infectious latent state. Figure 2(a) compares prediction performance
among the diﬀerent approximate inference methods. 2. Smoothing: Given an
individual?s interaction patterns and past health with missing periods, we infer
the infectious latent states during these missing periods. Figure 2(b) compares
the performance of the three inference methods. 3. Expansion: Given the
health records of a portion (? 10%) of the population, we estimate the individ-
ual infectious states of the entire population before medically inspecting them.
For example, given either a group of volunteers willing to report their symp-
toms or the symptom data of patients who came to hospitals, we determine the
probabilities that the people near these individuals also became or will become

12

infected. This information helps the government or aid agencies to eﬃciently
distribute limited medical resources to those most in need. Figure 2(c) compares
the performance of the diﬀerent methods. From the above three graphs, we can
see that all three methods identify the infectious states in an accurate way.
However, VISKM outperforms Gibbs sampling and particle ﬁltering in terms
of area under the ROC curve for all three tasks. VISKM has an advantage in
the smoothing task because the backward pass helps to infer the missing states
using subsequent observations. In addition, the performance of Gibbs and PF
improves as the number of samples/particles increases. Figure 2(d) shows the
performance of the three tasks on the Dartmouth data set. We do not apply the
same comparison because it takes too much time for sampling. From the graph,
we can see that VISKM infers most of the infectious moments of individuals in
an accurate way for a large social system. In addition, the smoothing results
are slightly better than the prediction results because we can leverage obser-
vations from both directions. The expansion case is relatively poor, because
we use only very limited information to derive the results; however, even in
this case the ROC curve has good discriminating power to diﬀerentiate between
infectious and susceptible individuals. Collective Statistics Inference: After de-
termining the individual results, we aggregate them to approximate the total
number of infected individuals in the social system as time evolves. This oﬀers
a collective statistical summary of the spread of disease in one area as in tradi-
tional research, which typically scales the sample statistics with respect to the
sample ratio. Figures 2(e) and (f) show that given 20% of the Social Evolution
data and 10% of the Dartmouth data, VISKM estimates the collective statistics
better than the other methods. Eﬃciency and Scalability: Table 1 shows the
running time of diﬀerent algorithms for the Social Evolution data on the same
computer. From the table, we can see that Gibbs sampling runs slightly longer
than PF, but they are in the same scale. However, VISKM requires much less
computation time. 2

Code and data are available at http://cse.buﬀalo.edu/wendong/.
7
1
1
0.9
0.9
0.8
0.8
0.8
0.7 0.6 0.5 0.4
VISKM?Prediction PF?Prediction?10000 PF?Prediction?1000 Gibbs?Prediction?10000

Gibbs?Prediction?1000

0.2 0.1 0
0
0.1
0.2
0.3

13

0.4
0.5
0.6
0.7
0.8
0.9
0.6 0.5 0.4
VISKM?Smoothing PF?Smoothing?10000 PF?Smoothing?1000 Gibbs?Smoothing?10000

Gibbs?Smoothing?1000

0.3 0.2 0.1 0
1
0
0.1
0.2
0.3
(a) Prediction
0.6
1
45
0.9
40
Number of Patients
0.6 0.5 0.4 0.3
0
0.1
0.2
0.3
0.4
0.5
0.6
0.7
0.9
0.4
VISKM?Expansion PF?Expansion?10000 PF?Expansion?1000 Gibbs?Expansion?10000

Gibbs?Expansion?1000

0.3
0.1 0
1
0
0.1
0.2
0.8
0.9
0.3
0.4
0.5

14

0.6
0.7
0.8
0.9
1
False Positive Rate
(c) Expansion
30 25 20 15
150
Real Number VISKM?Aggregation Scaling
100
50
10
VISKM?Prediction VISKM?Smoothing VISKM?Expansion
0.1
0.8
Real Number VISKM?Aggregation PF?10000 Gibbs?10000 Scaling
35
0.7
0.2
0.7
0.5
(b) Smoothing
0.8
True Positive Rate
0.5
0.6
False Positive Rate
False Positive Rate
0
0.4
0.7
0.2
Number of Patients
0.3
0.7
True Positive Rate
True Positive Rate
True Positive Rate
1 0.9
5 1
False Positive Rate
0
0
0
20

15

40
60
80
100
120
140
0
500
(d) Dartmouth
(e) Social Evolution Statistics
1000
1500
2000
2500
3000
Time Sequence
Time Sequence
(f) Dartmouth Statistics
Figure 2: Experimental results. (a-c) show the prediction, smoothing, and
expansion performance comparisons for Social Evolution data, while (d) shows
performance of the three tasks for Dartmouth data. (e-f) represent the statistical
inferences for both data sets. Table 1: Running time for diﬀerent approximate
inference algorithms. Gibbs 10000 refers to Gibbs sampling for 10,000 iterations,
and PF 1000 to particle ﬁltering for 1000 iterations. Other entries follow the
same pattern. All times are measured in seconds. 60 People 30 People 15 People

VISKM 0.78 0.39 0.19
Gibbs 1000 771 255 101
Gibbs 10000 7820 2556 1003
PF 1000 601 166 122
PF 10000 6100 1888 1435
In addition, the computation time of VISKM grows linearly with the number
of individuals, which validates the complexity analysis in Section 3.2. Thus, it
oﬀers excellent scalability for large social systems. In comparison, Gibbs sam-
pling and PF grow super linearly with the number of individuals, and roughly
linearly with the number of samples. Summary: Our proposed VISKM achieves
higher accuracy in terms of area under ROC curve and collective statistics than
Gibbs sampling or particle ﬁltering (within 10,000 iterations). More impor-
tantly, VISKM is more eﬃcient than sampling with much less computation
time. Additionally, the computation time of VISKM grows linearly with the
number of individuals, demonstrating its excellent scalability for large social
systems.

5
Conclusions
In this paper, we leverage sensor network and social network data to cap-
ture temporal evolution in social dynamics and infer individual behaviors. In

16

order to deﬁne the adaptive transition kernel, we introduce a stochastic dy-
namic mode that captures the dynamics of complex interactions. In addition,
in order to make tractable inferences we propose a variational inference algo-
rithm the computation complexity of which grows linearly with the number of
individuals. Large-scale experiments on epidemic dynamics demonstrate that
our method eﬀectively captures the evolution of social dynamics and accurately
infers individual behaviors. More accurate collective eﬀects can be also derived
through the aggregated results. Potential applications for our algorithm include
the dynamics of emotion, opinion, rumor, collaboration, and friendship. 8

2 References

[1] Adam Arkin, John Ross, and Harley H McAdams. Stochastic kinetic analysis
of developmental pathway bifurcation in phage -infected escherichia coli cells.
Genetics, 149(4):1633?1648, 1998. 1 [2] Matthew Brand, Nuria Oliver, and Alex
Pentland. Coupled hidden markov models for complex action recognition. In
Proc. of CVPR, pages 994?999, 1997. 1 [3] Claudio Castellano, Santo Fortunato,
and Vittorio Loreto. Statistical physics of social dynamics. Reviews of modern
physics, 81(2):591, 2009. 1 [4] Ido Cohn, Tal El-Hay, Nir Friedman, and Raz
Kupferman. Mean ﬁeld variational approximation for continuous-time bayesian
networks. The Journal of Machine Learning Research, 11:2745? 2783, 2010. 1
[5] Wen Dong, Katherine Heller, and Alex Sandy Pentland. Modeling infection
with multi-agent dynamics. In International Conference on Social Computing,
Behavioral-Cultural Modeling, and Prediction, pages 172?179. Springer, 2012.
4.2 [6] Wen Dong, Bruno Lepri, and Alex Sandy Pentland. Modeling the co-
evolution of behaviors and social relationships using mobile phone data.
In
Proc. of the 10th International Conference on Mobile and Ubiquitous Multi-
media, pages 134?143. ACM, 2011. 4.2 [7] Wen Dong, Alex Pentland, and
Katherine A Heller. Graph-coupled hmms for modeling the spread of infection.
In Proc. of UAI, pages 227?236, 2012. 4.2 [8] Arnaud Doucet and Adam M
Johansen. A tutorial on particle ﬁltering and smoothing: Fifteen years later.
Handbook of Nonlinear Filtering, 12(656-704):3, 2009. 4.2 [9] Steven N Durlauf
and H Peyton Young. Social dynamics, volume 4. MIT Press, 2004. 1 [10]
Stephen Eubank, Hasan Guclu, VS Anil Kumar, Madhav V Marathe, Aravind
Srinivasan, Zoltan Toroczkai, and Nan Wang. Modelling disease outbreaks in re-
alistic urban social networks. Nature, 429(6988):180?184, 2004. 1 [11] Daniel T
Gillespie. Stochastic simulation of chemical kinetics. Annu. Rev. Phys. Chem.,
58:35?55, 2007. 1 [12] Andrew Golightly and Darren J Wilkinson. Bayesian
parameter inference for stochastic biochemical network models using particle
markov chain monte carlo. Interface focus, 2011. 1 [13] Creighton Heaukulani
and Zoubin Ghahramani. Dynamic probabilistic models for latent feature prop-
agation in social networks. In Proc. of ICML, pages 275?283, 2013. 1 [14] Tom
Heskes and Onno Zoeter. Expectation propagation for approximate inference in
dynamic bayesian networks. In Proc. of UAI, pages 216?223, 2002. 1, 3.2 [15]
Matt J Keeling and Pejman Rohani. Modeling infectious diseases in humans and

17

animals. Princeton University Press, 2008. 4.2 [16] David Kotz, Tristan Hender-
son, Ilya Abyzov, and Jihwang Yeo. CRAWDAD data set dartmouth/campus
(v. 2007-02-08). Downloaded from http://crawdad.org/dartmouth/campus/,
2007. 4.2 [17] Kevin Murphy and Stuart Russell. Rao-blackwellised particle
ﬁltering for dynamic bayesian networks. In Sequential Monte Carlo methods
in practice, pages 499?515. Springer, 2001. 1 [18] Uri Nodelman, Christian
R Shelton, and Daphne Koller. Continuous time bayesian networks. In Proc.
of UAI, pages 378?387. Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc., 2002. 1, 2.2 [19]
Manfred Opper and Guido Sanguinetti. Variational inference for markov jump
processes. In Proc. of NIPS, pages 1105?1112, 2008. 1 [20] V. Rao and Y. W.
Teh. Fast MCMC sampling for markov jump processes and continuous time
bayesian networks.
In Proc. of UAI, 2011. 1 [21] Joshua W Robinson and
Alexander J Hartemink. Learning non-stationary dynamic bayesian networks.
The Journal of Machine Learning Research, 11:3647?3680, 2010. 1 [22] Darren
J Wilkinson. Stochastic modeling for systems biology. CRC press, 2011. 1, 2.2,
2.2 [23] Jonathan S Yedidia, William T Freeman, and Yair Weiss. Understand-
ing belief propagation and its generalizations. Exploring artiﬁcial intelligence
in the new millennium, 8:236?239, 2003. 3.2 9

18

