Adaptive Averaging in Accelerated Descent

Dynamics

Authored by:

Peter L. Bartlett
Walid Krichene
Alexandre Bayen

Abstract

We study accelerated descent dynamics for constrained convex opti-
mization. This dynamics can be described naturally as a coupling of a
dual variable accumulating gradients at a given rate $eta(t)$, and a primal
variable obtained as the weighted average of the mirrored dual trajectory,
with weights $w(t)$. Using a Lyapunov argument, we give suﬃcient con-
ditions on $eta$ and $w$ to achieve a desired convergence rate. As an
example, we show that the replicator dynamics (an example of mirror de-
scent on the simplex) can be accelerated using a simple averaging scheme.
We then propose an adaptive averaging heuristic which adaptively com-
putes the weights to speed up the decrease of the Lyapunov function. We
provide guarantees on adaptive averaging in continuous-time, prove that
it preserves the quadratic convergence rate of accelerated ﬁrst-order meth-
ods in discrete-time, and give numerical experiments to compare it with
existing heuristics, such as adaptive restarting. The experiments indicate
that adaptive averaging performs at least as well as adaptive restarting,
with signiﬁcant improvements in some cases.

1 Paper Body

We study the problem of minimizing a convex function f over a feasible set X
, a closed convex subset of E = Rn . We will assume that f is diﬀerentiable,
that its gradient ?f is a Lipschitz function with Lipschitz constant L, and that
the set of minimizers S = arg minx?X f (x) is non-empty. We will focus on
the study of continuous-time, ﬁrst-order dynamics for optimization. First-order
methods have seen a resurgence of interest due to the signiﬁcant increase in
both size and dimensionality of the data sets typically encountered in machine
learning and other applications, which makes higher-order methods computa-
tionally intractable in most cases. Continuous-time dynamics for optimization
have been studied for a long time, e.g. [6, 9, 5], and more recently [20, 2, 1, 3,
11, 23], in which a connection is made between Nesterov?s accelerated methods

1

[14, 15] and a family of continuous-time ODEs. Many optimization algorithms
can be interpreted as a discretization of a continuous-time process, and study-
ing the continuous-time dynamics is useful for many reasons: The analysis is
often simpler in continuous-time, it can help guide the design and analysis of
new algorithms, and it provides intuition and insight into the discrete process.
For example, Su et al. show in [20] that Nesterov?s original method [14] is a
discretization of a second-order ODE, and use this interpretation to propose
a restarting heuristic which empirically speeds up the convergence.
In [11],
we generalize this approach to the proximal version of Nesterov?s method [15]
which applies to constrained convex problems, and show that the continuous-
time ODE can be interpreted as coupled dynamics of a dual variable Z(t) which
evolves in the dual space E ? , and a primal variable X(t) which is obtained
as the weighted average of a non-linear transformation of the dual trajectory.
More precisely, ? ? Z(t) = ? rt ?f (X(t)) ? ? ? ?

R t r?1 ? ?? ? (Z(? ))d?
X(t) = 0 R t ? r?1 d? ? 0 ? ? ? X(0) = ?? ? (Z(0)) = x0 , ?
Walid Krichene is currently aﬃliated with Google. walidk@google.com
30th Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2016),

Barcelona, Spain.

where r ? 2 is a ﬁxed parameter, the initial condition x0 is a point in the
feasible set X , and ?? ? is a Lipschitz function that maps from the dual space E
? to the feasible set X , which we refer to as the mirror map (such a function can
be constructed using standard results from convex analysis, by taking the convex
conjugate of a strongly convex function ? with domain X ; see the supplementary
material for a brief review of the deﬁnition and basic properties of mirror maps).
Using a Lyapunov argument, we show that the solution trajectories of this ODE
exhibit a quadratic convergence rate, i.e.
if f ? is the minimum of f over the
feasible set, then f (X(t)) ? f ? ? C/t2 for a constant C which depends
on the initial conditions. This formalized an interesting connection between
acceleration and averaging, which had been observed in [8] in the special case of
unconstrained quadratic minimization. A natural question that arises is whether
diﬀerent averaging schemes can be used to achieve the same rate, or perhaps
faster rates. In this article, we provide a positive answer. We study a broad
family of Accelerated Mirror Descent (AMD) dynamics, given by ? ? Z(t) =
??(t)?f (X(t)) ? ? ? ? R Rt X(t0 )W (t0 )+ tt w(? )?? ? (Z(? ))d? 0 AMDw,?
X(t) = , with W (t) = 0 w(? )d? W (t) ? ? ? ? X(t0 ) = ?? ? (Z(t0 )) = x0 ,

(1)
parameterized by two positive, continuous weight functions w and ?, where
w is used in the averaging and ? determines the rate at which Z accumulates
gradients. This is illustrated in Figure 1.
In our formulation we choose to
initialize the ODE at t0 ¿ 0 instead of 0 (to guarantee existence and uniqueness
of a solution, as discussed in Section 2). We give a uniﬁed study of this ODE
using an appropriate Lyapunov function, given by Lr (X, Z, t) = r(t)(f (X) ? f
? ) + D?? (Z, z ? ),

(2)
where D?? is the Bregman divergence associated with ? ? (a non-negative

2

function deﬁned on E ? ? E ? ), and r(t) is a desired convergence rate (a
non-negative function deﬁned on R+ ). By construction, Lr is a non-negative
function on X ? E ? ? R+ . If t 7? Lr (X(t), Z(t), t) is a non-increasing function
for all solution trajectories (X(t), Z(t)), then Lr is said to be a Lyapunov function
for the ODE, in reference to Aleksandr Mikhailovich Lyapunov [12]. We give in
Theorem 2 a suﬃcient condition on ?, w and r for Lr to be a Lyapunov function
for AMDw,? , and show that under these conditions, f (X(t)) converges to f ?
at the rate 1/r(t). E

??
X
E?
?? ? (Z(t))
Z(t)
X(t)
??(t)?f (X(t))
?? ?
Figure 1: Illustration of AMDw,? . The dual variable Z evolves in the
dual space E ? , and accumulates negative gradients at a rate ?(t), and the
primal variable X(t) (green solid line) is obtained by averaging the mirrored
trajectory {?? ? (Z(? )), ? ? [t0 , t]} (green dashed line), with weights w(?
). In Section 3, we give an equivalent formulation of AMDw,? written purely
in the primal space. We give several examples of these dynamics for simple
constraint sets. In particular, when the feasible set is the probability simplex,
we derive an accelerated version of the replicator dynamics, an ODE that plays
an important role in evolutionary game theory [22] and viability theory [4].
Many heuristics have been developed to empirically speed up the convergence
of accelerated methods. Most of these heuristics consist in restarting the ODE
(or the algorithm in discrete time) whenever a simple condition is met. For
example, a gradient restart heuristic is proposed in [17], in which the algorithm
is restarted whenever the trajectory forms an acute angle with the gradient
(which intuitively indicates that the trajectory is not making progress), and a
speed restarting heuristic ? is proposed in [20], in which the ODE is restarted
whenever the speed kX(t)k decreases (which intuitively indicates that progress
is slowing). These heuristics are known to empirically improve 2

the speed of convergence, but provide few guarantees. For example, the
gradient restart in [17] is only studied for unconstrained quadratic problems,
and the speed restart in [20] is only studied for unconstrained strongly convex
problems.
In particular, it is not guaranteed (to our knowledge) that these
heuristics preserve the original convergence rate of the non-restarted method,
when the objective function is not strongly convex. In Section 4, we propose a
new heuristic that provides such guarantees, and that is based on a simple idea
for adaptively computing the weights w(t) along the solution trajectories. The
heuristic simply decreases the time derivative of the Lyapunov function Lr (X(t),
Z(t), t) whenever possible. Thus it preserves the 1/r(t) convergence rate. Other
adaptive methods have been applied to convex optimization, such as Adagrad
[7] and Adam [10], which adapt the learning rate in ﬁrst-order methods, by

3

maintaining moment estimates of the observed gradients. They are particularly
well suited to problems with sparse gradients. While these methods are similar
in spirit to adaptive averaging, they are not designed for accelerated methods. In
Section 5, we give numerical experiments in which we compare the performance
of adaptive averaging and restarting. The experiments indicate that adaptive
averaging compares favorably in all of the examples, and gives a signiﬁcant
improvement in some cases. We conclude with a brief discussion in Section 6.

2
Accelerated mirror descent with generalized averaging
We start by giving an equivalent form of AMDw,? , which we use to brieﬂy
discuss existence and uniqueness of a solution. Writing the second equation as
X(t)W (t) ? X(t0 )W (t0 ) = Rt w(? )?? ? (Z(? ))d? , then taking the
time-derivative, we have t0 ? X(t)W (t) + X(t)w(t) = w(t)?? ? (Z(t)). Thus
the ODE is equivalent to ? ? Z(t) = ??(t)?f (X(t)) ? ? ? 0 w(t) ? AMDw,?
X(t) = W (?? ? (Z(t)) ? X(t)) (t) ? ? ? X(t0 ) = ?? ? (Z(t0 )) = x0 .

The following theorem guarantees existence and uniqueness of the solution.
Theorem 1. Suppose that W (t0 ) ¿ 0. Then AMDw,? has a unique maximal
(i.e. deﬁned on a maximal interval) solution (X(t), Z(t)) that is C 1 ([t0 , +?)).
Furthermore, for all t ? t0 , X(t) belongs to the feasible set X . Proof. Recall
that, by assumption, ?f and ?? ? are both Lipschitz, and w, ? are continuous.
Furthermore, W (t) is non-decreasing and continuous, as the integral of a non-
negative function, thus w(t)/W (t) ? w(t)/W (t0 ). This guarantees that on any
ﬁnite interval [t0 , T ), the functions ?(t) and w(t) ? w(t)/W (t) are bounded.
Therefore, ??(t)?f (X) and W (t) (?? (Z) ? X) are Lipschitz functions of (X,
Z), uniformly in t ? [t0 , T ). By the Cauchy-Lipschitz theorem (e.g. Theorem
2.5 in [21]), there exists a unique C 1 solution deﬁned on [t0 , T ). Since T is
arbitrary, this deﬁnes a unique solution on all of [t0 , +?).
Indeed, any two
solutions deﬁned on [t0 , T1 ) and [t0 , T2 ) with T2 ¿ T1 coincide on [t0 ,
T1 ). Finally, feasibility of the solution follows from the fact that X is convex
and X(t) is the weighted average of points in X , speciﬁcally, x0 and the set
{?? ? (Z(? )), ? ? [t0 , t]}. Note that in general, it is important to initialize
the ODE at t0 and not 0, since W (0) = 0 and w(t)/W (t) can diverge at 0,
in which case one cannot apply the Cauchy-Lipschitz theorem. It is possible
however to prove existence and uniqueness with t0 = 0 for some choices of
w, by taking a sequence of Lipschitz ODEs that approximate the original one,
as is done in [20], but this is a technicality and does not matter for practical
purposes. We now move to our main result for this section. Suppose that r
is an increasing, positive diﬀerentiable function on [t0 , +?), and consider the
candidate Lyapunov function Lr deﬁned in (2), where the Bregman divergence
term is given by D?? (z, y) := ? ? (z) ? ? ? (y) ? h?? ? (y), z ? yi ,

and z ? is a point in the dual space such that ?? ? (z ? ) = x? belongs to the
set of minimizers S. Let (X(t), Z(t)) be the unique maximal solution trajectory
of AMDw,? . 3

Taking the derivative of t 7? Lr (X(t), Z(t), t) = r(t)(f (X(t)) ? f ? ) + D??

(Z(t), z ? ), we have

D E D E d ? ? Lr (X(t), Z(t), t) = r0 (t)(f (X(t)) ? f ? ) + r(t) ?f (X(t)),

4

X(t) + Z(t), ?? ? (Z(t)) ? ?? ? (z ? ) dt

D E W (t) ? 0 ? ? ? = r (t)(f (X(t)) ? f ) + r(t) ?f (X(t)), X(t) + ??(t)?f

(X(t)), X(t) + X(t) ? x w(t)

D E ?(t)W (t) ? ? (f (X(t)) ? f ? )(r0 (t) ? ?(t)) + ?f (X(t)), X(t) r(t) ? ,

(3) w(t)

where we used the expressions for Z? and ?? ? (Z) from AMD0w,? in the
second equality, and convexity of f in the last inequality. Equipped with this
bound, it becomes straightforward to give suﬃcient conditions for Lr to be a
Lyapunov function. Theorem 2. Suppose that for all t ? [t0 , +?), 0 1. ?(t) D
? r (t) and E ? 2. ?f (X(t)), X(t) r(t) ?

?(t)W (t) w(t)
? 0.
Then Lr is a Lyapunov function for AMDw,? , and for all t ? t0 , f (X(t)) ?

f ? ?

Lr (X(t0 ),Z(t0 ),t0 ) . r(t)
d Proof. The two conditions, combined with inequality (3), imply that dt
Lr (X(t), Z(t), t) ? 0, thus Lr is a Lyapunov function. Finally, since D?? is
non-negative, and Lr is decreasing, we have

f (X(t)) ? f ? ?
Lr (X(t), Z(t), t) Lr (X(t0 ), Z(t0 ), t0 ) ? . r(t) r(t)
which proves the claim. Note that the second condition depends on the
solution trajectory X(t), and may be hard to check a priori. However, we give
one special case in which the condition trivially holds. Corollary 1. Suppose
that for all t ? [t0 , +?), ?(t) =

w(t)r(t) W (t) , ?
w(t) r 0 (t) W (t) ? r(t) . Then Lr (X(t0 ),Z(t0 ),t0 ) . r(t)
and
Lyapunov function for AMDw,? , and for all t ? t0 , f (X(t)) ? f ?
Lr is a
Next, we describe a method to construct weight functions w, ? that satisfy
the conditions of Corolw(t) r 0 (t) lary 1, given a desired rate r. Of course, it
suﬃces to construct w that satisﬁes W (t) ? r(t) , then to set ?(t) =

w(t)r(t) W (t) .
We can reparameterize the weight function by writing
integrating from t0 to t, we have
W (t) W (t0 )
=e
Rt t0
a(? )d?
w(t) = w(t0 )
w(t) W (t)
= a(t). Then
, and
a(t) Rtt a(? )d? e 0 . a(t0 )
(4)

5

Therefore the conditions of the corollary are satisﬁed whenever w(t) is of
the form (4) and a : R+ ? 0 (t) R+ is a continuous, positive function with a(t)
? rr(t) . Note that the expression of w is deﬁned up to the constant w(t0 ),
which reﬂects the fact that the condition of the corollary is scale-invariant (if
the condition holds for a function w, then it holds for ?w for all ? ¿ 0). Example
1. Let r(t) = t2 . Then r0 (t)/r(t) = 2/t, and we can take a(t) = ?t with ? ?
2. Then Rt
a(? )d?
a(t) ?/t ? ln(t/t0 ) e t0 e = (t/t0 )??1 and ?(t) = w(t)r(t) w(t) = a(t = ?/t
W (t) = ?t, and we recover 0) 0 the weighting scheme used in [11]. Example 2.
More generally, if r(t) = tp , p ? 1, then r0 (t)/r(t) = p/t, and we can take a(t)
= ?t p?1 with ? ? p. Then w(t) = (t/t0 )??1 , and ?(t) = w(t)r(t) . W (t) = ?t
We also exhibit in the following a second energy function that is guaranteed
to decrease under the same conditions. This energy function, unlike the Lya-
punov function Lr , does not guarantee a speciﬁc convergence rate. However,
it captures a natural measure of energy in the system. To deﬁne this energy
function, we will use the following characterization of the inverse mirror map:
By duality of the subdiﬀerentials (e.g. Theorem 23.5 in [18]), we have for a pair
of convex conjugate functions ? and ? ? that x ? ?? ? (x? ) if and only if x?
? ??(x). To simplify the discussion, we will assume that ? is also diﬀerentiable,
so that (?? ? )?1 = ?? (this assumption can be relaxed). In what follows, ? =
??(X) and Z? = ?? ? (Z). we will denote by X 4

? = ??(X). Theorem 3. Let (X(t), Z(t)) be the unique maximal solution of

AMDw,? , and let X Consider the energy function Er (t) = f (X(t)) +

1 ? D?? (Z(t), X(t)). r(t)
(5)
Then if w, ? satisfy condition (2) of Theorem 2, Er is a decreasing function
of time. Proof. To make the notation more concise, we omit the explicit depen-
dence on time in this proof. ? = ? ? (Z) ? ? ? (X) ? ? X, Z ? X ? . Taking the
time-derivative , we have We have D?? (Z, X) E E D E D D E D d ?? ?? ? X,
? Z ?X ? ? X, Z? ? X ? = ?? ? (Z), Z? ? ?? ? (X), ? X D?? (Z, X) dt D E D
E ? Z ?X ? . = ?? ? (Z) ? X, Z? ? X,

D E ? Z ?X ? = ? and X, Using the second equation in AMD0w,? , we have

?? ? (Z) ? X = a1 X,

? ? Z ?X ? a ?? ? (Z) ? ?? ? (X), Combining, we have D E ? 0 by
monotonicity of ?? . ? d ? ? ? D? (Z, X) ? ? X, ?f (X) , and we can ﬁnally
bound the derivative of Er : dt

a
D E 1 d 0 d ? ? r D?? (Z, X) ? Er (t) = ?f (X), X? + D?? (Z, X) 2 dt r dt

r D E ? ? ?f (X), X? 1? . ar

Therefore condition (2) of Theorem 2 implies that
d dt Er (t)
? 0.
This energy function can be interpreted, loosely speaking, as the sum of a
potential energy given by 1 ? Indeed, when the problem is unconstrained, f (X),
and a kinetic energy given by r(t) D?? (Z, X): ? = then one can take ? ? (z) =

6

12 kzk2 , in which case ?? ? = ?? = I, the identity, and D?? (Z, X) ? 1 ? kZ ?
Xk2 = 1 k X k2 , a quantity proportional to the kinetic energy. 2

3
2
a
Primal Representation and Example Dynamics
An equivalent primal representation can be obtained by rewriting the equa-
tions in terms of Z? = ?? ? (Z) and its derivatives (Z? is a primal variable that
remains in X , since ?? ? maps into X ). In this section, we assume that ? ? is
twice diﬀerentiable on E ? . Taking the time derivative of ? = ?? ? (Z(t)), we
have Z(t) ?? ? ? Z(t) = ?2 ? ? (Z(t))Z(t) = ??(t)?2 ? ? ? ??(Z(t))?f (X(t)), 2

?
where ?2 ? ? (z) is the Hessian of ? ? at z, deﬁned as ?2 ? ? (z)ij = ??z?j
?z(z) . Then using the averaging i expression for X, we can write AMDw,? in
the following primal form

? R ? )d? x0 W (t0 )+ tt w(? )Z(? ? Z(t) ? 2 ? 0 ? ? = ??(t)? ? ? ??(

Z(t))?f W (t) AMDpw,? ? ? Z(t0 ) = x0 .

(6)
A similar derivation can be made for the mirror descent ODE without ac-
celeration, which can be written as follows [11] (see also the original derivation
of Nemirovski and Yudin in Chapter 3 in [13]) ? ? ? = ??f (X(t)) ? Z(t) MD
X(t) = ?? ? (Z(t)) ? ? X(t ) = x . 0 0

Note that this can be interpreted as a limit case of AMD?,w with ?(t) ? 1
and w(t) a Dirac function ? ? at t. Taking the time derivative of X(t) = ?? ?
(Z(t)), we have X(t) = ?2 ? ? (Z(t))Z(t), which leads to the primal form of the
mirror descent ODE ( MD

p
? X(t) = ??2 ? ? ? ??(X(t))?f (X(t)) X(t0 ) = x0 .
5
(7)
The operator ?2 ? ? ? ?? appears in both primal representations (6) and
(7), and multiplies the gradient of f . It can be thought of as a transformation
of the gradient which ensures that the primal trajectory remains in the feasible
set, this is illustrated in the supplementary material. For some choices of ?, ?2
? ? ? ?? has a simple expression. We give two examples below.

We also observe that in its primal form, AMDpw,? is a generalization of the
ODE family studied d ? in [23], which can be written as dt ??(X(t) + e??(t)
X(t)) = ?e?(t)+?(t) ?f (X(t)), for which ??(t) they prove the convergence rate
O(e ). This corresponds to setting, in our notation, a(t) = e?(t) , ?(t) r(t) = e
and taking ?(t) = a(t)r(t) (which corresponds to the condition of Corollary 1).
n Positive-orthant-constrained dynamics orthant + , and consider P Suppose
that X is the positive P zR ? i ?1 the negative entropy function ?(x) = i xi ln
xi . Then its dual is ? (z) = i e , and we have ??(x)i = 1 + ln xi and ?2 ? ?
(z)i,j = ?ij ezi ?1 , where ?ij is 1 if i = j and 0 otherwise. Thus for all x ? Rn+
, ?2 ? ? ? ??(x) = diag(x). Therefore, the primal forms (7) and (6), reduce to,
respectively, (

7

?i, X? i = ?Xi ?f (X)i ?i, Z?? i = ??(t)Z?i ?f (X)i ? 0 ) = x0 X(0) = x0 Z(t
where for the second ODE we write X compactly to denote the weighted
average given by the second equation of AMDw,? . When f is aﬃne, the
mirror descent ODE lead to Lotka-Volterra equation which has applications in
economics and ecology. For the mirror descent ODE, one can verify that the
solution remains in the positive orthant since X? tends to 0 as Xi approaches
the boundary of the feasible set. Similarly for the accelerated version, Z?? tends
to 0 as Z? approaches the boundary, thus Z? remains feasible, and so does X
by convexity. Simplex-constrained dynamics: Pn the replicator equation. Now
suppose that X is the n-simplex, n X = ? = {x ? R : + i=1 xi = 1}. Consider
the distance-generating function ?(x) = Pn x ln x + ? (x), where i i X i=1 Pn
?X (?) is the convex indicator function of the feasible set. Then its conjugate
is ? ? (z) = ln ( i=1 ezi ), deﬁned on E ? , and we have ??(x)i = 1 + ln xi , ??
? (z)i = zi Pe z k ke

?j x Pi i k xk
(
, and ?2 ? ? (z)ij =
?
(
xi xj P 2 k xk )
? j ez i Pi z k ke
?
ezi ezj P z 2. k) ke
(
Then it is simple to calculate ?2 ? ? ? ??(x)ij =
= ?ij xi ? xi xj . Therefore, the primal forms (7) and (6) reduce to, respec-

tively,

?i, X? i + Xi (?f (X)i ? hX, ?f (X)i) = 0 X(0) = x0
(
? ?f (X) = 0 ?i, Z?? i + ?(t)Z?i ?f (X)i ? Z, ? Z(0) = x0 .
The ﬁrst ODE is known as the replicator dynamics [19], and has many appli-
cations in evolutionary game theory [22] and viability theory [4], among others.
See the supplementary material for additional discussion on the interpretation
and applications of the replicator dynamics. This example shows that the repli-
cator dynamics can be accelerated simply by performing the original replicator
update on the ? in which (i) the gradient of the objective function is scaled by
?(t) at time t, and (ii) the variable Z, gradient is evaluated at X(t), the weighted
average of the Z? trajectory.

4
Adaptive Averaging Heuristic
In this section, we propose an adaptive averaging heuristic for Dadaptively
computing E the weights w. ?(t) ?(t) ? Note that in Corollary 1, we simply set
a(t) = r(t) so that ?f (X(t)), X(t) r(t) ? a(t) is identically zero (thus trivially
satisfying condition (2) of Theorem 2). However, from the bound (3), if this
term is negative, then this helps further decrease the Lyapunov function Lr (as
well as the energy function Er ). A simple strategy is then to adaptively choose

8

a(t) as follows D E ( ? a(t) = ?(t) if ?f (X(t)), X(t) ¿ 0, r(t) (8) ?(t) a(t) ? r(t)
otherwise. If we further have ?(t) ? r0 (t), then the conditions of Theorem 2
and Theorem 3 are satisﬁed, which guarantee that Lr is a Lyapunov function
and that the energy Er decreases. In particular, such a heuristic would preserve
the convergence rate r(t) by Theorem 2. 6

We now propose a discrete version of the heuristic when r(t) = t2 . We
consider the quadratic rate in particular since in this case the discretization
proposed by [11] preserves the quadratic rate, and corresponds to a ﬁrst-order
accelerated method2 for which many heuristics have been developed, such as the
restarting heuristics [17, 20] discussed in the introduction. To satisfy condition
(1) of ? Theorem 2, we choose ?(t) = ?t with ? ? 2. Note that in this case,
?(t) r(t) = t . In the supplementary ? material, we propose a discretization
of the heuristic (8), using the correspondance t = k s, for a step size s. The
resulting algorithm is summarized in Algorithm 1, where ? ? is a smooth
distance generating function, and R is a regularizer assumed to be strongly
convex and smooth. We give a bound on the convergence rate of Algorithm 1
in the supplementary material. The proof relies on a discrete counterpart of the
Lyapunov function Lr . ? The algorithm keeps ak = ak?1 whenever f (? x(k+1)
) ? f (? x(k) ), and sets ak to k? otherwise. This s results in a non-increasing
sequence ak . It is worth observing that in continuous time, from the expression
(4), a constant a(t) over an interval [t1 , t2 ] corresponds to an exponential
increase in the weight w(t) over that interval, while a(t) = ?t corresponds to a
polynomial increase w(t) = (t/t0 )??1 . Intuitively, adaptive averaging increases
the weights w(t) on portions of the trajectory which make progress.

Algorithm 1 Accelerated mirror descent with adaptive averaging 1: Initialize
x ?(0) = x0 , z?(0) = x0 , a1 = ??s 2: for k ? N do D E 3: z?(k+1) = arg
minz??X ?ks ?f (x(k) ), z? + D? (? z , z?(k) ). D E 4: x ?(k+1) = arg minx??X
?s ?f (x(k) ), x ? + R(? x, x(k) ) 6:

x(k+1) = ?k+1 z?(k+1) + (1 ? ?k+1 )? x(k+1) , with ?k =
max ak = min ak?1 , ?k?s
7: 8:
if f (? x(k+1) ) ? f (? x(k) ) ¿ 0 then ? ? ak = k s
5:
5
? sa ? k . 1+ sak
Numerical Experiments
In this section, we compare our adaptive averaging heuristic (in its discrete
version given in Algorithm 1) to existing restarting heuristics. We consider
simplex-constrained problems and take the distance generating function ? to be
the entropy function, so that the resulting algorithm is a discretization of the
accelerated replicator ODE studied in Section 3. We perform the experiments
in R3 so that we can visualize the solution trajectories (the supplementary
material contains additional experiments in higher dimension). We consider
diﬀerent objective functions: A strongly convex quadratic given by f (x) = (x
? s)T A(x ? s) for a positive deﬁnite matrix A, a weakly convex quadratic, a
linear function f (x) = cT x, and the Kullback-Leibler divergence, f (x) = DKL

9

(x? , x). We compare the following methods: 1. The original accelerated mirror
descent method (in which the weights follow a predetermined ? schedule given
by ak = k? ), s 2. Our adaptive averaging, in which ak is computed adaptively
following Algorithm 1, 3. The gradient restarting heuristic in [17], in which the
algorithm is restarted from the current

point whenever ?f (x(k) ), x(k+1) ? x(k) ¿ 0, 4. The speed restarting
heuristic in [20], in which the algorithm is restarted from the current point
whenever kx(k+1) ? x(k) k ? kx(k) ? x(k?1) k. The results are shown in
Figure 2. Each subﬁgure is divided into four plots: Clockwise from the top left,
we show the value of the objective function, the trajectory on the simplex, the
value of the energy function Er and the value of the Lyapunov function Lr .
2 For faster rates r(t) = tp , p ¿ 2, it is possible to discretize the ODE and
preserve the convergence rate, as proposed by Wibisono et al.
[23], however
this discretization results in a higher-order method such as Nesterov?s cubic
accelerated Newton method [16].

7
The experiments show that adaptive averaging compares favorably to the
restarting heuristics on all these examples, with a signiﬁcant improvement in
the strongly convex case. Additionally, the experiments conﬁrm that under
the adaptive averaging heuristic, the Lyapunov function is decreasing. This is
not the case for the restarting heuristics as can be seen on the weakly convex
example.
It is interesting to observe, however, that the energy function Er
is non-increasing for all the methods in our experiments. If we interpret the
energy as the sum of a potential and a kinetic term, then this could be explained
intuitively by the fact that restarting keeps the potential energy constant, and
decreases the kinetic energy (since the velocity is reset to zero).
It is also
worth observing that even though the Lyapunov function Lr is non-decreasing,
it will not necessarily converge to 0 when there is more than one minimizer (its
limit will depend on the choice of z ? in the deﬁnition of Lr ). Finally, we
observe that the methods have a diﬀerent qualitative behavior: The original
accelerated method typically exhibits oscillations around the set of minimizers.
The heuristics alleviate these oscillations in diﬀerent ways: Intuitively, adaptive
averaging acts by increasing the weights on portions of the trajectory which
make the most progress, while the restarting heuristics reset the velocity to zero
whenever the algorithm detects that the trajectory is moving in a bad direction.
The speed restarting heuristic seems to be more conservative in that it restarts
more frequently.

(a) Strongly convex quadratic.
(b) Weakly convex function.
(c) Linear function.
(d) KL divergence.
Figure 2: Examples of accelerated descent with adaptive averaging and

restarting.

6
Conclusion
Motivated by the averaging formulation of accelerated mirror descent, we

10

studied a family of ODEs with a generalized averaging scheme, and gave simple
suﬃcient conditions on the weight functions to guarantee a given convergence
rate in continuous time. We showed as an example how the replicator ODE
can be accelerated by averaging. Our adaptive averaging heuristic preserves the
convergence rate (since it preserves the Lyapunov function), and it seems to per-
form at least as well as other heuristics for ﬁrst-order accelerated methods, and
in some cases considerably better. This encourages further investigation into
the performance of this adaptive averaging, both theoretically (by attempting to
prove faster rates, e.g. for strongly convex functions), and numerically, by test-
ing it on other methods, such as the higher-order accelerated methods proposed
in [23]. 8

2 References

[1] H. Attouch and J. Peypouquet. The rate of convergence of nesterov?s accel-
erated forwardbackward method is actually faster than 1/k 2 . SIAM Journal
on Optimization, 26(3):1824?1834, 2016.
[2] H. Attouch, J. Peypouquet, and
P. Redont. Fast convergence of an inertial gradient-like system with vanish-
ing viscosity. CoRR, abs/1507.04782, 2015.
[3] H. Attouch, J. Peypouquet,
and P. Redont. Fast convex optimization via inertial dynamics with hessian
driven damping. CoRR, abs/1601.07113, 2016. [4] J.-P. Aubin. Viability The-
ory. Birkhauser Boston Inc., Cambridge, MA, USA, 1991. [5] A. Bloch, editor.
Hamiltonian and gradient ﬂows, algorithms, and control. American Mathemat-
ical Society, 1994. [6] A. A. Brown and M. C. Bartholomew-Biggs. Some eﬀec-
tive methods for unconstrained optimization based on the solution of systems
of ordinary diﬀerential equations. Journal of Optimization Theory and Appli-
cations, 62(2):211?224, 1989. [7] J. Duchi, E. Hazan, and Y. Singer. Adaptive
subgradient methods for online learning and stochastic optimization. J. Mach.
Learn. Res., 12:2121?2159, July 2011.
[8] N. Flammarion and F. R. Bach.
From averaging to acceleration, there is only a step-size. In 28th Conference
on Learning Theory, COLT, pages 658?695, 2015. [9] U. Helmke and J. Moore.
Optimization and dynamical systems. Communications and control engineering
series. Springer-Verlag, 1994. [10] D. P. Kingma and J. Ba. Adam: A method
for stochastic optimization. In Proceedings of the 3rd International Conference
[11] W. Krichene, A. Bayen, and
on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2014.
P. Bartlett. Accelerated mirror descent in continuous and discrete time.
In
[12] A. Lyapunov. General Problem of the Stability Of Motion.
NIPS, 2015.
Control Theory and Applications Series. Taylor & Francis, 1992.
[13] A. S.
Nemirovsky and D. B. Yudin. Problem Complexity and Method Eﬃciency in
Optimization. Wiley-Interscience series in discrete mathematics. Wiley, 1983.
[14] Y. Nesterov. A method of solving a convex programming problem with con-
vergence rate o(1/k2). Soviet Mathematics Doklady, 27(2):372?376, 1983. [15]
Y. Nesterov. Smooth minimization of non-smooth functions. Mathematical
Programming, 103 (1):127?152, 2005. [16] Y. Nesterov. Accelerating the cubic
regularization of newton?s method on convex problems. Mathematical Pro-

11

[17] B. O?Donoghue and E. Cand?s. Adap-
gramming, 112(1):159?181, 2008.
tive restart for accelerated gradient schemes. Foundations of Computational
Mathematics, 15(3):715?732, 2015. ISSN 1615-3375. [18] R. Rockafellar. Con-
vex Analysis. Princeton University Press, 1970. [19] K. Sigmund. Complexity,
Language, and Life: Mathematical Approaches, chapter A Survey of Replica-
tor Equations, pages 88?104. Springer Berlin Heidelberg, Berlin, Heidelberg,
1986. [20] W. Su, S. Boyd, and E. Cand?s. A diﬀerential equation for modeling
Nesterov?s accelerated gradient method: Theory and insights. In NIPS, 2014.
[21] G. Teschl. Ordinary diﬀerential equations and dynamical systems, volume
140. American Mathematical Soc., 2012.
[22] J. W. Weibull. Evolutionary
game theory. MIT press, 1997. [23] A. Wibisono, A. C. Wilson, and M. I. Jor-
dan. A variational perspective on accelerated methods in optimization. CoRR,
abs/1603.04245, 2016. 9

12

