Mean teachers are better role models:

Weight-averaged consistency targets improve

semi-supervised deep learning results

Authored by:

Harri Valpola

Antti Tarvainen

Abstract

The recently proposed Temporal Ensembling has achieved state-of-
the-art results in several semi-supervised learning benchmarks. It main-
tains an exponential moving average of label predictions on each training
example, and penalizes predictions that are inconsistent with this tar-
get. However, because the targets change only once per epoch, Tem-
poral Ensembling becomes unwieldy when learning large datasets. To
overcome this problem, we propose Mean Teacher, a method that aver-
ages model weights instead of label predictions. As an additional beneﬁt,
Mean Teacher improves test accuracy and enables training with fewer la-
bels than Temporal Ensembling. Using the same network architecture,
Mean Teacher achieves error rate 4.35% on SVHN with 250 labels, better
than Temporal Ensembling does with 1000 labels. We show that Mean
Teacher is compatible with residual networks, and improve state of the
art on CIFAR-10 with 4000 labels from 10.55% to 6.28%. Our prelimi-
nary experiments also suggest a large improvement over state of the art
on semi-supervised ImageNet 2012.

1 Paper Body

Deep learning has seen tremendous success in areas such as image and speech
recognition. In order to learn useful abstractions, deep learning models require
a large number of parameters, thus making them prone to over-ﬁtting (Figure
1a). Moreover, adding high-quality labels to training data manually is often ex-
pensive. Therefore, it is desirable to use regularization methods that exploit un-
labeled data eﬀectively to reduce over-ﬁtting in semi-supervised learning. When
a percept is changed slightly, a human typically still considers it to be the same
object. Correspondingly, a classiﬁcation model should favor functions that give
consistent output for similar data points. One approach for achieving this is
to add noise to the input of the model. To enable the model to learn more

1

abstract invariances, the noise may be added to intermediate representations,
an insight that has motivated many regularization techniques, such as Dropout
[27]. Rather than minimizing the classiﬁcation cost at the zero-dimensional
data points of the input space, the regularized model minimizes the cost on a
manifold around each data point, thus pushing decision boundaries away from
the labeled data points (Figure 1b). Since the classiﬁcation cost is undeﬁned
for unlabeled examples, the noise regularization by itself does not aid in semi-
supervised learning. To overcome this, the model [20] evaluates each data point
with and without noise, and then apply a consistency cost between the two
predictions.
In this case, the model assumes a dual role as a teacher and a
student. As a student, it learns as before; as a teacher, it generates targets,
which are then used by itself as a student for learning. Since the model itself
generates targets, they may very well be incorrect. If too much weight is given
to the generated targets, the cost of inconsistency outweighs that of misclassi-
ﬁcation, preventing the learning of new 31st Conference on Neural Information
Processing Systems (NIPS 2017), Long Beach, CA, USA.

Figure 1: A sketch of a binary classiﬁcation task with two labeled examples
(large blue dots) and one unlabeled example, demonstrating how the choice
of the unlabeled target (black circle) aﬀects the ﬁtted function (gray curve).
(a) A model with no regularization is free to ﬁt any function that predicts
the labeled training examples well. (b) A model trained with noisy labeled data
(small dots) learns to give consistent predictions around labeled data points. (c)
Consistency to noise around unlabeled examples provides additional smoothing.
For the clarity of illustration, the teacher model (gray curve) is ﬁrst ﬁtted to the
labeled examples, and then left unchanged during the training of the student
model. Also for clarity, we will omit the small dots in ﬁgures d and e.
(d)
Noise on the teacher model reduces the bias of the targets without additional
training. The expected direction of stochastic gradient descent is towards the
mean (large blue circle) of individual noisy targets (small blue circles).
(e)
An ensemble of models gives an even better expected target. Both Temporal
Ensembling and the Mean Teacher method use this approach. information. In
eﬀect, the model suﬀers from conﬁrmation bias (Figure 1c), a hazard that can
be mitigated by improving the quality of targets. There are at least two ways to
improve the target quality. One approach is to choose the perturbation of the
representations carefully instead of barely applying additive or multiplicative
noise. Another approach is to choose the teacher model carefully instead of
barely replicating the student model. Concurrently to our research, Miyato
et al.
[15] have taken the ﬁrst approach and shown that Virtual Adversarial
Training can yield impressive results. We take the second approach and will
show that it too provides signiﬁcant beneﬁts. To our understanding, these two
approaches are compatible, and their combination may produce even better
outcomes. However, the analysis of their combined eﬀects is outside the scope
of this paper. Our goal, then, is to form a better teacher model from the
student model without additional training. As the ﬁrst step, consider that the
softmax output of a model does not usually provide accurate predictions outside
training data. This can be partly alleviated by adding noise to the model at

2

inference time [4], and consequently a noisy teacher can yield more accurate
targets (Figure 1d). This approach was used in Pseudo-Ensemble Agreement [2]
and has lately been shown to work well on semi-supervised image classiﬁcation
[13, 22]. Laine & Aila [13] named the method the ? model; we will use this name
for it and their version of it as the basis of our experiments. The ? model can be
further improved by Temporal Ensembling [13], which maintains an exponential
moving average (EMA) prediction for each of the training examples. At each
training step, all the EMA predictions of the examples in that minibatch are
updated based on the new predictions. Consequently, the EMA prediction of
each example is formed by an ensemble of the model?s current version and those
earlier versions that evaluated the same example. This ensembling improves the
quality of the predictions, and using them as the teacher predictions improves
results. However, since each target is updated only once per epoch, the learned
information is incorporated into the training process at a slow pace. The larger
the dataset, the longer the span of the updates, and in the case of on-line
learning, it is unclear how Temporal Ensembling can be used at all. (One could
evaluate all the targets periodically more than once per epoch, but keeping the
evaluation span constant would require O(n2 ) evaluations per epoch where n
is the number of training examples.)

2
Mean Teacher
To overcome the limitations of Temporal Ensembling, we propose averaging
model weights instead of predictions. Since the teacher model is an average of
consecutive student models, we call this the Mean Teacher method (Figure 2).
Averaging model weights over training steps tends to produce a 2

prediction
prediction
3
3
classiﬁcation cost
consistency cost
?
??
? exponential ?? moving average
3 label
input
student model
teacher model
Figure 2: The Mean Teacher method. The ﬁgure depicts a training batch
with a single labeled example. Both the student and the teacher model evaluate
the input applying noise (?, ? 0 ) within their computation. The softmax output
of the student model is compared with the one-hot label using classiﬁcation cost
and with the teacher output using consistency cost. After the weights of the
student model have been updated with gradient descent, the teacher model
weights are updated as an exponential moving average of the student weights.
Both model outputs can be used for prediction, but at the end of the training the

3

teacher prediction is more likely to be correct. A training step with an unlabeled
example would be similar, except no classiﬁcation cost would be applied. more
accurate model than using the ﬁnal weights directly [18]. We can take advantage
of this during training to construct better targets. Instead of sharing the weights
with the student model, the teacher model uses the EMA weights of the student
model. Now it can aggregate information after every step instead of every epoch.
In addition, since the weight averages improve all layer outputs, not just the top
output, the target model has better intermediate representations. These aspects
lead to two practical advantages over Temporal Ensembling: First, the more
accurate target labels lead to a faster feedback loop between the student and the
teacher models, resulting in better test accuracy. Second, the approach scales
to large datasets and on-line learning. More formally, we deﬁne the consistency
cost J as the expected distance between the prediction of the student model
(with weights ? and noise ?) and the expected prediction of the teacher model
(with weights ?0 and noise ? 0 ). h J(?) = Ex,?0 ,? kf (x, ?0 , ? 0 )

f (x, ?, ?)k
2
i
The diﬀerence between the ? model, Temporal Ensembling, and Mean
teacher is how the teacher predictions are generated. Whereas the ? model
uses ?0 = ?, and Temporal Ensembling approximates f (x, ?0 , ? 0 ) with a
weighted average of successive predictions, we deﬁne ?t0 at training step t as
the EMA of successive ? weights: ?t0 = ??t0

1
+ (1
?)?t
where ? is a smoothing coeﬃcient hyperparameter. An additional diﬀerence
between the three algorithms is that the ? model applies training to ?0 whereas
Temporal Ensembling and Mean Teacher treat it as a constant with regards to
optimization. We can approximate the consistency cost function J by sampling
noise ?, ? 0 at each training step with stochastic gradient descent. Following
Laine & Aila [13], we use mean squared error (MSE) as our consistency cost
function. In the experiments section, we will also explore the use of other cost
functions. 3

Table 1: Error rate percentage on SVHN over 10 runs (4 runs when using all
labels). We use exponential moving average weights in the evaluation of all our
models. All the methods use a similar 13-layer CNN architecture. See Table
5 in the Appendix for results without input augmentation. 250 labels 73257
images GAN [24] ? model [13] Temporal Ensembling [13] VAT+EntMin [15]
Supervised-only 27.77 ? 3.18 ? model 9.69 ? 0.92 Mean Teacher 4.35 ? 0.50

500 labels 73257 images 18.44 ? 4.8 6.65 ? 0.53 5.12 ? 0.13 16.88 ? 1.30 6.83

? 0.66 4.18 ? 0.27

1000 labels 73257 images 8.11 ? 1.3 4.82 ? 0.17 4.42 ? 0.16 3.86 12.32 ? 0.95

4.95 ? 0.26 3.95 ? 0.19

73257 labels 73257 images 2.54 ? 0.04 2.74 ? 0.06 2.75 ? 0.10 2.50 ? 0.07

2.50 ? 0.05

4

Table 2: Error rate percentage on CIFAR-10 over 10 runs (4 runs when
using all labels). 1000 labels 50000 images GAN [24] ? model [13] Temporal
Ensembling [13] VAT+EntMin [15] Supervised-only 46.43 ? 1.21 ? model 27.36
? 1.20 Mean Teacher 21.55 ? 1.48

3
2000 labels 50000 images
33.94 ? 0.73 18.02 ? 0.60 15.73 ? 0.31
4000 labels 50000 images 18.63 ? 2.32 12.36 ? 0.31 12.16 ? 0.31 10.55 20.66

? 0.57 13.20 ? 0.27 12.31 ? 0.28

50000 labels 50000 images 5.56 ? 0.10 5.60 ? 0.10 5.82 ? 0.15 6.06 ? 0.11

5.94 ? 0.15

Experiments
To test our hypotheses, we ﬁrst replicated the ? model [13] in TensorFlow
[1] as our baseline. We then modiﬁed the baseline model to use weight-averaged
consistency targets. The model architecture is a 13-layer convolutional neural
network (CNN) with three types of noise: random translations and horizontal
ﬂips of the input images, Gaussian noise on the input layer, and dropout applied
within the network. We use mean squared error as the consistency cost and ramp
up its weight from 0 to its ﬁnal value during the ﬁrst 80 epochs. The details of
the model and the training procedure are described in Appendix B.1. 3.1

Comparison to other methods on SVHN and CIFAR-10
We ran experiments using the Street View House Numbers (SVHN) and
CIFAR-10 benchmarks [16]. Both datasets contain 32x32 pixel RGB images
belonging to ten diﬀerent classes. In SVHN, each example is a close-up of a
house number, and the class represents the identity of the digit at the center
of the image. In CIFAR-10, each example is a natural image belonging to a
class such as horses, cats, cars and airplanes. SVHN contains of 73257 training
samples and 26032 test samples. CIFAR-10 consists of 50000 training samples
and 10000 test samples. Tables 1 and 2 compare the results against recent
state-of-the-art methods. All the methods in the comparison use a similar 13-
layer CNN architecture. Mean Teacher improves test accuracy over the ? model
and Temporal Ensembling on semi-supervised SVHN tasks. Mean Teacher also
improves results on CIFAR-10 over our baseline ? model. The recently published
version of Virtual Adversarial Training by Miyato et al.
[15] performs even
better than Mean Teacher on the 1000-label SVHN and the 4000-label CIFAR-
10. As discussed in the introduction, VAT and Mean Teacher are complimentary
approaches. Their combination may yield better accuracy than either of them
alone, but that investigation is beyond the scope of this paper. 4

Table 3: Error percentage over 10 runs on SVHN with extra unlabeled train-

ing data.

? model (ours) Mean Teacher
500 labels 73257 images 6.83 ? 0.66 4.18 ? 0.27
500 labels 173257 images 4.49 ? 0.27 3.02 ? 0.16
500 labels 573257 images 3.26 ? 0.14 2.46 ? 0.06
Figure 3: Smoothened classiﬁcation cost (top) and classiﬁcation error (bot-
tom) of Mean Teacher and our baseline ? model on SVHN over the ﬁrst 100000

5

training steps. In the upper row, the training classiﬁcation costs are measured
using only labeled data. 3.2

SVHN with extra unlabeled data
Above, we suggested that Mean Teacher scales well to large datasets and on-
line learning. In addition, the SVHN and CIFAR-10 results indicate that it uses
unlabeled examples eﬃciently. Therefore, we wanted to test whether we have
reached the limits of our approach. Besides the primary training data, SVHN
includes also an extra dataset of 531131 examples. We picked 500 samples from
the primary training as our labeled training examples. We used the rest of the
primary training set together with the extra training set as unlabeled examples.
We ran experiments with Mean Teacher and our baseline ? model, and used
either 0, 100000 or 500000 extra examples. Table 3 shows the results. 3.3

Analysis of the training curves
The training curves on Figure 3 help us understand the eﬀects of using
Mean Teacher. As expected, the EMA-weighted models (blue and dark gray
curves in the bottom row) give more accurate predictions than the bare student
models (orange and light gray) after an initial period. Using the EMA-weighted
model as the teacher improves results in the semi-supervised settings. There
appears to be a virtuous feedback cycle of the teacher (blue curve) improving the
student (orange) via consistency cost, and the student improving the teacher via
exponential moving averaging. If this feedback cycle is detached, the learning
is slower, and the model starts to overﬁt earlier (dark gray and light gray).
Mean Teacher helps when labels are scarce. When using 500 labels (middle
column) Mean Teacher learns faster, and continues training after ? model stops
improving. On the other hand, in the all-labeled case (left column), Mean
Teacher and the ? model behave virtually identically. 5

Figure 4: Validation error on 250-label SVHN over four runs per hyperpa-
rameter setting and their means. In each experiment, we varied one hyperpa-
rameter, and used the evaluation run hyperparameters of Table 1 for the rest.
The hyperparameter settings used in the evaluation runs are marked with the
bolded font weight. See the text for details. Mean Teacher uses unlabeled train-
ing data more eﬃciently than the ? model, as seen in the middle column. On the
other hand, with 500k extra unlabeled examples (right column), ? model keeps
improving for longer. Mean Teacher learns faster, and eventually converges to
a better result, but the sheer amount of data appears to oﬀset ? model?s worse
predictions. 3.4

Ablation experiments
To assess the importance of various aspects of the model, we ran experiments
on SVHN with 250 labels, varying one (or a few) hyperparameters at a time
while keeping the others ﬁxed. Removal of noise (Figures 4(a) and 4(b)). In
the introduction and Figure 1, we presented the hypothesis that the ? model
produces better predictions by adding noise to the model on both sides. But
after the addition of Mean Teacher, is noise still needed? Yes. We can see that
either input augmentation or dropout is necessary for passable performance.
On the other hand, input noise does not help when augmentation is in use.
Dropout on the teacher side provides only a marginal beneﬁt over just having

6

it on the student side, at least when input augmentation is in use. Sensitivity
to EMA decay and consistency weight (Figures 4(c) and 4(d)). The essential
hyperparameters of the Mean Teacher algorithm are the consistency cost weight
and the EMA decay ?. How sensitive is the algorithm to their values? We can
see that in each case the good values span roughly an order of magnitude and
outside these ranges the performance degrades quickly. Note that EMA decay ?
= 0 makes the model a variation of the ? model, although somewhat ineﬃcient
one because the gradients are propagated through only the student path. Note
also that in the evaluation runs we used EMA decay ? = 0.99 during the
ramp-up phase, and ? = 0.999 for the rest of the training. We chose this
strategy because the student improves quickly early in the training, and thus
the teacher should forget the old, inaccurate, student weights quickly. Later
the student improvement slows, and the teacher beneﬁts from a longer memory.
Decoupling classiﬁcation and consistency (Figure 4(e)). The consistency to
teacher predictions may not necessarily be a good proxy for the classiﬁcation
task, especially early in the training. So far our model has strongly coupled
these two tasks by using the same output for both. How would decoupling the
tasks change the performance of the algorithm? To investigate, we changed the
model to have two top layers and produce two outputs. We then trained one
of the outputs for classiﬁcation and the other for consistency. We also added a
mean squared error cost between the output logits, and then varied the weight
of this cost, allowing us to control the strength of the coupling. Looking at the
results (reported using the EMA version of the classiﬁcation output), we can
see that the strongly coupled version performs well and the too loosely coupled
versions do not. On the other hand, a moderate decoupling seems to have the
beneﬁt of making the consistency ramp-up redundant. 6

Table 4: Error rate percentage of ResNet Mean Teacher. We report the
test results from 10 runs for CIFAR-10 and validation results from 2 runs for
ImageNet. CIFAR-10 1000 labels 50000 images State of the art CNN Mean
Teacher ResNet Mean Teacher

21.55 ? 1.48 10.08 ? 0.41
CIFAR-10 4000 labels 50000 images 10.55 [15] 12.31 ? 0.28 6.28 ? 0.15
ImageNet 2012 128000 labels 1280000 images 35.24 ? 0.90 [19] 19.76 ? 0.05
Changing from MSE to KL-divergence (Figure 4(f)) Following Laine & Aila
[13], we use mean squared error (MSE) as our consistency cost function, but
KL-divergence would seem a more natural choice. Which one works better?
We can see that MSE works better than KL-divergence or their intermediate
versions. See Appendix C for details of the cost function family we used for this
experiment and for our intuition about why MSE may perform so well. 3.5

Mean Teacher with residual networks on CIFAR-10 and ImageNet
In the experiments above, we used a traditional 13-layer convolutional ar-
chitecture, which has the beneﬁt of making comparisons to earlier work easy.
In order to explore the eﬀect of the model architecture, we ran experiments
using a 12-block Residual Network [8] with Shake-Shake regularization [5] on
CIFAR-10. The details of the model and the training procedure are described
in Appendix B.2. As shown in Table 4, the results improve remarkably with the

7

better network architecture. To test scaling of the method to realistic images,
we ran experiments on Imagenet 2012 dataset [21] with 10% of labels. We used
a residual network with squeeze-and-excitation blocks [10] and ShakeShake reg-
ularization, and saw a clear improvement over the state of the art. However, the
ImageNet results come with caveats: As the test set is not publicly available, we
measured the results using the validation set. We also used a very small 8-block
architecture, and probably did not use the best hyperparameters. Regardless,
the results suggest that Mean Teacher is useful also on large natural images.

4
Related work
Noise regularization of neural networks was proposed by Sietsma & Dow
[25]. More recently, several types of perturbations have been shown to reg-
ularize intermediate representations eﬀectively in deep learning. Adversarial
Training [6] changes the input slightly to give predictions that are as diﬀer-
ent as possible from the original predictions. Dropout [27] zeroes random di-
mensions of layer outputs. Dropconnect [30] generalizes Dropout by zeroing
individual weights instead of activations. Stochastic Depth [11] drops entire
layers of residual networks, and Swapout [26] generalizes Dropout and Stochas-
tic Depth. Shake-shake regularization [5] duplicates residual paths and samples
a linear combination of their outputs independently during forward and back-
ward passes. Several semi-supervised methods are based on training the model
predictions to be consistent to perturbation. The Denoising Source Separation
framework (DSS) [28] uses denoising of latent variables to learn their likelihood
estimate. The variant of Ladder Network [20] implements DSS with a deep
learning model for classiﬁcation tasks. It produces a noisy student predictions
and clean teacher predictions, and applies a denoising layer to predict teacher
predictions from the student predictions. The ? model [13] improves the model
by removing the explicit denoising layer and applying noise also to the teacher
predictions. Similar methods had been proposed already earlier for linear mod-
els [29] and deep learning [2]. Virtual Adversarial Training [15] is similar to the
? model but uses adversarial perturbation instead of independent noise. The
idea of a teacher model training a student is related to model compression [3]
and distillation [9]. The knowledge of a complicated model can be transferred
to a simpler model by training the simpler model with the softmax outputs of
the complicated model. The softmax outputs contain 7

more information about the task than the one-hot outputs, and the require-
ment of representing this knowledge regularizes the simpler model. Besides its
use in model compression, distillation can be used to harden trained models
against adversarial attacks [17]. The diﬀerence between distillation and con-
sistency regularization is that distillation is performed after training whereas
consistency regularization is performed on training time. Consistency regular-
ization can be seen as a form of label propagation [32]. Training samples that
resemble each other are more likely to belong to the same class. Label propaga-
tion takes advantage of this assumption by pushing label information from each
example to examples that are near it according to some metric. Label prop-
agation can also be applied to deep learning models [31]. However, ordinary

8

label propagation requires a predeﬁned distance metric in the input space. In
contrast, consistency targets employ a learned distance metric implied by the
abstract representations of the model. As the model learns new features, the
distance metric changes to accommodate these features. Therefore, consistency
targets guide learning in two ways. On the one hand they spread the labels
according to the current distance metric, and on the other hand, they aid the
network learn a better distance metric.

5
Conclusion
Temporal Ensembling, Virtual Adversarial Training and other forms of con-
sistency regularization have recently shown their strength in semi-supervised
learning.
In this paper, we propose Mean Teacher, a method that averages
model weights to form a target-generating teacher model. Unlike Temporal En-
sembling, Mean Teacher works with large datasets and on-line learning. Our
experiments suggest that it improves the speed of learning and the classiﬁcation
accuracy of the trained network. In addition, it scales well to state-of-the-art
architectures and large image sizes. The success of consistency regularization
depends on the quality of teacher-generated targets. If the targets can be im-
proved, they should be. Mean Teacher and Virtual Adversarial Training rep-
resent two ways of exploiting this principle. Their combination may yield even
better targets. There are probably additional methods to be uncovered that
improve targets and trained models even further.

Acknowledgements We thank Samuli Laine and Timo Aila for fruitful dis-
cussions about their work, and Phil Bachman and Colin Raﬀel for corrections
to the pre-print version of this paper. We also thank everyone at The Curious
AI Company for their help, encouragement, and ideas.

2 References

[1] Abadi, Mart?n, Agarwal, Ashish, Barham, Paul, Brevdo, Eugene, Chen,
Zhifeng, Citro, Craig, Corrado, Greg S., Davis, Andy, Dean, Jeﬀrey, Devin,
Matthieu, Ghemawat, Sanjay, Goodfellow, Ian, Harp, Andrew, Irving, Geof-
frey, Isard, Michael, Jia, Yangqing, Jozefowicz, Rafal, Kaiser, Lukasz, Kudlur,
Manjunath, Levenberg, Josh, Man?, Dan, Monga, Rajat, Moore, Sherry, Mur-
ray, Derek, Olah, Chris, Schuster, Mike, Shlens, Jonathon, Steiner, Benoit,
Sutskever, Ilya, Talwar, Kunal, Tucker, Paul, Vanhoucke, Vincent, Vasudevan,
Vijay, Vi?gas, Fernanda, Vinyals, Oriol, Warden, Pete, Wattenberg, Martin,
Wicke, Martin, Yu, Yuan, and Zheng, Xiaoqiang. TensorFlow: Large-Scale Ma-
chine Learning on Heterogeneous Systems. 2015. [2] Bachman, Philip, Alsharif,
Ouais, and Precup, Doina. Learning with Pseudo-Ensembles. arXiv:1412.4864
[cs, stat], December 2014. arXiv: 1412.4864.
[3] Bucilu?a, Cristian, Caru-
ana, Rich, and Niculescu-Mizil, Alexandru. Model compression. In Proceedings
of the 12th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery
and data mining, pp. 535?541. ACM, 2006.
[4] Gal, Yarin and Ghahramani,
Zoubin. Dropout as a Bayesian Approximation: Representing Model Uncer-

9

tainty in Deep Learning. In Proceedings of The 33rd International Conference
on Machine Learning, pp. 1050?1059, 2016. 8

[5] Gastaldi, Xavier. Shake-Shake regularization. arXiv:1705.07485 [cs],
May 2017. arXiv: 1705.07485.
[6] Goodfellow, Ian J., Shlens, Jonathon, and
Szegedy, Christian. Explaining and Harnessing Adversarial Examples. Decem-
ber 2014. arXiv: 1412.6572. [7] Guo, Chuan, Pleiss, Geoﬀ, Sun, Yu, and Wein-
berger, Kilian Q. On Calibration of Modern Neural Networks. arXiv:1706.04599
[cs], June 2017. arXiv: 1706.04599.
[8] He, Kaiming, Zhang, Xiangyu, Ren,
Shaoqing, and Sun, Jian. Deep Residual Learning for Image Recognition.
arXiv:1512.03385 [cs], December 2015. arXiv: 1512.03385.
[9] Hinton, Ge-
oﬀrey, Vinyals, Oriol, and Dean, Jeﬀ. Distilling the Knowledge in a Neu-
ral Network. arXiv:1503.02531 [cs, stat], March 2015. arXiv: 1503.02531.
[10] Hu, Jie, Shen, Li, and Sun, Gang. Squeeze-and-Excitation Networks.
arXiv:1709.01507 [cs], September 2017. arXiv: 1709.01507.
[11] Huang, Gao,
Sun, Yu, Liu, Zhuang, Sedra, Daniel, and Weinberger, Kilian. Deep Networks
with Stochastic Depth. arXiv:1603.09382 [cs], March 2016. arXiv: 1603.09382.
[12] Kingma, Diederik and Ba, Jimmy. Adam: A Method for Stochastic Opti-
mization. arXiv:1412.6980 [cs], December 2014. arXiv: 1412.6980. [13] Laine,
Samuli and Aila, Timo. Temporal Ensembling for Semi-Supervised Learning.
arXiv:1610.02242 [cs], October 2016. arXiv: 1610.02242.
[14] Maas, Andrew
L., Hannun, Awni Y., and Ng, Andrew Y. Rectiﬁer nonlinearities improve neu-
ral network acoustic models. In Proc. ICML, volume 30, 2013.
[15] Miyato,
Takeru, Maeda, Shin-ichi, Koyama, Masanori, and Ishii, Shin. Virtual Adver-
sarial Training: a Regularization Method for Supervised and Semi-supervised
Learning. arXiv:1704.03976 [cs, stat], April 2017. arXiv: 1704.03976. [16] Net-
zer, Yuval, Wang, Tao, Coates, Adam, Bissacco, Alessandro, Wu, Bo, and Ng,
Andrew Y. Reading digits in natural images with unsupervised feature learn-
ing. In NIPS Workshop on Deep Learning and Unsupervised Feature Learn-
ing, 2011.
[17] Papernot, Nicolas, McDaniel, Patrick, Wu, Xi, Jha, Somesh,
and Swami, Ananthram. Distillation as a Defense to Adversarial Perturba-
tions against Deep Neural Networks. arXiv:1511.04508 [cs, stat], November
2015. arXiv: 1511.04508.
[18] Polyak, B. T. and Juditsky, A. B. Acceler-
ation of Stochastic Approximation by Averaging. SIAM J. Control Optim.,
30(4):838?855, July 1992.
[19] Pu,
Yunchen, Gan, Zhe, Henao, Ricardo, Yuan, Xin, Li, Chunyuan, Stevens, An-
drew, and Carin, Lawrence. Variational Autoencoder for Deep Learning of Im-
ages, Labels and Captions. arXiv:1609.08976 [cs, stat], September 2016. arXiv:
1609.08976. [20] Rasmus, Antti, Berglund, Mathias, Honkala, Mikko, Valpola,
Harri, and Raiko, Tapani. Semisupervised Learning with Ladder Networks.
In Cortes, C., Lawrence, N. D., Lee, D. D., Sugiyama, M., and Garnett, R.
(eds.), Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 28, pp. 3546?3554.
Curran Associates, Inc., 2015.
[21] Russakovsky, Olga, Deng, Jia, Su, Hao,
Krause, Jonathan, Satheesh, Sanjeev, Ma, Sean, Huang, Zhiheng, Karpathy,
Andrej, Khosla, Aditya, Bernstein, Michael, Berg, Alexander C., and FeiFei,
Li. ImageNet Large Scale Visual Recognition Challenge. arXiv:1409.0575 [cs],
September 2014. arXiv: 1409.0575. [22] Sajjadi, Mehdi, Javanmardi, Mehran,

ISSN 0363-0129. doi: 10.1137/0330046.

10

and Tasdizen, Tolga. Regularization With Stochastic Transformations and Per-
turbations for Deep Semi-Supervised Learning. In Lee, D. D., Sugiyama, M.,
Luxburg, U. V., Guyon, I., and Garnett, R. (eds.), Advances in Neural Infor-
mation Processing Systems 29, pp. 1163?1171. Curran Associates, Inc., 2016.
9

[23] Salimans, Tim and Kingma, Diederik P. Weight normalization: A simple
reparameterization to accelerate training of deep neural networks. In Advances
in Neural Information Processing Systems, pp. 901?901, 2016.
[24] Salimans,
Tim, Goodfellow, Ian, Zaremba, Wojciech, Cheung, Vicki, Radford, Alec, and
Chen, Xi. Improved techniques for training gans. In Advances in Neural In-
formation Processing Systems, pp. 2226?2234, 2016. [25] Sietsma, Jocelyn and
Dow, Robert JF. Creating artiﬁcial neural networks that generalize. Neural
networks, 4(1):67?79, 1991.
[26] Singh, Saurabh, Hoiem, Derek, and Forsyth,
David. Swapout: Learning an ensemble of deep architectures. arXiv:1605.06465
[cs], May 2016. arXiv: 1605.06465.
[27] Srivastava, Nitish, Hinton, Geoﬀrey,
Krizhevsky, Alex, Sutskever, Ilya, and Salakhutdinov, Ruslan. Dropout: A
Simple Way to Prevent Neural Networks from Overﬁtting. J. Mach. Learn.
Res., 15(1):1929?1958, January 2014. ISSN 1532-4435. [28] S?rel?, Jaakko and
Valpola, Harri. Denoising Source Separation. Journal of Machine Learning
Research, 6(Mar):233?272, 2005.
[29] Wager, Stefan,
Wang, Sida, and Liang, Percy. Dropout Training as Adaptive Regularization.
arXiv:1307.1493 [cs, stat], July 2013. arXiv: 1307.1493.
[30] Wan, Li, Zeiler,
Matthew, Zhang, Sixin, Le Cun, Yann, and Fergus, Rob. Regularization of
Neural Networks using DropConnect. pp. 1058?1066, 2013.
[31] Weston, Ja-
son, Ratle, Fr?d?ric, Mobahi, Hossein, and Collobert, Ronan. Deep learning
via semi-supervised embedding. In Neural Networks: Tricks of the Trade, pp.
639?655. Springer, 2012. [32] Zhu, Xiaojin and Ghahramani, Zoubin. Learning
from labeled and unlabeled data with label propagation. 2002.

ISSN ISSN 1533-7928.

10

11

