Lookahead Bayesian Optimization with

Inequality Constraints

Authored by:

Remi Lam

Karen Willcox

Abstract

We consider the task of optimizing an objective function subject to
inequality constraints when both the objective and the constraints are
expensive to evaluate. Bayesian optimization (BO) is a popular way to
tackle optimization problems with expensive objective function evalua-
tions, but has mostly been applied to unconstrained problems. Several
BO approaches have been proposed to address expensive constraints but
are limited to greedy strategies maximizing immediate reward. To ad-
dress this limitation, we propose a lookahead approach that selects the
next evaluation in order to maximize the long-term feasible reduction of
the objective function. We present numerical experiments demonstrating
the performance improvements of such a lookahead approach compared
to several greedy BO algorithms, including constrained expected improve-
ment (EIC) and predictive entropy search with constraint (PESC).

1 Paper Body

Constrained optimization problems are often challenging to solve, due to com-
plex interactions between the goals of minimizing (or maximizing) the objective
function while satisfying the constraints. In particular, non-linear constraints
can result in complicated feasible spaces, sometimes partitioned in disconnected
regions. Such feasible spaces can be diﬃcult to explore for a local optimizer, po-
tentially preventing the algorithm from converging to a global solution. Global
optimizers, on the other hand, are designed to tackle disconnected feasible spaces
and optimization of multi-modal objective functions. Such algorithms typically
require a large number of evaluations to converge. This can be prohibitive when
the evaluation of the objective function or the constraints is expensive, or when
there is a ﬁnite budget of evaluations allocated for the optimization, as it is often
the case with expensive models. This evaluation budget typically results from
resource scarcity such as the restricted availability of a high-performance com-
puter, ﬁnite ﬁnancial resources to build prototypes, or even time when working

1

on a paper submission deadline. Bayesian optimization (BO) [19] is a global op-
timization technique designed to address problems with expensive function eval-
uations. Its constrained extension, constrained Bayesian optimization (CBO),
iteratively builds a statistical model for the objective function and the con-
straints. Based on this model that leverages all the past evaluations, a utility
function quantiﬁes the merit of evaluating any design under consideration. At
each iteration, a CBO algorithm evaluates the expensive objective function and
constraints at the design which maximizes this utility function. In most exist-
ing methods, the utility function only quantiﬁes the reward obtained over the
immediate next step, and ignores the gains that could be collected at future
steps. This results in greedy CBO algorithms. However, quantifying long-term
rewards may be beneﬁcial. For instance, in the presence of constraints, it could
be valuable to learn the boundaries of the feasible space. In order to do so, it is
likely that an infeasible design would need to be evaluated, bringing no imme-
diate improvement, 31st Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems
(NIPS 2017), Long Beach, CA, USA.

but leading to long-term beneﬁts. Such strategy requires planning over
several steps. Planning is also required to balance the so-called exploration-
exploitation trade-oﬀ. Intuitively, in order to improve the statistical model, the
beginning of the optimization should mainly be dedicated to exploring the de-
sign space, while the end of the optimization should focus on exploiting that
statistical model to ﬁnd the best design. To balance this trade-oﬀ in a prin-
cipled way, the optimizer needs to plan ahead and be aware of the remaining
evaluation budget. To address the shortcomings of greedy algorithms, we pro-
pose a new lookahead formulation for CBO with a ﬁnite budget. This approach
is aware of the remaining budget and can balance the exploration-exploitation
trade-oﬀ in a principled way. In this formulation, the best optimization pol-
icy sequentially evaluates the design yielding the maximum cumulated reward
over multiple steps. This optimal policy is the solution of an intractable dy-
namic programming (DP) problem. We circumvent this issue by employing an
approximate dynamic programming (ADP) algorithm: rollout, building on the
unconstrained BO algorithm in [17]. Numerical examples illustrate the ben-
eﬁts of the proposed lookahead algorithm over several greedy ones, especially
when the objective function is multi-modal and the feasible space has a complex
topology. The next section gives an overview of CBO and discusses some of the
related work (Sec. 2). Then, we formulate the lookahead approach to CBO as
a dynamic programming problem and demonstrate how to approximately solve
it by adapting the rollout algorithm (Sec. 3). Numerical results are provided in
Sec. 4. Finally, we present our conclusions in Sec. 5.

2
Constrained Bayesian Optimization
We consider the following optimization problem: (OPc) x? = argmin f (x)

x?X

s.t.
(1)
gi (x) ? 0, ?i ? {1, . . . , I},

2

where x is a d-dimensional vector of design variables. The design space X is
a bounded subset of Rd , f : X 7? R is an objective function, I is the number
of inequality constraints and gi : X 7? R is the ith constraint function. The
functions f and gi are considered expensive to evaluate. We are interested in
ﬁnding the minimizer x? of the objective function f subject to the non-linear
constraints gi ? 0 with a ﬁnite budget of N evaluations. We refer to this problem
as the original constrained problem (OPc). Constrained Bayesian optimization
(CBO) addresses the original constrained problem (OPc) by modeling the ob-
jective function f and the constraints gi as realizations of stochastic processes.
Typically, each expensive-to-evaluate function is modeled with an independent
Gaussian process (GP). At every iteration n, new evaluations of f and gi become
available and augment a training set Sn = {(xj , f (xj ), g1 (xj ), ? ? ? , gI (xj
))}nj=1 . Using Bayes rule, the statistical model is updated and the posterior
quantities of the GP, conditioned on Sn , reﬂect the current representation of
the unknown expensive functions. In particular, for any design x, the posterior
mean ?n (x; ?) and the posterior variance ? 2n (x; ?) of the GP associated
with the expensive function ? ? {f, g1 , ? ? ? , gI } can be computed cheaply
using a closed-form expression (see [24] for an overview of GP). CBO leverages
this statistical model to quantify, in a cheap-to-evaluate utility function Un ,
the usefulness of any design under consideration. The next design to evaluate
is then selected by solving the following auxiliary problem (AP): (AP)

xn+1 = argmax Un (x; Sn ).
(2)
x?X
The vanilla CBO algorithm is summarized in Algorithm 1. Many utility
functions have been proposed in the literature. To decide which design to eval-
uate next, [27] proposed the use of constrained expected improvement EIc ,
which, in the case of independent GPs, can be computed in closed-form as the
product of the expected improvement (obtained by considering the GP asso-
ciated with the objective function) and the probability of feasibility associated
with each constraint. This approach was later applied to machine learning appli-
cations [6] and extended to the multi-objective case [5]. Note that this method
transforms an original constrained optimization problem into an unconstrained
auxiliary problem by modifying the utility function. Other attempts to cast the
constrained problem into an unconstrained one include [3]. That work uses 2

Algorithm 1 Constrained Bayesian Optimization Input: Initial training set
S1 , budget N for n = 1 to N do Construct GPs using Sn Update hyper-
parameters Solve AP for xn+1 = argmaxx?X Un (x; Sn ) Evaluate f (xn+1
), g1 (xn+1 ), ? ? ? , gI (xn+1 ) Sn+1 = Sn ? {(xn+1 , f (xn+1 ), g1 (xn+1
), ? ? ? , gI (xn+1 ))} end for

a penalty method to transform the original constrained problem into an
unconstrained problem, to which they apply a radial basis functions (RBF)
method for global optimization (constrained RBF methods exist as well [25]).
Other techniques from local constrained optimization have been leveraged in [10]
where the utility function is constructed based on an augmented Lagrangian for-
mulation. This technique was recently extended in [22] where a slack-variables

3

formulation allows the handling of equality and mixed constraints. Another
approach is proposed by [1]: at each iteration, a ﬁnite set of candidate designs
is ﬁrst generated from a Latin hypercube, second, candidate designs with ex-
pected constraint violation higher than a user-deﬁned threshold are rejected.
Finally, among the remaining candidates, the ones achieving the best expected
improvement are evaluated (several designs can be selected simultaneously at
each iteration in this formulation). Another method [26] solves a constrained
auxiliary optimization problem: the next design is selected to maximize the ex-
pected improvement subject to approximated constraints (the posterior mean
of the GP associated with a constraint is used in lieu of the constraint itself).
Note that the two previous methods solve a constrained auxiliary problem. An-
other method to address constrained BO is proposed by [11], who develop an
integrated conditional expected improvement criterion. Given a candidate de-
sign, this criterion quantiﬁes the expected improvement point-wise (conditioned
on the fact that the candidate will be evaluated). This pointwise improvement
is then integrated over the entire design space. In the unconstrained case, in
the integration phase, equal weight is given to designs throughout the design
space. The constrained case is addressed by deﬁning a weight function that
depends on the feasible probability of a design:
improvement at designs that
are likely to be infeasible have low weight. The probability of a design being
feasible is calculated using a classiﬁcation GP. The computation of this crite-
rion is more involved as there is no closed-form formulation available for the
integration and techniques such as Monte Carlo or Markov chain Monte Carlo
must be employed. In a similar spirit, [21] introduces a utility function which
quantiﬁes the beneﬁt of evaluating a design by integrating its eﬀect over the
design space. The proposed utility function computes the expected reduction of
the feasible domain below the best feasible value evaluated so far. This results
in the expected volume of excursion criteria which also requires approximation
techniques to be computed. The former approaches revolve around comput-
ing a quantity based on improvement and require having at least one feasible
design. Other strategies use information gain as the key element to drive the
optimization strategy.
[7] proposed a two-step approach for constrained BO
when the objective and the constraints can be evaluated independently. The
ﬁrst step chooses the next location by maximizing the constrained EI [27], the
second step chooses whether to evaluate the objective or a constraint using an
information gain metric (i.e., entropy search [12]). [13, 14] developed a strategy
that simultaneously selects the design to be evaluated and the model to query
(the objective or a constraint). The criterion used, predictive entropy search
with constraints (PESC), is an extension of predictive entropy search (PES)
[15]. One of the advantages of information gain-based methods stems from the
fact that one does not need to start with a feasible design. All aforementioned
methods use myopic utilities to select the next design to evaluate, leading to
suboptimal optimization strategies. In the unconstrained BO setting, multiple-
steps lookahead algorithms have been explored [20, 8, 18, 9, 17] and were shown
to improve the performance of BO. To our knowledge, such lookahead strategies
for constrained optimization have not yet been addressed in the literature and

4

also have the potential to improve the performance of CBO algorithms. 3

3
Lookahead Formulation of CBO
In this section, we formulate CBO with a ﬁnite budget as a dynamic pro-
gramming (DP) problem (Sec. 3.1). This leads to an optimal but computation-
ally challenging optimization policy. To mitigate the cost of computing such
a policy, we employ an approximate dynamic programming algorithm, rollout,
and demonstrate how it can be adapted to CBO with a ﬁnite budget (Sec. 3.2).
3.1

Dynamic Programming Formulation
We seek an optimization policy which leads, after consumption of the eval-
uation budget, to the maximum feasible decrease of the objective function.
Because the value of the expensive objective function and constraints are not
known before their evaluations, it is impossible to quantify such long-term re-
ward within a cheap-to-evaluate utility function Un . However, CBO endows
the objective function and the constraints with a statistical model that can be
interrogated to inform the optimizer of the likely values of f and gi at a given
design. This statistical model can be leveraged to simulate optimization scenar-
ios over multiple steps and quantify their probabilities. Using this simulation
mechanism, it is possible to quantify, in an average sense, the long-term reward
achieved under a given optimization policy. The optimal policy is the solution
of the DP problem that we formalize now. Let n be the current iteration num-
ber of the CBO algorithm, and N the total budget of evaluations, or horizon.
We refer to the future iterations of the optimization generated by simulation
as stages. For any stage k ? {n, ? ? ? , N }, all the information collected
is contained in the training set Sk . The function f and the I functions gi are
modeled with independent GPs. Their posterior quantities, conditioned on Sk
, fully characterize our knowledge of f and gi . Thus, we deﬁne the state of our
knowledge at stage k to be the training set Sk ? Zk . Based on the training
set Sk , the simulation makes a decision regarding the next design xk+1 ? X to
evaluate using an optimization policy. An optimization policy ? = {?1 , ? ? ?
, ?N } is a sequence of rules, ?k : Zk 7? X for k ? {1, ? ? ? , N }, mapping a
training set Sk to a design xk+1 = ?k (Sk ).

In the simulations, the values f (xk+1 ) and gi (xk+1 ) are unknown and
are treated as uncertainties. f We model those I + 1 uncertain quantities with I
+ 1 independent Gaussian random variables Wk+1 gi and Wk+1 based on the
GPs: f Wk+1 ? N (?k (xk+1 ; f ), ? 2k (xk+1 ; f )),

gi Wk+1
? N (?k (xk+1 ; gi ), ? 2k (xk+1 ; gi )), and ? 2k (xk+1 ; ?) are the

posterior mean

(3) (4)
where we recall that ?k (xk+1 ; ?) and variance of the GP associated with
any expensive function ? ? {f, g1 , ? ? ? , gI }, conditioned on Sk , at xk+1
. Then, the 1 I simulation generates an outcome. A simulated outcome wk+1
= (fk+1 , gk+1 , ? ? ? , gk+1 )?W? f g gI 1 RI+1 is a sample of the (I +
1)-dimensional random variable Wk+1 = [Wk+1 , Wk+1 , ? ? ? , Wk+1 ].

5

Note that simulating an outcome does not require evaluating the expensive f
and gi . In particular, i fk+1 and gk+1 are not f (xk+1 ) and gi (xk+1 ). 1
I Once an outcome wk+1 = (fk+1 , gk+1 , ? ? ? , gk+1 ) is simulated, the
system transitions to a new state Sk+1 , governed by the system dynamic Fk :
Zk ? X ? W 7? Zk+1 given by:
1 I Sk+1 = Fk (Sk , xk+1 , wk+1 ) = Sk ? {(xk+1 , fk+1 , gk+1 , ? ? ? ,
gk+1 )). (5) Now that the simulation mechanism is deﬁned, one needs a metric
to assert the quality of a given optimization policy. At stage k, a stage-reward
function rk : Zk ? X ? W 7? R quantiﬁes the merit 1 I of querying a design if
the outcome wk = (fk+1 , gk+1 , ? ? ? , gk+1 ) occurs. This stage-reward is
deﬁned as the reduction of the objective function satisfying the constraints: n
o Sk rk (Sk , xk+1 , wk+1 ) = max 0, fbest ? fk+1 , (6) Sk i if gk+1 ? 0 for
all i ? {1, ? ? ? , I}, and rk (?, ?, ?) = 0 otherwise, where fbest is the best
feasible value at stage k. Thus, the expected (long-term) reward starting from
training set Sn under optimization policy ? is: ” N # X J? (Sn ) = E rk (Sk ,
?k (Sk ), wk+1 ) , (7) k=n

4
where the expectation is taken with respect to the (correlated) simulated
values (wn+1 , ? ? ? , wN +1 ), and the state evolution is governed by Eq. 5.
An optimal policy, ? ? , is a policy maximizing this long-term expected reward
in the space of admissible policies ?: J?? (Sn ) = max J? (Sn ).

(8)
???
The optimal reward J?? (Sn ) is given by Bellman?s principle of optimality
and can be computed using the DP recursive algorithm, working backward from
k = N ? 1 to k = n, JN (SN ) =

max E[rN (SN , xN +1 , wN +1 )] =
xN +1 ?X
max EIc (xN +1 ; SN )
xN +1 ?X
Jk (Sk ) = max E[rk (Sk , xk+1 , wk+1 ) + Jk+1 (Fk (Sk , xk+1 , wk+1

))],

(9)
xk+1 ?X
where each expectation is taken with respect to one simulated outcome vector
wk+1 , and we have used the fact that E[rk (Sk , xk+1 , wk+1 )] = EIc (xk+1
; Sk ) is the constrained expected improvement known in closed-form [27]. The
optimal reward is given by J?? (Sn ) = Jn (Sn ). Thus, at iteration n of the
CBO algorithm, the optimal policy select the next design xn+1 that maximizes
Jn (Sn ) given by Eqs. 9. In other words, the best decision to make at iteration n
maximizes, on average, the sum of the immediate reward rn and the future long-
term reward Jn+1 (Sn+1 ) obtained by making optimal subsequent decisions.
This is illustrated in Fig. 1, left panel.

Sk wk+1 Sk+1 xk+1
xk+2
wk+2 Sk+2

6

xk+3
Sk wk+1 Sk+1 ?k+1 (Sk+1 ) xk+1
wk+2 Sk+2 ?k+2 (Sk+2 )
???
???
???
???
???
???
???
???
Figure 1: Left: Tree illustrating the intractable DP formulation. Each black
circle represents a training set and a design, each white circle is a training
set. Dashed lines represent simulated outcomes resulting in expectations. The
double arrows represent designs selected with the (unknown) optimal policy,
leading to nested maximizations. Double arrows depict the bidirectional way
information propagates when the optimal policy is built: each optimal decision
depends on the previous steps and relies on the optimality of the future decisions.
Right: Single arrows represent designs selected using a heuristic. This illustrates
the unidirectional propagation of information when a known heuristic drives the
simulations: each decision depends on the previous steps but is independent
of the future ones. The absence of nested maximization leads to a tractable
formulation.

3.2
Rollout for Constrained Bayesian Optimization
The best optimization policy evaluates, at each iteration n of the CBO algo-
rithm, the design xn+1 maximizing the optimal reward J?? (Sn ) (Eq. 8). This
requires solving a problem with several nested maximizations and expectations
(Eqs. 9), which is computationally intractable. To mitigate the cost of solving
the DP algorithm, we employ an approximate dynamic programming (ADP)
technique: rollout (see [2, 23] for an overview). Rollout selects the next design
by maximizing a (suboptimal) long-term reward J? . The reward is computed
by simulating optimization scenarios over several future steps. However, the
simulated steps are not controlled by the optimal policy ? ? . Instead, rollout
uses a suboptimal policy ?, i.e. a heuristic, to drive the simulation. This circum-
vents the need for nested maximizations (as illustrated in Fig. 1, right panel)
and simpliﬁes the computation of J? compared to J?? . We now formalize the
rollout algorithm, propose a heuristic ? adapted to the context of CBO with a
ﬁnite budget, and detail further numerical approximations. Let us consider the
iteration n of the CBO algorithm. The long-term reward J? (Sn ) induced by a
(known) heuristic ? = {?1 , ? ? ? , ?N }, starting from state Sn , is deﬁned
by Eq. 7. This can be rewritten as J? (Sn ) = Hn , where Hn is recursively
deﬁned, from k = N back to k = n, by: HN +1 (SN +1 ) = 0 Hk (Sk ) = E[rk
(Sk , ?k (Sk ), wk+1 ) + ?Hk+1 (Fk (Sk , ?k (Sk ), wk+1 ))], 5

(10)

7

where each expectation is taken with respect to one simulated outcome vector
wk+1 , and ? ? [0, 1] is a discount factor encouraging the early collection of
reward. A discount factor ? = 0 leads to a greedy policy, focusing on immediate
reward.
In that case, the reward J? simpliﬁes to the constrained expected
improvement EIc . A discount factor ? = 1, on the other hand, is indiﬀerent to
when the reward is collected. The fundamental simpliﬁcation introduced by the
rollout algorithm lies in the absence of nested maximizations in Eqs. 10. This
is illustrated in Fig. 1, right panel. By applying a known heuristic, information
only propagates forward: every simulated step depends on the previous steps,
but is independent from the future simulated steps. This is in contrast to
the DP algorithm, illustrated in Fig. 1. Because the optimal policy is not
known, it needs to be built by solving a sequence of nested problems. Thus,
information propagates both forward and backward. While Hn is simpler to
compute than Jn , it still requires computing nested expectations for which
there is no closed-form expression. To further alleviate the cost of computing
the long-term reward, we introduce two numerical simpliﬁcations. First, we use
a rolling horizon h ? N to decrease the ? = min{N, n+h}. number of future
steps simulated. A rolling horizon h replaces the horizon N by N Second, the
expectations with respect to the (I + 1)-dimensional Gaussian random variables
are numerically approximated using Gauss-Hermite quadrature. We obtain the
following formulation: ? ? (S ? ) = 0 H N +1 N +1 ? k (Sk ) = EIc (?k (Sk );
Sk ) + ? H

Nq X
(q)
? k+1 (Fk (Sk , ?k (Sk ), w ?(q) [H k+1 ))],
(11)
q=1 (q)
where Nq is the number of quadrature weights ?(q) ? R and points wk+1 ?
RI+1 . For all iteration n ? {1, ? ? ? , N } and for all xn+1 ? X , we deﬁne
the utility function of our rollout algorithm for CBO with ﬁnite budget to be:
Un (xn+1 ; Sn ) = EIc (xn+1 ; Sn ) + ?

Nq X
(q)
? n+1 (Fn (Sn , xn+1 , w ?(q) [H n+1 ))].
(12)
q=1
The heuristic ? is problem-dependent. A desirable heuristic combines two
properties: (1) it is cheap to compute, (2) it is a good approximation of the
optimal policy ? ? . In the case of CBO with a ﬁnite budget, the heuristic
? ought to mimic the exploration-exploitation trade-oﬀ balanced by the opti-
mal policy ? ? . To do so, we propose using a combination of greedy CBO
algorithms: maximization of the constrained expected improvement (which has
an exploratory behavior) and a constrained optimization based on the posterior
means of the GPs (which has an exploitative behavior). For a given iteration n,
we deﬁne the heuristic ? = {?n+1 , ? ? ? , ?N? } such that for stages ? ? 1},

8

the policy component ?k : Zk 7? X , maps a state Sk to the design xk+1 k ?
{n + 1, ? ? ? , N satisfying: xk+1 = argmax EIc (x; Sk ).

(13)
x?X
The last policy component, ?N? : ZN? 7? X , maps a state SN? to xN? +1

such that: xN? +1 = argmin ?N? (x; f ) s.t. P F (x; SN? ) ? 0.99,

(14)
x?X
where P F is the probability of feasibility known in closed-form. Every
evaluation of the utility function Un requires O Nqh applications of a heuristic
component ?k . The heuristic that we propose

optimizes a quantity that requires O —Sk —2 of work. To summarize, the
proposed approach sequentially selects the next design to evaluate by maximiz-
ing the long-term reward induced by a heuristic. This rollout algorithm is a
one-step lookahead formulation (one maximization) and is easier to solve than
the N -steps lookahead approach (N nested maximizations) presented in Sec.
3.1. Rollout is a closed-loop approach where the information collected at a
given stage of the simulation is used to simulate the next stages. The heuristic
used in the rollout is problem-dependent, and we proposed using a combination
of greedy CBO algorithms to construct such a heuristic. The computation of
the utility function is detailed in Algorithm 2. 6

Algorithm 2 Rollout Utility Function Function: utility(x, h, S) Construct
GPs using S if h = 0 then U ? EIc (x; S) else U ? EIc (x; S) Generate Nq
Gauss-Hermite quadrature weights ?(q) and points w(q) associated with x for
q = 1 to Nq do S 0 ? S ? {(x, w(q) )} if h ¿ 1 then x0 ? ?(S 0 ) using Eq. 13
else x0 ? ?(S 0 ) using Eq. 14 end if U ? U + ??(q) utility(x0 , h ? 1, S 0 ) end
for end if Output: U

4
Results
In this section, we numerically investigate the proposed algorithm and demon-
strate its performance on classic test functions and a reacting ﬂow problem. To
compare the performance of the diﬀerent CBO algorithms tested, we use the
utility gap metric [14]. At iteration n, the utility gap en measures the error
between the optimum feasible value f ? and the value of the objective function
at a recommended design x?n :

—f (x?n ) ? f ? — if x?n is feasible, en = (15) —? ? f ? — else, where ? is a
user-deﬁned penalty punishing infeasible recommendations. The recommended
design, x?n , diﬀers from the design selected for evaluation xn . It is the design
that the algorithm would recommend to evaluate if the optimization were to
be stopped at iteration n, without early notice. We use the same system of
recommendation as [14]: x?n = argmin ?n (x; f ) s.t. P F (x; Sn ) ? 0.975. (16)
x?X

Note that the utility gap en is not guaranteed to decrease because recom-
mendations x?n are not necessarily better with iterations. In particular, en is
not the best error achieved in the training set Sn . In the following numerical
experiments, for the rollout algorithm, we use independent zero-mean GPs with

9

automatic relevance determination (ARD) square-exponential kernel to model
each expensive-toevaluate function. In Algorithm. 1, when the GPs are con-
structed, the vector of hyper-parameters ? i associated with the ith GP kernel
is estimated by maximization of the marginal likelihood. However, to reduce
the cost of computing Un , the hyper-parameters are kept constant in the simu-
lated steps (i.e., in Algorithm. 2). To compute the expectations of Eqs. 11-12,
we employ Nq = 3I+1 Gauss-Hermite quadrature weights and points and we
set the discount factor to ? = 0.9. Finally, at iteration n, the Sn best value
fbest is set to the minimum posterior mean ?n (x; f ) over the designs x in the
training set Sn , such that the posterior mean of each constraint is feasible. If
no such point can be found, Sn 2 then fbest is set to the maximum of {?n (x;
f ) + 3?m } over the designs x in Sn , where ?m is the maximum variance of
the GP associated with f . The EIC algorithm is computed as a special case
of the rollout with rolling horizon h = 0, and we use the Spearmint package1
to run the PESC algorithm. We additionally run a CBO algorithm that selects
the next design to evaluate based on the posterior means of the GPs2 : xn+1
= argmin ?n (x; f ) s.t. ?n (x; gi ) ? 0, ?i ? {1, . . . , I}. (17) x?X

1 2
https://github.com/HIPS/Spearmint/tree/PESC As suggested by a reviewer.
7
0.0 log10 Median Utility Gap en
log10 Median Utility Gap en
1 0 ?1 ?2 ?3
P ESC PM EIc
?4
Rollout, h = 1 Rollout, h = 2 Rollout, h = 3
?5 0
5
10
15
20 25 Iteration n
30
35
40
P ESC PM EIc
?0.5
Rollout, h = 1 Rollout, h = 2 Rollout, h = 3
?1.0 ?1.5 ?2.0 ?2.5 ?3.0 0
5
10
15
20 25 Iteration n
30
35
40

10

Figure 2: Left: Multi-modal objective and single constraint (P1). Right:
Linear objective and multiple non-linear constraints (P2). Shaded region indi-
cates 95% conﬁdence interval of the median statistic. We refer to this algorithm
as PM. We also compare the CBO algorithms to three local algorithms (SLSQP,
MMA and COBYLA) and to one global evolutionary algorithm (ISRES). We
now consider four problems with diﬀerent design space dimensions d, several
numbers of constraints I, and various topologies of the feasible space. The three
ﬁrst problems, P1-3, are analytic functions while the last one, P4, uses a reacting
ﬂow model that requires solving a set of partial diﬀerential equations (PDEs)
[4]. For P1 and P2, we use N = 40 evaluations (as in [6, 10]). For P3 and P4, we
use a small number of iterations N = 60, which corresponds to situations where
the functions are very expensive to evaluate (e.g. solving large systems of PDEs
can take over a day on a supercomputer). The full description of the problems
is available in the appendix. In Figs. 2-3, we show the median of the utility gap,
the shadings represent the 95% conﬁdence interval of the median computed by
bootstrap. Other statistics of the utility gap are shown in the appendix. For
P1, the median utility gap for EIC, PESC, PM and the rollout algorithm with h
? {1, 2, 3} is shown in Fig. 2 (left panel). The PM algorithm does not improve
its recommendations. This is not surprising because PM focuses on exploitation
(PM does not depends on posterior variance) which can result in the algorithm
failing to make further progress. Such behavior has already been reported in
[16] (Sec. 3). The three other CBO algorithms perform similarly in the ﬁrst 10
iterations. PESC is the ﬁrst to converge to a utility gap ? 10?2.7 . The rollout
performs better or similarly than EIC. In the 15 ﬁrst iterations, longer rolling
horizons lead to slightly lower utility gaps. This is likely to be due to the more
exploratory behavior associated with lookahead, which helps diﬀerentiating the
global solution from the local ones. For the remaining iterations, the shorter
rolling horizons reduce the utility gap faster than longer rolling horizons before
reaching a plateau. EIC and rollout outperform PESC after 25 iterations. We
note that EIC and rollout have essentially converged. For P2, the median perfor-
mance of EIC, PESC, PM and rollout with rolling horizon h ? {1, 2, 3} is shown
in Fig. 2 (right panel). The PM algorithm reduces the utility gap in the ﬁrst 10
iterations, but reaches a plateau at 10?1.7 . The three other CBO algorithms
perform similarly up to iteration 15, where PESC reaches a plateau 3 . This
similarity may be explained by the fact that the local solutions are easily diﬀer-
entiable from the global one, leading to no advantage for exploratory behavior.
In this example, the rollout algorithms reached the same plateau at 10?3 , with
longer horizons h taking more iterations to converge. EIC performs better than
rollout h = 2 before its performance slightly decreases, reaching a plateau at
a larger utility gap 10?2.6 (note that the utility gap is not computed with the
best value observed so far and thus is not guaranteed to decrease). This increase
of the median utility gap can be explained by the fact that a few runs change
their recommendation from one local minimum to another one, resulting in the
change in median utility function. This is also reﬂected in the 95% conﬁdence
interval of the median, which further indicates that the statistic is sensitive to a
few runs. For P3, the median utility gap for the four CBO algorithms is shown

11

in Fig. 3 (left panel). PM is rapidly outperformed by the other algorithms.
The PESC algorithm is outperformed by EIC and rollout after 25 iterations.
Again, we note that rollout with h = 1 obtains a lower utility gap that EIC at
every iteration. The rollout with h ? {2, 3} exhibits a diﬀerent behavior:
it
starts decreasing the utility gap later in the optimization but achieves a better
performance when the evaluation budget 3

Results obtained for PESC mean utility gap are consistent with [13].
8
3.5 log10 Median Utility Gap en
log10 Median Utility Gap en
2.2 2.0 1.8 1.6
P ESC PM EIc
1.4
Rollout, h = 1 Rollout, h = 2 Rollout, h = 3
1.2 0
10
20
30 Iteration n
40
50
2.5
Rollout, h = 1 Rollout, h = 2 Rollout, h = 3
2.0 1.5 1.0 0.5 0.0 ?0.5 0
60
P ESC PM EIc
3.0
10
20
30 Iteration n
40
50
60
Figure 3: Left: Multi-modal 4-d objective and constraint (P3). Right: Re-
acting ﬂow problem (P4). The awareness of the remaining budget explains the
sharp decrease in the last iterations for the rollout. is consumed. Note that none
of the algorithms has converged to the global solution, and the strong multi-
modality of the objective and constraint function seems to favor exploratory
behaviors. For the reacting ﬂow problem P4, the median performances are
shown in Fig. 3 (right panel). PM rapidly reaches a plateau at en ? 101.3 .
PESC reduces rapidly the utility gap, outperforming the other algorithms after
15 iterations. EIC and rollout perform similarly and slowly decrease the utility
gap up to iteration 40, where EIC reaches a plateau and rollout continues to im-
prove performance, slightly outperforming PESC at the end of the optimization.
The results are summarized in Table. 1, and show that the rollout algorithm
with diﬀerent rolling horizons h (R-h) performs similarly or favorably compared

12

to the other algorithms. Table 1: Log median utility gap log10 (eN ). Statistics
computed over m independent runs. Prob

d
N
I
m
SLSQP
MMA
COBYLA
ISRES
PESC
PM
EIC
R-1
R-2
R-3
P1 P2 P3 P4
2 2 4 4
40 40 60 60
1 2 1 1
500 500 500 50
0.59 -0.40 2.15 0.80
0.59 -0.40 3.06 0.80
-0.05 -0.82 3.06 0.80
-0.19 -0.70 1.68 0.13
-2.68 -2.43 1.66 0.09
0.30 -1.76 1.79 1.26
-4.45 -2.62 1.60 0.57
-4.59 -2.99 1.48 -0.10
-4.52 -2.99 1.31 -0.10
-4.42 -2.994 1.35 0.19
Based on the four previous examples, we notice that increasing the rolling
horizon h does not necessarily improve the performance of the rollout algorithm.
One possible reason stems from the fact that lookahead algorithms rely more
on the statistical model that greedy algorithms. Because this model is learned
as the optimization unfolds, it is an imperfect model (in particular the hyperpa-
rameters of the GPs are updated after each iteration, but not after each stage of
a simulated scenario). By simulating too many steps with the GPs, one may be
over-conﬁdently using the model. In some sense, the rolling horizon h, as well as
the discount factor ?, can be interpreted as a form of regularization. The eﬀect
of a larger rolling horizon is problem-dependent, and experiment P3 suggests
that multimodal problems in higher dimension may beneﬁts from longer rolling
horizons.

5
Conclusions

13

We proposed a new formulation for constrained Bayesian optimization with
a ﬁnite budget of evaluations. The best optimization policy is deﬁned as the
one maximizing, in average, the cumulative feasible decrease of the objective
function over multiple steps. This optimal policy is the solution of a dynamic
programming problem that is intractable due to the presence of nested max-
imizations. To circumvent this diﬃculty, we employed the rollout algorithm.
Rollout uses a heuristic to simulate optimization scenarios over several step,
thereby computing an approximation of the long-term reward. This heuristic
is problem-dependent and, in this paper, we proposed to use a combination
of cheap-to-evaluate greedy CBO algorithms to construct such heuristic. The
proposed algorithm was numerically investigated and performed similarly or fa-
vorably compared to constrained expected improvement (EIC) and predictive
entropy search with constraint (PESC). This work was supported in part by
the AFOSR MURI on multi-information sources of multi-physics systems under
Award Number FA9550-15-1-0038, program manager Dr. Jean-Luc Cambier. 4
For cost reasons, the median for h = 3 was computed with m = 100 inde-

pendent runs instead of 500.

9

2 References

[1] C. Audet, A. J. Booker, J. E. Dennis Jr, P. D. Frank, and D. W. Moore.
A surrogate-model-based method for constrained optimization. AIAA paper,
4891, 2000.
[2] D. P. Bertsekas. Dynamic programming and optimal control,
volume 1. Athena Scientiﬁc, 1995. [3] M. Bj?rkman and K. Holmstr?m. Global
optimization of costly nonconvex functions using radial basis functions. Opti-
mization and Engineering, 4(1):373?397, 2000. [4] M. Buﬀoni and K. E. Willcox.
Projection-based model reduction for reacting ﬂows. In 40th Fluid Dynamics
Conference and Exhibit, page 5008, 2010. [5] P. Feliot, J. Bect, and E. Vazquez.
A Bayesian approach to constrained single-and multi-objective optimization.
Journal of Global Optimization, 67(1-2):97?133, 2017. [6] J. Gardner, M. Kus-
ner, K. Q. Weinberger, J. Cunningham, and Z. Xu. Bayesian optimization with
inequality constraints. In T. Jebara and E. P. Xing, editors, Proceedings of the
31st International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML-14), pages 937?945.
JMLR Workshop and Conference Proceedings, 2014.
[7] M. A. Gelbart, J.
Snoek, and R. P. Adams. Bayesian optimization with unknown constraints.
arXiv preprint arXiv:1403.5607, 2014. [8] D. Ginsbourger and R. Le Riche. To-
wards Gaussian process-based optimization with ﬁnite time horizon. In mODa
9?Advances in Model-Oriented Design and Analysis, pages 89?96. Springer,
2010.
[9] J. Gonz?lez, M. Osborne, and N. D. Lawrence. GLASSES: Reliev-
ing the myopia of Bayesian optimisation. In Proceedings of the 19th Interna-
tional Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence and Statistics, pages 790?799, 2016.
[10] R. B. Gramacy, G. A. Gray, S. Le Digabel, H. K. H. Lee, P. Ranjan, G.
Wells, and S. M. Wild. Modeling an augmented Lagrangian for blackbox con-
strained optimization. Technometrics, 58(1):1?11, 2016.
[11] R. B. Gramacy

14

and H. K. H. Lee. Optimization under unknown constraints. arXiv preprint
arXiv:1004.4027, 2010.
[12] P. Hennig and C. J. Schuler. Entropy search for
information-eﬃcient global optimization. The Journal of Machine Learning Re-
search, 13(1):1809?1837, 2012. [13] J. M. Hern?ndez-Lobato, M. A. Gelbart, R.
P. Adams, M. W. Hoﬀman, and Z. Ghahramani. A general framework for con-
strained bayesian optimization using information-based search. arXiv preprint
arXiv:1511.09422, 2015.
[14] J. M. Hern?ndez-Lobato, M. A. Gelbart, M. W.
Hoﬀman, R. P. Adams, and Z. Ghahramani. Predictive entropy search for
bayesian optimization with unknown constraints. In Proceedings of the 32nd
International Conference on Machine Learning, Lille, France, 2015.
[15] J. M.
Hern?ndez-Lobato, M. W. Hoﬀman, and Z. Ghahramani. Predictive entropy
In Advances
search for eﬃcient global optimization of black-box functions.
in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 918?926, 2014.
[16] D. R.
Jones. A taxonomy of global optimization methods based on response sur-
faces. Journal of Global Optimization, 21(4):345?383, 2001.
[17] R. R. Lam,
K. E. Willcox, and D. H. Wolpert. Bayesian optimization with a ﬁnite bud-
get: An approximate dynamic programming approach. In Advances in Neural
Information Processing Systems, pages 883?891, 2016.
[18] C. K. Ling, K. H.
Low, and P. Jaillet. Gaussian process planning with lipschitz continuous re-
ward functions: Towards unifying Bayesian optimization, active learning, and
beyond. arXiv preprint arXiv:1511.06890, 2015. [19] J. Mockus, V. Tiesis, and
A. Zilinskas. The application of bayesian methods for seeking the extremum.
Towards Global Optimization, 2(117-129):2, 1978. [20] M. A. Osborne, R. Gar-
nett, and S. J. Roberts. Gaussian processes for global optimization.
In 3rd
International Conference on Learning and Intelligent Optimization (LION3),
pages 1?15, 2009. [21] V. Picheny. A stepwise uncertainty reduction approach
to constrained global optimization. In AISTATS, pages 787?795, 2014.

10
[22] V. Picheny, R. B. Gramacy, S. Wild, and S. Le Digabel. Bayesian opti-
mization under mixed constraints with a slack-variable augmented Lagrangian.
In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 1435?1443, 2016.
[23] W. B. Powell. Approximate Dynamic Programming: Solving the Curses of
Dimensionality, volume 842. John Wiley & Sons, 2011.
[24] C. E. Rasmussen
and C. K. I. Williams. Gaussian Processes for Machine Learning. MIT Press,
Cambridge, MA, 2006.
[25] R. G. Regis. Constrained optimization by radial
basis function interpolation for high-dimensional expensive black-box problems
with infeasible initial points. Engineering Optimization, 46(2):218?243, 2014.
[26] M. J. Sasena, P. Y. Papalambros, and P. Goovaerts. The use of surrogate
modeling algorithms to exploit disparities in function computation time within
simulation-based optimization. Constraints, 2:5, 2001. [27] M. Schonlau, W. J.
Welch, and D. R. Jones. Global versus local search in constrained optimization
of computer models. Lecture Notes-Monograph Series, pages 11?25, 1998.

11

15

