Deep Recurrent Neural Network-Based
Identiﬁcation of Precursor microRNAs

Authored by:

Seonwoo Min
Sungroh Yoon
Seunghyun Park
Hyun-Soo Choi

Abstract

MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are small non-coding ribonucleic acids (RNAs)
which play key roles in post-transcriptional gene regulation. Direct iden-
tiﬁcation of mature miRNAs is infeasible due to their short lengths, and
researchers instead aim at identifying precursor miRNAs (pre-miRNAs).
Many of the known pre-miRNAs have distinctive stem-loop secondary
structure, and structure-based ﬁltering is usually the ﬁrst step to predict
the possibility of a given sequence being a pre-miRNA. To identify new
pre-miRNAs that often have non-canonical structure, however, we need
to consider additional features other than structure. To obtain such ad-
ditional characteristics, existing computational methods rely on manual
feature extraction, which inevitably limits the eﬃciency, robustness, and
generalization of computational identiﬁcation. To address the limitations
of existing approaches, we propose a pre-miRNA identiﬁcation method
that incorporates (1) a deep recurrent neural network (RNN) for auto-
mated feature learning and classiﬁcation, (2) multimodal architecture for
seamless integration of prior knowledge (secondary structure), (3) an at-
tention mechanism for improving long-term dependence modeling, and
(4) an RNN-based class activation mapping for highlighting the learned
representations that can contrast pre-miRNAs and non-pre-miRNAs. In
our experiments with recent benchmarks, the proposed approach outper-
formed the compared state-of-the-art alternatives in terms of various per-
formance metrics.

1 Paper Body

MicroRNAs (miRNAs) play crucial roles in post-transcriptional gene regulation
by binding to the 30 untranslated region of target messenger RNAs [16]. Among
the research problems related to miRNA, computational identiﬁcation of miR-
NAs has been one of the most signiﬁcant. The biogenesis of a miRNA consists of

1

the primary miRNA stage, the precursor miRNA (pre-miRNA) stage, and the
mature miRNA stage [17]. Mature miRNAs are usually short, having only 20?23
base pairs (bp), and it is diﬃcult to identify them directly. Most computational
approaches focus on detecting ? To

whom correspondence should be addressed.
31st Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017),

Long Beach, CA, USA.

pre-miRNAs since they are usually more identiﬁable because they are longer
(approximately 80bp) and have a distinctive stem-loop secondary structure. In
terms of the machine learning (ML), pre-miRNA identiﬁcation can be viewed as
a binary classiﬁcation problem in which a given sequence must be classiﬁed as ei-
ther a pre-miRNA or a non-pre-miRNA. A variety of computational approaches
for miRNA identiﬁcation have been proposed, and we can broadly classify them
[18] into rule-based such as MIReNA [1], and ML-based approaches, which can
be categorized into three groups in terms of the classiﬁcation algorithm used:
(1) MiPred [12], microPred [2], triplet-SVM [3], iMiRNA-SSF [38], miRNApre
[39], and miRBoost [4] use support vector machines; (2) MiRANN [1] and DP-
miRNA [37] use neural networks; and (3) (CSHMM) [5], which use a context-
sensitive hidden Markov model. Known pre-miRNAs have distinctive structural
characteristics, and therefore most computational methods make ﬁrst-order de-
cisions based on the secondary structure of the input RNA sequence. However,
the identiﬁcation of new pre-miRNAs with non-canonical structure and subtle
properties, and maybe both, it requires the consideration of features other than
secondary structure. Some authors [19] have even argued that the performance
of ML-based tools are more dependent on the set of input features than the
ML algorithms that are used. The discovery of new features which are eﬀective
in pre-miRNA identiﬁcation currently involves either searching for hand-crafted
features (such as the frequency of nucleotide triplets in the loop, global and
intrinsic folding attributes, stem length, and minimum free energy) or combin-
ing existing features. One recent study utilized 187 such features [4], another
48 features [2], most of which were manually prepared. Manual feature ex-
traction requires ingenuity and inevitably limits the eﬃciency, robustness, and
generalization of the resulting identiﬁcation scheme developed. Furthermore,
neural network-based methods above only use neural networks for classiﬁcation
of hand-designed features, and not for feature learning. Similar challenges exist
in other disciplines. Recently, end-to-end deep learning approaches have been
successfully applied to tasks such as speech and image recognition, largely elim-
inating the manual construction of feature engineerings. Motivated by these
successes, we propose a deep neural network-based pre-miRNA identiﬁcation
method which we call deepMiRGene to address the limitations of existing ap-
proaches. It incorporates the following key components: 1. A deep recurrent
neural network (RNN) with long short-term memory (LSTM) units for RNA se-
quence modeling, automated feature learning, and robust classiﬁcation based on
the learned representations. 2. A multimodal architecture for seamless integra-
tion of prior knowledge (such as the importance of RNA secondary structure in
pre-miRNA identiﬁcation) with automatically learned features. 3. An attention

2

mechanism for eﬀective modeling of the long-term dependence of the primary
structure (i.e., sequence) and the secondary structure of RNA molecules. 4.
An RNN-based class activation mapping (CAM) to highlight the learned rep-
resentations in the way that contrasts pre-miRNAs and non-pre-miRNAs to
obtain biological insight. We found that simply combining existing deep learn-
ing modules did not deliver satisfactory performance in our task. Thus our
contribution can be seen as inventing a novel pipeline and with components op-
timized for handling RNA sequences and structures to predict (possibly subtle)
premiRNA signals, rather than just assembling pre-packaged components. Our
research for an optimal set of RNN architectures and hyperparameters for pre-
miRNA identiﬁcation involved an exploration of the design space spanned by
the components of our methodology. The result of this research is a technique
with demonstrable advantages over other state-of-the-art alternatives in terms
of both cross-validation results but also the generalization ability (i.e., perfor-
mance on test data). The source code for the proposed method is available at
https://github.com/eleventh83/deepMiRGene.

2 2.1
Related Work The Secondary Structure of a Pre-miRNA
The secondary structure of an RNA transcript represents the base-pairing
interactions within that transcript. The usual secondary structure of a pre-
miRNA is shown in Fig. 1, which shows that a pre-miRNA is a base-paired
double helix rather than a single strand, and this pairing is one 2

..((((((((......))))))))..
3?
folding
3?
A
. .
C ( ( ( ( ( ( ( ( A U G U G C C A C G U
.
5?
5?
C G A C A C G G U G C A A ) ) ) ) ) ) ) ) . .
. .
secondary structure
ACGUGCCACGAUUCAACGUGGCACAG
.
sequence
3?
.
B 5?
.
A
Figure 1: (A) sequence of a pre-miRNA, and (B) the secondary structure of
the given sequence. The dot-bracket notation in (A) describes RNA secondary

3

structures. Unpaired nucleotides are represented as ?.?s and base-paired nu-
cleotides are represented as ?(?s and ?)?s. (#sample, lseq)

(#sample, lseq, 16)
A?en?on (So?max)
Input Sequences Folding
States Merging
Onehot Encoding
Secondary Structures
Dropout (0.1)
LSTM Layer
LSTM Layer
LLSTM 1
LLSTM 2
Dropout (0.1)
Dropout (0.1)
(#sample, lseq,20)
Preprocessing
(#sample, 2) Fully Connected Layer
Fully Connected Layer
Fully Connected Layer
LFC 1
LFC 2
LFC 3
(lseqx10)x400
400x100
100x2
Dropout (0.1)
Dropout (0.1)
Dropout (0.1)
So?max
Output True/False
(#sample, lseqx10)
Neural Network Layers
Figure 2: Overview of our method: #sample is the number of input se-
quences and lseq is the maximum length of the input sequence. The dimension
of intermediate data is labeled (#sample, lseq , 16). of the most prominent fea-
tures for pre-miRNA identiﬁcation [12, 2]. The secondary structure of a given
sequence can be predicted by tools such as RNAfold [5], which is widely used. It
constructs a thermodynamically stable secondary structure from a given RNA
sequence by calculating the minimum free energy and the probable base-pairings
[20]. However, reliable pre-miRNA identiﬁcation requires features other than
the secondary structure to be considered, since false positives may be gener-
ated due to the limitations of structure prediction algorithms and the inherent
unpredictability of these structures [21]. 2.2

Deep Recurrent Neural Networks

4

RNNs are frequently used for sequential modeling and learning. RNNs pro-
cess one element of input data at a time and implicitly store past information
using cyclic connections of hidden units [8]. However, early RNNs often had dif-
ﬁculty in learning long-term dependencies because of the vanishing or exploding
gradient problem [9]. Recent deep RNNs incorporate mechanisms to address this
problem. Explicit memory units, such as LSTM units [10] or GRUs [3], are one
such mechanism. An LSTM unit, for works as a sophisticated hidden unit that
uses multiplicative gates to learn when to input, output, and forget in addition
to cyclic connections to store the state vector. A more recent innovation [2] is
the attention mechanism. This can take various forms, but in our system, a
weighted combination of the output vectors at each point in time replaces the
single ﬁnal output vector of a standard RNN. An attention mechanism of this
sort helps learn long-term dependencies and also facilitates the interpretation
of results, e.g., by showing how closely the output at a speciﬁc time point is
related to the ﬁnal output [30, 29, 2].

3
Methodology
Fig. 2 shows the proposed methodology of our system. The input con-
sists of either a set of premiRNA sequences (in the training phase) or a test
sequence (in the testing phase). The output for each input sequence is a two-
dimensional (softmax) vector which indicates whether the input sequence en-
codes pre-miRNA or not. In a preprocessing phase, we derive the secondary
structure of the input sequence and then encode the sequence and its structure
together into a 16-dimensional binary vector. Encoded vectors are then pro-
cessed by the RNN architecture, consisting of LSTM layers and fully connected
(FC) layers, and the attention mechanism. The pseudocode of our approach is
available as Appendix A, in the supplementary material. 3

3.1
Preprocessing
Preprocessing a set of input pre-miRNA sequences involves two tasks. First,
RNAfold is used to obtain the secondary structure of each sequence; we already
noted the importance of this data. We clarify that each position in an RNA
sequence as one of {A, C, G, U}, and the corresponding location in the secondary
structure as one of {(, ), ., :}. This dot-bracket notation is shown in Fig. 1. The
symbol ?:? represents a position inside a loop (unpaired nucleotides surrounded
by a stem). Let xs and xt denote an input sequence and its secondary structure,
respectively. Then, xs ? {A, C, G, U}—xs — and xt ? {(, ), ., :}—xt — .
Note that —xs — = —xt —. Next, each input sequence xs is combined with its
secondary structure xt into a numerical representation. This is a simple one-hot
encoding [4], which gave better results in our experiments than a soft encoding
(see Section 4). Our encoding scheme uses a 16-dimensional one-hot vector, in
which position i (i = 0, 1, .
, 15) is interpreted as follows: ? ? 0 then
A 0 then ( ? ? ? ? ? ? 1 then G 1 then ) if bi/4c = and if i%4 = ? ? 2
then C 2 then . ? ? ? ? 3 then U 3 then : The ?%? symbol denotes the
modulus operator. After preprocessing, the sequence xs and the structure xt
are together represented by the matrix Xs ? {0, 1}—xs —?16 , each row of

.

.

5

which is the 16-dimensional one-hot vector described above. For instance, xs =
AUG and xt = (:) are represented by the following 3 ? 16 binary matrix: ? ?
A C G U z }— { z }— { z }— { z }— { ?1 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0? ? ? Xs
= ?0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1? . ?0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 0 0 0? — {z } ().:

3.2
Neural Network Architecture
The main features of our neural network is the attention mechanism provided
by the LTSM and FC layers. 1) LSTM layers: The purpose of these layers is
sequential modeling of the primary and secondary structure of the input pre-
miRNA transcripts. We use two stacked LSTM layers denoted by LLSTM 1 and
LLSTM respectively. LLSTM takes the matrix Xs produced in the preprocessing
stage and returns a 2 1 weight matrix H1 , as follows: H1 = LLSTM (Xs ) ?
R—xs —?d1 , 1

(1)
where d1 is the number of LSTM units in the ﬁrst layer. Similarly, the
second layer ﬁrst returns a second weight matrix H2 : H2 = LLSTM (H1 ) ?
R—xs —?d2 , 2

(2)
where d2 is the number of LSTM units in the second layer. We apply
an attention mechanism to the output of LLSTM with the aim of learning the
importance 2 of each position of xs . The neural networks ﬁrst learn an attention
weight for each output of the second LSTM layer for each sequence position in
a training process. These weights are collectively represented by a matrix ? ?
Rd2 ?—xs — . An attention weight matrix ?att ? R—xs —?—xs — is then
constructed as follows: ?att = H2 ?.

(3)
?att = softmax(diag(?att )) ? R—xs — ,
(4)
This yields the attention weight vector ?att
4
where the ith element of ?att corresponds to the attention weight for the ith
position of xs . Then, Hatt ? R—xs —?d2 , the attention-weighted representa-
tion of H2 , can be expressed as follows: Hatt = H2 (?att ? ud2 ),

(5)
where ud2 is the d2 -dimensional unit vector, and and ? respectively denote
the element-wise multiplication and outer product operators. ? att for the
Finally, we reshape the matrix Hatt by ﬂattening it into a (d2 ? —xs —)-
dimensional vector h sake of compatibility with third-party software. We use
the standard nonlinearities (i.e., hyperbolic tangent and logistic sigmoid) inside
each LSTM cell. 2) Fully connected layers: The neural network collects the
outputs from the last LSTM layer and makes a ﬁnal decision using three FC
layers. We denote the operations performed by these three FC FC layers by
LFC 1 ,L2 , and L3 , which allows us to represent the outputs of the three FC
layers as ? att , f2 = LFC (f1 ), and y? = LFC (f2 ), where f1 ? Rd3 and f2
? Rd4 are intermediate f1 = LFC h 1 2 3 vectors, and y? ? R2 denotes the
ﬁnal softmax output; d3 and d4 are the numbers of hidden nodes in the last

6

two FC layers. The ﬁrst two FC layers use logistic sigmoids as theirs activation
functions, while the last FC layer uses the softmax function. 3.3

Training
We based our training objective on binary cross-entropy (also known as
logloss). As will be explained in Section 4 (see Table 1), we encountered a
class-imbalance problem in this study, since there exist signiﬁcantly more nega-
tive training examples (non-pre-miRNA sequences) than positives (known pre-
miRNA sequences). We addressed this issue by augmenting the logloss training
objective with balanced class weights [31], so that the training error E is ex-
pressed as follows:
1 X ? E=? c yi log(? yi ) + c+ (1 ? yi ) log(1 ? y?i ) b i where b is the
mini-batch size (we used b = 128), and yi ? {0, 1} is the class label provided in
training data (yi = 0 for pre-miRNA; yi = 1 for non-pre-miRNA); c? and c+
represent the balanced class weights given by ck =

N , 2 ? nk
k ? {?, +}
(6)
where N is the total number of training examples and nk is the number of
examples in either the positive or the negative class. We minimized E using the
Adam [6] gradient descent method, which uses learning rates which adapt to the
ﬁrst and second moments of the gradients of each parameter. We tried other
optimization methods (e.g., the stochastic gradient descent [27] and RMSprop
[28]), but they did not give better results. We used dropout regularization with
an empirical setup. In the LSTM layers, a dropout parameter for input gates
and another for recurrent connection were both set to 0.1. In the FC layers, we
set the dropout parameter to 0.1. We tried batch normalization [22], but did
not ﬁnd it eﬀective. All the weights were randomly initialized in the range of
[?0.05, 0.05]. The number of hidden nodes in the LSTM (d1 , d2 ) and the FC
(d3 , d4 ) layers were determined by cross validation as d1 = 20, d2 = 10, d3
= 400, and d4 = 100. The mini-batch size and training epochs were set to 128
and 300 respectively.

4
Experimental Results
We used three public benchmark datasets [4] named human, cross-species,
and new. The positive pre-miRNA sequences in all three datasets were obtained
from miRBase [25] (release 18). For the negative training sets, we obtained
noncoding RNAs other than pre-miRNAs and exonic regions of protein-coding
genes from NCBI (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov), fRNAdb [23], NONCODE
[24], and 5

Table 1: Numbers of sequences in the three benchmark datasets [4] used
in this study. The median length of each dataset is given in brackets. Type
Dataset name Positive examples Negative examples

Human
Cross-species
863 (85) 7422 (92)
1677 (93) 8266 (96)

7

New 690 (71) 8246 (96)
Table 2: Performance evaluation of diﬀerent pre-miRNA identiﬁcation meth-
ods with cross-validation (CV) and test data using sensitivity (SE), speciﬁcity
(SP), positive predictive value (PPV), F-score, geometric mean (g-mean), area
under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC), and area under the
precision-recall curve (AUPR). Human

Cross-species
Methods
SE1
SP2 PPV3 F-score4 g-mean5 AUROC AUPR
miRBoost (CV) CSHMM (CV) triplet-SVM (CV) microPred (CV) MIReNA

(CV) Proposed (CV)

0.803 0.713 0.669 0.763 0.818 0.799
0.988 0.777 0.986 0.989 0.943 0.988
0.887 0.559 0.851 0.888 0.624 0.885
0.843 0.570 0.749 0.820 0.708 0.839
0.891 0.673 0.812 0.869 0.878 0.888
0.957 0.974 0.984
miRBoost (test) CSHMM (test) triplet-SVM (test) microPred (test) MIReNA

(test) Proposed (test)

0.884 0.616 0.744 0.779 0.826 0.822
0.969 0.978 0.992 0.988 0.941 0.992
0.768 0.768 0.914 0.882 0.617 0.919
0.822 0.684 0.821 0.827 0.706 0.868
0.925 0.777 0.859 0.877 0.881 0.903
0.947 0.980 0.981
SE
SP
PPV F-score g-mean AUROC AUPR
0.854 0.890 0.915
0.861 0.826 0.735 0.825 0.766 0.886
0.977 0.576 0.967 0.975 0.952 0.982
0.884 0.533 0.819 0.875 0.765 0.911
0.872 0.564 0.775 0.848 0.765 0.898
0.917 0.524 0.843 0.897 0.854 0.933
0.943 0.970 0.985
0.869 0.873 0.927
0.830 0.892 0.918
0.856 0.749 0.760 0.814 0.796 0.900
0.844 0.960 0.977 0.985 0.950 0.983
0.526 0.791 0.870 0.919 0.764 0.913
0.651 0.769 0.812 0.863 0.780 0.906
0.850 0.848 0.862 0.896 0.870 0.940
0.952 0.963 0.984
0.908 0.906 0.955

8

P P P P TP: true positive, TN: true negative, FP: false positive, FN: false
negative. 1 SE = TP/(TP + FN) 2 SP = ? 3 4 TN/(TN + FP) PPV (precision)
= TP/(TP + FP) F-score = 2TP/(2TP + FP + FN) 5 g-mean = SE ? SP

snoRNA-LBME-db [26]. Note that we only acquired those datasets that had
undergone redundancy removal and had annotation corrected by the data own-
ers. As shown in Table 1, the human dataset contains 863 human pre-miRNA
sequences (positive examples) and 7422 non-pre-miRNA sequences (negative
examples). The cross-species dataset contains 1677 pre-miRNA sequences col-
lected from various species (e.g., human, mouse, and ﬂy), and 8266 non-miRNA
sequences. The new dataset has 690 newly discovered pre-miRNA sequences,
which are in miRBase releases 19 and 20, with 8246 non-pre-miRNA sequences.
For the human and cross-species datasets, 10% of the data was randomly chosen
as a clean test dataset (also known as a publication dataset) and was never used
in training. Using the remaining 90% of each dataset, we carried out ﬁve-fold
cross-validation for training and model selection. Note that the new dataset
was used for testing purposes only, as described in Tran et al. [4]. Additional
details of the experimental settings used can be found in Appendix B. 4.1

Validation and Test Performance Evaluation
We used seven evaluation metrics: sensitivity (SE), speciﬁcity (SP), positive
predictive value (PPV), Fscore, the geometric mean of SE and SP (g-mean), the
area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUROC), and the area
under the precision-recall curve (AUPR). Higher sensitivity indicates a more
accurate pre-miRNAs predictor which is likely to assist the discovery of novel
pre-miRNAs. Higher speciﬁcity indicates more eﬀective ﬁltering of pseudo pre-
miRNAs, which increases the eﬃciency of biological experiments. Because they
take account of results with diﬀerent decision thresholds, AUROC and AUPR
typically deliver more information than the more basic metrics such as sensitiv-
ity, speciﬁcity, and PPV, which are computed with a single decision threshold.
Note that miRBoost, MIReNA, and CSHMM do not provide decision values,
and so the AUROC and AUPR metrics cannot be obtained from these meth-
ods. The results of a cross-validation performance comparison are shown in the
upper half of Table 2, while the results of the test performance comparison are
shown in the bottom half. For the human dataset, the cross-validation perfor-
mance of our method was comparable to that of others, but our method achieved
the highest test performance in terms of F-score, AUROC, and AUPRG. For
the cross-species dataset, our method achieved the best overall performance in
terms of both crossvalidation and test evaluation results. Some tools, such as
miRBoost, showed fair performance in 6

Table 3: Evaluation of performance on the new dataset. Methods miRBoost

CSHMM triplet-SVM microPred MIReNA Proposed method

SE
SP
PPV
F-score
g-mean
AUROC

9

AUPR
0.921 0.536 0.721 0.728 0.450 0.917
0.936 0.069 0.981 0.970 0.941 0.964
0.609 0.046 0.759 0.672 0.392 0.682
0.733 0.085 0.740 0.699 0.419 0.782
0.928 0.192 0.841 0.840 0.650 0.941
0.934 0.940 0.981
0.766 0.756 0.808
0.987 0.978 0.988
1 0.9 0.8
0.783
0.799
0.795
0.727
0.7 0.6 0.5
0.875 0.888
0.839
0.649 0.537 SE
SP Sequence only
F-score Structure only
g-mean Multimodal
Figure 3: Using both sequence and structure information gives the best
performance on the human dataset. Each bar shows the metrics of average
cross-validation results. terms of the cross-validation but failed to deliver the
same level of performance on the test data. These results suggest that our
approach provides better generalization than the alternatives. The similarity of
the performance in terms of the cross-validation and test results suggests that
overﬁtting was handled eﬀectively. Following the experimental setup used by
Tran et al.
[4], we also evaluated the proposed method on the new dataset,
with a model trained by the cross-species dataset, as shown in Table 3, to assess
the potential of our approach in the search for novel pre-miRNAs. Again, our
method did not show the best performance in terms of basic metrics such as
sensitivity and speciﬁcity, but it returned the best values of AUROC and AUPR.
The results show that the proposed method can be used eﬀectively to identify
novel pre-miRNAs as well as to ﬁlter out pseudo pre-miRNAs. To evaluate the
statistical signiﬁcance of our approach, we applied a Kolmogorov-Smirnov test
[40] to the classiﬁcations produced by our method, grouped by true data labels.
For the human, cross-species, and new datasets, the p-values we obtained were
5.23 ? 10?54 , 6.06 ? 10?102 , and 7.92 ? 10?49 respectively, indicating that
the chance of these results occurring at random is very small indeed. 4.2

Eﬀectiveness of Multimodal Learning
Our approach to the identiﬁcation of pre-miRNAs takes both biological se-
quence information and secondary structure information into account. To assess
the beneﬁt of this multimodality, we measured the performance of our method
using only sequences or secondary structures in training on the human dataset.

10

As shown in Fig. 3, all of the performance metrics were higher when both se-
quence and structure information were used together. Compared with the use
of sequence or structure alone, the sensitivity of the multimodal approach was
increased by 48% point and 2% point, respectively. For speciﬁcity, the cases
using both sequence and structure achieved higher performance values (0.988)
than those of the sequence only (0.987) and structure only (0.978) cases. Simi-
larly, in terms of F-score, using the multimodality gave 29% point and 5% point
higher scores (0.839) than using sequence only (0.649) or structure only (0.795),
respectively. 4.3

Gaining Insights by Analyzing Attention Weights
A key strength of our approach is its ability to learn the features useful for
pre-miRNA identiﬁcation from data. This improves eﬃciency, and also has the
potential to aid the discovery of subtle features that might be missed in manual
feature design. However, learned features, which are implicitly represented by
the trained weights of a deep model, come without intuitive signiﬁcance. To
address this issue, we experimented with the visualization of attention weights
using the class activation mapping [32], a technique that was originally proposed
to interpret the operation of 7

A negative predicted examples
B
C Stem-loop
positive predicted examples
sequence position (%)
U
C
sequence position (%)
G
C A
C
G
U
G
A
30 U
A
G
G A A 50
U
U
A
G U
A
A
U U
A
U

11

A
C
G
U
A
U
A
C
G 60
A
U A
10 U
U
A C
G
A
U
A
UGGGAAACAUACUUCUUUAUAUGCCCAUAUGGACCUGCUAAGCUAUGGAAUGUAAAGAAGUAUGUAUCUCA
3?
5? stem
mature miRNA
C
G
C
20 U
5?
U
A U
C C
40 A G
A U
A A
U
G
C
G
U
G
C
U
A
5? 3? Homo sapiens miR-1-1 70
Figure 4: Attention weighted RNN outputs with the human dataset. (A)
Class activation mapping for predicted examples (negatives: non-pre-miRNAs).
(B) Class activation mapping for predicted examples (positives: pre-miRNAs).

12

(C) Stem-loop structure of a pre-miRNA (homo sapiens miR-1-1). Table 4:
Performance of diﬀerent types of neural network, assessed in terms of ﬁve-fold
cross-validation results from the human dataset. The number of stacked layers is
shown in brackets. ATT means that an attention mechanism was included, and
a BiLSTM is a bi-directional LSTM. The conﬁguration that we ﬁnally adopted
is shown in row 6. No.

Type
SE
SP
F-score
1 2 3
1D-CNN(2) 1D-CNN(2)+LSTM(2) 1D-CNN(2)+LSTM(2)+ ATT
0.745 0.707 0.691
0.978 0.976 0.979
0.771 0.738 0.739
g-mean 0.853 0.830 0.822
4 5 6
LSTM(2) LSTM(1) + ATT LSTM(2) + ATT (proposed)
0.666 0.781 0.799
0.988 0.987 0.988
0.751 0.824 0.839
0.810 0.878 0.888
7 8
BiLSTM(1) + ATT BiLSTM(2) + ATT
0.783 0.795
0.987 0.987
0.827 0.834
0.879 0.886
convolutional neural networks (CNNs) in image classiﬁcation by highlighting
discriminative regions. We modiﬁed the class activation mapping of RNNs to
discover which part of the sequential output is signiﬁcant for identifying pre-
miRNAs. We performed one-dimensional global average pooling (GAP) on the
attention weighted output Hatt (see Section 3.2) to derive a d2 -dimensional
weight vector ?gap . We then multiplied Hatt by ?gap to obtain a class acti-
vation map of size —xs — for each sequence sample. Fig. 4 (A) and Fig. 4
(B) show the resulting heatmap representations of class activation mapping on
the human dataset for positive and negative predicted examples, respectively.
Since sequences can have diﬀerent lengths, we normalized the sequence lengths
to 1 and presented individual positions in a sequence between 0% and 100% in
the x-axis. By comparing the plots in Fig. 4 (A) and (B), we can see that class
activation maps of the positive and negative data show clear diﬀerences, espe-
cially at the 20?50% sequence positions, within the red box in Fig. 4 (B). This
region corresponds to the 50 stem region of typical pre-miRNAs, as shown in
Fig. 4 (C). This region coincides with the location of a mature miRNA encoded
within a pre-miRNA, suggesting that the data-driven features learned by our
approach have revealed relevant characteristics of pre-miRNAs. The presence

13

of some nucleotide patterns has recently been reported in the mature miRNA
region inside a pre-miRNA [33]. We anticipate that further interpretation of
our data-driven features may assist in conﬁrming such patterns, and also in
discovering novel motifs in pre-miRNAs. 4.4

Additional Experiments
1) Architecture exploration: We explored various alternative network archi-
tectures, as listed in Table 4, which shows the performance of diﬀerent network
architectures, annotated with the number of layers and any of attention mech-
anism. Rows 1?3 of the table, show results for CNNs with and without LSTM
networks. Rows 4?6 show the results of LSTM networks. Rows 7?8, show re-
sults for bi-directional LSTM (BiLSTM) networks. More details can be found
in Appendix C.1. 2) Additional results: Appendix C.2?4 presents more details
of hyperparameter tuning, the design decisions made between the uses of soft
and hard encoding, and running-time comparisons. 8

5
Discussion
Given the importance of the secondary structure in pre-miRNA identiﬁca-
tion (e.g., see Section 4.2), we derived the secondary structure of each input
sequence using RNAfold. We then combined the secondary structure informa-
tion with the primary structure (i.e. the sequence), and sent the result to the
RNN. However, a fully end-to-end approach to pre-miRNA identiﬁcation we
would need to learn even the secondary structure from the input sequences.
Due to the limited numbers of known pre-miRNA sequences, this remains as
challenging future work. Our experimental results supported the eﬀectiveness of
a multi-modal approach that considers sequences and structures together from
an early stage of the pipeline. Incorporating other types of information would
be possible and might improve performance further. For example, sequencing
results from RNA-seq experiments reﬂect the expression levels and the positions
of each sequenced RNA [34]; and conservation information would allow a phy-
logenetic perspective [35]. Such additional information could be integrated into
the current framework by representing it as new network branches and merg-
ing them with the current data before the FC layers. Our proposed method
has the clear advantage over existing approaches that it does not require hand-
crafted features. But we need to ensure that learned feature provide satisfactory
performance, and they also need to have some biological meaning. Biomedical
researchers naturally hesitate to use a black-box methodology. Our method of
visualizing attention weights provides a tool for opening that black-box, and
assist data-driven discovery. Acknowledgments This work was supported in
part by the Samsung Research Funding Center of the Samsung Electronics [No.
SRFC-IT1601-05], the Institute for Information & communications Technology
Promotion (IITP) grant funded by the Korea government (MSIT) [No. 2016-0-
00087], the Future Flagship Program funded by the Ministry of Trade, Industry
& Energy (MOTIE, Korea) [No. 10053249], the Basic Science Research Pro-
gram through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF) funded by the
Ministry of Science, ICT & Future Planning [No. 2016M3A7B4911115], and
Brain Korea 21 Plus Project in 2017.

14

2 References

[1] M. E. Rahman, et al. MiRANN: A reliable approach for improved classiﬁca-
tion of precursor microRNA using Artiﬁcial Neural Network model. Genomics,
99(4):189?194, 2012.
[2] K. Xu, et al. Show, Attend and Tell: Neural Image
Caption Generation with Visual Attention. In ICML, volume 14, pages 77?81,
2015.
[3] J. Chung, et al. Empirical evaluation of gated recurrent neural net-
works on sequence modeling. arXiv preprint arXiv:1412.3555, 2014. [4] P. Baldi
and S. Brunak. Chapter 6. Neural Networks: applications. In Bioinformatics:
The Machine Learning Approach. MIT press, 2001.
[5] I. L. Hofacker. Vi-
enna RNA secondary structure server. Nucleic acids research, 31(13):3429?3431,
[6] D. P. Kingma and J. Ba. Adam: A Method for Stochastic Opti-
2003.
mization. CoRR, abs/1412.6980, 2014.
[7] V. D. T. Tran, et al. miRBoost:
boosting support vector machines for microRNA precursor classiﬁcation. RNA,
21(5):775?785, 2015. [8] Y. LeCun, Y. Bengio, and G. Hinton. Deep learning.
Nature, 521(7553):436?444, 2015.
[9] Y. Bengio, P. Simard, and P. Frasconi.
Learning long-term dependencies with gradient descent is diﬃcult. Neural Net-
works, IEEE Transactions on, 5(2):157?166, 1994.
[10] S. Hochreiter and J.
Schmidhuber. Long short-term memory. Neural computation, 9(8):1735?1780,
1997.
[11] R. Batuwita and V. Palade. microPred: eﬀective classiﬁcation of
pre-miRNAs for human miRNA gene prediction. Bioinformatics, 25(8):989?995,
2009. [12] P. Jiang, et al. MiPred: classiﬁcation of real and pseudo microRNA
precursors using random forest prediction model with combined features. Nu-
cleic acids research, 35(suppl 2):W339?W344, 2007.
[13] S. Agarwal, et al.
Prediction of novel precursor miRNAs using a context-sensitive hidden Markov
model (CSHMM). BMC bioinformatics, 11(Suppl 1):S29, 2010.

9
[14] A. Mathelier and A. Carbone. MIReNA: ﬁnding microRNAs with high
accuracy and no learning at genome scale and from deep sequencing data. Bioin-
formatics, 26(18):2226?2234, 2010. [15] C. Xue, et al. Classiﬁcation of real and
pseudo microRNA precursors using local structure-sequence features and sup-
port vector machine. BMC bioinformatics, 6(1):310, 2005. [16] R. C. Lee, R. L.
Feinbaum, and V. Ambros. The C. elegans heterochronic gene lin-4 encodes
small RNAs with antisense complementarity to lin-14. Cell, 75(5):843?854,
1993.
[17] D. P. Bartel. MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and
function. cell, 116(2):281?297, 2004.
[18] D. Kleftogiannis, et al. Where we
stand, where we are moving: Surveying computational techniques for identifying
miRNA genes and uncovering their regulatory role. Journal of biomedical infor-
matics, 46(3):563?573, 2013. [19] I. de ON Lopes, A. Schliep, and A. C. d. L. de
Carvalho. The discriminant power of RNA features for pre-miRNA recognition.
BMC bioinformatics, 15(1):1, 2014. [20] R. Lorenz, et al. ViennaRNA Package
[21] R. B. Lyngs?. Com-
2.0. Algorithms for Molecular Biology, 6(1):1, 2011.
plexity of pseudoknot prediction in simple models.
In Automata, Languages
and Programming, pages 919?931. Springer, 2004. [22] S. Ioﬀe and C. Szegedy.
Batch normalization: Accelerating deep network training by reducing internal
covariate shift. arXiv preprint arXiv:1502.03167, 2015.
[23] T. Kin, et al. fR-

15

NAdb: a platform for mining/annotating functional RNA candidates from non-
coding RNA sequences. Nucleic acids research, 35(suppl 1):D145?D148, 2007.
[24] D. Bu, et al. NONCODE v3. 0:
integrative annotation of long noncod-
ing RNAs. Nucleic acids research, page gkr1175, 2011. [25] S. Griﬃths-Jones,
et al. miRBase: microRNA sequences, targets and gene nomenclature. Nucleic
acids research, 34(suppl 1):D140?D144, 2006. [26] L. Lestrade and M. J. Weber.
snoRNA-LBME-db, a comprehensive database of human H/ACA and C/D box
snoRNAs. Nucleic acids research, 34(suppl 1):D158?D162, 2006. [27] L. Bottou.
Stochastic gradient learning in neural networks. Proceedings of Neuro-N?mes,
91(8), 1991. [28] T. Tieleman and G. Hinton. Lecture 6.5-rmsprop: Divide the
gradient by a running average of its recent magnitude. COURSERA: Neural
Networks for Machine Learning, 4:2, 2012. [29] O. Vinyals, et al. Grammar as a
foreign language. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages
2773?2781, 2015. [30] T. Rockt?schel, et al. Reasoning about entailment with
neural attention. arXiv preprint arXiv:1509.06664, 2015.
[31] G. King and L.
Zeng. Logistic regression in rare events data. Political analysis, 9(2):137?163,
2001. [32] B. Zhou, et al. Learning deep features for discriminative localization.
In Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recog-
nition, pages 2921?2929, 2016. [33] J. Starega-Roslan, P. Galka-Marciniak, and
W. J. Krzyzosiak. Nucleotide sequence of miRNA precursor contributes to cleav-
age site selection by Dicer. Nucleic acids research, 43(22):10939?10951, 2015.
[34] M. R. Friedl?nder, et al. Discovering microRNAs from deep sequencing data
using miRDeep. Nature biotechnology, 26(4):407?415, 2008.
[35] N. Mendes,
A. T. Freitas, and M.-F. Sagot. Current tools for the identiﬁcation of miRNA
genes and their targets. Nucleic acids research, 37(8):2419?2433, 2009.
[36]
T. Mikolov, et al. Distributed representations of words and phrases and their
compositionality. In Advances in neural information processing systems, pages
3111?3119, 2013.
[37] J. Thomas, S. Thomas, and L. Sael. DP-miRNA: An
improved prediction of precursor microRNA using deep learning model. In Big
Data and Smart Computing (BigComp), 2017 IEEE International Conference
on, pages 96?99. IEEE, 2017.
[38] J. Chen, X. Wang, and B. Liu. IMiRNA-
SSF: improving the identiﬁcation of MicroRNA precursors by combining neg-
ative sets with diﬀerent distributions. Scientiﬁc reports, 6, 2016.
[39] L. Wei,
et al. Improved and promising identiﬁcation of human microRNAs by incorpo-
rating a high-quality negative set. IEEE/ACM Transactions on Computational
Biology and Bioinformatics, 11(1):192?201, 2014.
[40] H. W. Lilliefors. On
the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test for normality with mean and variance unknown.
Journal of the American statistical Association, 62(318):399?402, 1967.

10

16

