Associative Embedding: End-to-End Learning for

Joint Detection and Grouping

Authored by:

Jia Deng

Alejandro Newell

Zhiao Huang

Abstract

We introduce associative embedding, a novel method for supervising
convolutional neural networks for the task of detection and grouping. A
number of computer vision problems can be framed in this manner includ-
ing multi-person pose estimation, instance segmentation, and multi-object
tracking. Usually the grouping of detections is achieved with multi-stage
pipelines, instead we propose an approach that teaches a network to si-
multaneously output detections and group assignments. This technique
can be easily integrated into any state-of-the-art network architecture that
produces pixel-wise predictions. We show how to apply this method to
multi-person pose estimation and report state-of-the-art performance on
the MPII and MS-COCO datasets.

1 Paper Body

Many computer vision tasks can be viewed in the context of detection and group-
ing: detecting smaller visual units and grouping them into larger structures. For
example, in multi-person pose estimation we detect body joints and group them
into individual people; in instance segmentation we detect pixels belonging to
a semantic class and group them into object instances; in multi-object tracking
we detect objects across video frames and group them into tracks.
In all of
these cases, the output is a variable number of visual units and their assign-
ment into a variable number of visual groups. Such tasks are often approached
with two-stage pipelines that perform detection ﬁrst and grouping second. But
such approaches may be suboptimal because detection and grouping are tightly
coupled: for example, in multiperson pose estimation, the same features used
to recognize wrists or elbows in an image would also suggest whether a wrist
and elbow belong to the same limb. In this paper we ask whether it is possi-
ble to jointly perform detection and grouping using a singlestage deep network
trained end-to-end. We propose associative embedding, a novel method to ex-

1

press output for joint detection and grouping. The basic idea is to introduce, for
each detection, a vector embedding that serves as a ?tag? to identify its group
assignment. All detections associated with the same tag value belong to the
same group. Concretely, the network outputs a heatmap of per-pixel * Work
done while a visiting student at the University of Michigan. 31st Conference on
Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017), Long Beach, CA, USA.

detection scores and a set of per-pixel embeddings. The detections and
groups are decoded by extracting the corresponding embeddings from pixel lo-
cations with top detection scores. To train a network to produce the correct
tags, we use a loss function that encourages pairs of tags to have similar values
if the corresponding detections belong to the same group or dissimilar values
otherwise. It is important to note that we have no ?ground truth? tags for the
network to predict, because what matters is not the particular tag values, only
the diﬀerences between them. The network has the freedom to decide on the
tag values as long as they agree with the ground truth grouping. We apply our
approach to multiperson pose estimation, an important task for understanding
humans in images. Given an input image, multi-person pose estimation seeks
to detect each person and localize their body joints. Unlike single-person pose
there are no prior assumptions of a person?s location or size. Multi-person
pose systems must scan the whole image detecting all people and their cor-
responding keypoints. For this task, we integrate associative embedding with
a stacked hourglass network [31], which produces a detection heatmap and a
tagging heatmap for each body joint, and then group body joints with similar
tags into individual people. Experiments demonstrate that our approach out-
performs all recent methods and achieves state-of-the-art results on MS-COCO
[27] and MPII Multiperson Pose [3]. Our contributions are two fold: (1) we in-
troduce associative embedding, a new method for singlestage, end-to-end joint
detection and grouping. This method is simple and generic; it works with any
network architecture that produces pixel-wise prediction; (2) we apply asso-
ciative embedding to multiperson pose estimation and achieve state-of-the-art
results on two standard benchmarks.

2
Related Work
Vector Embeddings Our method is related to many prior works that use
vector embeddings. Works in image retrieval have used vector embeddings to
measure similarity between images [12, 43]. Works in image classiﬁcation, im-
age captioning, and phrase localization have used vector embeddings to connect
visual features and text features by mapping them to the same vector space
[11, 14, 22]. Works in natural language processing have used vector embed-
dings to represent the meaning of words, sentences, and paragraphs [30, 24].
Our work diﬀers from these prior works in that we use vector embeddings as
identity tags in the context of joint detection and grouping. Perceptual Orga-
nization Work in perceptual organization aims to group the pixels of an image
into regions, parts, and objects. Perceptual organization encompasses a wide
range of tasks of varying complexity from ﬁgure-ground segmentation [28] to
hierarchical image parsing [15]. Prior works typically use a two stage pipeline

2

[29], detecting basic visual units (patches, superpixels, parts, etc.) ﬁrst and
grouping them second. Common grouping approaches include spectral cluster-
ing [41, 36], conditional random ﬁelds (e.g.
[23]), and generative probabilistic
models (e.g. [15]). These grouping approaches all assume pre-detected basic vi-
sual units and pre-computed aﬃnity measures between them but diﬀer among
themselves in the process of converting aﬃnity measures into groups. In con-
trast, our approach performs detection and grouping in one stage using a generic
network that includes no special design for grouping. It is worth noting a close
connection between our approach to those using spectral clustering. Spectral
clustering (e.g. normalized cuts [36]) techniques takes as input pre-computed
aﬃnities (such as predicted by a deep network) between visual units and solves
a generalized eigenproblem to produce embeddings (one per visual unit) that
are similar for visual units with high aﬃnity. Angular Embedding [28, 37] ex-
tends spectral clustering by embedding depth ordering as well as grouping. Our
approach diﬀers from spectral clustering in that we have no intermediate repre-
sentation of aﬃnities nor do we solve any eigenproblems. Instead our network
directly outputs the ﬁnal embeddings. Our approach is also related to the work
by Harley et al. on learning dense convolutional embeddings [16], which trains
a deep network to produce pixel-wise embeddings for the task of semantic seg-
mentation. Our work diﬀers from theirs in that our network produces not only
pixel-wise embeddings but also pixel-wise detection scores. Our novelty lies in
the integration of detection and grouping into a single network; to the best
of our knowledge such an integration has not been attempted for multiperson
human pose estimation. Multiperson Pose Estimation Recent methods have
made great progress improving human pose estimation in images in particular
for single person pose estimation [40, 38, 42, 31, 8, 5, 32, 4, 9, 13, 2

Figure 1: We use the stacked hourglass architecture from Newell et al. [31].
The network performs repeated bottom-up, top-down inference producing a
series of intermediate predictions (marked in blue) until the last ?hourglass?
produces a ﬁnal result (marked in green). Each box represents a 3x3 convolu-
tional layer. Features are combined across scales by upsampling and performing
elementwise addition. The same ground truth is enforced across all predictions
made by the network. 26, 18, 7, 39, 34]. For multiperson pose, prior and con-
current work can be categorized as either topdown or bottom-up. Top-down
approaches [33, 17, 10] ﬁrst detect individual people and then estimate each
person?s pose. Bottom-up approaches [35, 20, 21, 6] instead detect individual
body joints and then group them into individuals. Our approach more closely
resembles bottom-up approaches but diﬀers in that there is no separation of a
detection and grouping stage. The entire prediction is done at once in a sin-
gle stage. This does away with the need for complicated post-processing steps
required by other methods [6, 20].

3
Approach
To introduce associative embedding for joint detection and grouping, we
ﬁrst review the basic formulation of visual detection. Many visual tasks involve
detection of a set of visual units. These tasks are typically formulated as scoring

3

of a large set of candidates. For example, single-person human pose estimation
can be formulated as scoring candidate body joint detections at all possible pixel
locations. Object detection can be formulated as scoring candidate bounding
boxes at various pixel locations, scales, and aspect ratios. The idea of associative
embedding is to predict an embedding for each candidate in addition to the
detection score. The embeddings serve as tags that encode grouping: detections
with similar tags should be grouped together. In multiperson pose estimation,
body joints with similar tags should be grouped to form a single person. It is
important to note that the absolute values of the tags do not matter, only the
distances between tags. That is, a network is free to assign arbitrary values to
the tags as long as the values are the same for detections belonging to the same
group. To train a network to predict the tags, we enforce a loss that encourages
similar tags for detections from the same group and diﬀerent tags for detections
across diﬀerent groups. Speciﬁcally, this tagging loss is enforced on candidate
detections that coincide with the ground truth. We compare pairs of detections
and deﬁne a penalty based on the relative values of the tags and whether the
detections should be from the same group. 3.1

Network Architecture
Our approach requires that a network produce dense output to deﬁne a de-
tection score and vector embedding at each pixel of the input image. In this work
we use the stacked hourglass architecture, a model used previously for single-
person pose estimation [31]. Each ?hourglass? is comprised of a standard set
of convolutional and pooling layers to process features down to a low resolution
capturing the full global context of the image. These features are upsampled
and combined with outputs from higher resolutions until reaching a ﬁnal out-
put resolution. Stacking multiple hourglasses enables repeated bottom-up and
top-down inference to produce a more accurate ﬁnal prediction. Intermediate
predictions are made by the network after each hourglass (Fig. 1). We refer
the reader to [31] for more details of the network architecture. The stacked
hourglass model was originally developed for single-person human pose estima-
tion and designed to output a heatmap for each body joint of a target person.
The pixel with the highest heatmap activation is used as the predicted location
for that joint. The network consolidates global and local features to capture
information about the full structure of the body while preserving ﬁne 3

Figure 2: An overview of our approach for producing multi-person pose
estimates. For each joint of the body, the network simultaneously produces
detection heatmaps and predicts associative embedding tags. We take the top
detections for each joint and match them to other detections that share the
same embedding tag to produce a ﬁnal set of individual pose predictions.

details for precise localization. This balance between global and local context
is just as important when predicting poses of multiple people. We make some
modiﬁcations to the network architecture to increase its capacity and accom-
modate the increased diﬃculty of multi-person pose estimation. We increase
the number of features at each drop in resolution of the hourglass (256 ? 384 ?
512 ? 640 ? 768). In addition, individual layers are composed of 3x3 convolu-
tions instead of residual modules. Residual links are still included across each

4

hourglass as well as skip connections at each resolution. 3.2

Detection and Grouping
For multiperson pose estimation, we train the network to detect joints in
a similar manner to prior work on single-person pose estimation [31]. The
model predicts a detection score at each pixel location for each body joint (?left
wrist?, ?right shoulder?, etc.)
regardless of person identity. The diﬀerence
from single-person pose being that an ideal heatmap for multiple people should
have multiple peaks (e.g. to identify multiple left wrists belonging to diﬀerent
people), as opposed to just a single peak for a single target person. During
training, we impose a detection loss on the output heatmaps. The detection
loss computes mean square error between each predicted detection heatmap
and its ?ground truth? heatmap which consists of a 2D gaussian activation
at each keypoint location. This loss is the same as the one used by Newell et
al.
[31]. Given the top activating detections from these heatmaps we need to
pull together all joints that belong to the same individual. For this, we turn to
the associative embeddings. For each joint of the body, the network produces
additional channels to deﬁne an embedding vector at every pixel. Note that
the dimension of the embeddings is not critical. If a network can successfully
predict high-dimensional embeddings to separate the detections into groups, it
should also be able to learn to project those high-dimensional embeddings to
lower dimensions, as long as there is enough network capacity. In practice we
have found that 1D embedding is suﬃcient for multiperson pose estimation, and
higher dimensions do not lead to signiﬁcant improvement. Thus throughout this
paper we assume 1D embeddings. We think of these 1D embeddings as ?tags?
indicating which person a detected joint belongs to. Each detection heatmap
has its own corresponding tag heatmap, so if there are m body joints to predict
then the network will output a total of 2m channels; m for detection and m for
grouping. To parse detections into individual people, we get the peak detections
for each joint and retrieve their corresponding tags at the same pixel location
(illustrated in Fig. 2). We then group detections across body parts by comparing
the tag values of detections and matching up those that are close enough. A
group of detections now forms the pose estimate for a single person. 4

Figure 3: Tags produced by our network on a held-out validation image
from the MS-COCO training set. The tag values are already well separated
and decoding the groups is straightforward. The grouping loss assesses how
well the predicted tags agree with the ground truth grouping. Speciﬁcally, we
retrieve the predicted tags for all body joints of all people at their ground truth
locations; we then compare the tags within each person and across people. Tags
within a person should be the same, while tags across people should be diﬀerent.
Rather than enforce the loss across all possible pairs of keypoints, we produce
a reference embedding for each person. This is done by taking the mean of
the output embeddings of all joints belonging to a single person. Within an
individual, we compute the squared distance between the reference embedding
and the predicted embedding for each joint. Then, between pairs of people, we
compare their reference embeddings to each other with a penalty that drops
exponentially to zero as the distance between the two tags increases. Formally,

5

let hk ? RW ?H be the predicted tagging heatmap for the k-th body joint,
where h(x) is a tag value at pixel location x. Given N people, let the ground
truth body joint locations be T = {(xnk )}, n = 1, . . . , N, k = 1 . . . , K,
where xnk is the ground truth pixel location of the k-th body joint of the n-th
person. Assuming all K joints are annotated, the reference embedding for the
nth person would be X ?n = 1 h hk (xnk ) K k

The grouping loss Lg is then deﬁned as 2
1 ? 1 XX ? 1 XX ? 2 exp{? 2 h Lg (h, T ) = hn ? hk (xnk ) + 2 n ? hn0 }

NK n N n 0 2? n

k
The ﬁrst half of the loss pulls together all of the embeddings belonging to
an individual, and the second half pushes apart embeddings across people. We
use a ? value of 1 in our training. 3.3

Parsing Network Output
Once the network has been trained, decoding is straightforward. We perform
non-maximum suppression on the detection heatmaps and threshold to get a
set of detections for each body joint. Then, for each detection we retrieve its
corresponding associative embedding tag. To give an impression of the types
of tags produced by the network and the trivial nature of grouping we refer
to Figure 3; we plot a set of detections where the y-axis indicates the class of
body joint and the x-axis the assigned embedding. To produce a ﬁnal set of
predictions we iterate through each joint one by one. An ordering is determined
by ﬁrst considering joints around the head and torso and gradually moving out
to the limbs. We use the detections from the ﬁrst joint (the neck, for example)
to form our initial pool of detected people. Then, given the next joint, say the
left shoulder, we have to ﬁgure out how to best match its detections to the
current pool of people. Each detection is deﬁned by its score and embedding
tag, and each person is deﬁned by the mean embedding of their current joints.
5

Figure 4: Qualitative results on MSCOCO validation images We compare
the distance between these embeddings, and for each person we greedily assign
a new joint based on the detection with the highest score whose embedding falls
within some distance threshold. New detections that are not matched are used
to start a new person instance. This accounts for cases where perhaps only a
leg or hand is visible for a particular person. We repeat this process for each
joint of the body until every detection has been assigned to a person. No steps
are taken to ensure anatomical correctness or reasonable spatial relationships
between pairs of joints. Missing joints: In some evaluation settings we may need
to ensure that each person has a prediction for all joints, but our parsing does
not guarantee this. Missing joints are usually ﬁne, as in cases with truncation
and extreme occlusion, but when it is necessary to produce complete predictions
we introduce an additional processing step: given a missing joint, we identify
all pixels whose embedding falls close enough to the target person, and choose
the pixel location with the highest activation. This score may be lower than our
usual cutoﬀ threshold for detections. Multiscale Evaluation: While it is feasible
to train a network to predict poses for people of all scales, there are some

6

drawbacks. Extra capacity is required of the network to learn the necessary
scale invariance, and the precision of predictions for small people will suﬀer due
to issues of low resolution after pooling. To account for this, we evaluate images
at test time at multiple scales. We take the heatmaps produced at each scale
and resize and average them together. Then, to combine tags across scales, we
concatenate the set of tags at a pixel location into a vector v ? Rm (assuming
m scales). The decoding process remains unchanged.

4
Experiments
Datasets We evaluate on two datasets: MS-COCO [27] and MPII Human
Pose [3]. MPII Human Pose consists of about 25k images and contains around
40k total annotated people (three-quarters of which are available for training).
Evaluation is performed on MPII Multi-Person, a set of 1758 groups of multiple
people taken from the test set as outlined in [35]. The groups for MPII Multi-
Person are usually a subset of the total people in a particular image, so some
information is provided to make sure predictions are made on the correct targets.
This includes a general bounding box and 6

Iqbal&Gall, ECCV16 [21] Insafutdinov et al., ECCV16 [20] Insafutdinov et
al., arXiv16a [35] Levinkov et al., CVPR17 [25] Insafutdinov et al., CVPR17
[19] Cao et al., CVPR17 [6] Fang et al., ICCV17 [10] Our method

Head 58.4 78.4 89.4 89.8 88.8 91.2 88.4 92.1
Shoulder 53.9 72.5 84.5 85.2 87.0 87.6 86.5 89.3
Elbow 44.5 60.2 70.4 71.8 75.9 77.7 78.6 78.9
Wrist 35.0 51.0 59.3 59.6 64.9 66.8 70.4 69.8
Hip 42.2 57.2 68.9 71.1 74.2 75.4 74.4 76.2
Knee 36.7 52.0 62.7 63.0 68.8 68.9 73.0 71.6
Ankle 31.1 45.4 54.6 53.5 60.5 61.7 65.8 64.7
Total 43.1 59.5 70.0 70.6 74.3 75.6 76.7 77.5
Table 1: Results (AP) on MPII Multi-Person. CMU-Pose [6] G-RMI [33]

Our method

AP 0.611 0.643 0.663
AP50 0.844 0.846 0.865
AP75 0.667 0.704 0.727
APM 0.558 0.614 0.613
APL 0.684 0.696 0.732
AR 0.665 0.698 0.715
AR50 0.872 0.885 0.897
AR75 0.718 0.755 0.772
ARM 0.602 0.644 0.662
ARL 0.749 0.771 0.787
Table 2: Results on MS-COCO test-std, excluding systems trained with

external data.

CMU-Pose [6] Mask-RCNN [17] G-RMI [33] Our method
AP 0.618 0.627 0.649 0.655
AP50 0.849 0.870 0.855 0.868
AP75 0.675 0.684 0.713 0.723

7

APM 0.571 0.574 0.623 0.606
APL 0.682 0.711 0.700 0.726
AR 0.665 ? 0.697 0.702
AR50 0.872 ? 0.887 0.895
AR75 0.718 ? 0.755 0.760
ARM 0.606 ? 0.644 0.646
ARL 0.746 ? 0.771 0.781
Table 3: Results on MS-COCO test-dev, excluding systems trained with
external data. scale term used to indicate the occupied region. No information is
provided on the number of people or the scales of individual ﬁgures. We use the
evaluation metric outlined by Pishchulin et al. [35] calculating average precision
of joint detections. MS-COCO [27] consists of around 60K training images with
more than 100K people with annotated keypoints. We report performance on
two test sets, a development test set (test-dev) and a standard test set (test-std).
We use the oﬃcial evaluation metric that reports average precision (AP) and
average recall (AR) in a manner similar to object detection except that a score
based on keypoint distance is used instead of bounding box overlap. We refer
the reader to the MS-COCO website for details [1]. Implementation Details The
network used for this task consists of four stacked hourglass modules, with an
input size of 512 ? 512 and an output resolution of 128 ? 128. We train the
network using a batch size of 32 with a learning rate of 2e-4 (dropped to 1e-5
after about 150k iterations) using Tensorﬂow [2]. The associative embedding
loss is weighted by a factor of 1e-3 relative to the MSE loss of the detection
heatmaps. The loss is masked to ignore crowds with sparse annotations. At test
time an input image is run at multiple scales; the output detection heatmaps
are averaged across scales, and the tags across scales are concatenated into
higher dimensional tags. Following prior work [6], we apply a single-person
pose model [31] trained on the same dataset to investigate further reﬁnement
of predictions. We run each detected person through the single person model,
and average the output with the predictions from our multiperson pose model.
From Table 5, it is clear the beneﬁt of this reﬁnement is most pronounced in the
single-scale setting on small ﬁgures. This suggests output resolution is a limit
of performance at a single scale. Using our method for evaluation at multiple
scales, the beneﬁts of single person reﬁnement are almost entirely mitigated as
illustrated in Tables 4 and 5. MPII Results Average precision results can be
seen in Table 1 demonstrating an improvement over state-of-the-art methods in
overall AP. Associative embedding proves to be an eﬀective method for teaching
the network to group keypoint detections into individual people.
It requires
no assumptions about the number of people present in the image, and also
oﬀers a mechanism for the network to express confusion of joint assignments.
For example, if the same joint of two people overlaps at the exact same pixel
location, the predicted associative embedding will be a tag somewhere between
the respective tags of each person. We can get a better sense of the associative
embedding output with visualizations of the embedding heatmap (Figure 5).
We put particular focus on the diﬀerence in the predicted embeddings when 7
Figure 5: Here we visualize the associative embedding channels for diﬀerent

8

joints. The change in embedding predictions across joints is particularly appar-
ent in these examples where there is signiﬁcant overlap of the two target ﬁgures.
multi scale multi scale + reﬁne

Head 92.9 93.1
Shoulder 90.9 90.3
Elbow 81.0 81.9
Wrist 71.0 72.1
Hip 79.3 80.2
Knee 70.6 72.0
Ankle 63.4 67.8
Total 78.5 79.6
Table 4: Eﬀect of single person reﬁnement on a held out validation set on

MPII.

single scale single scale + reﬁne multi scale multi scale + reﬁne
AP 0.566 0.628 0.650 0.655
AP50 0.818 0.846 0.867 0.868
AP75 0.618 0.692 0.713 0.723
APM 0.498 0.575 0.597 0.606
APL 0.670 0.706 0.725 0.726
Table 5: Eﬀect of multi-scale evaluation and single person reﬁnement on
MS-COCO test-dev. people overlap heavily as the severe occlusion and close
spacing of detected joints make it much more diﬃcult to parse out the poses of
individual people. MS-COCO Results Table 2 and 3 report our results on MS-
COCO. We report results on both test-std and test-dev because not all recent
methods report on test-std. We see that on both sets we achieve the state of
the art performance. An illustration of the network?s predictions can be seen
in Figure 4. Typical failure cases of the network stem from overlapping and
occluded joints in cluttered scenes. Table 5 reports performance of ablated ver-
sions of our full pipeline, showing the contributions from applying our model at
multiple scales and from further reﬁnement using a single-person pose estima-
tor. We see that simply applying our network at multiple scales already achieves
competitive performance against prior state of the art methods, demonstrating
the eﬀectiveness of our end-to-end joint detection and grouping. We perform an
additional experiment on MS-COCO to gauge the relative diﬃculty of detection
versus grouping, that is, which part is the main bottleneck of our system. We
evaluate our system on a held-out set of 500 training images. In this evaluation,
we replace the predicted detections with the ground truth detections but still
use the predicted tags. Using the ground truth detections improves AP from
59.2 to 94.0. This shows that keypoint detection is the main bottleneck of our
system, whereas the network has learned to produce high quality grouping. This
fact is also supported by qualitative inspection of the predicted tag values, as
shown in Figure 3, from which we can see that the tags are well separated and
decoding the grouping is straightforward.

5
Conclusion

9

In this work we introduce associative embeddings to supervise a convolu-
tional neural network such that it can simultaneously generate and group de-
tections. We apply this method to multi-person pose and demonstrate the feasi-
bility of training to achieve state-of-the-art performance. Our method is general
enough to be applied to other vision problems as well, for example instance seg-
mentation and multi-object tracking in video. The associative embedding loss
can be implemented given any network that produces pixelwise predictions, so
it can be easily integrated with other state-of-the-art architectures. 8

6
Acknowledgements
This work is partially supported by the National Science Foundation under
Grant No. 1734266. ZH is partially supported by the Institute for Interdisci-
plinary Information Sciences, Tsinghua University.

2 References

[1] COCO: Common Objects in Context. http://mscoco.org/home/. [2] Mart?n
Abadi, Ashish Agarwal, Paul Barham, Eugene Brevdo, Zhifeng Chen, Craig
Citro, Greg S. Corrado, Andy Davis, Jeﬀrey Dean, Matthieu Devin, Sanjay Ghe-
mawat, Ian Goodfellow, Andrew Harp, Geoﬀrey Irving, Michael Isard, Yangqing
Jia, Rafal Jozefowicz, Lukasz Kaiser, Manjunath Kudlur, Josh Levenberg, Dan
Man?, Rajat Monga, Sherry Moore, Derek Murray, Chris Olah, Mike Schuster,
Jonathon Shlens, Benoit Steiner, Ilya Sutskever, Kunal Talwar, Paul Tucker,
Vincent Vanhoucke, Vijay Vasudevan, Fernanda Vi?gas, Oriol Vinyals, Pete
Warden, Martin Wattenberg, Martin Wicke, Yuan Yu, and Xiaoqiang Zheng.
TensorFlow: Large-scale machine learning on heterogeneous systems, 2015.
Software available from tensorﬂow.org. [3] Mykhaylo Andriluka, Leonid Pishchulin,
Peter Gehler, and Bernt Schiele. 2d human pose estimation: New benchmark
and state of the art analysis.
In Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition
(CVPR), 2014 IEEE Conference on, pages 3686?3693. IEEE, 2014. [4] Vasileios
Belagiannis and Andrew Zisserman. Recurrent human pose estimation. In Au-
tomatic Face & Gesture Recognition (FG 2017), 2017 12th IEEE International
Conference on, pages 468?475. IEEE, 2017. [5] Adrian Bulat and Georgios Tz-
imiropoulos. Human pose estimation via convolutional part heatmap regression.
In ECCV, 2016.
[6] Zhe Cao, Tomas Simon, Shih-En Wei, and Yaser Sheikh.
Realtime multi-person 2d pose estimation using part aﬃnity ﬁelds. In Computer
Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2017 IEEE Conference on, 2017. [7]
Joao Carreira, Pulkit Agrawal, Katerina Fragkiadaki, and Jitendra Malik. Hu-
man pose estimation with iterative error feedback. In Proceedings of the IEEE
Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, pages 4733?4742,
2016.
[8] Xiao Chu, Wei Yang, Wanli Ouyang, Cheng Ma, Alan L Yuille, and
Xiaogang Wang. Multi-context attention for human pose estimation. 2017. [9]
Xiaochuan Fan, Kang Zheng, Yuewei Lin, and Song Wang. Combining local ap-
pearance and holistic view: Dual-source deep neural networks for human pose
estimation. In Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and

10

[10] Hao-Shu Fang, Shuqin Xie,
Pattern Recognition, pages 1347?1355, 2015.
Yu-Wing Tai, and Cewu Lu. RMPE: Regional multi-person pose estimation.
In ICCV, 2017. [11] Andrea Frome, Greg S Corrado, Jon Shlens, Samy Bengio,
Jeﬀ Dean, Tomas Mikolov, et al. Devise: A deep visual-semantic embedding
model. In Advances in neural information processing systems, pages 2121?2129,
2013.
[12] Andrea Frome, Yoram Singer, Fei Sha, and Jitendra Malik. Learn-
ing globally-consistent local distance functions for shape-based image retrieval
and classiﬁcation. In 2007 IEEE 11th International Conference on Computer
Vision, pages 1?8. IEEE, 2007. [13] Georgia Gkioxari, Alexander Toshev, and
Navdeep Jaitly. Chained predictions using convolutional neural networks. In
European Conference on Computer Vision, pages 728?743. Springer, 2016. [14]
Yunchao Gong, Liwei Wang, Micah Hodosh, Julia Hockenmaier, and Svetlana
Lazebnik. Improving image-sentence embeddings using large weakly annotated
photo collections. In European Conference on Computer Vision, pages 529?545.
Springer, 2014. [15] Feng Han and Song-Chun Zhu. Bottom-up/top-down image
parsing with attribute grammar. IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and
Machine Intelligence, 31(1):59?73, 2009. [16] Adam W Harley, Konstantinos G
Derpanis, and Iasonas Kokkinos. Learning dense convolutional embeddings for
semantic segmentation. In International Conference on Learning Representa-
tions (Workshop), 2016.

9
[17] Kaiming He, Georgia Gkioxari, Piotr Doll?r, and Ross Girshick. Mask
r-cnn. 2017.
[18] Peiyun Hu and Deva Ramanan. Bottom-up and top-down
reasoning with hierarchical rectiﬁed gaussians. In Proceedings of the IEEE Con-
ference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, pages 5600?5609, 2016.
[19] Eldar Insafutdinov, Mykhaylo Andriluka, Leonid Pishchulin, Siyu Tang,
Bjoern Andres, and Bernt Schiele. Articulated multi-person tracking in the
wild. arXiv preprint arXiv:1612.01465, 2016.
[20] Eldar Insafutdinov, Leonid
Pishchulin, Bjoern Andres, Mykhaylo Andriluka, and Bernt Schiele. Deepercut:
A deeper, stronger, and faster multi-person pose estimation model. In European
Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV), May 2016. [21] Umar Iqbal and Juer-
gen Gall. Multi-person pose estimation with local joint-to-person associations.
arXiv preprint arXiv:1608.08526, 2016.
[22] Andrej Karpathy and Li Fei-Fei.
Deep visual-semantic alignments for generating image descriptions. In Proceed-
ings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition,
pages 3128?3137, 2015.
[23] Vladlen Koltun. Eﬃcient inference in fully con-
nected crfs with gaussian edge potentials. Adv. Neural Inf. Process. Syst,
2011.
[24] Quoc V Le and Tomas Mikolov. Distributed representations of
sentences and documents. In ICML, volume 14, pages 1188?1196, 2014.
[25]
Evgeny Levinkov, Jonas Uhrig, Siyu Tang, Mohamed Omran, Eldar Insafutdi-
nov, Alexander Kirillov, Carsten Rother, Thomas Brox, Bernt Schiele, and Bjo-
ern Andres. Joint graph decomposition & node labeling: Problem, algorithms,
applications. In IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition
(CVPR), 2017.
[26] Ita Lifshitz, Ethan Fetaya, and Shimon Ullman. Human
pose estimation using deep consensus voting. In European Conference on Com-
puter Vision, pages 246?260. Springer, 2016. [27] Tsung-Yi Lin, Michael Maire,

11

Serge Belongie, James Hays, Pietro Perona, Deva Ramanan, Piotr Doll?r, and
C Lawrence Zitnick. Microsoft coco: Common objects in context. In European
Conference on Computer Vision, pages 740?755. Springer, 2014.
[28] Michael
Maire. Simultaneous segmentation and ﬁgure/ground organization using angu-
lar embedding. In European Conference on Computer Vision, pages 450?464.
Springer, 2010.
[29] Michael Maire, X Yu Stella, and Pietro Perona. Object
detection and segmentation from joint embedding of parts and pixels. In 2011
International Conference on Computer Vision, pages 2142?2149. IEEE, 2011.
[30] Tomas Mikolov, Ilya Sutskever, Kai Chen, Greg S Corrado, and Jeﬀ Dean.
Distributed representations of words and phrases and their compositionality.
In Advances in neural information processing systems, pages 3111?3119, 2013.
[31] Alejandro Newell, Kaiyu Yang, and Jia Deng. Stacked hourglass networks
for human pose estimation. ECCV, 2016.
[32] Guanghan Ning, Zhi Zhang,
and Zhihai He. Knowledge-guided deep fractal neural networks for human pose
estimation. arXiv preprint arXiv:1705.02407, 2017.
[33] George Papandreou,
Tyler Zhu, Nori Kanazawa, Alexander Toshev, Jonathan Tompson, Chris Bre-
gler, and Kevin Murphy. Towards accurate multi-person pose estimation in the
wild. arXiv preprint arXiv:1701.01779, 2017. [34] Leonid Pishchulin, Mykhaylo
Andriluka, Peter Gehler, and Bernt Schiele. Poselet conditioned pictorial struc-
tures. In Proceedings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pat-
tern Recognition, pages 588?595, 2013. [35] Leonid Pishchulin, Eldar Insafutdi-
nov, Siyu Tang, Bjoern Andres, Mykhaylo Andriluka, Peter Gehler, and Bernt
Schiele. Deepcut: Joint subset partition and labeling for multi person pose es-
timation. In IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition
(CVPR), June 2016.
[36] Jianbo Shi and Jitendra Malik. Normalized cuts
and image segmentation. IEEE Transactions on pattern analysis and machine
intelligence, 22(8):888?905, 2000.

10
[37] X Yu Stella. Angular embedding:

from jarring intensity diﬀerences
to perceived luminance. In Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, 2009.
CVPR 2009. IEEE Conference on, pages 2302?2309. IEEE, 2009. [38] Jonathan
Tompson, Ross Goroshin, Arjun Jain, Yann LeCun, and Christoph Bregler. Ef-
ﬁcient object localization using convolutional networks. In Proceedings of the
IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, pages 648?656,
2015. [39] Jonathan J Tompson, Arjun Jain, Yann LeCun, and Christoph Bre-
gler. Joint training of a convolutional network and a graphical model for human
pose estimation. In Advances in neural information processing systems, pages
1799?1807, 2014. [40] Alexander Toshev and Christian Szegedy. Deeppose: Hu-
man pose estimation via deep neural networks. In Computer Vision and Pat-
tern Recognition (CVPR), 2014 IEEE Conference on, pages 1653?1660. IEEE,
2014. [41] Ulrike Von Luxburg. A tutorial on spectral clustering. Statistics and
computing, 17(4):395?416, 2007. [42] Shih-En Wei, Varun Ramakrishna, Takeo
Kanade, and Yaser Sheikh. Convolutional pose machines. Computer Vision and
Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2016 IEEE Conference on, 2016.
[43] Kilian Q
Weinberger, John Blitzer, and Lawrence K Saul. Distance metric learning for
large margin nearest neighbor classiﬁcation. In Advances in neural information

12

processing systems, pages 1473?1480, 2005.

11

13

