Neural Program Meta-Induction

Authored by:

Pushmeet Kohli
Rudy R. Bunel
Jacob Devlin
Rishabh Singh

Matthew Hausknecht

Abstract

Most recently proposed methods for Neural Program induction work
under the assumption of having a large set of input/output (I/O) ex-
amples for learning any given input-output mapping. This paper aims
to address the problem of data and computation eﬃciency of program
induction by leveraging information from related tasks. Speciﬁcally, we
propose two novel approaches for cross-task knowledge transfer to im-
prove program induction in limited-data scenarios. In our ﬁrst proposal,
portfolio adaptation, a set of induction models is pretrained on a set of
related tasks, and the best model is adapted towards the new task us-
ing transfer learning. In our second approach, meta program induction,
a $k$-shot learning approach is used to make a model generalize to new
tasks without additional training. To test the eﬃcacy of our methods, we
constructed a new benchmark of programs written in the Karel program-
ming language. Using an extensive experimental evaluation on the Karel
benchmark, we demonstrate that our proposals dramatically outperform
the baseline induction method that does not use knowledge transfer. We
also analyze the relative performance of the two approaches and study
conditions in which they perform best. In particular, meta induction out-
performs all existing approaches under extreme data sparsity (when a very
small number of examples are available), i.e., fewer than ten. As the num-
ber of available I/O examples increase (i.e. a thousand or more), portfolio
adapted program induction becomes the best approach. For intermediate
data sizes, we demonstrate that the combined method of adapted meta
program induction has the strongest performance.

1 Paper Body

Neural program induction has been a very active area of research in the last few
years, but this past work has made highly variable set of assumptions about the
amount of training data and types of training signals that are available. One

1

common scenario is example-driven algorithm induction, where the goal is to
learn a model which can perform a speciﬁc task (i.e., an underlying program
or algorithm), such as sorting a list of integers[7, 11, 12, 21]. Typically, the
goal of these works are to compare a newly proposed network architecture to
a baseline model, and the system is trained on input/output examples (I/O
examples) as a standard supervised learning task. For example, for integer
sorting, the I/O examples would consist of pairs of unsorted and sorted integer
lists, and the model would be trained to maximize cross-entropy loss of the
output sequence.
In this way, the induction model is similar to a standard
sequence generation task such as machine translation or image captioning. In
these works, the authors typically assume that a near-inﬁnite amount of I/O
examples corresponding to a particular task are available. ?

Work performed at Microsoft Research.
31st Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017),

Long Beach, CA, USA.

Other works have made diﬀerent assumptions about data: Li et al.

[14]
trains models from scratch using 32 to 256 I/O examples. Lake et al. [13] learns
to induce complex concepts from several hundred examples. Devlin et al.
[5],
Duan et al. [6], and Santoro et al. [19] are able to perform induction using as
few one I/O example, but these works assume that a large set of background
tasks from the same task family are available for training. Neelakantan et al.
[16] and Andreas et al.
[1] also develop models which can perform induction
on new tasks that were not seen at training time, but are conditioned on a
natural language representation rather than I/O examples. These varying as-
sumptions about data are all reasonable in diﬀering scenarios. For example, in
a scenario where a reference implementation of the program is available, it is
reasonable to expect that an unlimited amount of I/O examples can be gener-
ated, but it may be unreasonable to assume that any similar program will also
be available. However, we can also consider a scenario like FlashFill [9], where
the goal is to learn a regular expression based string transformation program
based on userprovided examples, such as ?John Smith ? Smith, J.?). Here, it
is only reasonable to assume that a handful of I/O examples are available for
a particular task, but that many examples are available for other tasks in the
same family (e.g., ?Frank Miller ? Frank M?). In this work, we compare several
diﬀerent techniques for neural program induction, with a particular focus on
how the relative accuracy of these techniques diﬀers as a function of the avail-
able training data. In other words, if technique A is better than technique B
when only ﬁve I/O examples are available, does this mean A will also be bet-
ter than B when 50 I/O examples are available? What about 1000? 100,000?
How does this performance change if data for many related tasks is available?
To answer these questions, we evaluate four general techniques for cross-task
knowledge sharing: ? Plain Program Induction (PLAIN) - Supervised learning
is used to train a model which can perform induction on a single task, i.e.,
read in an input example for the task and predict the corresponding output.
No cross-task knowledge sharing is performed. ? Portfolio-Adapted Program
Induction (PLAIN + ADAPT) - Simple transfer learning is used to to adapt a

2

model which has been trained on a related task for a new task. ? Meta Pro-
gram Induction (META) - A k-shot learning-style model is used to represent an
exponential family of tasks, where the training I/O examples corresponding to
a task are directly conditioned on as input to the network. This model can gen-
eralize to new tasks without any additional training. ? Adapted Meta Program
Induction (META + ADAPT) - The META model is adapted to a speciﬁc new
task using round-robin hold-one-out training on the task?s I/O examples. We
evaluate these techniques on a synthetic domain described in Section 2, using a
simple but strong network architecture. All models are fully example-driven, so
the underlying program representation is only used to generate I/O examples,
and is not used when training or evaluating the model.

2
Karel Domain
In order to ground the ideas presented here, we describe our models in re-
lation to a particular synthetic domain called ?Karel?. Karel is an educational
programming language developed at Stanford University in the 1980s[17]. In
this language, a virtual agent named Karel the Robot moves around a 2D grid
world placing markers and avoiding obstacle. The domain speciﬁc language
(DSL) for Karel is moderately complex, as it allows if/then/else blocks, for
loops, and while loops, but does not allow variable assignments. Compared to
the current program induction benchmarks, Karel introduces a new challenge of
learning programs with complex control ﬂow, where the stateof-the-art program
synthesis techniques involving constraint-solving and enumeration do not scale
because of the prohibitively large search space. Karel is also an interesting do-
main as it is used for example-driven programming in an introductory Stanford
programming course.2 In this course, students are provided with several I/O
grids corresponding to some underlying Karel program that they have never
seen before, and must write a single program which can be run on all inputs
to generate the corresponding outputs. This diﬀers from typical programming
assignments, since the program speciﬁcation is given in the form of I/O exam-
ples rather than natural language. An example is given in Figure 1. Note that
inducing Karel programs is not a toy reinforcement learning task. 2

The programs are written manually by students; it is not used to teach

program induction or synthesis.

2
Since the example I/O grids are of varying dimensions, the learning task is
not to induce a single trace that only works on grids of a ﬁxed size, but rather
to induce a program that can can perform the desired action on ?arbitrary-size
grids?, thereby forcing it to use the loop structure appropriately.

Figure 1: Karel Domain: On the left, a sample task from the Karel domain
with two training I/O ? O). ? The computer is Karel, the circles examples (I1 ,
O1 ), (I2 , O2 ) and one test I/O example (I, represent markers and the brick wall
represents obstacles. On the right, the language spec for Karel. In this work,
we only explore the induction variant of Karel, where instead of attempting to
synthesize ? from a corresponding input grid I. ? the program, we attempt to
directly generate the output grid O Although the underlying program is used

3

to generate the training data, it is not used by the model in any way, so in
principle it does not have to explicitly exist. For example, a more complex
real-world analogue would be a system where a user controls a drone to provide
examples of a task such as ?Fly around the boundary of the forest, and if you
see a deer, take a picture of it, then return home.? Such a task might be diﬃcult
to represent using a program, but could be possible with a suﬃciently powerful
and well-trained induction model, especially if cross-task knowledge sharing is
used.
3
Plain Program Induction
In this work, plain program induction (denoted as PLAIN) refers to the
supervised training of a parametric model using a set of input/output examples
(I1 , O1 ), ..., (IN , ON ), such that the model ? In this scenario, all I/O examples
in can take some new I? as input and emit the corresponding O. training and
test correspond to the same task (i.e., underlying program or algorithm), such
as sorting a list of integers. Examples of past work in plain program induction
using neural networks include [7, 11, 12, 8, 4, 20, 2]. For the Karel domain,
we use a simple architecture shown on the left side of Figure 2. The input
feature map are an 16-dimensional vector with n-hot encodings to represent the
objects of the cell, i.e., (AgentFacingNorth, AgentFacingEast, ..., OneMarker,
TwoMarkers, ..., Obstacle). Additionally, instead of predicting the output grid
directly, we use an LSTM to predict the delta between the input grid and output
grid as a series of tokens using. For example, AgentRow=+1 AgentCol=+2
HeroDir=south MarkerRow=0 MarkerCol=0 MarkerCount=+2 would indicate
that the hero has moved north 1 row, east 2 rows, is facing south, and also added
two markers on its starting position. This sequence can be deterministically
applied to the input to create the output grid. Speciﬁc details about the model
architecture and training are given in Section 8.

4
Portfolio-Adapted Program Induction
Most past work in neural programs induction assumes that a very large
amount of training data is available to train a particular task, and ignores data
sparsity issues entirely. However, in a practical scenario such as the FlashFill
domain described in Section 1 or the real-world Karel analogue 3

Figure 2: Network Architecture: Diagrams for the general network architec-
tures used for the Karel domain. Speciﬁcs of the model are provided in Section
8.

described in Section 2, I/O examples for a new task must be provided by
the user. In this case, it may be unrealistic to expect more than a handful of
I/O examples corresponding to a new task. Of course, it is typically infeasible
to train a deep neural network from scratch with only a handful of training
examples. Instead, we consider a scenario where data is available for a number
of background tasks from the same task family. In the Karel domain, the task
family is simply any task from the Karel DSL, but in principle the task family
can be more a more abstract concept such as ?The set of string transformations
that a user might perform on columns in a spreadsheet.? One way of taking

4

advantage of such background tasks is with straightforward transfer learning,
which we refer to as portfolio-adapted program induction (denoted as PLAIN
+ ADAPT). Here, we have a portfolio of models each trained on a single back-
ground I/O task. To train an induction model for a new task, we select the
?best? background model and use it as an initialization point for training our
new model. This is analogous to the type of transfer learning used in standard
classiﬁcation tasks like image recognition or machine translation [10, 15]. The
criteria by which we select this background model is to score the training I/O
examples for the new task with each model in the portfolio, and select the one
with the highest log-likelihood.

5
Meta Program Induction
Although we expect that PLAIN + ADAPT will allow us to learn an in-
duction model with fewer I/O examples than training from scratch, it is still
subject to the normal pitfalls of SGD-based training. In particular, it is typi-
cally very diﬃcult to train powerful DNNs using very few I/O examples (e.g.,
¡ 100) without encountering signiﬁcant overﬁtting. An alternative method is to
train a single network which represents an entire (exponentially large) family
of tasks, and the latent representation of a particular task is represented by
conditioning on the training I/O examples for that task. We refer to this type
of model as meta induction (denoted as META) because instead of using SGD
to learn a latent representation of a particular task based on I/O examples, we
are using SGD to learn how to learn a latent task representation based on I/O
examples. More speciﬁcally, our meta induction architecture takes as input a
set of demonstration examples ? and emits the corresponding output O. ? A
diagram (I1 , O1 ), ..., (Ik , Ok ) and an additional eval input I, is shown in
Figure 2. The number of demonstration examples k is typically small, e.g., 1 to
5. At training time, we are given a large number of tasks with k + 1 examples
each. During training, one example is chosen at random to represent the eval
example, the others are used to represent the demonstration examples. At test
time, we are given k I/O examples which correspond to a new task ? Then,
we are able to generate that was not seen at training, along with one or more
eval inputs I. ? the corresponding O for the new task without performing any
SGD. The META model could also be described as a k-shot learning system,
closely related to Duan et al.
[19]. In a scenario where
a moderate number of I/O examples are available at test time, e.g., 10 to 100,
performing meta induction is non-trivial. It is not computationally feasible to
train a model which is 4

[6] and Santoro et al.

directly conditioned on k = 100 examples, and using a larger value of k at
test time than training time creates an undesirable mismatch. So, if the model
is trained using k examples but n examples are available at test time (n ¿ k), the
approach we take is to randomly sample a number of k-sized sets and performing
ensembling of the softmax log probabilities for each output token. There are
(n choose k) total subsets available, but we found little improvement in using
more than 2 ? n/k. We set k = 5 in all experiments, and present results using
diﬀerent values of n in Section 8.

5

6
Adapted Meta Program Induction
The previous approach to use n ¿ k I/O examples at test time seems rea-
sonable, but certainly not optimal. An alternative approach is to combine the
best aspects of META and PLAIN + ADAPT, and adapt the meta model to a
particular new task using SGD. To do this, we can repeatedly sample k + 1 I/O
examples from the n total examples provided, and ﬁne tune the META model
for the new task in the exact manner that it was trained originally. For decod-
ing, we still perform the same algorithm as the META model, but the weights
have been adapted for the particular Figure 3: Data-Mixture Regularization
task being decoded. In order to mitigate overﬁtting, we found that it is useful
to perform ?data-mixture regularization,? where the I/O examples for the new
task are mixed with random training data corresponding to other tasks. In all
experiments here we sample 10% of the I/O examples in a minibatch from the
new task and 90% from random training tasks. It is potential that underﬁt-
ting could occur in this scenario, but note that the meta network is already
trained to represent an exponential number of tasks, so using a single task for
10% of the data is quite signiﬁcant. Results with data mixture adaptation are
shown in Figure 3, which demonstrates that this acts as a strong regularizer
and moderately improves held-out loss.

7
Comparison with Existing Work on Neural Program Induction
There has been a large amount of past work in neural program induction, and
many of these works have made diﬀerent assumptions about the conditions of the
induction scenario. Here, our goal is to compare the four techniques presented
here to each other and to past work across several attributes: ? Example-Driven
Induction - 3 = The system is trained using I/O examples as speciﬁcation. 7
= The system uses some other speciﬁcation, such as natural language. ? No
Explicit Program Representation - 3 = The system can be trained without
any explicit program or program trace. 7 = The system requires a program or
program trace. ? Task-Speciﬁc Learning - 3 = The model is trained to maximize
performance on a particular task. 7 = The model is trained for a family of
tasks. ? Cross-Task Knowledge Sharing - 3 = The system uses information
from multiple tasks when training a model for a new task. 7 = The system
uses information from only a single task for each model. The comparison is
presented in Table 1. The PLAIN technique is closely related to the example-
driven induction models such as Neural Turing Machines[7] or Neural RAM[12],
which typically have not focused on cross-task knowledge transfer. The META
model is closely related are the k-shot imitation learning approaches [6, 5, 19],
but these papers did not explore task-speciﬁc adaptation.

8
Experimental Results
In this section we evaluate the four techniques PLAIN, PLAIN + ADAPT,
META, META + ADAPT on the Karel domain. The primary goal is to compare
performance relative to the number of training I/O examples available for the
test task. 5

6

System
ExampleDriven Induction
No Explicit Program or Trace
TaskSpeciﬁc Learning
Novel Architectures Applied to Program Induction NTM [7], Stack RNN
[11], NRAM [12] Neural Transducers [8], Learn Algo [21] 3 3 3 Others [4, 20, 2,
13] NPI [18] Recursive NPI [3], NPL [14]

Trace-Augmented Induction 3 7 3 7
3 3
Cross-Task Knowledge Sharing
7
3 7
Non Example-Driven Induction (e.g., Natural Language-Driven Induction)
Inducing Latent Programs [16] 7 3 3 3 Neural Module Networks [1] k-shot Imi-
tation Learning 1-Shot Imitation Learning [6] 3 3 RobustFill [5], Meta-Learning
[19]
7
3
Techniques Explored in This Work Plain Program Induction 3 3 Portfolio-
Adapted Program Induction 3 3 Meta Program Induction 3 3 Adapted Meta
Program Induction 3 3

3 3 7 3
7 3(Weak) 3(Strong) 3(Strong)
Table 1: Comparison with Existing Work: Comparison of existing work

across several attributes.

For the primary experiments reported here, the overall network architecture
is sketched in Figure 2, with details as follows: The input encoder is a 3-layer
CNN with a FC+relu layer on top. The output decoder is a 1-layer LSTM.
For the META model, the task encoder uses 1-layer CNN to encode the input
and output for a single example, which are concatenated on the feature map
dimension and fed through a 6-layer CNN with a FC+relu layer on top. Mul-
tiple I/O examples were combined with max-pooling on the ﬁnal vector. All
convolutional layers use a 3 ? 3 kernel with a 64-dimensional feature map. The
fully-connected and LSTM are 1024-dimensional. Diﬀerent model sizes are ex-
plored later in this section. The dropout, learning rate, and batch size were
optimized with grid search for each value of n using a separate set of validation
tasks. Training was performed using SGD + momentum and gradient clipping
using an in-house toolkit. All training, validation, and test programs were gen-
erated by treating the Karel DSL as a probabilistic context free grammar and
performing top-down expansion with uniform probability at each node. The
input grids were generated by creating a grid of a random size and inserting the
agent, markers, and obstacles at random. The output grid was generated by
executing the program on the input grid, and if the agent ran into an obstacle
or did not move, then the example was thrown out and a new input grid was
generated. We limit the nesting depth of control ﬂow to be at most 4 (i.e. at
most 4 nested if/while blocks can be chosen in a valid program). We sample

7

I/O grids of size n ? m, where n and m are integers sampled uniformly from the
range 2 to 20. We sample programs of size upto 20 statements. Every program
and I/O grid in the training/validation/test set is unique. Results are presented
in Figure 4, evaluated on 25 test tasks with 100 eval examples each.3 The x-
axis represents the number of training/demonstration I/O examples available
for the test task, denoted as n. The PLAIN system was trained only on these
n examples directly. The PLAIN + ADAPT system was also trained on these
n examples, but was initialized using a portfolio of m models that had been
trained on d examples each. Three diﬀerent values of m and d are shown in the
ﬁgure. The META model in this ﬁgure was trained on 1,000,000 tasks with 6
I/O examples each, but smaller amounts of META training are shown in Figure
5. A point-by-point analysis is given below: 3

Note that each task and eval example is evaluated independently, so the size

of the test set does not aﬀect the accuracy.

6
Figure 4: Induction Results: Comparison of the four induction techniques
on the Karel scenario. The accuracy denotes the total percentage of examples
for which the 1-best output grid was exactly equal to the reference.

? PLAIN vs. PLAIN + ADAPT: PLAIN + ADAPT signiﬁcantly outper-
forms PLAIN unless n is very large (10k+), in which case both systems perform
equally well. This result makes sense, since we expect that much of the represen-
tation learning (e.g., how to encode an I/O grid with a CNN) will be independent
of the exact task. ? PLAIN + ADAPT Model Portfolio Size: Here, we compare
the three model portfolio settings shown for PLAIN + ADAPT. The number of
available models (m = 1 vs. m = 25) only has a small eﬀect on accuracy, and
this eﬀect is only present for small values of n (e.g., n ¡ 100) when the absolute
performance is poor in any case. This implies that the majority of cross-task
knowledge sharing is independent of the exact details of a task. On the other
hand, the number of examples used to train each model in the portfolio (d =
1000 vs d = 100000) has a much larger eﬀect, especially for moderate values
of n, e.g., 50 to 100. This makes sense, as we would not expect a signiﬁcant
beneﬁt from adaptation unless (a) d n, and (b) n is large enough to train a
robust model. ? META vs. META + ADAPT: META + ADAPT does not
improve over META for small values of n, which is in-line with the common ob-
servation that SGD-based training is diﬃcult using a small number of samples.
However, for large values of n, the accuracy of META + ADAPT increases sig-
niﬁcantly while the META model remains ﬂat. ? PLAIN + ADAPT vs. META
+ ADAPT: Perhaps the most interesting result in the entire chart is the fact
that the accuracy crosses over, and PLAIN + ADAPT outperforms META +
ADAPT by a signiﬁcant margin for large values of n (i.e., 1000+). Intuitively,
this makes sense, since the meta induction model was trained to represent an
exponential family of tasks moderately well, rather than represent a single task
with extreme precision. Because the network architecture of the META model
is a superset of the PLAIN model, these results imply that for a large value of n,
the model is becoming stuck in a poor local optima.4 To validate this hypothesis,
we performed adaptation on the meta network after randomly re-initializing all

8

of the weights, and found that in this case the performance of META + ADAPT
matches that of PLAIN + ADAPT for large values of n. This conﬁrms that the
pre-trained meta network is actually a worse starting point than training from
scratch when a large number of training I/O examples are available. Learning
Curves: The left side of Figure 4 presents average held-out loss for the various
techniques using 50 and 1000 training I/O examples. Epoch 0 on the META
+ ADAPT corresponds to the META 4 Since the DNN is over-parameterized
relative to the number of training examples, the system is able to overﬁt the
training examples in all cases. Therefore ?poor local optimal? is referring to
the model?s ability to generalize to the test examples.

7
Figure 5: Ablation results for Karel Induction.

loss. We can see that the
PLAIN + ADAPT loss starts out very high, but the model able to adapt to the
new task quickly. The META + ADAPT loss starts out very strong, but only
improves by a small amount with adaptation. For 1000 I/O examples, it is able
to overtake the META + ADAPT model by a small amount, supporting what
was observed in Figure 4. Varying the Model Size: Here, we present results
on three architectures: Large = 64-dim feature map, 1024-dim FC/RNN (used
in the primary results); Medium = 32-dim feature map, 256-dim FC/RNN;
Small = 16-dim feature map, 64-dim FC/RNN. All models use the structure
described earlier in this section. We can see the center of Figure 5 that model
size has a much larger impact on the META model than the PLAIN, which is
intuitive ? representing an entire family tasks from a given domain requires
signiﬁcantly more parameters than a single task. We can also see that the
larger models outperform the smaller models for any value of n, which is likely
because the dropout ratio was selected for each model size and value of n to
mitigate overﬁtting. Varying the Amount of META Training: The META model
presented in Figure 4 represents a very optimistic scenario which is trained on
1,000,000 background tasks with 6 I/O examples each. On the right side of
Figure 5, we present META results using 100,000 and 10,000 training tasks. We
see a signiﬁcant loss in accuracy, which demonstrates that it is quite challenging
to train a META model that can generalize to new tasks.

9
Conclusions
In this work, we have contrasted two techniques for using cross-task knowl-
edge sharing to improve neural program induction, which are referred to as
adapted program induction and meta program induction. Both of these tech-
niques can be used to improve accuracy on a new task by using models that
were trained on related tasks from the same family. However, adapted induc-
tion uses a transfer learning style approach while meta induction uses a k-shot
learning style approach. We applied these techniques to a challenging induction
domain based on the Karel programming language, and found that each tech-
nique, including unadapted induction, performs best under certain conditions.
Speciﬁcally, the preferred technique depends on the number of I/O examples
(n) that are available for the new task we want to learn, as well as the amount
of background data available. These conclusions can be summarized by the

9

following table: Technique

Background Data Required
When to Use
PLAIN
None
n is very large (10,000+)
PLAIN + ADAPT
Few related tasks (1+) with a large number of I/O examples (1,000+)
n is fairly large (1,000 to 10,000)
META
Many related tasks (100k+) with a small number of I/O examples (5+)
n is small (1 to 20)
META + ADAPT
Same as META
n is moderate (20 to 100)
Although we have only applied these techniques to a single domain, we be-
lieve that these conclusions are highly intuitive, and should generalize across do-
mains. In future work, we plan to explore more principled methods for adapted
meta adaption, in order to improve upon results in the very limited-example
scenario. 8

2 References

[1] Jacob Andreas, Marcus Rohrbach, Trevor Darrell, and Dan Klein. Neural
module networks. pages 39?48, 2016. [2] Marcin Andrychowicz and Karol Ku-
rach. Learning eﬃcient algorithms with hierarchical attentive memory. CoRR,
abs/1602.03218, 2016. [3] Jonathon Cai, Richard Shin, and Dawn Song. Mak-
ing neural programming architectures generalize via recursion. In ICLR, 2017.
[4] Ivo Danihelka, Greg Wayne, Benigno Uria, Nal Kalchbrenner, and Alex
Graves. Associative long shortterm memory. ICML, 2016.
[5] Jacob Devlin,
Jonathan Uesato, Surya Bhupatiraju, Rishabh Singh, Abdel-rahman Mohamed,
and Pushmeet Kohli. Robustﬁll: Neural program learning under noisy I/O.
CoRR, abs/1703.07469, 2017. [6] Yan Duan, Marcin Andrychowicz, Bradly C.
Stadie, Jonathan Ho, Jonas Schneider, Ilya Sutskever, Pieter Abbeel, and Wo-
jciech Zaremba. One-shot imitation learning. CoRR, abs/1703.07326, 2017. [7]
Alex Graves, Greg Wayne, and Ivo Danihelka. Neural turing machines. arXiv
preprint arXiv:1410.5401, 2014. [8] Edward Grefenstette, Karl Moritz Hermann,
Mustafa Suleyman, and Phil Blunsom. Learning to transduce with unbounded
memory. NIPS, 2015.
[9] Sumit Gulwani, William R Harris, and Rishabh
Singh. Spreadsheet data manipulation using examples. Communications of
the ACM, 2012.
[10] Mi-Young Huh, Pulkit Agrawal, and Alexei A. Efros.
What makes imagenet good for transfer learning? CoRR, abs/1608.08614,
2016. URL http://arxiv.org/abs/1608.08614.
[11] Armand Joulin and Tomas
Mikolov. Inferring algorithmic patterns with stack-augmented recurrent nets. In
NIPS, pages 190?198, 2015. [12] Karol Kurach, Marcin Andrychowicz, and Ilya

10

Sutskever. Neural random-access machines. ICLR, 2016. [13] Brenden M Lake,
Ruslan Salakhutdinov, and Joshua B Tenenbaum. Human-level concept learning
through probabilistic program induction. Science, 350(6266):1332?1338, 2015.
[14] Chengtao Li, Daniel Tarlow, Alexander L. Gaunt, Marc Brockschmidt, and
Nate Kushman. Neural program lattices. In ICLR, 2017. [15] Minh-Thang Lu-
ong and Christopher D. Manning. Stanford neural machine translation systems
for spoken language domains. 2015. [16] Arvind Neelakantan, Quov V. Le, and
Ilya Sutskever. Neural programmer: Inducing latent programs with gradient de-
scent. ICLR, 2016. [17] Richard E Pattis. Karel the robot: a gentle introduction
to the art of programming. John Wiley & Sons, Inc., 1981. [18] Scott Reed and
Nando de Freitas. Neural programmer-interpreters. ICLR, 2016.
[19] Adam
Santoro, Sergey Bartunov, Matthew Botvinick, Daan Wierstra, and Timothy
Lillicrap. Metalearning with memory-augmented neural networks. In Interna-
tional conference on machine learning, pages 1842?1850, 2016.
[20] Sainbayar
Sukhbaatar, Arthur Szlam, Jason Weston, and Rob Fergus. End-to-end mem-
ory networks. NIPS, 2015.
[21] Wojciech Zaremba, Tomas Mikolov, Armand
Joulin, and Rob Fergus. Learning simple algorithms from examples. CoRR,
abs/1511.07275, 2015. URL http://arxiv.org/abs/1511.07275.

9

11

