OnACID: Online Analysis of Calcium Imaging

Data in Real Time

Authored by:

Liam Paninski

Eftychios A. Pnevmatikakis

Dmitri Chklovskii
Johannes Friedrich
Andrea Giovannucci

Matt Kaufman

Anne Churchland

Abstract

Optical imaging methods using calcium indicators are critical for mon-
itoring the activity of large neuronal populations in vivo. Imaging experi-
ments typically generate a large amount of data that needs to be processed
to extract the activity of the imaged neuronal sources. While deriving such
processing algorithms is an active area of research, most existing meth-
ods require the processing of large amounts of data at a time, rendering
them vulnerable to the volume of the recorded data, and preventing real-
time experimental interrogation. Here we introduce OnACID, an Online
framework for the Analysis of streaming Calcium Imaging Data, including
i) motion artifact correction, ii) neuronal source extraction, and iii) ac-
tivity denoising and deconvolution. Our approach combines and extends
previous work on online dictionary learning and calcium imaging data
analysis, to deliver an automated pipeline that can discover and track the
activity of hundreds of cells in real time, thereby enabling new types of
closed-loop experiments. We apply our algorithm on two large scale ex-
perimental datasets, benchmark its performance on manually annotated
data, and show that it outperforms a popular oﬄine approach.

1 Paper Body

Calcium imaging methods continue to gain traction among experimental neuro-
scientists due to their capability of monitoring large targeted neuronal popula-
tions across multiple days or weeks with decisecond temporal and single-neuron
spatial resolution. To infer the neural population activity from the raw imag-
ing data, an analysis pipeline is employed which typically involves solving the

1

following problems (all of which are still areas of active research): i) correcting
for motion artifacts during the imaging experiment, ii) identifying/extracting
the sources (neurons and axonal or dendritic processes) in the imaged ﬁeld of
view (FOV), and iii) denoising and deconvolving the neural activity from the
dynamics of the expressed calcium indicator. 1 2

These authors contributed equally to this work. To whom correspondence

should be addressed.

31st Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017),

Long Beach, CA, USA.

The ﬁne spatiotemporal resolution of calcium imaging comes at a data rate
cost; a typical two-photon (2p) experiment on a 512?512 pixel large FOV im-
aged at 30Hz, generates ?50GB of data (in 16-bit integer format) per hour.
These rates can be signiﬁcantly higher for other planar and volumetric imaging
techniques, e.g., light-sheet [1] or SCAPE imaging [4], where the data rates can
exceed 1TB per hour. The resulting data deluge poses a signiﬁcant challenge. Of
the three basic pre-processing problems described above, the problem of source
extraction faces the most severe scalability issues. Popular approaches reshape
the data movies into a large array with dimensions (#pixels) ? (#timesteps),
that is then factorized (e.g., via independent component analysis [20] or con-
strained non-negative matrix factorization (CNMF) [26]) to produce the loca-
tions in the FOV and temporal activities of the imaged sources. While eﬀective
for small or medium datasets, direct factorization can be impractical, since a
typical experiment can quickly produce datasets larger than the available RAM.
Several strategies have been proposed to enhance scalability, including parallel
processing [9], spatiotemporal decimation [10], dimensionality reduction [23],
and out-of-core processing [13]. While these approaches enable eﬃcient pro-
cessing of larger datasets, they still require signiﬁcant storage, power, time,
and memory resources. Apart from recording large neural populations, optical
methods can also be used for stimulation [5]. Combining optogenetic meth-
ods for recording and perturbing neural ensembles opens the door to exciting
closed-loop experiments [24, 15, 8], where the pattern of the stimulation can be
determined based on the recorded activity during behavior. In a typical closed-
loop experiment, the monitored/perturbed regions of interest (ROIs) have been
preselected by analyzing oﬄine a previous dataset from the same FOV. Monitor-
ing the activity of a ROI, which usually corresponds to a soma, typically entails
averaging the ﬂuorescence over the corresponding ROI, resulting in a signal
that is only a proxy for the actual neural activity and which can be sensitive
to motion artifacts and drifts, as well as spatially overlapping sources, back-
ground/neuropil contamination, and noise. Furthermore, by preselecting the
ROIs, the experimenter is unable to detect and incorporate new sources that
become active later during the experiment, which prevents the execution of truly
closed-loop experiments. In this paper, we present an Online, single-pass, algo-
rithmic framework for the Analysis of Calcium Imaging Data (OnACID). Our
framework is highly scalable with minimal memory requirements, as it processes
the data in a streaming fashion one frame at a time, while keeping in memory
a set of low dimensional suﬃcient statistics and a small minibatch of the last

2

i) The frame
data frames. Every frame is processed in four sequential steps:
is registered against the previous denoised (and registered) frame to correct for
motion artifacts. ii) The ﬂuorescence activity of the already detected sources is
tracked. iii) Newly appearing neurons and processes are detected and incorpo-
rated to the set of existing sources. iv) The ﬂuorescence trace of each source is
denoised and deconvolved to provide an estimate of the underlying spiking ac-
tivity. Our algorithm integrates and extends the online NMF algorithm of [19],
the CNMF source extraction algorithm of [26], and the near-online deconvolu-
tion algorithm of [11], to provide a framework capable of real time identiﬁcation
and processing of hundreds of neurons in a typical 2p experiment (512?512 pixel
wide FOV imaged at 30Hz), enabling novel designs of closed-loop experiments.
We apply OnACID to two large-scale (50 and 65 minute long) mouse in vivo 2p
datasets; our algorithm can ﬁnd and track hundreds of neurons faster than real-
time, and outperforms the CNMF algorithm of [26] benchmarked on multiple
manual annotations using a precision-recall framework.

2
Methods
We illustrate OnACID in process in Fig. 1. At the beginning of the experi-
ment (Fig. 1-left), only a few components are active, as shown in the panel A
by the max-correlation image3 , and these are detected by the algorithm (Fig.
1B). As the experiment proceeds more neurons activate and are subsequently de-
tected by OnACID (Fig. 1 middle, right) which also tracks their activity across
time (Fig. 1C). See also Supplementary Movie 1 for an example in simulated
data. Next, we present the steps of OnACID in more detail. 3 The correlation
image (CI) at every pixel is equal to the average temporal correlation coeﬃcient
between that pixel and its neighbors [28] (8 neighbors were used for our analy-
sis). The max-correlation image is obtained by computing the CI for each batch
of 1000 frames, and then taking the maximum over all these images.

2
1000 frames
6000 frames
90000 frames
Max-Correlation Image
A
Found Components
B
C 5s
30s
5min
Figure 1: Illustration of the online data analysis process. Snapshots of the
online analysis after processing 1000 frames (left), 6000 frames (middle), and
90000 frames (right). A) ”Max-correlation” image of registered data at each
snapshot point (see text for deﬁnition). B) Spatial footprints (shapes) of the
components (neurons and processes) found by OnACID up to each point. C)
Examples of neuron activity traces (marked by contours in panel A and high-
lighted in red in panel B). As the experiment proceeds, OnACID detects newly

3

active neurons and tracks their activity. Motion correction: Our online approach
allows us to employ a very simple yet eﬀective motion correction scheme: each
denoised dataframe can be used to register the next incoming noisy dataframe.
To enhance robustness we use the denoised background/neuropil signal (deﬁned
in the next section) as a template to align the next dataframe. We use rigid, sub-
pixel registration [16], although piecewise rigid registration can also be used at
an additional computational cost. This simple alignment process is not suitable
for oﬄine algorithms due to noise in the raw data, leading to the development of
various algorithms based on template matching [14, 23, 25] or Hidden Markov
Models [7, 18]. Source extraction: A standard approach for source extraction is
to model the ﬂuorescence within a matrix factorization framework [20, 26]. Let
Y ? Rd?T denote the observed ﬂuorescence across space and time in a matrix
format, where d denotes the number of imaged pixels, and T the length of the
experiment in timepoints. If the number of imaged sources is K, then let A ?
Rd?K denote the matrix where column i encodes the ”spatial footprint” of the
source i. Similarly, let C ? RK?T denote the matrix where each row encodes
the temporal activity of the corresponding source. The observed data matrix
can then be expressed as Y = AC + B + E, (1) d?T where B, E ? R denote
matrices for background/neuropil activity and observation noise, respectively.
A common approach, introduced in [26], is to express the background matrix B
as a low rank matrix, i.e., B = bf , where b ? Rd?nb and f ? Rnb ?T denote
the spatial and temporal components of the low rank background signal, and
nb is a small integer, e.g., nb = 1, 2. The CNMF framework of [26] operates
by alternating optimization of [A, b] given the data Y and estimates of [C; f ],
and vice versa, where each column of A is constrained to be zero outside of a
neighborhood around its previous estimate. This strategy exploits the spatial
locality of each neuron to reduce the computational complexity. This framework
can be adapted to a data streaming setup using the online NMF algorithm of
[19], where the observed ﬂuorescence at time t can be written as yt = Act + bft
+ ?t . (2) Proceeding in a similar alternating way, the activity of all neurons
at time t, ct , and temporal background ft , given yt and the spatial footprints
and background [A, b], can be found by solving a nonnegative least squares
problem, whereas [A, b] can be estimated eﬃciently as in [19] by only ?t = [ct
; ft ]) keeping in memory the suﬃcient statistics (where we deﬁne c Wt =

t?1 t Wt?1
?¿ + 1t yt c t ,
Mt = 3
t?1 t Mt?1
?t c ?¿ + 1t c t ,
(3)
while at the same time enforcing the same spatial locality constraints as in
the CNMF framework. Deconvolution: The online framework presented above
estimates the demixed ﬂuorescence traces c1 , . . . , cK of each neuronal source.
The ﬂuorescence is a ﬁltered version of the underlying neural activity that we
want to infer. To further denoise and deconvolve the neural activity from the
dynamics of the indicator we use the OASIS algorithm [11] that implements

4

the popular spike deconvolution algorithm of [30] in a nearly online fashion by
adapting the highly eﬃcient Pool Adjacent Violators Algorithm used in isotonic
regression [3]. The calcium dynamics is modeled with Pp a stable autoregressive
process of order p, ct = i=1 ?i ct?i + st . We use p = 1 here, but can extend
to p = 2 to incorporate the indicator rise time [11]. OASIS solves a modiﬁed
LASSO problem minimize ?,? c s

1 c 2 k?
? yk2 + ?k?sk1
subject to s?t = c?t ? ?? ct?1 ? smin or s?t = 0
(4)
where the ‘1 penalty on ?s or the minimal spike size smin can be used
to enforce sparsity of the neural activity. The algorithm progresses through
each time series sequentially from beginning to end and backtracks only to the
most recent spike. We can further restrict the lag to few frames, to obtain a
good approximate solution applicable for real-time experiments. Detecting new
components: The approach explained above enables tracking the activity of a
ﬁxed number of sources, and will ignore neurons that become active later in
the experiment. To account for a variable number of sources in an online NMF
setting, [12] proposes to add a new random component when the correlation
coeﬃcient between each data frame and its representation in terms of the current
factors is lower than a threshold. This approach is insuﬃcient here since the
footprint of a new neuron in the whole FOV is typically too small to modify the
correlation coeﬃcient signiﬁcantly. We approach the problem by introducing a
buﬀer that contains the last lb instances of the residual signal rt = yt ? Act
? bft , where lb is a reasonably small number, e.g., lb = 100. On this buﬀer,
similarly to [26], we perform spatial smoothing with a Gaussian kernel with
radius similar to the expected neuron radius, and then search for the point in
space that explains the maximum variance. New candidate components anew ,
and cnew are estimated by performing a local rank-1 NMF of the residual matrix
restricted to a ﬁxed neighborhood around the point of maximal variance. To
limit false positives, the candidate component is screened for quality. First, to
prevent noise overﬁtting, the shape anew must be signiﬁcantly correlated (e.g.,
?s ? 0.8 ? 0.9) to the residual buﬀer averaged over time and restricted to the
spatial extent of anew . Moreover, if anew signiﬁcantly overlaps with any of
the existing components, then its temporal component cnew must not be highly
correlated with the corresponding temporal components; otherwise we reject it
as a possible duplicate of an existing component. Once a new component is
accepted, [A, b], [C; f ] are augmented with anew and cnew respectively, and
the suﬃcient statistics are updated as follows:

1 1 tMt C?buf c¿ ¿ new Mt = , (5) Wt = Wt , Ybuf cnew , ¿ kcnew k2 t
t cnew C?buf where Ybuf , C?buf denote the matrices Y, [C; f ], restricted to
the last lb frames that the buﬀer stores. This process is repeated until no new
components are accepted, at which point the next frame is read and processed.
The whole online procedure is described in Algorithm 1; the supplement includes
pseudocode description of all the referenced routines. Initialization: To initialize
our algorithm we use the CNMF algorithm on a short initial batch of data of

5

length Tb , (e.g., Tb = 1000). The suﬃcient statistics are initialized from the
components that the oﬄine algorithm ﬁnds according to (3). To ensure that
new components are also initialized in the darker parts of the FOV, each data
frame is normalized with the (running) mean for every pixel, during both the
oﬄine and the online phases. Algorithmic Speedups: Several algorithmic and
computational schemes are employed to boost the speed of the algorithm and
make it applicable to real-time large-scale experiments. In [19] block coordinate
descent is used to update the factors A, warm started at the value from the
previous iteration. The same trick is used here not only for A, but also for C,
since the calcium traces are continuous and typically change slowly. Moreover,
the temporal traces of components that do not spatially overlap with each other
can be updated simultaneously in vector form; we use a simple greedy scheme to
partition the components into spatially non-overlapping groups. Since neurons?
shapes are not expected to change at a fast timescale, updating their values
(i.e., recomputing A and b) is not required at every timepoint; in practice we
update every lb timesteps. 4

Algorithm 1 O NACID Require: Data matrix Y , initial estimates A, b, C, f
, S, current number of components K, current timestep t0 , rest of parameters.
1: W = Y [:, 1 : t0 ]C ¿ /t0 2: M = CC ¿ /t0 . Initialize suﬃcient statistics
3: G = D ETERMINE G ROUPS([A, b], K) . Alg. S1-S2 4: Rbuf = [Y ? [A,
b][C; f ]][:, t0 ? lb + 1 : t0 ] . Initialize residual buﬀer 5: t = t0 6: while there
is more data do 7: t?t+1 8: yt ? A LIGN F RAME(yt , bft?1 ) .
[16] 9: [ct
; ft ] ? U PDATE T RACES([A, b], [ct?1 ; ft?1 ], yt , G) . Alg. S3 10: C, S
? OASIS(C, ?, smin , ?) . [11] 11: [A, b], [C, f ], K, G, Rbuf , W, M ? 12: D
ETECT N EW C OMPONENTS([A, b], [C, f ], K, G, Rbuf , yt , W, M ) . Alg.
S4 13: Rbuf ? [Rbuf [:, 2 : lb ], yt ? Act ? bft ] . Update residual buﬀer 14: if
mod (t ? t0 , lb ) = 0 then . Update W, M, [A, b] every lb timesteps 15: W, M
? U PDATE S UFF S TATISTICS(W, M, yt , [ct ; ft ]) . Equation (3) 16: [A,
b] ? U PDATE S HAPES[W, M, [A, b]] . Alg. S5 17: return A, b, C, f , S false
pos false neg

B
C
1
28 Processing time [ms]
true pos
Pearson?s r
A
0.8 0.6 0.4 0.2 oﬄine ? 5 2 lag (frames)
0
24
20
500
1000
1500 frame
2000

6

Figure 2: Application to simulated data. A) Detected and missed compo-
nents. B) Tukey boxplot of spike train correlations with ground truth. Online
deconvolution recovers spike trains well and the accuracy increases with the
allowed lag in spike assignment. C) Processing time is less than 33 ms for all
the frames. Additionally, the suﬃcient statistics Wt , Mt are only needed for
updating the estimates of [A, b] so they can be updated only when required.
Motion correction can be sped up by estimating the motion only on a small
(active) contiguous part of the FOV. Finally, as shown in [10], spatial decima-
tion can bring signiﬁcant speed beneﬁts without compromising the quality of
the results. Software: OnACID is implemented in Python and is available at
https://github.com/ simonsfoundation/caiman as part of the CaImAn package
[13].
3
Results
Benchmarking on simulated data: To compare to ground truth spike trains,
we simulated a 2000 frame dataset taken at 30Hz over a 256 ? 256 pixel wide
FOV containing 400 ”donut” shaped neurons with Poisson spike trains (see
supplement for details). OnACID was initialized on the ﬁrst 500 frames. During
initialization, 265 active sources were accurately detected (Fig. S2). After the
full 2000 frames, the algorithm had detected and tracked all active sources, plus
one false positive (Fig. 2A). After detecting a neuron, we need to extract its
spikes with a short time-lag, to enable interesting closed loop experiments. To
quantify performance we measured the correlation of the inferred spike train
with the ground truth (Fig. 2B). We varied the lag in the online estimator, i.e.
the number of future samples observed before assigning a spike at time zero.
Lags of 2-5 yield already similar 5

Table 1: OnACID signiﬁcantly outperforms the oﬄine CNMF approach.
Benchmarking is against two independent manual annotations within the preci-
sion/recall (and their harmonic mean F1 score) framework. For each row-column
pair, the column dataset is regarded as the ground truth. F1 (precision, recall)
OnACID CNMF Labeler 2

Labeler 1 0.79 (0.87,0.72) 0.71 (0.74, 0.69) 0.89 (0.89,0.89)
Labeler 2 0.78 (0.86,0.71) 0.71 (0.75,0.68) -
CNMF 0.79 (0.83,0.75) -
results as the solution with unrestricted lag. A further requirement for on-
line closed-loop experiments is that the computational processing is fast enough.
To balance the computational load over frames, we distributed here the shape
update over the frames, while still updating each neuron every 30 frames on
average. Because the shape update is the last step of the loop in Algorithm 1,
we keep track of the time already spent in the iteration and increase or decrease
the number of updated neurons accordingly. In this way the frame processing
rate remained always higher than 30Hz (Fig. 2C). Application to in vivo 2p
mouse hippocampal data: Next we considered a larger scale (90K frames, 480
? 480 pixels) real 2p calcium imaging dataset taken at 30Hz (i.e., 50 minute
experiment). Motion artifacts were corrected prior to the analysis described
below. The online algorithm was initialized on the ﬁrst 1000 frames of the

7

dataset using a Python implementation of the CNMF algorithm found in the
CaImAn package [13]. During initialization 139 active sources were detected;
by the end of all 90K frames, 727 active sources had been detected and tracked
(5 of which were discarded due to their small size). Benchmarking against of-
ﬂine processing and manual annotations: We collected manual annotations from
two independent labelers who were instructed to ﬁnd round or donut shaped
neurons of similar size using the ImageJ Cell Magic Wand tool [31] given i) a
movie obtained by removing a running 20th percentile (as a crude background
approximation) and downsampling in time by a factor of 10, and ii) the max-
correlation image. The goal of this pre-processing was to suppress silent and
promote active cells. The labelers found respectively 872 and 880 ROIs. We
also compared with the CNMF algorithm applied to the whole dataset which
found 904 sources (805 after ﬁltering for size). To quantify performance we
used a precision/recall framework similar to [2]. As a distance metric between
two cells we used the Jaccard distance, and the pairing between diﬀerent an-
notations was computed using the Hungarian algorithm, where matches with
distance ¿ 0.7 were discarded4 . Table. 1 summarizes the results within the
precision/recall framework. The online algorithm not only matches but outper-
forms the oﬄine approach of CNMF, reaching high performance values (F1 =
0.79 and 0.78 against the two manual annotations, as opposed to 0.71 against
both annotations for CNMF). The two annotations matched closely with each
other (F1 = 0.89), indicating high reliability, whereas OnACID vs CNMF also
produced a high score (F1 = 0.79), suggesting signiﬁcant overlap in the mis-
matches between the two algorithms against manual annotations. Fig. 3 oﬀers a
more detailed view, where contour plots of the detected components are super-
imposed on the max-correlation image for the online (Fig. 3A) and oﬄine (Fig.
3B) algorithms (white) and the annotations of Labeler 1 (red) restricted to a
200?200 pixel part of the FOV. Annotations of matches and mismatches between
the online algorithm and the two labelers, as well as between the two labelers
in the entire FOV are shown in Figs. S3-S8. For the automated procedures
binary masks and contour plots were constructed by thresholding the spatial
footprint of each component at a level equal to 0.2 times its maximum value. A
close inspection at the matches between the online algorithm and the manual
annotation (Fig. 3A-left) indicates that neurons with a strong footprint in the
max-correlation image (indicating calcium transients with high amplitude com-
pared to noise and background/neuropil activity) are reliably detected, despite
the high neuron density and level of overlap. On the other hand, mismatches
(Fig. 3B-left) can sometimes be attributed to shape mismatches, manually se-
lected components with no signature in the max-correlation image (indicating
faint or possibly unclear activity) that are not detected by the online algorithm
(false negatives), or small partially visible processes detected by OnACID but
ignored by the labelers (”false” positives). 4 Note that the Cell Magic Wand
Tool by construction, tends to select circular ROI shapes whereas the results
of the online algorithm do not pose restrictions on the shapes. As a result the
computed Jaccard distances tend to be overestimated. This explains our choice
of a seemingly high mismatch threshold.

8

6
A
D
Mismatches
1 CDF
Matches
0.6 0.2
3
0 0.5 1 correlation coeﬃcient
E
2
Cost of tracking neurons? activity real time
32
1
28
Oﬄine
Human
0.3
0.9
20 ?m
Time [ms]
B
Human
800
20 16
500
12
200
8 0
3
10
20 30 40 Time [min]
inferred neurons
24
Online
50
Cost of updating shapes per neuron 0.65 Time [ms]
2 1
0.55 0.45
C 1
300
online oﬄine
r=0.89
80 Time [ms]
r=0.98 2 r=0.76
500 700 neurons

9

Cost of adding neurons real time
60 40 20
3
200 20 min
400 600 neurons
800
Figure 3: Application to an in vivo 50min long hippocampal dataset and
comparison against an oﬄine approach and manual annotation. A-left) Matched
inferred locations between the online algorithm (white) and the manual anno-
tation of Labeler 1 (red), superimposed on the maxcorrelation image. A-right)
False positive (white) and false negative (red) mismatches between the online
algorithm and a manual annotation. B) Same for the oﬄine CNMF algorithm
(grey) against the same manual annotation (red). The online approach outper-
forms the CNMF algorithm in the precision/recall framework (F1 score 0.77 vs
0.71). The images are restricted to a 200?200 pixel part of the FOV. Matches
and non-matches for the whole FOV are shown in the supplement. C) Examples
of inferred sources and their traces from the two algorithms and corresponding
annotation for three indentiﬁed neurons (also shown with orange arrows in pan-
els A,B left). The algorithm is capable of identifying new neurons once they
become active, and track their activity similarly to oﬄine approaches. D) Em-
pirical CDF of correlation coeﬃcients between the matched traces between the
online and the oﬄine approaches over the entire 50 minute traces. The ma-
jority of the correlation coeﬃcients has very high values suggesting that the
online algorithm accurately tracks the neural activity across time (see also cor-
relation coeﬃcients for the three examples shown in panel C). E) Timing of
the online process. Top: Time required per frame when no shapes are updated
and no neurons are updated (top). The algorithms is always faster than real
time in tracking neurons and scales mildly with the number of neurons. Time
required to update shapes per neuron (middle), and add new neurons (bottom)
as a function of the number of neurons. Adding neurons is slower but occurs
only sporadically aﬀecting only mildly the required processing time (see text for
details).

7
Fig. 3C shows examples of the traces from three selected neurons. OnACID
can detect and track neurons with very sparse spiking over the course of the
entire 50 minute experiment (Fig. 3C-top), and produce traces that are highly
correlated with their oﬄine counterparts. To examine the quality of the inferred
traces (where ground truth collection at such scale is both very strenuous and
severely impeded by the presence of background signals and neuropil activity),
we compared the traces between the online algorithm and the CNMF approach
on matched pairs of components. Fig. 3D shows the empirical cumulative distri-
bution function (CDF) of the correlation coeﬃcients from this comparison. The
majority of the coeﬃcients attain values close to 1, suggesting that the online
algorithm can detect new neurons once they become active and then reliably
track their activity. OnACID is faster than real time on average: In addition
to being more accurate, OnACID is also considerably faster as it required ?27

10

minutes, i.e., ? 2? faster than real time on average, to analyze the full dataset
(2 minutes for initialization and 25 for the online processing) as opposed to ?1.5
hours for the oﬄine approach and ?10 hours for each of the annotators (who
only select ROIs). Fig. 3E illustrates the time consumption of the various steps.
In the majority of the frames where no spatial shapes are being updated and no
new neurons are being incorporated, OnACID processing speed exceeds the data
rate of 30Hz (Fig. 3E-top), and this processing time scales only mildly with the
inclusion of new neurons. The cost of updating shapes and suﬃcient statistics
per neuron is also very low (¡ 1ms), and only scales mildly with the number of
existing neurons (Fig. 3E-middle). As argued before this cost can be distributed
among all the frames while maintaining faster than real time processing rates.
The expensive step appears when detecting and including one or possibly more
new neurons in the algorithm (Fig. 3E-bottom). Although this occurs only spo-
radically, several speedups can be potentially employed here to achieve beyond
real time at every frame (see also Discussion section), which would facilitate
zero-lag closed-loop experiments. Application to in vivo 2p mouse parietal cor-
tex data: As a second application to 2p data we used a 116,000 frame dataset,
taken at 30Hz over a 512?512 FOV (64min long). The ﬁrst 3000 frames were
used for initialization during which the CNMF algorithm found 442 neurons,
before switching to OnACID, which by the end of the experiment found a to-
tal of 752 neurons (734 after ﬁltering for size). Compared to two independent
manual annotations of 928 and 875 ROIs respectively, OnACID achieved F1
= 0.76, 0.79 signiﬁcantly outperforming CNMF (F1 = 0.65, 0.66 respectively).
The matches and mismatches between OnACID and Labeler 1 on a 200?200
pixel part of the FOV are shown in Fig. 4A. Full FOV pairings as well as preci-
sion/recall metrics are given in Table 2. Table 2: Comparison of performance of
OnACID and the CNMF algorithm using the precision/recall framework for the
parietal cortex 116000 frames dataset. For each row-column pair, the column
dataset is regarded as ground truth. The numbers in the parentheses are the
precision and recall, respectively, preceded by their harmonic mean (F1 score).
OnACID signiﬁcantly outperforms the oﬄine CNMF approach. F1 (precision,
recall) OnACID CNMF Labeler 2

Labeler 1 0.76 (0.86,0.68) 0.65 (0.70, 0.60) 0.89 (0.86,0.91)
Labeler 2 0.79 (0.86,0.72) 0.66 (0.74,0.59) -
CNMF 0.65 (0.55,0.82) -
For this dataset, rigid motion correction was also performed according to
the simple method of aligning each frame to the denoised (and registered) back-
ground from the previous frame. Fig. 4B shows that this approach produced
strikingly similar results to an oﬄine template based, rigid motion correction
method [25]. The diﬀerence in the displacements produced by the two methods
was less than 1 pixel for all 116,000 frames with standard deviations 0.11 and
0.12 pixel for the x and y directions, respectively. In terms of timing, OnACID
processed the dataset in 48 minutes, again faster than real time on average.
This also includes the time needed for motion correction, which on average took
5ms per frame (a bit less than 10 minutes in total).

4

11

Discussion - Future Work
Although at ﬁrst striking, the superior performance of OnACID compared
to oﬄine CNMF, for the datasets presented in this work, can be attributed to
several factors. Calcium transient events are localized both in space (spatial
footprint of a neuron), and in time (typically 0.3-1s for genetic indica8

Matches
B
Mismatches
x shift [pixels]
0.8
Online
y shift [pixels]
Human
A
Displacements
4 0 -4
oﬄine online
-8 4 0 -4 -8
oﬄine online
-12
20?m
0.2
0
20
Time [min]
40
60
Figure 4: Application to an in vivo 64min long parietal cortex dataset.
A-left) Matched inferred locations between the online algorithm (white) and
the manual annotation of Labeler 1 (red). A-right) False positive (white) and
false negative (red) mismatches between the online algorithm and a manual
annotation. B) Displacement vectors estimated by OnACID during motion
registration compared to a template based algorithm. OnACID estimates the
same motion vectors at a sub-pixel resolution (see text for more details).

tors). By looking at a short rolling buﬀer OnACID is able to more robustly
detect activity compared to oﬄine approaches that look at all the data simul-
taneously. Moreover, OnACID searches for new activity in the residuals buﬀer
that excludes the activity of already detected neurons, making it easier to de-
tect new overlapping components. Finally, oﬄine CNMF requires the a priori
speciﬁcation of the number of components, making it more prone to either false
positive or false negative components. For both the datasets presented above,
the analysis was done using the same space correlation threshold ?s = 0.9. This
strict choice leads to results with high precision and lower recall (see Tables 1
and 2). Results can be moderately improved by allowing a second pass of the
data that can identify neurons that were initially not selected. Moreover, by re-
laxing the threshold the discrepancy between the precision and recall scores can

12

be reduced, with only marginal modiﬁcations to the F1 scores (data not shown).
Our current implementation performs all processing serially. In principle, sig-
niﬁcant speed gains can be obtained by performing computations not needed at
each timestep (updating shapes and suﬃcient statistics) or occur only sporad-
ically (incorporating a new neuron) in a parallel thread with shared memory.
Moreover, diﬀerent online dictionary learning algorithms that do not require the
solution of an inverse problem at each timestep can potentially further speed up
our framework [17]. For detecting centroids of new sources OnACID examines
a static image obtained by computing the variance across time of the spatially
smoother residual buﬀer. While this approach works very well in practice it
eﬀectively favors shapes looking similar to a pre-deﬁned Gaussian blob (when
spatially smoothed). Diﬀerent approaches for detecting neurons in static images
can be possibly used here, e.g., [22], [2], [29], [27]. Apart from facilitating closed-
loop behavioral experiments and rapid general calcium imaging data analysis,
our online pipeline can be potentially employed to future, optical-based, brain
computer interfaces [6, 21] where high quality real-time processing is critical to
their performance. These directions will be pursued in future work.

Acknowledgments We thank Sue Ann Koay, Jeﬀ Gauthier and David Tank
(Princeton University) for sharing their cortex and hippocampal data with us.
We thank Lindsey Myers, Sonia Villani and Natalia Roumelioti for providing
manual annotations. We thank Daniel Barabasi (Cold Spring Harbor Labora-
tory) for useful discussions. AG, DC, and EAP were internally funded by the
Simons Foundation. Additional support was provided by SNSF P300P2 158428
(JF), and NIH BRAIN Initiative R01EB22913, DARPA N66001-15-C-4032,
IARPA MICRONS D16PC00003 (LP). 9

2 References

[1] Misha B Ahrens, Michael B Orger, Drew N Robson, Jennifer M Li, and
Philipp J Keller. Whole-brain functional imaging at cellular resolution us-
ing light-sheet microscopy. Nature methods, 10(5):413?420, 2013.
[2] Noah
Apthorpe, Alexander Riordan, Robert Aguilar, Jan Homann, Yi Gu, David
Tank, and H Sebastian Seung. Automatic neuron detection in calcium imag-
ing data using convolutional networks.
In Advances in Neural Information
Processing Systems, pages 3270?3278, 2016.
[3] Richard E Barlow, David J
Bartholomew, JM Bremner, and H Daniel Brunk. Statistical inference under
order restrictions: The theory and application of isotonic regression. Wiley New
York, 1972. [4] Matthew B Bouchard, Venkatakaushik Voleti, C?sar S Mendes,
Clay Laceﬁeld, Wesley B Grueber, Richard S Mann, Randy M Bruno, and
Elizabeth MC Hillman. Swept confocallyaligned planar excitation (scape) mi-
croscopy for high-speed volumetric imaging of behaving organisms. Nature pho-
tonics, 9(2):113?119, 2015. [5] Edward S Boyden, Feng Zhang, Ernst Bamberg,
Georg Nagel, and Karl Deisseroth. Millisecondtimescale, genetically targeted
optical control of neural activity. Nature neuroscience, 8(9):1263? 1268, 2005.
[6] Kelly B Clancy, Aaron C Koralek, Rui M Costa, Daniel E Feldman, and

13

Jose M Carmena. Volitional modulation of optically recorded calcium signals
during neuroprosthetic learning. Nature neuroscience, 17(6):807?809, 2014. [7]
Daniel A Dombeck, Anton N Khabbaz, Forrest Collman, Thomas L Adelman,
and David W Tank.
Imaging large-scale neural activity with cellular resolu-
tion in awake, mobile mice. Neuron, 56(1):43?57, 2007. [8] Valentina Emiliani,
Adam E Cohen, Karl Deisseroth, and Michael H?usser. All-optical interroga-
tion of neural circuits. Journal of Neuroscience, 35(41):13917?13926, 2015. [9]
Jeremy Freeman, Nikita Vladimirov, Takashi Kawashima, Yu Mu, Nicholas J
Sofroniew, Davis V Bennett, Joshua Rosen, Chao-Tsung Yang, Loren L Looger,
and Misha B Ahrens. Mapping brain activity at scale with cluster comput-
ing. Nature methods, 11(9):941?950, 2014.
[10] Johannes Friedrich, Weijian
Yang, Daniel Soudry, Yu Mu, Misha B Ahrens, Rafael Yuste, Darcy S Peterka,
and Liam Paninski. Multi-scale approaches for high-speed imaging and anal-
ysis of large neural populations. bioRxiv, page 091132, 2016.
[11] Johannes
Friedrich, Pengcheng Zhou, and Liam Paninski. Fast online deconvolution of
calcium imaging data. PLOS Computational Biology, 13(3):e1005423, 2017. [12]
Sahil Garg, Irina Rish, Guillermo Cecchi, and Aurelie Lozano. Neurogenesis-
inspired dictionary learning: Online model adaption in a changing world. arXiv
preprint arXiv:1701.06106, 2017. [13] A Giovannucci, J Friedrich, B Deverett, V
Staneva, D Chklovskii, and E Pnevmatikakis. Caiman: An open source toolbox
for large scale calcium imaging data analysis on standalone machines. Cosyne
Abstracts, 2017. [14] David S Greenberg and Jason ND Kerr. Automated cor-
rection of fast motion artifacts for two-photon imaging of awake animals. Jour-
nal of neuroscience methods, 176(1):1?15, 2009.
[15] Logan Grosenick, James
H Marshel, and Karl Deisseroth. Closed-loop and activity-guided optogenetic
control. Neuron, 86(1):106?139, 2015.
[16] Manuel Guizar-Sicairos, Samuel
T Thurman, and James R Fienup. Eﬃcient subpixel image registration algo-
rithms. Optics letters, 33(2):156?158, 2008. [17] Tao Hu, Cengiz Pehlevan, and
Dmitri B Chklovskii. A hebbian/anti-hebbian network for online sparse dictio-
nary learning derived from symmetric matrix factorization. In Signals, Systems
and Computers, 2014 48th Asilomar Conference on, pages 613?619. IEEE, 2014.
[18] Patrick Kaifosh, Jeﬀrey D Zaremba, Nathan B Danielson, and Attila Loson-
czy. Sima: Python software for analysis of dynamic ﬂuorescence imaging data.
Frontiers in neuroinformatics, 8:80, 2014.
[19] Julien Mairal, Francis Bach,
Jean Ponce, and Guillermo Sapiro. Online learning for matrix factorization and
sparse coding. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 11(Jan):19?60, 2010. 10
[20] Eran A Mukamel, Axel Nimmerjahn, and Mark J Schnitzer. Auto-
mated analysis of cellular signals from large-scale calcium imaging data. Neu-
ron, 63(6):747?760, 2009. [21] Daniel J O?shea, Eric Trautmann, Chandramouli
Chandrasekaran, Sergey Stavisky, Jonathan C Kao, Maneesh Sahani, Stephen
Ryu, Karl Deisseroth, and Krishna V Shenoy. The need for calcium imaging
in nonhuman primates: New motor neuroscience and brain-machine interfaces.
Experimental neurology, 287:437?451, 2017.
[22] Marius Pachitariu, Adam M
Packer, Noah Pettit, Henry Dalgleish, Michael Hausser, and Maneesh Sahani.
Extracting regions of interest from biological images with convolutional sparse
block coding.
In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages

14

[23] Marius Pachitariu, Carsen Stringer, Sylvia Schr?der,
1745?1753, 2013.
Mario Dipoppa, L Federico Rossi, Matteo Carandini, and Kenneth D Har-
ris. Suite2p: beyond 10,000 neurons with standard two-photon microscopy.
bioRxiv, page 061507, 2016.
[24] Adam M Packer, Lloyd E Russell, Henry
WP Dalgleish, and Michael H?usser. Simultaneous all-optical manipulation
and recording of neural circuit activity with cellular resolution in vivo. Nature
Methods, 12(2):140?146, 2015.
[25] Eftychios A Pnevmatikakis and Andrea
Giovannucci. Normcorre: An online algorithm for piecewise rigid motion cor-
rection of calcium imaging data. Journal of Neuroscience Methods, 291:83?94,
2017.
[26] Eftychios A Pnevmatikakis, Daniel Soudry, Yuanjun Gao, Timothy
A Machado, Josh Merel, David Pfau, Thomas Reardon, Yu Mu, Clay Laceﬁeld,
Weijian Yang, et al. Simultaneous denoising, deconvolution, and demixing of
calcium imaging data. Neuron, 89(2):285?299, 2016. [27] Stephanie Reynolds,
Therese Abrahamsson, Renaud Schuck, P Jesper Sj?str?m, Simon R Schultz,
and Pier Luigi Dragotti. Able: an activity-based level set segmentation algo-
rithm for two-photon calcium imaging data. eNeuro, pages ENEURO?0012,
2017.
[28] Spencer L Smith and Michael H?usser. Parallel processing of vi-
sual space by neighboring neurons in mouse visual cortex. Nature neuroscience,
13(9):1144?1149, 2010.
[29] Quico Spaen, Dorit S Hochbaum, and Roberto
As?n-Ach?. HNCcorr: A novel combinatorial approach for cell identiﬁcation in
calcium-imaging movies. arXiv preprint arXiv:1703.01999, 2017.
[30] Joshua
T Vogelstein, Adam M Packer, Timothy A Machado, Tanya Sippy, Baktash
Babadi, Rafael Yuste, and Liam Paninski. Fast nonnegative deconvolution for
spike train inference from population calcium imaging. Journal of neurophysi-
ology, 104(6):3691?3704, 2010. [31] Theo Walker. Cell magic wand tool, 2014.

11

15

