Welfare Guarantees from Data

Authored by:

Vasilis Syrgkanis

Darrell Hoy

Denis Nekipelov

Abstract

Analysis of eﬃciency of outcomes in game theoretic settings has been a
main item of study at the intersection of economics and computer science.
The notion of the price of anarchy takes a worst-case stance to eﬃciency
analysis, considering instance independent guarantees of eﬃciency. We
propose a data-dependent analog of the price of anarchy that reﬁnes this
worst-case assuming access to samples of strategic behavior. We focus on
auction settings, where the latter is non-trivial due to the private informa-
tion held by participants. Our approach to bounding the eﬃciency from
data is robust to statistical errors and mis-speciﬁcation. Unlike traditional
econometrics, which seek to learn the private information of players from
observed behavior and then analyze properties of the outcome, we directly
quantify the ineﬃciency without going through the private information.
We apply our approach to datasets from a sponsored search auction sys-
tem and ﬁnd empirical results that are a signiﬁcant improvement over
bounds from worst-case analysis.

1 Paper Body

A major ﬁeld at the intersection of economics and computer science is the anal-
ysis of the eﬃciency of systems under strategic behavior. The seminal work
of [6, 11] triggered a line of work on quantifying the ineﬃciency of computer
systems, ranging from network routing, resource allocation and more recently
auction marketplaces [10]. However, the notion of the price of anarchy suﬀers
from the pessimism of worst-case analysis. Many systems can be ineﬃcient in
the worst-case over parameters of the model, but might perform very well for
the parameters that arise in practice. Due to the large availability of datasets
in modern economic systems, we propose a data-dependent analog of the price
of anarchy, which assumes access to a sample of strategic behavior from the
system. We focus our analysis on auction systems where the latter approach is
more interesting due to the private information held by the participants of the
system, i.e. their private value for the item at sale. Since eﬃciency is a func-
tion of these private parameters, quantifying the ineﬃciency of the system from

1

samples of strategic behavior is non-trivial. The problem of estimation of the
ineﬃciency becomes an econometric problem where we want to estimate a func-
tion of hidden variables from observed strategic behavior. The latter is feasible
under the assumption that the observed behavior is the outcome of an equilib-
rium of the strategic setting, which connects observed behavior to unobserved
private information. Traditional econometric approaches to auctions [3, 8], ad-
dress such questions by attempting to exactly pin-point the private parameters
from the observed behavior and subsequently measuring the quantities of inter-
est, such as the eﬃciency of the allocation. The latter approach is problematic
in complex auction systems for two main reasons: (i) it leads to statistical in-
eﬃciency, (ii) it requires strong conditions on the connection between observed
behavior and private information. Even for a single-item ﬁrst-price auction,
uniform estimation of the private value of a player from T samples of observed
bids, can only be achieved at O(T 1/3 )-rates [3]. Moreover, uniquely identify-
ing the private information from the observed behavior, requires a one-to-one
mapping between the two 31st Conference on Neural Information Processing
Systems (NIPS 2017), Long Beach, CA, USA.

quantities. The latter requires strong assumptions on the distribution of pri-
vate parameters and can only be applied to simple auction rules. Our approach
bridges the gap between worst-case price of anarchy analysis and statistically
and modeling-wise brittle econometric analysis. We provide a data-dependent
analog of recent techniques for quantifying the worst-case ineﬃciency in auctions
[13, 4, 10], that do not require characterization of the equilibrium structure and
which directly quantify the ineﬃciency through best-response arguments, with-
out the need to pin-point the private information. Our approach makes minimal
? ? T )assumptions on the distribution of private parameters and on the auction
rule and achieves O( rates of convergence for many auctions used in practice,
such as the Generalized Second Price (GSP) auction [2, 14]. We applied our
approach to a real world dataset from a sponsored search auction system and
we portray the optimism of the data-dependent guarantees as compared to their
worst-case counterparts [1].

2
Preliminaries
We consider the single-dimensional mechanism design setting with n bidders.
The mechanism designer wants to allocate a unit of good to the bidders, subject
to some feasibility constraint on the vector of allocations (x1 , . . . , xn ). Let
X be the space of feasible allocations. Each bidder i has a private value vi ?
[0, H] per-unit of the good, and her utility when she gets allocation xi and is
asked to make a payment pi is vi ? xi ? pi . The value of each bidder is drawn
independently from distribution with CDF Fi , supported in Vi ? R+ and let
F = ?i Fi be the joint distribution. An auction A solicits a bid bi ? B from
each bidder i and decides on the allocation vector based on an allocation rule
X : B n ? X and a payment rule p : B n ? Rn . For a vector of values and bids,
the utility of a bidder is: Ui (b; vi ) = vi ? Xi (b) ? Pi (b). (1) A strategy
?i : Vi ? B, for each bidder i, maps the value of the bidder to a bid. Given
an auction A and distribution of values F, a strategy proﬁle ? is a Bayes-Nash

2

Equilibrium (BNE) if each bidder i with any value vi ? Vi maximizes her utility
in expectation over her opponents bids, by bidding ?i (vi ). The welfare of an
auction outcome is the expected utility generated for all the bidders, plus the
revenue of the auctioneer, which due to the form of bidder utilities boils down
to being the total value that the bidders get from the allocation. Thus the
expected utility of a strategy proﬁle ? is ? ? X W ELFARE(?; F) = Ev?F ? vi
? Xi (?(v))? (2) i?[n]

We denote with O PT(F) the expected optimal welfare: O PT(F) = Ev?F

[maxx?X

P
i?[n]
vi ? xi ].
Worst-case Bayes-Nash price of anarchy. The Bayesian price of anarchy of
an auction is deﬁned as the worst-case ratio of welfare in the optimal auction to
the welfare in a Bayes-Nash equilibrium of the original auction, taken over all
value distributions and over all equilibria. Let BN E(A, F) be the set of Bayes-
Nash equilibria of an auction A, when values are drawn from distributions F.
Then: P OA =

sup F,??BN E(F)
3
O PT(F) W ELFARE(?; F)
(3)
Distributional Price of Anarchy: Reﬁning the P OA with Data
We will assume that we observe T samples b1:T = {b1 , .
.

, bT } of
bid proﬁles from running T times an auction A. Each bid proﬁle bt is drawn
i.i.d. based on an unknown Bayes-Nash equilibrium ? of the auction, i.e.: let D
denote the distribution of the random variable ?(v), when v is drawn from F.
Then bt are i.i.d. samples from D. Our goal is to reﬁne our prediction on the
eﬃciency of the auction and compute a bound on the price of anarchy of the
auction conditional on the observed data set. More formally, we want to derive
statements of the form: conditional on b1:T , with probability at least 1 ? ?:
W ELFARE(?; F) ? ?1? O PT(F), where ?? is the empirical analogue of the
worst-case price of anarchy ratio. 2

.

Inﬁnite data limit We will tackle this question in two steps, as is standard
in estimation theory. First we will look at the inﬁnite data limit where we know
the actual distribution of equilibrium bids D. We deﬁne a notion of price of
anarchy that is tailored to an equilibrium bid distribution, which we refer to as
the distributional price of anarchy. In Section 4 we give a distribution-dependent
upper bound on this ratio for any single-dimensional auction. Subsequently, in
Section 5, we show how one can estimate this upper bound on the distributional
price of anarchy from samples. Given a value distribution F and an equilibrium
?, let D(F, ?) denote the resulting equilibrium bid distribution. We then deﬁne
the distributional price of anarchy as follows: Deﬁnition 1 (Distributional Price
of Anarchy). The distributional price of anarchy DP OA(D) of an auction A and
a distribution of bid proﬁles D, is the worst-case ratio of welfare in the optimal

3

allocation to the welfare in an equilibrium, taken over all distributions of values
and all equilibria that could generate the bid distribution D: DP OA(D) =

sup F,??BN E(F) s.t. D(F,?)=D
O PT(F) W ELFARE(?; F)
(4)
This notion has nothing to do with sampled data-sets, but rather is a hy-
pothetical worst-case quantity that we could calculate had we known the true
bid generating distribution D. What does the extra information of knowing D
give us? To answer this question, we ﬁrst focus on the optimization problem
each bidder faces. At any Bayes-Nash equilibrium each player must be best-
responding in expectation over his opponent bids. Observe that if we know
the rules of the auction and the equilibrium distribution of bids D, then the
expected allocation and payment function of a player as a function of his bid
are uniquely determined: xi (b; D) = Eb?i ?D?i [Xi (b, b?i )]

pi (b; D) = Eb?i ?D?i [Pi (b, b?i )] .
(5)
Importantly, these functions do not depend on the distribution of values F,
other than through the distribution of bids D. Moreover, the expected revenue
of the auction is also uniquely determined: ” # X R EV(D) = Eb?D Pi (b) ,
(6) i

Thus when bounding the distributional price of anarchy, we can assume that
these functions and the expected revenue are known. The latter is unlike the
standard price of anarchy analysis, which essentially needs to take a worst-case
approach to these quantities. Shorthand notation Through the rest of the paper
we will ﬁx the distribution D. Hence, for brevity we omit it from notation, using
xi (b), pi (b) and R EV instead of xi (b; D), pi (b; D) and R EV(D).

4
Bounding the Distributional Price of Anarchy
We ﬁrst upper bound the distributional price of anarchy via a quantity that
is relatively easy to calculate as a function of the bid distribution D and hence
will also be rather straightforward to estimate from samples of D, which we defer
to the next section. To give intuition about the upper bound, we start with a
simple but relevant example of bounding the distributional price of anarchy in
the case when the auction A is the single-item ﬁrst price auction. We then
generalize the approach to any auction A. 4.1
Example: Single-Item First Price Auction
In a single item ﬁrst price auction, the designer wants to auction a single
indivisible good. Thus the space of feasible allocations X , are ones where
only one player gets allocation xi = 1 and other players get allocation 0. The
auctioneer solicits bids bi from each bidder and allocates the good to the highest
bidder (breaking ties lexicographically), charging him his bid. Let D be the
equilibrium distribution of bids and let Gi be the CDF of the bid of player i.
For simplicity we assume that Gi is continuous (i.e. the distribution is atomless).
Q Then the expected allocation of a player i from submitting a bid b is equal
to xi (b) = G?i (b) = j6=i Gj (b) and his expected payment is pi (b) = b ? xi
(b), leading to expected utility: ui (b; vi ) = (vi ? b)G?i (b). 3

4

The quantity DP OA is a complex object as it involves the structure of
the set of equilibria of the given auction. The set of equilibria of a ﬁrst price
auction when bidders values are drawn from diﬀerent distributions is an horriﬁc
object.1 However, we can upper bound this quantity by a much simpler data-
dependent quantity by simply invoking the fact that under any equilibrium bid
distribution no player wants to deviate from his equilibrium bid. Moreover, this
data-dependent quantity can be much better than its worst-case counterpart
used in the existing literature on the price of anarchy. Lemma 1. Let A be
the single item ﬁrst price auction and let D be the equilibrium distribution of
maxi?[n] Eb?i ?D?i [maxj6=i bj ] ?(D) bids, then DP OA(D) ? 1?e . ??(D) ,
where ?(D) = Eb?D [maxi?[n] bi ] Proof. Let Gi be the CDF of the bid of each
player under distribution D. Moreover, let ? denote the equilibrium strategy
that leads to distribution D. By the equilibrium condition, we know that for all
vi ? Vi and for all b0 ? B, ui (?i (vi ); vi ) ? ui (b0 ; vi ) = (vi ? b0 ) ? G?i (b0
).

(7)
We will give a special deviating strategy used in the literature [13], that
will show that either the players equilibrium utility is large or the expected
maximum Rother bid is high. Let Ti denote the ? expected maximum other
bid which can be expressed as Ti = 0 1 ? G?i (z)dz. We consider the randomized
deviation where the player submits a randomized bid in z ? [0, vi (1 ? e?? )]
with PDF f (z) = ?(vi1?z) . Then the expected utility from this deviation is:
E0 [ui (b ; vi )] = b

Adding the quantity 1 ? Ti
vi (1?e?? )
Z
0
1 ?
0
R vi (1?e?? ) 0
1 (vi ? z) ? G?i (z)f (z)dz = ?
(1 ? G?i (z))dz ?
1 ? Ti
Z
vi (1?e?? )
G?i (z)dz
on both sides, we get: Eb0 [ui (b0 ; vi )] +
??
? vi 1?e? . Invoking the equilibrium condition we get: ui (?i (vi ); vi ) +

Subsequently, for any x?i ? [0, 1]: ui (?i (vi ); vi ) +

(8)
0
1 1 ? e?? Ti ? x?i ? vi ? x?i . ? ?
1 ? Ti
??
? vi 1?e?

5

.
(9)
If x?i is the expected allocation of player i under the eﬃcient allocation rule
Xi? (v) ? 1{vi = maxj vj }, then taking expectation of Equation (9) over vi
and adding across all players we get: ” # X X 1 1 ? e?? E [ui (?i (vi ); vi )] + E
Ti Xi? (v) ? O PT(F) (10) vi ?v i ? i P The theorem then follows by invoking
the fact that for any feasible allocation x: i Ti ? xi ? maxi Ti = ?(D)R EV(D),
using the fact that expected total agent utility plus total revenue at equilibrium
is equal to expected welfare at equilibrium and setting ? = ?(D). Comparison
with worst-case P OA In the worst-case, ?(D) is upper bounded by 1, leading
to the well-known worst-case price of anarchy ratio of the single-item ﬁrst price
auction of (1 ? 1/e)?1 , irrespective of the bid distribution D. However, if we
know the distribution D then we can explicitly estimate ?, which can lead to a
much better ratio (see Figure 1). Moreover, observe that even if we had samples
from the bid distribution D, then estimating ?(D) is very easy as it corresponds
to the ratio of two expectations, each of which can be estimating to within an O(
?1T ) error by a simple average and using standard concentration inequalities.
Even thought this improvement, when compared to the worst-case bound might
not be that drastic in the ﬁrst price auction, the extension of the analysis in
the next section will be applicable even to auctions where the analogue of the
quantity ?(D) is not even bounded in the worst-case.
In those settings, the
empirical version of the price of anarchy analysis is of crucial importance to
get any eﬃciency bound. 1 Even for two bidders with uniformly distributed
values U [0, a] and U [0, b], the equilibrium strategy requires solving a complex
system of partial diﬀerential equations, which took several years of research in
economics to solve (see [15, 7])

4
Price of Anarchy
4
3
2
1
0
1
2
3
4
?
Figure 1: The upper bound on the distributional price of anarchy of an

auction

?(D) 1?e??(D
as a function of ?(D).
Comparison with value inversion approach Apart from being just a primer
to our main general result in the next section, the latter result about the data-
dependent eﬃciency bound for the ﬁrst price auction, is itself a contribution
to the literature. It is notable to compare the latter result with the standard

6

econometric approach to estimating values in a ﬁrst price auction pioneered
by [3] (see also [8]). Traditional non-parametric auction econometrics use the
equilibrium best response condition to pin-point the value of a player from
his observed bid, by what is known as value inversion.
In particular, if the
function: ui (b0 ; vi ) = (vi ? b0 ) ? G?i (b0 ) has a unique maximum for each
vi and this maximum is strictly monotone in vi , then given the equilibrium
bid of a player bi and given a data distribution D we can reverse engineer the
value vi (bi ) that the player mustPhave. Thus if we know the bid distribution
D we can calculate the equilibrium welfare as Eb?D [ i vi (bi ) ? Xi (b)].
Moreover, we can calculate the expected optimal welfare as: Eb?D [maxi vi
(bi )]. Thus we can pin-point the distributional price of anarchy. However,
the latter approach suﬀers from two main drawbacks: (i) estimating the value
inversion function vi (?) uniformly over b from samples, can only happen at
very slow rates that are at least O(1/T 1/3 ) and which require diﬀerentiability
assumptions from the value and bid distribution as well as strong conditions that
the density of the value distribution is bounded away from zero in all the support
(with this lower bound constant entering the rates of convergence), (ii) the
main assumption of the latter approach is that the optimal bid is an invertible
function and that given a bid there is a single value that corresponds to that bid.
This assumption might be slightly benign in a single item ﬁrst price auction,
but becomes a harsher assumption when one goes to more complex auction
schemes. Our result in Lemma 1 suﬀers neither of these drawbacks: it admits
fast estimation rates from samples, makes no assumption on properties of the
value and bid distribution and does not require invertibility of the best-response
correspondence. Hence it provides an upper bound on the distributional price
of anarchy that is statistically robust to both sampling and mis-speciﬁcation
errors. The robustness of our approach comes with the trade-oﬀ that we are
now only estimating a bound on the eﬃciency of the outcome, rather than
exactly pinpointing it. 4.2

Generalizing to any Single-Dimensional Auction Setting
Our analysis on DP OA is based on the reformulation of the auction rules as
an equivalent pay-yourbid auction and then bounding the price of anarchy as a
function of the ratio of how much a player needs to pay in an equivalent pay-
your-bid auction, so as to acquire his optimal allocation vs. how much revenue is
the auctioneer collecting. For any auction, we can re-write the expected utility
of a bid b:

pi (b) ui (b; vi ) = xi (b) vi ? (11) xi (b) This can be viewed as the same
form of utility if the auction was a pay-your-bid auction and the player pi (b)
submitted a bid of xpii(b) (b) . We refer to this term as the price-per-unit and
denote it ppu(b) = xi (b) . Our analysis will be based on the price-per-unit
allocation rule x ?(?), which determines the expected allocation of a player as
a function of his price-per-unit. Given this notation, we can re-write the utility
that an agent achieves if he submits a bid that corresponds to a price-per-unit
of z as: u ?i (z; vi ) = x ?(z)(vi ? z). The latter is exactly the form of a
pay-your-bid auction. Our upper bound on the DP OA, will be based on the
inverse of the PPU allocation rule; let ?i (z) = x ??1 i (z) be the price-per-unit

7

of the cheapest bid that achieves allocation at least z. More formally, 5

?i (z) = minb—xi (b)?z {ppu(b)}. For simplicity, we assume that any allo-
cation z ? [0, 1] is achieveable by some high enough bid b.2 Given this we can
deﬁne the threshold for an allocation: Deﬁnition 2 (Average Threshold). The
average threshold for agent i is Z 1 Ti = ?i (z) dz (12) 0

In Figures 3 and 2 we provide a pictorial representation of these quantities.
Connecting with the previous section, for a ﬁrst price auction, the price-per-
unit function is ppu(b) = b, the price-per-unit allocation function is x ?i (b) =
G?i (b) and the threshold function is ?i (z) = G?1 ?i (z). The average R 1 ?1
R? threshold Ti is equal to 0 G?i (z)dz = 0 1 ? G?i (b)db, i.e. the expected
maximum other bid. 1

x ?i (ppu) = ?i?1 (ppu)
E[Allocation]
E[Allocation]
1
Ti
x ?(ppu)
ui (b) ppu(b)
vi
PPU
PPU
Figure 2: For any bid b with PPC ppu(b), the area of a rectangle between
(ppu(b), x ?i (ppu(b))) and (vi , 0) on the bid allocation rule is the expected
utility ui (b). The BNE action b? is chosen to maximize this area.

Figure 3: The average threshold is the area to the left of the price-per-unit

allocation rule, integrate from 0 to 1.

We now give our main theorem, which is a distribution-dependent bound
on DP OA, that is easy to compute give D and which can be easily estimated
from samples of D. This theorem is a generalization of Lemma 1 in the previous
section. Theorem 2 (Distributional Price of Anarchy Bound). For any auction
A in a single dimensional setting and for any bid distribution P D, the distri-
butional price of anarchy is bounded by DP OA(D) ? n maxx?X ?(D) i=1 Ti
?xi , where ?(D) = . R EV(D) 1?e??(D) Theorem 2 provides our main method
for bounding the distributional price of anarchy. All we need is to compute the
revenue R EV of the auction and the quantity: Pn T = maxx?X i=1 Ti ? xi
, (13) under the given bid distribution D. Both of these are uniquely deﬁned
quantities if we are given D. Moreover, once we compute Ti , the optimization
problem in Equation (13) is simply a welfare maximization problem, where each
player?s value per-unit of the good is Ti . Thus, the latter can be solved in poly-
nomial time, whenever the welfare maximization problem over the feasible set
X is polynomial-time solvable. Theorem 2 can be viewed as a bid distribution-
dependent analogue of the revenue covering framework [4] and of the smooth
mechanism framework [13]. In particular, the quantity ?(D) is the datadepe-
nent analogue of the worst-case ? quantity used in the deﬁnition of ?-revenue
covering in [4] and is roughly related to the ? quantity used in the deﬁnition of
a (?, ?)-smooth mechanism in [13].

8

5
Distributional Price of Anarchy Bound from Samples
In the last section, we assumed we were given distribution D and hence we
could compute the quantity ? = RTEV , which gave an upper bound on the
DP OA. We now show how we can estimate this 2

The theory can be easily extended to allow for diﬀerent maximum achievable
allocations by each player, by simply integrating the average threshold only up
until the largest such allocation.

6
quantity ? when given access to i.i.d. samples b1:T from the bid distribution
D. We will separately estimate T and R EV. The latter is simple expectation
and thereby can be easily estimated by an average at ?1T rates. For the former
we ﬁrst need to estimate Ti for each player i, which requires estimation of the
allocation and payment functions xi (?; D) and pi (?; D). Since both of these
functions are expected values over the equilibrium bids of opponents, we will
approximate them by their empirical analogues: T 1X xbi (b) = Xi (b, bt?i ) T
t=1

T 1X pbi (b) = Pi (b, bt?i ). T t=1
(14)
To bound the estimation error of the quantities T?i produced by using the
latter empirical estimates of the allocation and payment function, we need to
provide a uniform convergence property for the error of these functions over the
bid b. Since b takes values in a continuous interval, we cannot simply apply
a union bound. We need to make assumptions on the structure of the class of
functions FXi = {Xi (b, ?) : b ? B} and FPi = {Pi (b, ?) : b ? B}, so as
uniformly bound their estimation error. For this we resort to the technology of
Rademacher complexity. For a generic class of functions F and a sequence of
random variables Z 1:T , the Rademacher complexity is deﬁned as: ” # T 1X
t 1:T t RT (F, Z ) = E sup ? f (Z ) . (15) ? 1:T f ?F T t=1 where each ? t
? {?1/2} is an i.i.d. Rademacher random variable, which takes each of those
values with equal probabilities. The following well known theorem will be useful
in our derivations: Theorem 3 ([12]). Suppose that for any sample Z 1:T of size
T , RT (F, Z 1:T ) ? RT and suppose that functions in F take values in [0, H].
Then with probability 1 ? ?:

r T
1 X 2 log(4/?)
f (Zt ) ? E[f (Z)] ? 2RT + H (16) sup
T f ?F T t=1 This Theorem reduces our uniform error problem to bounding
the Rademacher complexity of classes FXi and FPi , since we immediately have
the following corollary (where we also use that the allocation functions lie in
[0, 1] and the payment functions lie in [0, H]): Corollary 4. Suppose that for
any sample b1:T of size T , the Rademacher complexity of classes FXi and
FPi is at most RT . Then with probability 1??/2, both sup —xbi (b)?xi (b)—
and sup —pbi (b)?pi (b)— b?B b?B p are at most 2RT + H 2 log(4/?) / T
. ? ? We now provide conditions under which the Rademacher complexity of
these classes is O(1/ T ). Lemma 5. Suppose that B = [0, B] and for each

9

[0, B]n?1 7? [0, 1] and
bidder i and each bi ? B, the functions Xi (bi , ?) :
Pi (b, ?) :
[0, B]n?1 7? [0, H] can be computed as ﬁnite superposition of (i)
coordinate-wise multiplication of bid vectors b?i with constants; (ii) comparison
indicators 1{? ¿ ?} of coordinates or constants; (iii) pairwise addition ? + ? of
coordinates or constants. The Rademacher p complexity for both classes on a
sample of size T is O log(T ) / T . The proof of this Lemma follows by standard
arguments of Rademacher calculus, together with VC arguments on the class of
pairwise comparisons. Those arguments can be found in [5, Lemma 9.9] and [9,
Lemma 11.6.28]. Thereby, we omit its proof. The assumptions of Lemma 5 can
be directly veriﬁed, for instance, for the sponsored search auctions where the
constants that multiply each bid correspond to quality factors of the bidders,
e.g. as in [2] and [14] and then the allocation and the payment is a function of
the rank of the weighted bid of a player. In that case the price and the allocation
rule are determined solely by the ranks and the values of the score-weighted bids
?i bi , as well as the position speciﬁc quality factors ?j , for each position j in
the auction. Next we turn to the analysis of the estimation errors on quantities
Ti . We consider the following plugpbi (b) in estimator for Ti : We consider the
empirical analog of function ?i (?) by ?bi (z) = inf xbi (b) . b?[0,B], xbi (b)?z

7
Then the empirical analog of Ti is obtained by: Z1 Tbi =
?bi (z) dz.
(17)
0
To bound the estimation error of Tbi , we need to impose an additional
condition that ensures that any non-zero allocation requires the payment from
the bidder at least proportional to that allocation. Assumption 6. We assume
that pi (x?1 i (?)) is Lipschitz-continuous and that the mechanism is worstcase
interim individually rational, i.e. pi (b) ? H ? xi (b). ? ? T ) rates of
convergence of Tbi to Ti and of the Under this assumption we can establish
that O( ? = maxx?X Pn T?i ? xi of the optimized threshold to T as well as
the empirical empirical analog T i=1 ? T analog Rd EV of the revenue to R
EV . Thus the quantity ? ?= d , will also converge to ? = RTEV at R EV
that rate. This implies the following ﬁnal conclusion of this section. Theorem
7. Under Assumption 6 and the premises of Lemma 5, with probability 1 ? ?:
! r O PT(F) H log(n/?) ? b ? n max{L, H} ? +O (18) W ELFARE(?; F) 1 ?
e?b? T

6
Sponsored Search Auction: Model, Methodology and Data Analysis
We consider a position auction setting where k ordered positions are assigned
to n bidders. An outcome m in a position auction is an allocation of positions to
bidders. m(j) denotes the bidder who is allocated position j; m?1 (i) refers to the
position assigned to bidder i. When bidder i is assigned to slot j, the probability
of click ci,j is the product of the click-through-rate of the slot ?j and the quality
score of the bidder, ?i , so ci,j = ?j ?i (in the data the quality scores for each
bidder are varying across diﬀerent auctions and we used the average score as a
proxy for the score of a bidder). Each advertiser has a value-per-click (VPC) vi

10

, which is not observed in the data and which we assume is drawn from some
distribution Fi . Our benchmark for welfare will be the welfare of the auction
that chooses a P feasible allocation to maximize the welfare generated, thus O
PT = Ev [maxm i ?i ?m?1 (i) vi ]. We consider data generated by advertisers
repeatedly participating in a sponsored search auction. The mechanism that is
being repeated at each stage is an instance of a generalized second price auction
triggered by a search query. The rules of each auction are as follows: Each
advertiser i is associated with a click probability ?i and a scoring coeﬃcient si
and is asked to submit a bid-per-click bi . Advertisers are ranked by their rank-
score qi = si ? bi and allocated positions in decreasing order of rank-score as
long as they pass a rank-score reserve r. All the mentioned sets of parameters
? = (s, ?, ?, r) and the bids b are observable in the data. We will denote with
?b,? (j) the bidder allocated in slot j under a bid proﬁle b and parameter proﬁle
?1 ?. We denote with ?b,? (i) the slot allocated to bidder i. If advertiser i is
allocated position j, then he pays only when he is clicked and his payment, i.e.
his ncost-per-click is the minimal bid o max s?

(j+1) ?b?
(j+1) ,r
b,? b,? he had to place to keep his position, which is: cpcij (b; ?) =
. Mapping si this setting to our general model, the allocation function of the
auction is Xi (b) = ???1 (i) ? ?, b,?

the payment function is Pi (b) = ???1 (i) ? ? ? cpci??1 (i) (b; ?) and the

utility function is: b,? b,?

Ui (b; vi ) = ???1 (i) ? ?i ? vi ? cpci??1 (i) (b; ?) . b,?
b,?
Data Analysis We applied our analysis to the BingAds sponsored search
auction system. We analyzed eleven phrases from multiple thematic categories.
For each phrase we retrieved data of auctions for the phrase for the period of
a week. For each phrase and bidder that participated in the auctions for the
phrase we computed the allocation curve by simulating the auctions for the
week under any alternative bid an advertiser could submit (bids are multiples
of cents). See Figure 4 for the price-per-unit allocation curves x ?i (?) = ?i?1
(?) for a subset of the advertisers for a speciﬁc search phrase. We estimated
the average threshold T?i for each bidder by numerically 8

?
phrase1 phrase2 phrase3 phrase4 phrase5 phrase6 phrase7 phrase8 phrase9

phrase10 phrase11

T ? ?= d R EV .511 .509 2.966 1.556 .386 .488 .459 .419 .441 .377 .502
1 DP OA
?? ?
= 1?e?? .783 .784 .320 .507 .829 .791 .802 .817 .809 .833 .786
Figure 4: (left) Examples of price-per-unit allocation curves for a subset of
six advertisers for a speciﬁc keyword during the period of a week. All axes are
normalized to 1 for privacy reasons.
(right) Distributional Price of Anarchy
analysis for a set of eleven search phrases on the BingAds system.

11

integrating these allocation curves along the y axis. We then applied the
approach described in ? = maxx?X P ? Section 3 for each of the search phrases,
computing the quantity T i?[n] Ti ? xi = P ? maxm(?) i Ti ? ?i ? ?m?1
(i) . The latter optimization is simply the optimal assignment problem where
each player?s value-per-click is T?i and can be performed by greedily assigning
players to slots in decreasing order of T?i . We then estimate the expected
revenue by the empirical revenue Rd EV . ?

T We portray our results on the estimate ? ?= d and the implied bound on
the distributional price R EV of anarchy for each of the eleven search phrases
in Table 4. Phrases are grouped based on thematic category. Even though the
worst-case price of anarchy of this auction is unbounded (since scores si are
not equal to qualities ?i , which is required in worst-case P OA proofs [1]), we
observe that empirically the price of anarchy is very good and on average the
guarantee is approximately 80% of the optimal. Even if si = ?i the worst-case
bound on the P OA implies guarantees of approx. 34% [1], while the DP OA we
estimated implies signiﬁcantly higher percentages, portraying the value of the
empirical approach we propose.

2 References

[1] Ioannis Caragiannis, Christos Kaklamanis, Maria Kyropoulou, Brendan Lucier,
Renato Paes Leme, and ?va Tardos. Bounding the ineﬃciency of outcomes in
generalized second price auctions. pages 1?45, 2014.
[2] Benjamin Edelman,
Michael Ostrovsky, and Michael Schwarz. Internet advertising and the gener-
alized second-price auction: Selling billions of dollars worth of keywords. The
American economic review, 97(1):242?259, 2007. [3] Emmanuel Guerre, Isabelle
Perrigne, and Quang Vuong. Optimal nonparametric estimation of ﬁrst-price
[4] Jason Hartline, Darrell Hoy,
auctions. Econometrica, 68(3):525?574, 2000.
and Sam Taggart. Price of Anarchy for Auction Revenue.
In ACM Confer-
ence on Economics and Computation, pages 693?710, New York, New York,
USA, 2014. ACM Press. [5] Michael R Kosorok. Introduction to empirical pro-
cesses and semiparametric inference. Springer Science & Business Media, 2007.
[6] Elias Koutsoupias and Christos Papadimitriou. Worst-case equilibria.
In
STACS 99, pages 404?413. Springer, 1999. [7] Vijay Krishna. Auction Theory.
Academic Press, March 2002. [8] H. J. Paarsch and H. Hong. An Introduction
to the Structural Econometrics of Auction Data. MIT Press, 2006. 9

[9] D. Pollard. Convergence of Stochastic Processes. Springer-Verlag, 1984.
[10] Tim Roughgarden, Vasilis Syrgkanis, and ?va Tardos. The price of anar-
chy in auctions. CoRR, abs/1607.07684, 2016. [11] Tim Roughgarden and Eva
Tardos. How bad is selﬁsh routing? J. ACM, 49(2):236?259, March 2002. [12]
S. Shalev-Shwartz and S. Ben-David. Understanding Machine Learning: From
Theory to Algorithms. Understanding Machine Learning: From Theory to Al-
gorithms. Cambridge University Press, 2014.
[13] Vasilis Syrgkanis and Eva
Tardos. Composable and eﬃcient mechanisms. In ACM Symposium on Theory
of Computing, pages 211?220, 2013.
[14] Hal R Varian. Online ad auctions.

12

[15] William Vickrey.
The American Economic Review, pages 430?434, 2009.
Counterspeculation, auctions, and competitive sealed tenders. The Journal of
Finance, 16(1):8?37, 1961.

10

13

