Random Permutation Online Isotonic Regression

Authored by:

Wouter M. Koolen
Wojciech Kotlowski

Alan Malek

Abstract

We revisit isotonic regression on linear orders, the problem of ﬁtting
monotonic functions to best explain the data, in an online setting.
It
was previously shown that online isotonic regression is unlearnable in a
fully adversarial model, which lead to its study in the ﬁxed design model.
Here, we instead develop the more practical random permutation model.
We show that the regret is bounded above by the excess leave-one-out
loss for which we develop eﬃcient algorithms and matching lower bounds.
We also analyze the class of simple and popular forward algorithms and
recommend where to look for algorithms for online isotonic regression on
partial orders.

1 Paper Body

A function f : R ? R is called isotonic (non-decreasing) if x ? y implies f (x)
? f (y). Isotonic functions model monotonic relationships between input and
output variables, like those between drug dose and response [25] or lymph node
condition and survival time [24]. The problem of isotonic regression is to ﬁnd the
isotonic function that best explains a given data set or population distribution.
The isotonic regression problem has been extensively studied in statistics [1, 24],
which resulted in eﬃcient optimization algorithms for ﬁtting isotonic functions
to the data [7, 16] and sharp convergence rates of estimation under various model
assumptions [26, 29]. In online learning problems, the data arrive sequentially,
and the learner is tasked with predicting each subsequent data point as it arrives
[6]. In online isotonic regression, the natural goal is to predict the incoming data
points as well as the best isotonic function in hindsight. Speciﬁcally, for time
steps t = 1, .
, T , the learner observes an instance xi ? R, makes a
prediction ybi of the true label yi , which is assumed to lie in [0, 1]. There is no
restriction that the labels or predictions be isotonic. We evaluate a prediction
ybi by its squared loss (b yi ? yi )2 . The quality of an algorithm is measured by
its PT yi ? yi )2 ? L?T , where L?T is the loss of the best isotonic function on
the entire data regret, t=1 (b sequence. Isotonic regression is nonparametric:

.

.

1

the number of parameters grows linearly with the number of data points. It is
thus natural to ask whether there are eﬃcient, provably low regret algorithms
for online isotonic regression. As of yet, the picture is still very incomplete in
the online setting. The ﬁrst online results were obtained in the recent paper
[14] which considered linearly ordered domains in the adversarial ﬁxed design
model, i.e. a model in which all the inputs x1 , . . . , xT are given to the learner
before the start of prediction. The authors show that, due to the nonparametric
nature of the problem, many textbook online learning algorithms fail to learn
at all (including Online Gradient Descent, Follow the Leader and Exponential
Weights) in the sense that their worst-case regret grows 1 linearly with the
number of data points. They prove a ?(T 3 ) worst case regret lower bound,
and 1 ? 3 ) regret. Unfortunately, the ﬁxed design develop a matching algorithm
that achieves the optimal O(T assumption is often unrealistic. This leads us
to our main question: Can we design methods for online isotonic regression
that are practical (do not hinge on ﬁxed design)? 31st Conference on Neural
Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017), Long Beach, CA, USA.

Our contributions Our long-term goal is to design practical and eﬃcient
methods for online isotonic regression, and in this work we move beyond the
ﬁxed design model and study algorithms that do not depend on future instances.
Unfortunately, the completely adversarial design model (in which the instances
are selected by an adaptive adversary) is impossibly hard: every learner can
suﬀer linear regret in this model [14]. So in order to drop the ﬁxed design as-
sumption, we need to constrain the adversary in some other way. In this paper
we consider the natural random permutation model, in which all T instances and
labels are chosen adversarially before the game begins but then are presented
to the learner in a random order. This model corresponds with the intuition
that the data gathering process (which ﬁxes the order) is independent of the
underlying data generation mechanism (which ﬁxes instances and labels). We
will show that learning is possible in the random permutation model (in fact we
present a reduction ? 13 ) upper bound on showing that it is not harder than
adversarial ﬁxed design) by proving an O(T regret for an online-to-batch conver-
sion of the optimal ﬁxed design algorithm from [14] (Section 3). Our main tool
for analyzing the random permutation model is the leave-one-out loss, drawing
interesting connections with cross-validation and calibration. The leave-one-out
loss on a set of t labeled instances is the error of the learner predicting the
i-th label after seeing all remaining t ? 1 labels, averaged uniformly over i =
1, .
, t. We begin by proving a general correspondence between regret
and leave-one-out loss for the random permutation model in Section 2.1, which
allows us to use excess leave-one-out loss as a proxy for regret. We then describe
a version of online-to-batch conversion that relates the ﬁxed design model with
the random permutation model, resulting in an ? 31 ) regret. algorithm that
attains the optimal O(T Section 4 then turns to the computationally eﬃcient
and natural class of forward algorithms that use an oﬄine optimization oracle
to form their prediction. This class contains most common online 1 isotonic
regression algorithms. We then show a O(T 2 ) upper bound on the regret for
the entire class, 1 which improves to O(T 3 ) for the well-speciﬁed case where

.

.

2

the data are in fact generated from an isotonic function plus i.i.d. noise (the
most common model in the statistics literature). 1

While forward algorithms match the lower bound for the well-speciﬁed case,
there is a factor T 6 gap in the random permutation case. Section 4.6 proposes
a new algorithm that calls a weighted oﬄine oracle with a large weight on the
current instance. This algorithm can be eﬃciently computed via [16]. We prove
necessary bounds on the weight. Related work Oﬄine isotonic regression has
been extensively studied in statistics starting from work by [1, 4]. Applications
range across statistics, biology, medicine, psychology, etc.
[24, 15, 25, 22, 17].
In statistics, isotonic regression is studied in generative models [26, 3, 29]. In
machine learning, isotonic regression is used for calibrating class probability
estimates [28, 21, 18, 20, 27], ROC analysis [8], training Generalized Linear
Models and Single Index Models[12, 11], data cleaning [13], and ranking [19].
Fast algorithms for partial ordering are developed in [16]. In the online setting,
[5] bound the minimax regret for monotone predictors under logarithmic loss and
[23, 10] study online nonparametric regression in general. Eﬃcient algorithms
and worst-cases regret bounds for ﬁxed design online isotonic regression are
studied in [14]. Finally, the relation between regret and leave-one-out loss was
pioneered by [9] for linear regression.

2
Problem Setup
Given a ﬁnite set of instances {x1 , .

, xt } ? R, a function f : {x1 , .
. . , xt } ? [0, 1] is isotonic (non-decreasing) if xi ? xj implies f (xi ) ? f (xj )
for all i, j ? {1, . . . , t}. Given a set of labeled instances D = {(x1 , y1 ), . .
. , (xt , yt )} ? R ? [0, 1], let L? (D) denote the total squared loss of the best
isotonic function on D, t X L? (D) := min (yi ? f (xi ))2 . isotonic f

.

.

i=1
This convex optimization problem can be solved by the celebrated Pool
Adjacent Violators Algorithm (PAVA) in time linear in t [1, 7]. The optimal
solution, called the isotonic regression function, is piecewise constant and its
value on any of its levels sets equals the average of labels within that set [24]. 2
Online isotonic regression in the random permutation model is deﬁned as
follows. At the beginning of the game, the adversary chooses data instances x1
¡ . . . ¡ xT 1 and labels y1 , . . . , yT . A permutation ? = (?1 , . . . , ?T )
of {1, . . . , T } is then drawn uniformly at random and used to determine the
order in which the data will be revealed. In round t, the instance x?t is revealed
to the learner who then predicts yb?t . Next, the learner observes the true label
y?t and incurs the squared loss (b y?t ? y?t )2 . ? ? For a ﬁxed permutation
?, we use the shorthand notation Lt = L ({(x?1 , y?1 ), . . . , (x?t , y?t )}) to
denote the optimal isotonic regression loss of the ﬁrst t labeled instances (L?t
will clearly depend on ?, except for the case t = T ). The goal of the learner is
to minimize the expected regret, X

T T X RT := E? (y?t ? yb?t )2 ? L?T = rt , t=1
t=1
where we have decomposed the regret into its per-round increase, h i rt :=

E? (y?t ? yb?t )2 ? L?t + L?t?1 ,

3

(1)
L?0
:= 0. To simplify the analysis, let us assume that the prediction strategy
does not depend with on the order in which the past data were revealed (which
is true for all algorithms considered in this paper). Fix t and deﬁne D = {(x?1 ,
y?1 ), . . . , (x?t , y?t )} to be the set of ﬁrst t labeled instances. Furthermore,
let D?i = D{(x?i , y?i )} denote the set D with the instance from round i
removed. Using this notation, the expression under the expectation in (1) can
be written as 2 y?t ? yb?t (D?t ) ? L? (D) + L? (D?t ), where we made the
dependence of yb?t on D?t explicit (and used the fact that it only depends on
the set of instances, not on their order). By symmetry of the expectation over
permutations with respect to the indices, we have h h 2 i 2 i

E? y?t ? yb?t (D?t ) = E? y?i ? yb?i (D?i ) , and E? L? (D?t ) = E? L?

(D?i ) , for all i = 1, . . . , t. Thus, (1) can as well be rewritten as:

X t
2 1 y?i ? yb?i (D?i ) + L? (D?i ) ? L? (D) . rt = E? t i=1 Let us denote the
expression inside the expectation by rt (D) to stress its dependence on the set of
instances D, but not on the order in which they were revealed. If we can show
that rt (D) ? Bt holds PT for all t, then its expectation has the same bound, so
RT ? t=1 Bt . 2.1

Excess Leave-One-Out Loss and Regret
Our main tool for analyzing the random permutation model is the leave-
one-out loss. In the leave-one-out model, there is no sequential structure. The
adversary picks a data set D = {(x1 , y1 ), . . . , (xt , yt )} with x1 ¡ . . . ¡ xt .
An index i is sampled uniformly at random, the learner is given D?i , the entire
data set except (xi , yi ), and predicts ybi (as a function of D?i ) on instance
xi . We call the diﬀerence between the expected loss of the learner and L? (D)
the expected excess leave-one-out loss: ! X

t 2 1 ? ‘oot (D) := yi ? ybi (D?i ) ? L (D) . (2) t i=1 The random permutation
model has the important property that the bound on the excess leave-one-out
loss of a prediction algorithm translates into a regret bound. A similar result
has been shown by [9] for expected loss in the i.i.d. setting. Lemma 2.1. rt (D)
? ‘oot (D) for any t and any data set D = {(x1 , y1 ), . . . , (xt , yt )}. Pt 2
Proof. As x1 ¡ . . . ¡ xt , let (y1? , . . . , yt? ) = argminf1 ?...?ft i=1 (yi ? ﬁ )
be the isotonic Pt ? ? regression function on D. From the deﬁnition of L , we
can see that L (D) = i=1 (yi? ? yi )2 ? L? (D?i ) + (yi ? yi? )2 . Thus, the
regret increase rt (D) is bounded by rt (D) =

t X (yi ? ybi )2 + L? (D?i ) i=1
t
? L? (D) ?
t X (yi ? ybi )2 ? (yi ? y ? )2 i
i=1
1
t
= ‘oot (D).

4

We assume all points xt are distinct as it will signiﬁcantly simplify the pre-
sentation. All results in this paper are also valid for the case x1 ? . . . ? xT
.

3
However, we note that lower bounds for ‘oot (D) do not imply lower bounds
on regret. In what follows, our strategy will be to derive bounds ‘oot (D) ? Bt
for various algorithms, from PT which the regret bound RT ? t=1 Bt can be
immediately obtained. From now on, we abbreviate ‘oot (D) to ‘oot , (as D is
clear from the context); we will also consistently assume x1 ¡ . . . ¡ xt . 2.2

Noise free case
As a warm-up, we analyze the noise-free case (when the labels themselves
are isotonic) and demonstrate that analyzing ‘oot easily results in an optimal
bound for this setting. Proposition 2.2. Assume that the labels satisfy y1 ? y2 ?
. . . ? yt . The prediction ybi that is the linear interpolation between adjacent
labels ybi = 12 (yi?1 + yi+1 ), has ‘oot ?

1 1 , and thus RT ? log(T + 1). 2t 2
Pt 1 2 ? Proof. For ?i := yi ? yi?1 , it is easy to check that ‘oot = 4t i=1
(?i+1 ? ?i ) because the L (D) term is zero. This expression is a convex function
of ?1 , . . . , ?t+1 . Note that ?i ? 0 for each Pt+1 i = 1, . . . , t + 1, and
i=1 ?i = 1. Since the maximum of a convex function is at the boundary of the
feasible region, the maximizer is given by ?i = 1 for some i ? {1, . . . , t + 1},
and ?j = 0 for all j ? {1, . . . , t + 1}, j 6= i. This implies that ‘oot ? (2t)?1 .
2.3

General Lower Bound
In [14], a general lower bound was derived showing that the regret of any
online isotonic regression 1 procedure is at least ?(T 3 ) for the adversarial setup
(when labels and the index order were chosen adversarially). This lower bound
applies regardless of the order of outcomes, and hence it is also a lower bound
for the random permutation model. This bound translates into ‘oot = ?(t?2/3
).

3
Online-to-batch for ﬁxed design
Here, we describe an online-to-batch conversion that relates the adversarial
ﬁxed design model with the random permutation model considered in this paper.
In the ﬁxed design model with time horizon Tfd the learner is given the points
x1 , . . . , xTfd in advance (which is not the case in the random permutation
model), but the adversary chooses the order ? in which the labels are revealed
(as opposed to ? being drawn at random). We can think of an algorithm for
ﬁxed design as a prediction function
ybfd x?t y?1 , . . . , y?t?1 , {x1 , . . . , xTfd } , for any order ?, any set {x1 ,
. . . , xTfd } (and hence any time horizon Tfd ), and any time t. This notation
is quite heavy, but makes it explicit that the learner, while predicting at point
x?t , knows the previously revealed labels and the whole set of instances. In the
random permutation model, at trial t, the learner only knows the previously
revealed t ? 1 labeled instances and predicts on the new instance. Without loss
of generality, denote the past instances by D?i = {(x1 , y1 ), .
, (xi?1 ,

.

.

5

.

.

yi?1 ), (xi+1 , yi+1 ), . . . (xt , yt )}, and the new instance by xi , for some
, t}. Given an algorithm for ﬁxed design ybfd , we construct a
i ? {1, .
prediction ybt = ybt (D?i , xi ) of the algorithm in the random permutation
model. The reduction goes through an online-to-batch conversion. Speciﬁcally,
at trial t, given past labeled instances D?i , and a new point xi , the learner
plays the expectation of the prediction of the ﬁxed design algorithm with time
horizon T fd = t and points {x1 , . . . , xt } under a uniformly random time
from the past j ? {1, . . . , t} and a random permutation ? on {1, . . . , t},
with ?t = i, i.e.2 X

t
1 fd ybt = E{?:?t =i} yb (xi —y?1 , . . . , y?j?1 , {x1 , . . . , xt } . (3) t j=1
2 Choosing the prediction as an expectation is elegant but ineﬃcient. However,
the proof indicates that we might as well sample a single j and a single random
permutation ? to form the prediction and the reduction would also work in
expectation.

.

.

.

.

4
Note that this is a valid construction, as the right hand side only depends
on D?i and xi , which are known to the learner in a random permutation model
at round t. We prove (in Appendix A) that the excess leave-one-out loss of yb
at trial t is upper bounded by the expected regret (over all permutations) of
, t divided by t: Theorem 3.1. Let D = {(x1 , y1 ),
ybfd in trials 1, .
, (xt , yt )} be a set of t labeled instances. Fix any algorithm ybfd for
.
online adversarial isotonic regression with ﬁxed design, and let Regt (b y fd —
?) denote its regret on D when the labels are revealed in order ?. The random
permutation learner yb from (3) ensures y fd — ?)]. ‘oot (D) ? 1t E? [Regt (b 1
? 3 ) ﬁxed design regret result from [14]. This constructions allows im-
mediate transport of the O(T fd Theorem 3.2. There is an algorithm for the
random-permutation model with excess leave-one-out ? ? 23 ) and hence ex-
pected regret RT ? P O(t ? 13 ). ? ? 32 ) = O(T loss ‘oot = O(t t

.

.

.

.

.

, yi?1 , yi+1 , .

, yt ) is the label vector, y ? = (y1? , .

4
Forward Algorithms
For clarity of presentation, we use vector notation in this section: y = (y1
, yt? ) is the isotonic
.
, .
, yt ) is y
.
regression function, and y?i = (y1 , .
with i-th label removed. Moreover, keeping in mind that x1 ¡ .
¡ xt , we
.
can drop xi ?s entirely from the notation and refer to an instance xi simply
by its index i. Given labels y?i and some index i to predict on, we want a
good prediction for yi . Follow the Leader (FL) algorithms, which predict using
the best isotonic function on the data seen so far, are not directly applicable
to online isotonic regression: the best isotonic function is only deﬁned at the
observed data instances and can be arbitrary (up to monotonicity constraint)
otherwise. Instead, we analyze a simple and natural class of algorithms which
we dub forward algorithms3 . We deﬁne a forward algorithm, or FA, to be any
algorithm that estimates a label yi0 ? [0, 1] (possibly dependent on i and y?i ),
and plays with the FL strategy on the sequence of past data including the new
instance with the estimated label, i.e. performs oﬄine isotonic regression on y

.
.

6

0 , X

t yb = argmin (yj0 ? fj )2 , where y 0 = (y1 , . . . , yi?1 , yi0 , yi+1 , . . .

, yt ). f1 ?...?ft

j=1
Then, FA predicts with ybi , the value at index i of the oﬄine function of
the augmented data. Note that if the estimate turned out to be correct (yi0
= yi ), the forward algorithm would suﬀer no additional loss for that round.
Forward algorithms are practically important: we will show that many popu-
lar algorithms can be cast as FA with a particular estimate. FA automatically
inherit any computational advances for oﬄine isotonic regression; in particular,
they scale eﬃciently to partially ordered data [16]. To our best knowledge, we
are ﬁrst to give bounds on the performance of these algorithms in the online
setting. Alternative formulation We can describe a FA using a minimax repre-
sentation of the isotonic regression [see, e.g., 24]: the optimal isotonic regression
y ? satisﬁes yi? = min max y ‘,r = max min y ‘,r , r?i ‘?i

Pr
‘?i r?i
(4)
yj
j=‘ where y ‘,r = r¿+1 . The ?saddle point? (‘i , ri ) for which yi? = y ‘i
,ri , speciﬁes the boundaries of ? the level set {j : yj = yi? } of the isotonic
regression function that contains i.

It follows from (4) that isotonic regression is monotonic with respect to
labels: for any two label sequences y and z such that yi ? zi for all i, we have
yi? ? zi? for all i. Thus, if we denote the predictions for label estimates yi0
= 0 and yi0 = 1 by ybi0 and ybi1 , respectively, the monotonicity implies that
any FA has ybi0 ? ybi ? ybi1 . Conversely, using the continuity of isotonic
regression y ? as a function of y, (which follows from (4)), we can show that for
any prediction ybi with ybi0 ? ybi ? ybi1 , there exists an estimate yt0 ? [0,
1] that could generate this prediction. Hence, we can equivalently interpret FA
as an algorithm which in each trial predicts with some ybi in the range [b yi0 ,
ybi1 ]. 3

The name highlights resemblance to the Forward algorithm introduced by

[2] for exponential family models.

5
4.1
Instances
With the above equivalence between forward algorithms and algorithms that
predict in [b yi0 , ybi1 ], we can show that many of the well know isotonic
regression algorithms are forward algorithms and thereby add weight to our next
section where we prove regret bounds for the entire class. Isotonic regression
with interpolation (IR-Int)[28] Given y?i and index i, the algorithm ﬁrst ? ?
computes f ? , the isotonic regression of y?i , and then predicts with ybiint =
21 ﬁ?1 + ﬁ+1 , where ? we used f0? = 0 and ft+1 = 1. To see that this is a
FA, note that if we use estimate yi0 = ybiint , the ? ? , yi0 , ﬁ+1 , . . . , ft?
). isotonic regression of y 0 = (y1 , . . . , yi?1 , yi0 , yi+1 , . . . , yt ) is yb

7

.

.

, ﬁ?1 ? This is because: i) yb is isotonic by construction; ii) f
= (f1? , .
has the smallest squared error loss for y?t among isotonic functions; and iii) the
loss of yb on point yi0 is zero, and the loss of yb on all other points is equal to
the loss of f ? . Direct combination of ybi0 and ybi1 . It is clear from Section
4, that any algorithm that predicts ybi = ?i ybi0 + (1 ? ?i )b yi1 for some ?i ?
[0, 1] is a FA. The weight ?i can be set to a constant (e.g., ?i = 1/2), or can be
chosen depending on ybi1 and ybi0 . Such algorithms were considered by [27]:
log-IVAP : ybilog =

ybi1
ybi1 , + 1 ? ybi0
Brier-IVAP : ybiBrier =
1 + (b yi0 )2 ? (1 ? ybi1 )2 . 2
It is straightforward to show that both algorithms satisfy ybi0 ? ybi ? ybi1
and are thus instances of FA. Last-step minimax (LSM). LSM plays the minimax
strategy with one round remaining, n o ybi = argmin max (b y ? yi )2 ? L? (y)
, y b?[0,1] yi ?[0,1]

, yi?1 , b, yi+1 , .

where L? (y) is the isotonic regression loss on y. Deﬁne L?b = L? (y1 , . .
, yt ) for b ? {0, 1}, i.e. L?b is the loss of isotonic
.
regression function with label estimate yi0 = b. In ? 1+L? 0 ?L1 Appendix B
we show that ybi = and it is also an instance of FA. 2 4.2

.

.

Bounding the leave-one-out loss q We now give a O( logt t ) bound on the
leave-one-out loss for forward algorithms.
Interestingly, the bound holds no
matter what label estimate the algorithm uses. The proof relies on the stability
of isotonic regression with respect to a change of a single label. While the
bound looks suboptimal in light of Section 2.3, we will argue in Section 4.5
that the bound is actually tight (up to a logarithmic factor) for one FA and
experimentally verify that all other mentioned forward algorithms also have a
tight lower bound of that form for the same sequence of outcomes. We will
bound ‘oot by deﬁning ?i = ybi ? yi? and using the following simple inequality:
t

t
t
1X 1 X 2X (b yi ? yi )2 ? (yi? ? yi )2 = (b yi ? yi? )(b yi + yi? ? 2yi ) ?

—?i —. t i=1 t i=1 t i=1 q

log t Theorem 4.1. Any forward algorithm has ‘oot = O . t ‘oot =
Proof. Fix some forward algorithm. For any i, let {j : yj? = yi? } = {‘i ,
. . . , ri }, for some ‘i ? i ? ri , be the level set of isotonic regression at level
yi? . We need the stronger version of the minimax representation, shown in
Appendix C: yi? = min y ‘i ,r = max y ‘,ri . r?i

‘?i
(5)
n h o k We partition the points {1, . . . , t} into K consecutive segments:

Sk = i : yi? ? k?1 , for K K
K?1 ? ? k = 1, . . . , K ? 1 and SK = i : yi ? K . Due to monotonicity of y
, Sk are subsets of the form {‘k , . . . , rk } (where we use rk = ‘k ? 1 if Sk is

8

empty). From the deﬁnition, every level set of y ? is contained in Sk for some
k, and each ‘k (rk ) is a left-end (right-end) of some level set. 6

Now, choose some index i, and let Sk be such that i ? Sk . Let yi0 be the
estimate of the FA, and let y 0 = (y1 , . . . , yi?1 , yi0 , yi+1 , . . . , yt ). The
minimax representation (4) and deﬁnition of FA imply yi0 ? yi o r?i r?i ‘?i r?i
r ? ‘k + 1 yi0 ? yi yi0 ? yi ? min y ‘k ,r + min ? min y ‘k ,r + min r?i r?i r ?
‘k + 1 r?i r ? ‘k + 1 r¿k by (5) 1 ?1 1 1 ? y‘?k + min ? y‘?k ? ? yi? ? ? . r?i
r ? ‘k + 1 i ? ‘k + 1 K i ? ‘k + 1 1 1 + rk ?i+1 . Hence, we can bound —?i —
= —b A symmetric argument gives ybi ? yi? + K yi ? yi? — ?

P —Sk — 1 1 1 i?Sk —?i — ? K + 2 1 + log —Sk — , K + max i¿k +1
, rk ?i+1 . Summing over i ? Sk yields which allows the bound K 2X 2 ‘oot ?
—?i — ? + 4 (1 + log t). t i K t p The theorem follows from setting K = ?( t/
log t). n ybi = max min y 0‘,r ? min y 0‘k ,r = min y ‘k ,r +

4.3
Forward algorithms for the well-speciﬁed case
p P While the ‘oot upper bound of the previous section yields a regret
bound RT ? t O( log t/t) = ? 12 ) that is a factor O(T 16 ) gap from the lower
bound in Section 2.3, there are two pieces of good O(T news. First, forward
algorithms do get the optimal rate in the well-speciﬁed setting, popular in the
classical statistics literature, where the labels are generated i.i.d.
such that
E[yi ] = ?i with isotonic 1 ?1 ? .
. ? ?t .4 Second, there is a ?(t? 2 )
lower bound for forward algorithms as proven in the next section. Together,
these results imply that the random permutation model in indeed harder than
the well-speciﬁed case: forward algorithms are suﬃcient for the latter but not
the former. Theorem 4.2. For data generated from the well-speciﬁed setting
(monotonic means with i.i.d. noise), ? 13 ) bound on the regret. ? ? 23 ),
which translates to a O(T any FA has ‘oot = O(t The proof is given in Appendix
D. Curiously, the proof makes use of the existence of the seemingly ? ? 32 )
excess leave-one-out loss from Theorem 3.2. unrelated optimal algorithm with
O(t 4.4

.

Entropic loss
We now abandon the squared loss for a moment and analyze how a FA
performs when the loss function is the entropic loss, deﬁned as ?y log yb ?
(1 ? y) log(1 ? yb) for y ? [0, 1]. Entropic loss (precisely:
its binary-label
version known as log-loss) is extensively used in the isotonic regression context
for maximum likelihood estimation [14] or for probability calibration [28, 21, 27].
A surprising fact in isotonic regression is that minimizing entropic loss5 leads
to exactly the same optimal solution as in the squared loss case, the isotonic
regression function y ? [24]. Not every FA is appropriate for entropic loss, as
recklessly choosing the label estimate might result in an inﬁnite loss in just a
single trial (as noted by [27]). Indeed, consider a sequence of outcomes with
y1 = 0 and yi = 1 for i ¿ 1. While predicting on index i = 1, choosing y10 =
1 results in yb1 = 1, for which the entropic loss is inﬁnite (as y1 = 0). Does
there exists a FA which achieves a meaningful bound on ‘oot in the entropic loss
setup? We answer this question in the aﬃrmative, showing that the log-IVAP
predictor FA gets the same excess-leave-one-out loss bound as given in Theorem

9

4.1. As the reduction from the regret to leaveone-out loss (Lemma 2.1) does
not use any properties of the loss function, this immediately implies a bound on
the expected regret. Interestingly, the proof (given in Appendix G) uses as an
intermediate step the bound on —?i — for the worst possible forward algorithm
which always produces the estimate being the opposite of the actual label. q

log t Theorem 4.3. The log-IVAP algorithm has ‘oot = O for the entropic

loss. t 4 5

The ?(T 1/3 ) regret lower bound in [14] uses a mixture of well-speciﬁed
distributions and still applies. In fact, this statement applies to any Bregman
divergence [24].

7
4.5
Lower bound 1
The last result of this section is that FA can be made to have ‘oot = ?(t? 2
). We show this by means of a counterexample. Assume t = n2 for some integer
n ¿ 0 and let the labels ? be binary, yi ? {0, 1}. We split the set {1, . . . , t}
into n consecutive segments, each of size n = t. The proportion of ones (yi =
1) in the k-th segment is equal to nk , but within each segment all ones precede
all zeros. For instance, when t = 25, the label sequence is: 10000 — {z } 11100
— {z } 11110 — {z } 11111 — {z }, — {z } 11000 1/5

2/5
3/5
4/5
5/5
One can use the minimax formulation (4) to verify that the segments will
correspond to the level sets of the isotonic regression and that yi? = nk for any
i in the k-th segment. This sequence is hard: 1

Lemma 4.4. The IR-Int algorithm run on the sequence described above has
‘oot = ?(t? 2 ). We prove the lower bound for IR-Int, since the presentation (in
Appendix E) is clearest. Empirical simulations showing that the other forward
algorithms also suﬀer this regret are in Appendix F. 4.6

Towards optimal forward algorithms
An attractive feature of forward algorithms is that they generalize to partial
orders, for which eﬃcient ? ? 12 ) oﬄine optimization algorithms exist. How-
ever, in Section 4 we saw that FAs only give a O(t ? ? 23 ) is possible (with an
algorithm that is not known to scale rate, while in Section 3 we saw that O(t to
partial orders). Is there any hope of an algorithm that both generalizes and has
the optimal rate? In this section, we propose the Heavy-? algorithm, a slight
modiﬁcation of the forward algorithm that plugs in label estimate yi0 = ? ? [0,
1] with weight c (with unit weight on all other points), then plays the value of
the isotonic regression function. Implementation is straightforward for oﬄine
isotonic regression algorithms that permit the speciﬁcation of weights (such as
[16]). Otherwise, we might simulate such weighting by plugging in c copies of
the estimated label ? at location xi . What label estimate ? and weight c should
we use? We show that the choice of ? is not very sensitive, 1 but it is crucial
to tune the weight to c = ?(t 3 ). Lemmas H.1 and H.2 show that higher and

10

lower c are necessarily sub-optimal for ‘oot . This leaves only one choice for c,
for which we believe 1 ? ? 23 ). Conjecture 4.5. Heavy-? with weight c =
?(t 3 ) has ‘oot = O(t We cannot yet prove this conjecture, although numerical
experiments strongly suggest it. We do not believe that picking a constant label
? is special. For example, we might alternatively predict with the average of
the predictions of Heavy-1 and Heavy-0. Yet not any label estimate works. In
particular, if we estimate the label that would be predicted by IR-Int (see 4.1)
and the discussion below it), and we plug that in with any weight c ? 0, then
the isotonic regression function will still have that same 1 label estimate as its
value. This means that the ?(t? 2 ) lower bound of Section 4.5 applies.

5
Conclusion
We revisit the problem of online isotonic regression and argue that we need
a new perspective to design practical algorithms. We study the random permu-
tation model as a novel way to bypass the stringent ﬁxed design requirement of
previous work. Our main tool in the design and analysis of algorithms is the
leave-one-out loss, which bounds the expected regret from above. We start by
observing that the adversary from the adversarial ﬁxed design setting also pro-
vides a lower bound here. We then show that this lower bound can be matched
by applying online-to-batch conversion to the optimal algorithm for ﬁxed design.
Next we provide an online analysis of the natural, popular and practical class
of Forward Algorithms, which are deﬁned in terms of an oﬄine optimization
oracle. We show that Forward algorithms achieve a decent regret rate in all
cases, and match the optimal rate in special cases. We conclude by sketching
the class of practical Heavy algorithms and conjecture that a speciﬁc parameter
setting might guarantee the correct regret rate. Open problem The next major
challenge is the design and analysis of eﬃcient algorithms for online isotonic
regression on arbitrary partial orders. Heavy-? is our current best candidate.
We pose ? 13 ) regret on linear orders as an open problem. deciding if it in fact
even guarantees O(T 8

Acknowledgments Wojciech Kot?owski acknowledges support from the Pol-
ish National Science Centre (grant no. 2016/22/E/ST6/00299). Wouter Koolen
acknowledges support from the Netherlands Organization for Scientiﬁc Research
(NWO) under Veni grant 639.021.439. This work was done in part while Koolen
was visiting the Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing.

2 References

[1] M. Ayer, H. D. Brunk, G. M. Ewing, W. T. Reid, and E. Silverman. An
empirical distribution function for sampling with incomplete information. An-
nals of Mathematical Statistics, 26(4): 641?647, 1955.
[2] K. Azoury and M.
Warmuth. Relative loss bounds for on-line density estimation with the expo-
nential family of distributions. Journal of Machine Learning, 43(3):211?246,
2001. [3] Lucien Birg? and Pascal Massart. Rates of convergence for minimum
contrast estimators. Probability Theory and Related Fields, 97:113?150, 1993.

11

[4] H. D. Brunk. Maximum likelihood estimates of monotone parameters. An-
nals of Mathematical Statistics, 26(4):607?616, 1955.
[5] Nicol? Cesa-Bianchi
and G?bor Lugosi. Worst-case bounds for the logarithmic loss of predictors.
Machine Learning, 43(3):247?264, 2001.
[6] Nicol? Cesa-Bianchi and G?bor
Lugosi. Prediction, learning, and games. Cambridge University Press, 2006.
[7] Jan de Leeuw, Kurt Hornik, and Patrick Mair. Isotone optimization in R:
Pool-adjacent-violators algorithm (PAVA) and active set methods. Journal of
Statistical Software, 32:1?24, 2009. [8] Tom Fawcett and Alexandru Niculescu-
Mizil. PAV and the ROC convex hull. Machine Learning, 68(1):97?106, 2007.
[9] J?rgen Forster and Manfred K Warmuth. Relative expected instantaneous
loss bounds. Journal of Computer and System Sciences, 64(1):76?102, 2002.
[10] Pierre Gaillard and S?bastien Gerchinovitz. A chaining algorithm for on-
line nonparametric regression.
In Conference on Learning Theory (COLT),
pages 764?796, 2015. [11] Sham M Kakade, Varun Kanade, Ohad Shamir, and
Adam Kalai. Eﬃcient learning of generalized linear and single index models
In Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS),
with isotonic regression.
pages 927?935, 2011.
[12] Adam Tauman Kalai and Ravi Sastry. The isotron
algorithm: High-dimensional isotonic regression. In COLT, 2009. [13] Wojciech
Kot?owski and Roman S?owi?nski. Rule learning with monotonicity constraints.
In International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), pages 537?544, 2009.
[14] Wojciech Kot?owski, Wouter M. Koolen, and Alan Malek. Online isotonic
regression.
In Vitaly Feldman and Alexander Rakhlin, editors, Proceedings
of the 29th Annual Conference on Learning Theory (COLT), pages 1165?1189,
June 2016. [15] J. B. Kruskal. Multidimensional scaling by optimizing goodness
of ﬁt to a nonmetric hypothesis. Psychometrika, 29(1):1?27, 1964. [16] Rasmus
Kyng, Anup Rao, and Sushant Sachdeva. Fast, provable algorithms for isotonic
regression in all ‘p -norms. In Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS),
2015. [17] Ronny Luss, Saharon Rosset, and Moni Shahar. Eﬃcient regularized
isotonic regression with application to gene?gene interaction search. Annals of
Applied Statistics, 6(1):253?283, 2012. 9

In WSDM, pages 151?160. ACM, 2010.

[18] Aditya Krishna Menon, Xiaoqian Jiang, Shankar Vembu, Charles Elkan,
and Lucila OhnoMachado. Predicting accurate probabilities with a ranking loss.
In Interantional Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2012. [19] T. Moon,
A. Smola, Y. Chang, and Z. Zheng. Intervalrank: Isotonic regression with list-
wise and pairwise constraint.
[20]
Harikrishna Narasimhan and Shivani Agarwal. On the relationship between bi-
nary classiﬁcation, bipartite ranking, and binary class probability estimation.
In Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS), pages 2913?2921, 2013. [21]
Alexandru Niculescu-Mizil and Rich Caruana. Predicting good probabilities
with supervised learning. In ICML, volume 119, pages 625?632. ACM, 2005.
[22] G. Obozinski, C. E. Grant, G. R. G. Lanckriet, M. I. Jordan, and W. W. No-
ble. Consistent probabilistic outputs for protein function prediction. Genome
Biology, 2008 2008.
[23] Alexander Rakhlin and Karthik Sridharan. Online
nonparametric regression. In Conference on Learning Theory (COLT), pages
1232?1264, 2014.
[24] T. Robertson, F. T. Wright, and R. L. Dykstra. Order
Restricted Statistical Inference. John Wiley & Sons, 1998. [25] Mario Stylianou

12

and Nancy Flournoy. Dose ﬁnding using the biased coin up-and-down design
and isotonic regression. Biometrics, 58(1):171?177, 2002. [26] Sara Van de Geer.
Estimating a regression function. Annals of Statistics, 18:907?924, 1990.
[27]
Vladimir Vovk, Ivan Petej, and Valentina Fedorova. Large-scale probabilistic
predictors with and without guarantees of validity. In Neural Information Pro-
cessing Systems (NIPS), pages 892?900, 2015. [28] Bianca Zadrozny and Charles
Elkan. Transforming classiﬁer scores into accurate multiclass probability esti-
mates. In International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining
(KDD), pages 694?699, 2002.
[29] Cun-Hui Zhang. Risk bounds in isotonic
regression. The Annals of Statistics, 30(2):528?555, 2002.

10

13

