QMDP-Net: Deep Learning for Planning under

Partial Observability

Authored by:

Wee Sun Lee

David Hsu

Peter Karkus

Abstract

This paper introduces the QMDP-net, a neural network architecture
for planning under partial observability. The QMDP-net combines the
strengths of model-free learning and model-based planning. It is a recur-
rent policy network, but it represents a policy for a parameterized set of
tasks by connecting a model with a planning algorithm that solves the
model, thus embedding the solution structure of planning in a network
learning architecture. The QMDP-net is fully diﬀerentiable and allows
for end-to-end training. We train a QMDP-net on diﬀerent tasks so that
it can generalize to new ones in the parameterized task set and ?trans-
fer? to other similar tasks beyond the set. In preliminary experiments,
QMDP-net showed strong performance on several robotic tasks in sim-
ulation.
Interestingly, while QMDP-net encodes the QMDP algorithm,
it sometimes outperforms the QMDP algorithm in the experiments, as a
result of end-to-end learning.

1 Paper Body

Decision-making under uncertainty is of fundamental importance, but it is com-
putationally hard, especially under partial observability [24].
In a partially
observable world, the agent cannot determine the state exactly based on the
current observation; to plan optimal actions, it must integrate information over
the past history of actions and observations. See Fig. 1 for an example. In the
model-based approach, we may formulate the problem as a partially observable
Markov decision process (POMDP). Solving POMDPs exactly is computation-
ally intractable in the worst case [24]. Approximate POMDP algorithms have
made dramatic progress on solving large-scale POMDPs [17, 25, 29, 32, 37];
however, manually constructing POMDP models or learning them from data
remains diﬃcult. In the model-free approach, we directly search for an opti-
mal solution within a policy class. If we do not restrict the policy class, the
diﬃculty is data and computational eﬃciency. We may choose a parameterized

1

policy class. The eﬀectiveness of policy search is then constrained by this a pri-
ori choice. Deep neural networks have brought unprecedented success in many
domains [16, 21, 30] and provide a distinct new approach to decision-making un-
der uncertainty. The deep Q-network (DQN), which consists of a convolutional
neural network (CNN) together with a fully connected layer, has successfully
tackled many Atari games with complex visual input [21]. Replacing the post-
convolutional fully connected layer of DQN by a recurrent LSTM layer allows it
to deal with partial observaiblity [10]. However, compared with planning, this
approach fails to exploit the underlying sequential nature of decision-making.
We introduce QMDP-net, a neural network architecture for planning under
partial observability. QMDP-net combines the strengths of model-free learning
and model-based planning. A QMDP-net is a recurrent policy network, but
it represents a policy by connecting a POMDP model with an algorithm that
solves the model, thus embedding the solution structure of planning in a net-
work 31st Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017),
Long Beach, CA, USA.

(a)
(b)
(c)
(d)
Fig. 1: A robot learning to navigate in partially observable grid worlds. (a)
The robot has a map. It has a belief over the initial state, but does not know
the exact initial state. (b) Local observations are ambiguous and are insuﬃcient
to determine the exact state. (c, d) A policy trained on expert demonstrations
in a set of randomly generated environments generalizes to a new environment.
It also ?transfers? to a much larger real-life environment, represented as a LI-
DAR map [12].
learning architecture. Speciﬁcally, our network uses QMDP
[18], a simple, but fast approximate POMDP algorithm, though other more so-
phisticated POMDP algorithms could be used as well. A QMDP-net consists
of two main network modules (Fig. 2). One represents a Bayesian ﬁlter, which
integrates the history of an agent?s actions and observations into a belief, i.e.
a probabilistic estimate of the agent?s state. The other represents the QMDP
algorithm, which chooses the action given the current belief. Both modules are
diﬀerentiable, allowing the entire network to be trained end-to-end. We train a
QMDP-net on expert demonstrations in a set of randomly generated environ-
ments. The trained policy generalizes to new environments and also ?transfers?
to more complex environments (Fig. 1c?d). Preliminary experiments show
that QMDP-net outperformed state-of-the-art network architectures on several
robotic tasks in simulation. It successfully solved diﬃcult POMDPs that require
reasoning over many time steps, such as the well-known Hallway2 domain [18].
Interestingly, while QMDP-net encodes the QMDP algorithm, it sometimes out-
performed the QMDP algorithm in our experiments, as a result of end-to-end
learning.
2 2.1
Background Planning under Uncertainty
A POMDP is formally deﬁned as a tuple (S, A, O, T, Z, R), where S, A and

2

O are the state, action, and observation space, respectively. The state-transition
function T (s, a, s0 ) = P (s0 —s, a) deﬁnes the probability of the agent being
in state s0 after taking action a in state s. The observation function Z(s, a, o) =
p(o—s, a) deﬁnes the probability of receiving observation o after taking action a
in state s. The reward function R(s, a) deﬁnes the immediate reward for taking
action a in state s. In a partially observable world, the agent does not know
its exact state. It maintains a belief, which is a probability distribution over S.
The agent starts with an initial belief b0 and updates the belief bt at each time
step t with a Bayesian ﬁlter: P bt (s0 ) = ? (bt 1 , at , ot ) = ?O(s0 , at , ot )
s2S T (s, at , s0 )bt 1 (s), (1)

where ? is a normalizing constant. The belief bt recursively integrates
information from the entire past history (a1 , o1 , a2 , o2 , . . . , at , ot ) for
decision making. POMDP planning seeks a policy ? that maximizes the value,
i.e., the expected total discounted reward: P1 t V? (b0 ) = E R(st , at+1 ) b0 ,
? , (2) t=0 where st is the state at time t, at+1 = ?(bt ) is the action that the
policy ? chooses at time t, and 2 (0, 1) is a discount factor. 2.2

Related Work
To learn policies for decision making in partially observable domains, one
approach is to learn models [6, 19, 26] and solve the models through planning.
An alternative is to learn policies directly [2, 5]. Model learning is usually
not end-to-end. While policy learning can be end-to-end, it does not exploit
model information for eﬀective generalization. Our proposed approach combines
model-based and 2

model-free learning by embedding a model and a planning algorithm in a
recurrent neural network (RNN) that represents a policy and then training the
network end-to-end. RNNs have been used earlier for learning in partially ob-
servable domains [4, 10, 11]. In particular, Hausknecht and Stone extended DQN
[21], a convolutional neural network (CNN), by replacing its post-convolutional
fully connected layer with a recurrent LSTM layer [10]. Similarly, Mirowski
et al.
[20] considered learning to navigate in partially observable 3-D mazes.
The learned policy generalizes over diﬀerent goals, but in a ﬁxed environment.
Instead of using the generic LSTM, our approach embeds algorithmic structure
speciﬁc to sequential decision making in the network architecture and aims to
learn a policy that generalizes to new environments. The idea of embedding spe-
ciﬁc computation structures in the neural network architecture has been gaining
attention recently. Tamar et al.
implemented value iteration in a neural net-
work, called Value Iteration Network (VIN), to solve Markov decision processes
(MDPs) in fully observable domains, where an agent knows its exact state and
does not require ﬁltering [34]. Okada et al. addressed a related problem of path
integral optimal control, which allows for continuous states and actions [23].
Neither addresses the issue of partial observability, which drastically increases
the computational complexity of decision making [24]. Haarnoja et al. [9] and
Jonschkowski and Brock [15] developed end-to-end trainable Bayesian ﬁlters for
probabilistic state estimation. Silver et al. introduced Predictron for value esti-
mation in Markov reward processes [31]. They do not deal with decision making
or planning. Both Shankar et al. [28] and Gupta et al. [8] addressed planning

3

under partial observability. The former focuses on learning a model rather than
a policy. The learned model is trained on a ﬁxed environment and does not gen-
eralize to new ones. The latter proposes a network learning approach to robot
navigation in an unknown environment, with a focus on mapping. Its network
architecture contains a hierarchical extension of VIN for planning and thus does
not deal with partial observability during planning. The QMDP-net extends the
prior work on network architectures for MDP planning and for Bayesian ﬁlter-
ing. It imposes the POMDP model and computation structure priors on the
entire network architecture for planning under partial observability.

3
Overview
We want to learn a policy that enables an agent to act eﬀectively in a diverse
set of partially observable stochastic environments. Consider, for example, the
robot navigation domain in Fig. 1. The environments may correspond to diﬀer-
ent buildings. The robot agent does not observe its own location directly, but
estimates it based on noisy readings from a laser range ﬁnder. It has access to
building maps, but does not have models of its own dynamics and sensors. While
the buildings may diﬀer signiﬁcantly in their layouts, the underlying reasoning
required for eﬀective navigation is similar in all buildings. After training the
robot in a few buildings, we want to place the robot in a new building and have
it navigate eﬀectively to a speciﬁed goal. Formally, the agent learns a policy
for a parameterized set of tasks in partially observable stochastic environments:
W? = {W (?) — ? 2 ?}, where ? is the set of all parameter values. The param-
eter value ? captures a wide variety of task characteristics that vary within the
set, including environments, goals, and agents. In our robot navigation exam-
ple, ? encodes a map of the environment, a goal, and a belief over the robot?s
initial state. We assume that all tasks in W? share the same state space, action
space, and observation space. The agent does not have prior models of its own
dynamics, sensors, or task objectives. After training on tasks for some subset
of values in ?, the agent learns a policy that solves W (?) for any given ? 2 ?.
A key issue is a general representation of a policy for W? , without know-
ing the speciﬁcs of W? or its parametrization. We introduce the QMDP-net,
a recurrent policy network. A QMDP-net represents a policy by connecting a
parameterized POMDP model with an approximate POMDP algorithm and em-
bedding both in a single, diﬀerentiable neural network. Embedding the model
allows the policy to generalize over W? eﬀectively. Embedding the algorithm
allows us to train the entire network end-to-end and learn a model that compen-
sates for the limitations of the approximate algorithm. Let M (?) = (S, A, O, fT
(?—?), fZ (?—?), fR (?—?)) be the embedded POMDP model, where S, A and
O are the shared state space, action space, observation space designed manually
for all tasks in W? and fT (?—?), fZ (?—?), fR (?—?) are the state-transition,
observation, and reward functions to be learned from data. It may appear that
a perfect answer to our learning problem would have 3

(a)
(b)
(c) QMDP planner

4

QMDP planner
QMDP planner
QMDP planner
Policy Bayesian ﬁlter
Bayesian ﬁlter
Bayesian ﬁlter
Bayesian ﬁlter
Fig. 2: QMDP-net architecture.

fT (?—?), fZ (?—?), and fR (?—?)

(a) A policy maps a history of actions
and observations to a new action. (b) A QMDP-net is an RNN that imposes
structure priors for sequential decision making under partial observability. It
embeds a Bayesian ﬁlter and the QMDP algorithm in the network. The hidden
state of the RNN encodes the belief for POMDP planning. (c) A QMDP-net
unfolded in time.
represent the ?true?
underlying models of dynamics, observation, and reward for the task W (?).
This is true only if the embedded POMDP algorithm is exact, but not true in
general. The agent may learn an alternative model to mitigate an approximate
algorithm?s limitations and obtain an overall better policy. In this sense, while
QMDP-net embeds a POMDP model in the network architecture, it aims to
learn a good policy rather than a ?correct? model. A QMDP-net consists of
two modules (Fig. 2). One encodes a Bayesian ﬁlter, which performs state es-
timation by integrating the past history of agent actions and observations into
a belief. The other encodes QMDP, a simple, but fast approximate POMDP
planner [18]. QMDP chooses the agent?s actions by solving the correspond-
ing fully observable Markov decision process (MDP) and performing one-step
look-ahead search on the MDP values weighted by the belief. We evaluate the
proposed network architecture in an imitation learning setting. We train on
a set of expert trajectories with randomly chosen task parameter values in ?
and test with new parameter values. An expert trajectory consist of a sequence
of demonstrated actions and observations (a1 , o1 , a2 , o2 , .
.) for some
? 2 ?. The agent does not access the ground-truth states or beliefs along the
trajectory during the training. We deﬁne loss as the cross entropy between pre-
dicted and demonstrated action sequences and use RMSProp [35] for training.
See Appendix C.7 for details. Our implementation in Tensorﬂow [1] is available
online at http://github.com/AdaCompNUS/qmdp-net.

.

4
QMDP-Net
We assume that all tasks in a parameterized set W? share the same underly-
ing state space S, action space A, and observation space O. We want to learn a
QMDP-net policy for W? , conditioned on the parameters ? 2 ?. A QMDP-net
is a recurrent policy network. The inputs to a QMDP-net are the action at 2
A and the observation ot 2 O at time step t, as well as the task parameter ? 2
?. The output is the action at+1 for time step t + 1. A QMDP-net encodes
a parameterized POMDP model M (?) = (S, A, O, T = fT (?—?), Z = fZ
(?—?), R = fR (?—?)) and the QMDP algorithm, which selects actions by
solving the model approximately. We choose S, A, and O of M (?) manually,
based on prior knowledge on W? , speciﬁcally, prior knowledge on S, A, and

5

O. In general, S 6= S, A 6= A, and O 6= O. The model states, actions, and
observations may be abstractions of their real-world counterparts in the task.
In our robot navigation example (Fig. 1), while the robot moves in a contin-
uous space, we choose S to be a grid of ﬁnite size. We can do the same for A
and O, in order to reduce representational and computational complexity. The
transition function T , observation function Z, and reward function R of M (?)
are conditioned on ?, and are learned from data through end-to-end training.
In this work, we assume that T is the same for all tasks in W? to simplify the
network architecture.
In other words, T does not depend on ?. End-to-end
training is feasible, because a QMDP-net encodes both a model and the asso-
ciated algorithm in a single, fully diﬀerentiable neural network. The main idea
for embedding the algorithm in a neural network is to represent linear oper-
ations, such as matrix multiplication and summation, by convolutional layers
and represent maximum operations by max-pooling layers. Below we provide
some details on the QMDP-net?s architecture, which consists of two modules,
a ﬁlter and a planner. 4

(a) Bayesian ﬁlter module
(b) QMDP planner module
Fig. 3: A QMDP-net consists of two modules. (a) The Bayesian ﬁlter module
incorporates the current action at and observation ot into the belief. (b) The
QMDP planner module selects the action according to the current belief bt .
Filter module. The ﬁlter module (Fig. 3a) implements a Bayesian ﬁlter.
It
maps from a belief, action, and observation to a next belief, bt+1 = f (bt —at
, ot ). The belief is updated in two steps. The ﬁrst accounts for actions, the
second for observations: P b0t (s) = s0 2S T (s, at , s0 )bt (s0 ), (3) bt+1 (s)
= ?Z(s, ot )b0t (s),

(4)
where ot 2 O is the observation received after taking action at 2 A and ? is

a normalization factor.

(3) and Eq.

We implement the Bayesian ﬁlter by transforming Eq.

(4)
to layers of a neural network. For ease of discussion consider our N ?N grid
navigation task (Fig. 1a?c). The agent does not know its own state and only
observes neighboring cells. It has access to the task parameter ? that encodes
the obstacles, goal, and a belief over initial states. Given the task, we choose M
(?) to have a N ?N state space. The belief, bt (s), is now an N ?N tensor. Eq.
(3) is implemented as a convolutional layer with —A— convolutional ﬁlters.
We denote the convolutional layer by fT . The kernel weights of fT encode the
transition function T in M (?). The output of the convolutional layer, b0t (s,
a), is a N ?N ?—A— tensor.

b0t (s, a) encodes the updated belief after taking each of the actions, a 2 A.
We need to select the belief corresponding to the last action taken by the agent,
at . We can directly index b0t (s, a) by at if A = A. In general A 6= A, so we
cannot use simple indexing. Instead, we will use ?soft indexing?. First we encode
actions in A to actions in A through a learned function fA . fA maps from at to
an indexing vector wta , a distribution over actions in A. We then weight b0t (s,
a) by wta along the appropriate dimension, i.e. P b0t (s) = a2A b0t (s, a)wta

6

. (5) Eq. (4) incorporates observations through an observation model Z(s, o).
Now Z(s, o) is a N ?N ?—O— tensor that represents the probability of receiving
observation o 2 O in state s 2 S. In our grid navigation task observations depend
on the obstacle locations. We condition Z on the task parameter, Z(s, o) = fZ
(s, o—?) for ? 2 ?. The function fZ is a neural network, mapping from ? to
Z(s, o). In this paper fZ is a CNN.

Z(s, o) encodes observation probabilities for each of the observations, o 2 O.
We need the observation probabilities for the last observation ot . In general O
6= O and we cannot index Z(s, o) directly. Instead, we will use soft indexing
again. We encode observations in O to observations in O through fO . fO is a
function mapping from ot to an indexing vector, wto , a distribution over O.
We then weight Z(s, o) by wto , i.e. P Z(s) = o2O Z(s, o)wto . (6) Finally, we
obtain the updated belief, bt+1 (s), by multiplying b0t (s) and Z(s) element-
wise, and normalizing over states. In our setting the initial belief for the task W
(?) is encoded in ?. We initialize the belief in QMDP-net through an additional
encoding function, b0 = fB (?). 5

Planner module. The QMDP planner (Fig. 3b) performs value iteration at
its core. Q values are computed by iteratively applying Bellman updates, P 0 0
Qk+1 (s, a) = R(s, a) + (7) s0 2S T (s, a, s )Vk (s ), Vk (s) = maxa Qk (s, a).

(8)
Actions are then selected by weighting the Q values with the belief. We
can implement value iteration using convolutional and max pooling layers [28,
34]. In our grid navigation task Q(s, a) is a N ?N ?—A— tensor. Eq. (8) is
expressed by a max pooling layer, where Qk (s, a) is the input and Vk (s) is
the output. Eq. (7) is a N ?N convolution with —A— convolutional ﬁlters,
followed by an addition operation with R(s, a), the reward tensor. We denote
the convolutional layer by fT0 . The kernel weights of fT0 encode the transition
function T , similarly to fT in the ﬁlter. Rewards for a navigation task depend
on the goal and obstacles. We condition rewards on the task parameter, R(s,
a) = fR (s, a—?). fR maps from ? to R(s, a). In this paper fR is a CNN. We
implement K iterations of Bellman updates by stacking the layers representing
Eq. (7) and Eq. (8) K times with tied weights. After K iterations we get QK
(s, a), the approximate Q values for each state-action pair. We weight the Q
values by the belief to obtain action values, P q(a) = s2S QK (s, a)bt (s). (9)
Finally, we choose the output action through a low-level policy function, f? ,
mapping from q(a) to the action output, at+1 .

QMDP-net naturally extends to higher dimensional discrete state spaces
(e.g. our maze navigation task) where n-dimensional convolutions can be used
[14]. While M (?) is restricted to a discrete space, we can handle continuous
tasks W? by simultaneously learning a discrete M (?) for planning, and fA , fO
, fB , f? to map between states, actions and observations in W? and M (?).

5
Experiments
The main objective of the experiments is to understand the beneﬁts of struc-
ture priors on learning neural-network policies. We create several alternative
network architectures by gradually relaxing the structure priors and evaluate

7

the architectures on simulated robot navigation and manipulation tasks. While
these tasks are simpler than, for example, Atari games, in terms of visual per-
ception, they are in fact very challenging, because of the sophisticated long-term
reasoning required to handle partial observability and distant future rewards.
Since the exact state of the robot is unknown, a successful policy must reason
over many steps to gather information and improve state estimation through
partial and noisy observations. It also must reason about the trade-oﬀ between
the cost of information gathering and the reward in the distance future. 5.1

Experimental Setup
We compare the QMDP-net with a number of related alternative architec-
tures. Two are QMDP-net variants. Untied QMDP-net relaxes the constraints
on the planning module by untying the weights representing the state-transition
function over the diﬀerent CNN layers. LSTM QMDP-net replaces the ﬁlter
module with a generic LSTM module. The other two architectures do not em-
bed POMDP structure priors at all. CNN+LSTM is a state-of-the-art deep
CNN connected to an LSTM. It is similar to the DRQN architecture proposed
for reinforcement learning under partially observability [10]. RNN is a basic re-
current neural network with a single fully-connected hidden layer. RNN contains
no structure speciﬁc to planning under partial observability. Each experimental
domain contains a parameterized set of tasks W? . The parameters ? encode
an environment, a goal, and a belief over the robot?s initial state. To train a
policy for W? , we generate random environments, goals, and initial beliefs. We
construct ground-truth POMDP models for the generated data and apply the
QMDP algorithm.
If the QMDP algorithm successfully reaches the goal, we
then retain the resulting sequence of action and observations (a1 , o1 , a2 , o2 , .
. .) as an expert trajectory, together with the corresponding environment, goal,
and initial belief. It is important to note that the ground-truth POMDPs are
used only for generating expert trajectories and not for learning the QMDP-net.
6

For fair comparison, we train all networks using the same set of expert tra-
jectories in each domain. We perform basic search over training parameters, the
number of layers, and the number of hidden units for each network architecture.
Below we brieﬂy describe the experimental domains. See Appendix C for im-
plementation details. Grid-world navigation. A robot navigates in an unknown
building given a ﬂoor map and a goal. The robot is uncertain of its own location.
It is equipped with a LIDAR that detects obstacles in its direct neighborhood.
The world is uncertain: the robot may fail to execute desired actions, possibly
because of wheel slippage, and the LIDAR may produce false readings. We
implemented a simpliﬁed version of this task in a discrete n?n grid world (Fig.
1c). The task parameter ? is represented as an n?n image with three channels.
The ﬁrst channel encodes the obstacles in the environment, the second channel
encodes the goal, and the last channel encodes the belief over the robot?s initial
state. The robot?s state represents its position in the grid. It has ﬁve actions:
moving in each of the four canonical directions or staying put. The LIDAR
observations are compressed into four binary values corresponding to obstacles
in the four neighboring cells. We consider both a deterministic and a stochas-

8

tic variant of the domain. The stochastic variant adds action and observation
uncertainties. The robot fails to execute the speciﬁed move action and stays
in place with probability 0.2. The observations are faulty with probability 0.1
independently in each direction. We trained a policy using expert trajectories
from 10, 000 random environments, 5 trajectories from each environment. We
then tested on a separate set of 500 random environments. Maze navigation. A
diﬀerential-drive robot navigates in a maze with the help of a map, but it does
not know its pose (Fig. 1d). This domain is similar to the grid-world naviga-
tion, but it is signiﬁcant more challenging. The robot?s state contains both its
position and orientation. The robot cannot move freely because of kinematic
constraints. It has four actions: move forward, turn left, turn right and stay
put. The observations are relative to the robot?s current orientation, and the
increased ambiguity makes it more diﬃcult to localize the robot, especially when
the initial state is highly uncertain. Finally, successful trajectories in mazes are
typically much longer than those in randomly-generated grid worlds. Again we
trained on expert trajectories in 10, 000 randomly generated mazes and tested
them in 500 new ones.

Fig. 4: Highly ambiguous observations in a maze. The four observations (in

red) are the same, despite that the robot states are all diﬀerent. (a)

(b)
2-D object grasping. A robot gripper picks up novel objects from a table
using a two-ﬁnger hand with noisy touch sensors at the ﬁnger tips. The grip-
per uses the ﬁngers to perform compliant motions while maintaining contact
with the object or to grasp the object.
It knows the shape of the object to
be grasped, maybe from an object Fig. 5: Object grasping using touch sens-
database. However, it does not know its own pose relative ing. (a) An example
[3]. (b) Simpliﬁed to the object and relies on the touch sensors to localize 2-
D object grasping. Objects from the itself. We implemented a simpliﬁed 2-D
variant of this training set (top) and the test set (bottom). task, modeled as
a POMDP [13]. The task parameter ? is an image with three channels en-
coding the object shape, the grasp point, and a belief over the gripper?s initial
pose. The gripper has four actions, each moving in a canonical direction unless
it touches the object or the environment boundary. Each ﬁnger has 3 binary
touch sensors at the tip, resulting in 64 distinct observations. We trained on
expert demonstration on 20 diﬀerent objects with 500 randomly sampled poses
for each object. We then tested on 10 previously unseen objects in random
poses. 5.2

Choosing QMDP-Net Components for a Task
Given a new task W? , we need to choose an appropriate neural network
representation for M (?). More speciﬁcally, we need to choose S, A and O, and
a representation for the functions fR , fT , fT0 , fZ , fO , fA , fB , f? . This
provides an opportunity to incorporate domain knowledge in a principled way.
For example, if W? has a local and spatially invariant connectivity structure,
we can choose convolutions with small kernels to represent fT , fR and fZ . 7

In our experiments we use S = N ?N for N ?N grid navigation, and S = N ?N
?4 for N ?N maze navigation where the robot has 4 possible orientations. We use

9

—A— = —A— and —O— = —O— for all tasks except for the object grasping
task, where —O— = 64 and —O— = 16. We represent fT , fR and fZ by
CNN components with 3?3 and 5?5 kernels depending on the task. We enforce
that fT and fZ are proper probability distributions by using softmax and sigmoid
activations on the convolutional kernels, respectively. Finally, fO is a small fully
connected component, fA is a one-hot encoding function, f? is a single softmax
layer, and fB is the identity function. We can adjust the amount of planning in
a QMDP-net by setting K. A large K allows propagating information to more
distant states without aﬀecting the number of parameters to learn. However, it
results in deeper networks that are computationally expensive to evaluate and
more diﬃcult to train. We used K = 20 .
. 116 depending on the problem
size. We were able to transfer policies to larger environments by increasing K
up to 450 when executing the policy.
In our experiments the representation
of the task parameter ? is isomorphic to the chosen state space S. While the
architecture is not restricted to this setting, we rely on it to represent fT , fZ ,
fR by convolutions with small kernels. Experiments with a more general class
of problems is an interesting direction for future work. 5.3

.

Results and Discussion
The main results are reported in Table 1. Some additional results are re-
ported in Appendix A. For each domain, we report the task success rate and the
average number of time steps for task completion. Comparing the completion
time is meaningful only when the success rates are similar. QMDP-net suc-
cessfully learns policies that generalize to new environments. When evaluated
on new environments, the QMDP-net has higher success rate and faster com-
pletion time than the alternatives in nearly all domains. To understand better
the performance diﬀerence, we speciﬁcally compared the architectures in a ﬁxed
environment for navigation. Here only the initial state and the goal vary across
the task instances, while the environment remains the same. See the results in
the last row of Table 1. The QMDP-net and the alternatives have comparable
performance. Even RNN performs very well. Why? In a ﬁxed environment, a
network may learn the features of an optimal policy directly, e.g., going straight
towards the goal. In contrast, the QMDP-net learns a model for planning, i.e.,
generating a near-optimal policy for a given arbitrary environment. POMDP
structure priors improve the performance of learning complex policies. Moving
across Table 1 from left to right, we gradually relax the POMDP structure priors
on the network architecture. As the structure priors weaken, so does the overall
performance. However, strong priors sometimes over-constrain the network and
result in degraded performance. For example, we found that tying the weights
of fT in the ﬁlter and fT0 in the planner may lead to worse policies. While both
fT and fT0 represent the same underlying transition dynamics, using diﬀerent
weights allows each to choose its own approximation and thus greater ﬂexibility.
We shed some light on this issue and visualize the learned POMDP model in
Appendix B. QMDP-net learns ?incorrect?, but useful models. Planning under
partial observability is intractable in general, and we must rely on approxima-
tion algorithms. A QMDP-net encodes both a POMDP model and QMDP,
an approximate POMDP algorithm that solves the model. We then train the

10

network end-to-end. This provides the opportunity to learn an ?incorrect?, but
useful model that compensates the limitation of the approximation algorithm,
in a way similar to reward shaping in reinforcement learning [22]. Indeed, our
results show that the QMDP-net achieves higher success rate than QMDP in
nearly all tasks. In particular, QMDP-net performs well on the well-known Hall-
way2 domain, which is designed to expose the weakness of QMDP resulting from
its myopic planning horizon. The planning algorithm is the same for both the
QMDP-net and QMDP, but the QMDP-net learns a more eﬀective model from
expert demonstrations. This is true even though QMDP generates the expert
data for training. We note that the expert data contain only successful QMDP
demonstrations. When both successful and unsuccessful QMDP demonstrations
were used for training, the QMDP-net did not perform better than QMDP, as
one would expect. QMDP-net policies learned in small environments transfer
directly to larger environments. Learning a policy for large environments from
scratch is often diﬃcult. A more scalable approach 8

Table 1: Performance comparison of QMDP-net and alternative architec-
tures for recurrent policy networks. SR is the success rate in percentage. Time
is the average number of time steps for task completion. D-n and S-n denote
deterministic and stochastic variants of a domain with environment size n?n.
QMDP Domain

QMDP-net
Untied QMDP-net
LSTM QMDP-net
CNN +LSTM
RNN
SR
Time
SR
Time
SR
Time
SR
Time
SR
Time
SR
Time
Grid D-10 Grid D-18 Grid D-30
99.8 99.0 97.6
8.8 15.5 24.6
99.6 99.0 98.6
8.2 14.6 25.0
98.6 98.8 98.8
8.3 14.8 23.9
84.4 43.8 22.2
12.8 27.9 51.1

11

90.0 57.8 19.4
13.4 33.7 45.2
87.8 35.8 16.4
13.4 24.5 39.3
Grid S-18
98.1
23.9
98.8
23.9
95.9
24.0
23.8
55.6
41.4
65.9
34.0
64.1
Maze D-29 Maze S-19
63.2 63.1
54.1 50.5
98.0 93.9
56.5 60.4
95.4 98.7
62.5 57.1
9.8 18.9
57.2 79.0
9.2 19.2
41.4 80.8
9.8 19.6
47.0 82.1
Hallway2
37.3
28.2
82.9
64.4
69.6 104.4
82.8
89.7
77.8
99.5
68.0 108.8
Grasp
98.3
14.6
99.6
18.2

12

98.9
20.4
91.4
26.4
92.8
22.1
94.1
Intel Lab Freiburg
90.2 88.4
85.4 66.9
94.4 107.7 93.2 81.1
20.0 37.4
55.3 51.7
Fixed grid
98.8
17.4
98.6
99.8
17.0
17.6
97.0
19.7
98.4
25.7 -
19.9
98.0
19.8
would be to learn a policy in small environments and transfer it to large envi-
ronments by repeating the reasoning process. To transfer a learned QMDP-net
policy, we simply expand its planning module by adding more recurrent layers.
Speciﬁcally, we trained a policy in randomly generated 30 ? 30 grid worlds with
K = 90. We then set K = 450 and applied the learned policy to several real-life
environments, including Intel Lab (100?101) and Freiburg (139?57), using their
LIDAR maps (Fig. 1c) from the Robotics Data Set Repository [12]. See the
results for these two environments in Table 1. Additional results with diﬀerent
K settings and other buildings are available in Appendix A.

6
Conclusion
A QMDP-net is a deep recurrent policy network that embeds POMDP struc-
ture priors for planning under partial observability. While generic neural net-
works learn a direct mapping from inputs to outputs, QMDP-net learns how to
model and solve a planning task. The network is fully diﬀerentiable and allows
for end-to-end training. Experiments on several simulated robotic tasks show
that learned QMDP-net policies successfully generalize to new environments
and transfer to larger environments as well. The POMDP structure priors and
end-to-end training substantially improve the performance of learned policies.

13

Interestingly, while a QMDP-net encodes the QMDP algorithm for planning,
learned QMDP-net policies sometimes outperform QMDP. There are many ex-
citing directions for future exploration. First, a major limitation of our current
approach is the state space representation. The value iteration algorithm used
in QMDP iterates through the entire state space and is well known to suﬀer
from the ?curse of dimensionality?. To alleviate this diﬃculty, the QMDP-net,
through end-to-end training, may learn a much smaller abstract state space rep-
resentation for planning. One may also incorporate hierarchical planning [8].
Second, QMDP makes strong approximations in order to reduce computational
complexity. We want to explore the possibility of embedding more sophisticated
POMDP algorithms in the network architecture. While these algorithms pro-
vide stronger planning performance, their algorithmic sophistication increases
the diﬃculty of learning. Finally, we have so far restricted the work to imita-
tion learning. It would be exciting to extend it to reinforcement learning. Based
on earlier work [28, 34], this is indeed promising. Acknowledgments We thank
Leslie Kaelbling and Tom?s Lozano-P?rez for insightful discussions that

helped to improve our understanding of the problem. The work is supported
in part by Singapore Ministry of Education AcRF grant MOE2016-T2-2-068 and
National University of Singapore AcRF grant R-252-000-587112.

9

2 References

[1] M. Abadi, A. Agarwal, P. Barham, E. Brevdo, Z. Chen, C. Citro, G. S.
Corrado, A. Davis, J. Dean, M. Devin, et al. TensorFlow: Large-scale ma-
chine learning on heterogeneous systems, 2015. URL http://tensorﬂow.org/.
[2] J. A. Bagnell, S. Kakade, A. Y. Ng, and J. G. Schneider. Policy search
by dynamic programming. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Sys-
[3] H. Bai, D. Hsu, W. S. Lee, and V. A. Ngo.
tems, pages 831?838, 2003.
Monte carlo value iteration for continuous-state POMDPs.
In Algorithmic
Foundations of Robotics IX, pages 175?191, 2010.
[4] B. Bakker, V. Zhu-
matiy, G. Gruener, and J. Schmidhuber. A robot that reinforcement-learns
In International
to identify and memorize important previous observations.
Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems, pages 430?435, 2003.
[5] J.
Inﬁnite-horizon policy-gradient estimation. Jour-
Baxter and P. L. Bartlett.
nal of Artiﬁcial Intelligence Research, 15:319?350, 2001.
[6] B. Boots, S. M.
Siddiqi, and G. J. Gordon. Closing the learning-planning loop with predic-
tive state representations. The International Journal of Robotics Research,
30(7):954?966, 2011.
[7] K. Cho, B. Van Merri?nboer, C. Gulcehre, D. Bah-
danau, F. Bougares, H. Schwenk, and Y. Bengio. Learning phrase represen-
tations using RNN encoder-decoder for statistical machine translation. arXiv
preprint arXiv:1406.1078, 2014.
[8] S. Gupta, J. Davidson, S. Levine, R. Suk-
thankar, and J. Malik. Cognitive mapping and planning for visual navigation.
arXiv preprint arXiv:1702.03920, 2017. [9] T. Haarnoja, A. Ajay, S. Levine, and
P. Abbeel. Backprop kf: Learning discriminative deterministic state estimators.

14

sourceforge.net/.

In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 4376?4384, 2016.
[10] M. J. Hausknecht and P. Stone. Deep recurrent Q-learning for partially ob-
servable MDPs. arXiv preprint, 2015. URL http://arxiv.org/abs/1507.06527.
[11] S. Hochreiter and J. Schmidhuber. Long short-term memory. Neural Com-
putation, 9(8):1735?1780, 1997. [12] A. Howard and N. Roy. The robotics data
set repository (radish), 2003. URL http://radish.
[13] K.
Hsiao, L. P. Kaelbling, and T. Lozano-P?rez. Grasping POMDPs. In Interna-
tional Conference on Robotics and Automation, pages 4685?4692, 2007.
[14]
S. Ji, W. Xu, M. Yang, and K. Yu. 3D convolutional neural networks for hu-
man action recognition. IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine
Intelligence, 35(1):221?231, 2013. [15] R. Jonschkowski and O. Brock. End-to-
end learnable histogram ﬁlters. In Workshop on Deep Learning for Action and
Interaction at NIPS, 2016. URL http://www.robotics.tu-berlin.de/ﬁleadmin/
fg170/Publikationen pdf/Jonschkowski-16-NIPS-WS.pdf. [16] A. Krizhevsky, I.
Sutskever, and G. E. Hinton. Imagenet classiﬁcation with deep convolutional
neural networks. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages
1097?1105, 2012.
[17] H. Kurniawati, D. Hsu, and W. S. Lee. Sarsop: Eﬃ-
cient point-based POMDP planning by approximating optimally reachable be-
lief spaces.
[18] M.
L. Littman, A. R. Cassandra, and L. P. Kaelbling. Learning policies for par-
tially observable environments: Scaling up.
In International Conference on
Machine Learning, pages 362?370, 1995. [19] M. L. Littman, R. S. Sutton, and
S. Singh. Predictive representations of state. In Advances in Neural Informa-
tion Processing Systems, pages 1555?1562, 2002. [20] P. Mirowski, R. Pascanu,
F. Viola, H. Soyer, A. Ballard, A. Banino, M. Denil, R. Goroshin, L. Sifre,
K. Kavukcuoglu, et al. Learning to navigate in complex environments. arXiv
preprint arXiv:1611.03673, 2016.
[21] V. Mnih, K. Kavukcuoglu, D. Silver, A.
A. Rusu, J. Veness, M. G. Bellemare, A. Graves, M. Riedmiller, A. K. Fidjeland,
G. Ostrovski, et al. Human-level control through deep reinforcement learning.
Nature, 518(7540):529?533, 2015.

In Robotics: Science and Systems, volume 2008, 2008.

10
[22] A. Y. Ng, D. Harada, and S. Russell. Policy invariance under reward
transformations: Theory and application to reward shaping. In International
Conference on Machine Learning, pages 278?287, 1999.
[23] M. Okada, L.
Rigazio, and T. Aoshima. Path integral networks: End-to-end diﬀerentiable op-
timal control. arXiv preprint arXiv:1706.09597, 2017. [24] C. H. Papadimitriou
and J. N. Tsitsiklis. The complexity of Markov decision processes. Mathemat-
ics of Operations Research, 12(3):441?450, 1987. [25] J. Pineau, G. J. Gordon,
and S. Thrun. Applying metric-trees to belief-point POMDPs. In Advances in
Neural Information Processing Systems, page None, 2003. [26] G. Shani, R. I.
Brafman, and S. E. Shimony. Model-based online learning of POMDPs. In Eu-
ropean Conference on Machine Learning, pages 353?364, 2005.
[27] G. Shani,
J. Pineau, and R. Kaplow. A survey of point-based POMDP solvers. Au-
tonomous Agents and Multi-agent Systems, 27(1):1?51, 2013. [28] T. Shankar,
S. K. Dwivedy, and P. Guha. Reinforcement learning via recurrent convolu-
tional neural networks.
In International Conference on Pattern Recognition,

15

[29] D. Silver and J. Veness. Monte-carlo planning in
pages 2592?2597, 2016.
large POMDPs. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages
2164?2172, 2010. [30] D. Silver, A. Huang, C. J. Maddison, A. Guez, L. Sifre,
G. Van Den Driessche, J. Schrittwieser, I. Antonoglou, V. Panneershelvam, M.
Lanctot, et al. Mastering the game of Go with deep neural networks and tree
search. Nature, 529(7587):484?489, 2016.
[31] D. Silver, H. van Hasselt, M.
Hessel, T. Schaul, A. Guez, T. Harley, G. Dulac-Arnold, D. Reichert, N. Rabi-
nowitz, A. Barreto, et al. The predictron: End-to-end learning and planning.
arXiv preprint, 2016. URL https://arxiv.org/abs/1612.08810. [32] M. T. Spaan
and N. Vlassis. Perseus: Randomized point-based value iteration for POMDPs.
Journal of Artiﬁcial Intelligence Research, 24:195?220, 2005.
[33] C. Stach-
niss. Robotics 2D-laser dataset. URL http://www.ipb.uni-bonn.de/datasets/.
[34] A. Tamar, S. Levine, P. Abbeel, Y. Wu, and G. Thomas. Value itera-
tion networks. In Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages
2146?2154, 2016. [35] T. Tieleman and G. Hinton. Lecture 6.5 - rmsprop: Divide
the gradient by a running average of its recent magnitude. COURSERA: Neural
networks for machine learning, pages 26?31, 2012. [36] S. Xingjian, Z. Chen, H.
Wang, D.-Y. Yeung, W.-k. Wong, and W.-c. Woo. Convolutional LSTM net-
work: A machine learning approach for precipitation nowcasting. In Advances
in Neural Information Processing Systems, pages 802?810, 2015.
[37] N. Ye,
A. Somani, D. Hsu, and W. S. Lee. Despot: Online POMDP planning with
regularization. Journal of Artiﬁcial Intelligence Research, 58:231?266, 2017.

11

16

