A simple neural network module for relational

reasoning

Authored by:

David G. Barrett

Mateusz Malinowski

Razvan Pascanu

Tim Lillicrap
Peter Battaglia
Adam Santoro
David Raposo

Abstract

Relational reasoning is a central component of generally intelligent
behavior, but has proven diﬃcult for neural networks to learn. In this
paper we describe how to use Relation Networks (RNs) as a simple plug-
and-play module to solve problems that fundamentally hinge on relational
reasoning. We tested RN-augmented networks on three tasks: visual ques-
tion answering using a challenging dataset called CLEVR, on which we
achieve state-of-the-art, super-human performance; text-based question
answering using the bAbI suite of tasks; and complex reasoning about
dynamical physical systems. Then, using a curated dataset called Sort-
of-CLEVR we show that powerful convolutional networks do not have a
general capacity to solve relational questions, but can gain this capacity
when augmented with RNs. Thus, by simply augmenting convolutions,
LSTMs, and MLPs with RNs, we can remove computational burden from
network components that are not well-suited to handle relational reason-
ing, reduce overall network complexity, and gain a general ability to reason
about the relations between entities and their properties.

1 Paper Body

The ability to reason about the relations between entities and their properties
is central to generally intelligent behavior (Figure 1) [10, 7]. Consider a child
proposing a race between the two trees in the park that are furthest apart:
the pairwise distances between every tree in the park must be inferred and
compared to know where to run. Or, consider a reader piecing together evidence
to predict the culprit in a murder-mystery novel: each clue must be considered

1

in its broader context to build a plausible narrative and solve the mystery.
Symbolic approaches to artiﬁcial intelligence are inherently relational [16, 5].
Practitioners deﬁne the relations between symbols using the language of logic
and mathematics, and then reason about these relations using a multitude of
powerful methods, including deduction, arithmetic, and algebra. But symbolic
approaches suﬀer from the symbol grounding problem and are not robust to
small ?

Equal contribution.
31st Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017),

Long Beach, CA, USA.

Original Image:
Non-relational question: What is the size of the brown sphere?
Relational question: Are there any rubber things that have the same size as

the yellow metallic cylinder?

Figure 1: An illustrative example from the CLEVR dataset of relational
reasoning. An image containing four objects is shown alongside non-relational
and relational questions. The relational question requires explicit reasoning
about the relations between the four objects in the image, whereas the non-
relational question requires reasoning about the attributes of a particular object.
task and input variations [5]. Other approaches, such as those based on
statistical learning, build representations from raw data and often generalize
across diverse and noisy conditions [12]. However, a number of these approaches,
such as deep learning, often struggle in data-poor problems where the under-
lying structure is characterized by sparse but complex relations [3, 11]. Our
results corroborate these claims, and further demonstrate that seemingly sim-
ple relational inferences are remarkably diﬃcult for powerful neural network
architectures such as convolutional neural networks (CNNs) and multi-layer
perceptrons (MLPs). Here, we explore ?Relation Networks? (RN) as a gen-
eral solution to relational reasoning in neural networks. RNs are architectures
whose computations focus explicitly on relational reasoning [18]. Although sev-
eral other models supporting relation-centric computation have been proposed,
such as Graph Neural Neworks, Gated Graph Sequence Neural Netoworks, and
Interaction Networks, [20, 13, 2], RNs are simpler, more exclusively focused on
general relation reasoning, and easier to integrate within broader architectures.
Moreover, RNs require minimal oversight to construct their input, and can be
applied successfully to tasks even when provided with relatively unstructured
inputs coming from CNNs and LSTMs. We applied an RN-augmented architec-
ture to CLEVR [7], a recent visual question answering (QA) dataset on which
state-of-the-art approaches have struggled due to the demand for rich relational
reasoning. Our networks vastly outperformed the best generally-applicable vi-
sual QA architectures, and achieve state-of-the-art, super-human performance.
RNs also solve CLEVR from state descriptions, highlighting their versatility in
regards to the form of their input. We also applied an RN-based architecture to
the bAbI text-based QA suite [22] and solved 18/20 of the subtasks. Finally, we
trained an RN to make challenging relational inferences about complex physical
systems and motion capture data. The success of RNs across this set of sub-

2

stantially dissimilar task domains is testament to the general utility of RNs for
solving problems that require relation reasoning.

2
Relation Networks
An RN is a neural network module with a structure primed for relational
reasoning. The design philosophy behind RNs is to constrain the functional
form of a neural network so that it captures the core common properties of
relational reasoning. In other words, the capacity to compute relations is baked
into the RN architecture without needing to be learned, just as the capacity
to reason about spatial, translation invariant properties is built-in to CNNs,
and the capacity to reason about sequential dependencies is built into recurrent
neural networks. In its simplest form the RN is a composite function: ? ? X
RN(O) = f? ? g? (oi , oj )? , i,j

2
(1)
where the input is a set of ?objects? O = {o1 , o2 , ..., on }, oi ? Rm is the
ith object, and f? and g? are functions with parameters ? and ?, respectively.
For our purposes, f? and g? are MLPs, and the parameters are learnable
synaptic weights, making RNs end-to-end diﬀerentiable. We call the output
of g? a ?relation?; therefore, the role of g? is to infer the ways in which two
objects are related, or if they are even related at all. RNs have three notable
strengths: they learn to infer relations, they are data eﬃcient, and they operate
on a set of objects ? a particularly general and versatile input format ? in
a manner that is order invariant. RNs learn to infer relations The functional
form in Equation 1 dictates that an RN should consider the potential relations
between all object pairs. This implies that an RN is not necessarily privy to
which object relations actually exist, nor to the actual meaning of any particular
relation. Thus, RNs must learn to infer the existence and implications of object
relations. In graph theory parlance, the input can be thought of as a complete
and directed graph whose nodes are objects and whose edges denote the object
pairs whose relations should be considered. Although we focus on this ?all-
to-all? version of the RN throughout this paper, this RN deﬁnition can be
adjusted to consider only some object pairs. Similar to Interaction Networks
[2], to which RNs are related, RNs can take as input a list of only those pairs
that should be considered, if this information is available. This information
could be explicit in the input data, or could perhaps be extracted by some
upstream mechanism. RNs are data eﬃcient RNs use a single function g? to
compute each relation. This can be thought of as a single function operating
on a batch of object pairs, where each member of the batch is a particular
object-object pair from the same object set. This mode of operation encourages
greater generalization for computing relations, since g? is encouraged not to
over-ﬁt to the features of any particular object pair. Consider how an MLP
would learn the same function. An MLP would receive all objects from the
object set simultaneously as its input. It must then learn and embed n2 (where
n is the number of objects) identical functions within its weight parameters to
account for all possible object pairings. This quickly becomes intractable as the

3

number of objects grows. Therefore, the cost of learning a relation function n2
times using a single feedforward pass per sample, as in an MLP, is replaced by
the cost of n2 feedforward passes per object set (i.e., for each possible object
pair in the set) and learning a relation function just once, as in an RN. RNs
operate on a set of objects The summation in Equation 1 ensures that the RN
is invariant to the order of objects in its input, respecting the property that sets
are order invariant. Although we used summation, other commutative operators
? such as max, and average pooling ? can be used instead.

3
Tasks
We applied RN-augmented networks to a variety of tasks that hinge on
relational reasoning. To demonstrate the versatility of these networks we chose
tasks from a number of diﬀerent domains, including visual QA, text-based QA,
and dynamic physical systems. 3.1

CLEVR
In visual QA a model must learn to answer questions about an image (Figure
1). This is a challenging problem domain because it requires high-level scene
understanding [1, 14]. Architectures must perform complex relational reasoning
? spatial and otherwise ? over the features in the visual inputs, language inputs,
and their conjunction. However, the majority of visual QA datasets require
reasoning in the absence of fully speciﬁed word vocabularies, and perhaps more
perniciously, a vast and complicated knowledge of the world that is not available
in the training data. They also contain ambiguities and exhibit strong linguistic
biases that allow a model to learn answering strategies that exploit those biases,
without reasoning about the visual input [1, 15, 19]. To control for these issues,
and to distill the core challenges of visual QA, the CLEVR visual QA dataset
was developed [7]. CLEVR contains images of 3D-rendered objects, such as
spheres and cylinders (Figure 2). Each image is associated with a number of
questions that fall into diﬀerent 3

categories. For example, query attribute questions may ask ?What is the
color of the sphere??, while compare attribute questions may ask ?Is the cube
the same material as the cylinder??. For our purposes, an important feature
of CLEVR is that many questions are explicitly relational in nature. Remark-
ably, powerful QA architectures [24] are unable to solve CLEVR, presumably
because they cannot handle core relational aspects of the task. For example,
as reported in the original paper a model comprised of ResNet-101 image em-
beddings with LSTM question processing and augmented with stacked atten-
tion modules vastly outperformed other models at an overall performance of
68.5% (compared to 52.3% for the next best, and 92.6% human performance)
[7]. However, for compare attribute and count questions (i.e., questions heavily
involving relations across objects), the model performed little better than the
simplest baseline, which answered questions solely based on the probability of
answers in the training set for a given question category (Q-type baseline). We
used two versions of the CLEVR dataset: (i) the pixel version, in which images
were represented in standard 2D pixel form. (ii) a state description version, in
which images were explicitly represented by state description matrices contain-

4

ing factored object descriptions. Each row in the matrix contained the features
of a single object ? 3D coordinates (x, y, z); color (r, g, b); shape (cube, cylinder,
etc.); material (rubber, metal, etc.); size (small, large, etc.). When we trained
our models, we used either the pixel version or the state description version,
depending on the experiment, but not both together. 3.2

Sort-of-CLEVR
To explore our hypothesis that the RN architecture is better suited to gen-
eral relational reasoning as compared to more standard neural architectures, we
constructed a dataset similar to CLEVR that we call ?Sort-of-CLEVR?2 . This
dataset separates relational and non-relational questions. Sort-of-CLEVR con-
sists of images of 2D colored shapes along with questions and answers about the
images. Each image has a total of 6 objects, where each object is a randomly
chosen shape (square or circle). We used 6 colors (red, blue, green, orange,
yellow, gray) to unambiguously identify each object. Questions are hard-coded
as ﬁxed-length binary strings to reduce the diﬃculty involved with natural lan-
guage question-word processing, and thereby remove any confounding diﬃculty
with language parsing. For each image we generated 10 relational questions and
10 non-relational questions. Examples of relational questions are: ?What is the
shape of the object that is farthest from the gray object??; and ?How many
objects have the same shape as the green object??. Examples of non-relational
questions are: ?What is the shape of the gray object??; and ?Is the blue ob-
ject on the top or bottom of the scene??. The dataset is also visually simple,
reducing complexities involved in image processing. 3.3

bAbI
bAbI is a pure text-based QA dataset [22]. There are 20 tasks, each cor-
responding to a particular type of reasoning, such as deduction, induction, or
counting. Each question is associated with a set of supporting facts. For exam-
ple, the facts ?Sandra picked up the football? and ?Sandra went to the oﬃce?
support the question ?Where is the football?? (answer: ?oﬃce?). A model
succeeds on a task if its performance surpasses 95%. Many memory-augmented
neural networks have reported impressive results on bAbI. When training jointly
on all tasks using 10K examples per task, Memory Networks pass 14/20, DNC
16/20, Sparse DNC 19/20, and EntNet 16/20 (the authors of EntNets report
state-of-the-art at 20/20; however, unlike previously reported results this was
not done with joint training on all tasks, where they instead achieve 16/20) [23,
4, 17, 6]. 3.4

Dynamic physical systems
We developed a dataset of simulated physical mass-spring systems using the
MuJoCo physics engine [21]. Each scene contained 10 colored balls moving
on a table-top surface. Some of the balls moved independently, free to collide
with other balls and the barrier walls. Other randomly selected ball pairs were
connected by invisible springs or a rigid constraint. These connections prevented
the balls from moving independently, due to the force imposed through the
connections.
Input data consisted of state descriptions matrices, where each
ball was represented as a row in a matrix with features 2

The ?Sort-of-CLEVR? dataset will be made publicly available online

5

4
representing the rgb color values of each object and their spatial coordi-
nates (x and y) across 16 sequential time steps. The introduction of random
links between balls created an evolving physical system with a variable number
?systems? of connected balls (where ?systems? refers to connected graphs with
balls as nodes and connections between balls as edges). We deﬁned two separate
tasks: 1) infer the existence or absence of connections between balls when only
observing their color and coordinate positions across multiple sequential frames,
and 2) count the number of systems on the table-top, again when only observ-
ing each ball?s color and coordinate position across multiple sequential frames.
Both of these tasks involve reasoning about the relative positions and veloci-
ties of the balls to infer whether they are moving independently, or whether
their movement is somehow dependent on the movement of other balls through
invisible connections. For example, if the distance between two balls remains
similar across frames, then it can be inferred that there is a connection between
them. The ﬁrst task makes these inferences explicit, while the second task de-
mands that this reasoning occur implicitly, which is much more diﬃcult. For
further information on all tasks, including videos of the dynamic systems, see
the supplementary information.

4
Models
In their simplest form RNs operate on objects, and hence do not explicitly
operate on images or natural language. A central contribution of this work is
to demonstrate the ﬂexibility with which relatively unstructured inputs, such as
CNN or LSTM embeddings, can be considered as a set of objects for an RN. As
we describe below, we require minimal oversight in factorizing the RN?s input
into a set of objects. Final CNN feature maps

RN Object pair with question
object
-MLP -MLP
*
...
...
Conv.
+
small
Element-wise sum
What size is the cylinder that is left of the brown metal thing that is left of

the big sphere?
... what size
is ... sphere
LSTM
Figure 2: Visual QA architecture. Questions are processed with an LSTM to
produce a question embedding, and images are processed with a CNN to produce
a set of objects for the RN. Objects (three examples illustrated here in yellow,
red, and blue) are constructed using feature-map vectors from the convolved

6

image. The RN considers relations across all pairs of objects, conditioned on the
question embedding, and integrates all these relations to answer the question.
Dealing with pixels We used a CNN to parse pixel inputs into a set of objects.
The CNN took images of size 128 ? 128 and convolved them through four
convolutional layers to k feature maps of size d ? d, where k is the number
of kernels in the ﬁnal convolutional layer. We remained agnostic as to what
particular image features should constitute an object. So, after convolving the
image, each of the d2 k-dimensional cells in the d ? d feature maps was tagged
with a coordinate (from the range (?1, 1) for each of the x- and y-coordinates)3
indicating its relative spatial position, and was treated as an object for the RN
(see Figure 2). This means that an ?object? could comprise the background,
a particular physical object, a texture, conjunctions of physical objects, etc.,
which aﬀords the model great ﬂexibility in the learning process. 3

We also experimented without this tagging, and achieved performance of

88% on the validation set.

5
Conditioning RNs with question embeddings The existence and meaning
of an object-object relation should be question dependent. For example, if a
question asks about a large sphere, then the relations between small cubes are
probably irrelevant. So, weP modiﬁed the RN architecture such that g? could
condition its processing on the question: a = f? ( i,j g? (oi , oj , q)). To
get the question embedding q, we used the ﬁnal state of an LSTM that pro-
cessed question words. Question words were assigned unique integers, which
were then used to index a learnable lookup table that provided embeddings to
the LSTM. At each time-step, the LSTM received a single word embedding as
input, according to the syntax of the English-encoded question. Dealing with
state descriptions We can provide state descriptions directly into the RN, since
state descriptions are pre-factored object representations. Question process-
ing can proceed as before: questions pass through an LSTM using a learnable
lookup embedding for individual words, and the ﬁnal state of the LSTM is con-
catenated to each object-pair. Dealing with natural language For the bAbI suite
of tasks the natural language inputs must be transformed into a set of objects.
This is a distinctly diﬀerent requirement from visual QA, where objects were
deﬁned as spatially distinct regions in convolved feature maps. So, we ﬁrst took
the 20 sentences in the support set that were immediately prior to the probe
question. Then, we tagged these sentences with labels indicating their relative
position in the support set, and processed each sentence word-by-word with an
LSTM (with the same LSTM acting on each sentence independently). We note
that this setup invokes minimal prior knowledge, in that we delineate objects
as sentences, whereas previous bAbI models processed all word tokens from all
support sentences sequentially.
It?s unclear how much of an advantage this
prior knowledge provides, since period punctuation also unambiguously delin-
eates sentences for the token-by-token processing models. The ﬁnal state of the
sentence-processing-LSTM is considered to be an object. Similar to visual QA,
a separate LSTM produced a question embedding, which was appened to each
object pair as input to the RN. Our model was trained on the joint version of

7

bAbI (all 20 tasks simultaneously), using the full dataset of 10K examples per
task. Model conﬁguration details For the CLEVR-from-pixels task we used:
4 convolutional layers each with 24 kernels, ReLU non-linearities, and batch
normalization; 128 unit LSTM for question processing; 32 unit word-lookup
embeddings; four-layer MLP consisting of 256 units per layer with ReLU non-
linearities for g? ; and a three-layer MLP consisting of 256, 256 (with 50%
dropout), and 29 units with ReLU non-linearities for f? . The ﬁnal layer was
a linear layer that produced logits for a softmax over the answer vocabulary.
The softmax output was optimized with a cross-entropy loss function using the
Adam optimizer with a learning rate of 2.5e?4 . We used size 64 mini-batches
and distributed training with 10 workers synchronously updating a central pa-
rameter server. The conﬁgurations for the other tasks are similar, and can be
found in the supplementary information. We?d like to emphasize the simplicity
of our overall model architecture compared to the visual QA architectures used
on CLEVR thus far, which use ResNet or VGG embeddings, sometimes with
ﬁne-tuning, very large LSTMs for language encoding, and further processing
modules, such as stacked or iterative attention, or large fully connected layers
(upwards of 4000 units, often) [7].

5 5.1
Results CLEVR from pixels
Our model achieved state-of-the-art performance on CLEVR at 95.5%, ex-
ceeding the best model trained only on the pixel images and questions at the
time of the dataset?s publication by 27%, and surpassing human performance
in the task (see Table 1 and Figure 3). These results ? in particular, those ob-
tained in the compare attribute and count categories ? are a testament to the
ability of our model to do relational reasoning. In fact, it is in these categories
that state-of-the-art models struggle most. Furthermore, the relative simplicity
of the network components used in our model suggests that the diﬃculty of the
CLEVR task lies in its relational reasoning demands, not on the language or
the visual processing. Many CLEVR questions involve computing and compar-
ing more than one relation; for example, consider the question: ?There is a big
thing on the right side of the big rubber cylinder that is behind 6

Model
Overall
Count
Exist
92.6 41.8 46.8 52.3 68.5 76.6 95.5
86.7 34.6 41.7 43.7 52.2 64.4 90.1
96.6 50.2 61.1 65.2 71.1 82.7 97.8
Human Q-type baseline LSTM CNN+LSTM CNN+LSTM+SA CNN+LSTM+SA*

CNN+LSTM+RN

Compare Numbers 86.5 51.0 69.8 67.1 73.5 77.4 93.6
Query Attribute 95.0 36.0 36.8 49.3 85.3 82.6 97.9
Compare Attribute 96.0 51.3 51.8 53.0 52.3 75.4 97.1
* Our implementation, with optimized hyperparameters and trained end-
to-end using the same CNN as in our RN model. We also tagged coordinates,

8

which did not improve performance. Table 1: Results on CLEVR from pixels.
Performances of our model (RN) and previously reported models [8], measured
as accuracy on the test set and broken down by question category.

the large cylinder to the right of the tiny yellow rubber thing; What is
its shape??, which has three spatial relations (?right side?, ?behind?, ?right
of?). On such questions, our model achieves 93% performance, indicating that
the model can handle complex relational reasoning. Results using privileged
training information A more recent study reports overall performance of 96.9%
on CLEVR, but uses additional supervisory signals on the functional programs
used to generate the CLEVR questions [8]. It is not possible for us to directly
compare this to our work since we do not use these additional supervision signals.
Nonetheless, our approach greatly outperforms a version of their model that was
not trained with these extra signals, and even a version of their model trained
using 9K ground-truth programs. Thus, RNs can achieve very competitive, and
even super-human results under much weaker and more natural assumptions,
and even in situations when functional programs are unavailable.

Accuracy
compare numbers 1.0 0.5 0.25 0.0 overall
count
exist
query attribute
Accuracy
Human CNN+LSTM+RN CNN+LSTM+SA CNN+LSTM LSTM Q-type

baseline
0.75
more than
less than
query color
compare size
equal compare attribute
1.0 0.75 0.5 0.25 0.0
query size
query shape
query material
compare shape
compare material
compare color
Figure 3: Results on CLEVR from pixels. The RN-augmented model out-
performed all other models and exhibited super-human performance overall.
In particular, it solved ?compare attribute? questions, which trouble all other
models because they heavily depend on relational reasoning. 5.2

CLEVR from state descriptions
To demonstrate that the RN is robust to the form of its input, we trained
our model on the state description matrix version of the CLEVR dataset. The
model achieved an accuracy of 96.4%. This result demonstrates the generality of
the RN module, showing its capacity to learn and reason about object relations

9

while being agnostic to the kind of inputs it receives ? i.e., to the particular
representation of the object features to which it has access. Therefore, RNs are
not necessarily 7

restricted to visual problems, and can thus be applied in very diﬀerent con-

texts, and to diﬀerent tasks that require relational reasoning. 5.3

Sort-of-CLEVR from pixels
The results so far led us to hypothesize that the diﬃculty in solving CLEVR
lies in its heavy emphasis on relational reasoning, contrary to previous claims
that the diﬃculty lies in question parsing [9]. However, the questions in the
CLEVR dataset are not categorized based on the degree to which they may be
relational, making it hard to assess our hypothesis. Therefore, we use the Sort-
of-CLEVR dataset which we explicitly designed to seperate out relational and
non-relational questions (see Section 3.2). We ﬁnd that a CNN augmented with
an RN achieves an accuracy above 94% for both relational and non-relational
questions. However, a CNN augmented with an MLP only reached this per-
formance on the non-relational questions, plateauing at 63% on the relational
questions. This strongly indicates that models lacking a dedicated relational
reasoning component struggle, or may even be completely incapable of solving
tasks that require very simple relational reasoning. Augmenting these models
with a relational module, like the RN, is suﬃcient to overcome this hurdle. A
simple ?closest-to? or ?furthest-from? relation is particularly revealing of a
CNN+MLP?s lack of general reasoning capabilities (52.3% success). For these
relations a model must gauge the distances between each object, and then com-
pare each of these distances. Moreover, depending on the images, the relevant
distance could be quite small in magnitude, or quite large, further increasing
the combinatoric diﬃculty of this task. 5.4

bAbI
Our model succeeded on 18/20 tasks. Notably, it succeeded on the basic in-
duction task (2.1% total error), which proved diﬃcult for the Sparse DNC (54%),
DNC (55.1%), and EntNet (52.1%). Also, our model did not catastrophically
fail in any of the tasks: for the 2 tasks that it failed (the ?two supporting facts?,
and ?three supporting facts? tasks), it missed the 95% threshold by 3.1% and
11.5%, respectively. We also note that the model we evaluated was chosen based
on overall performance on a withheld validation set, using a single seed. That
is, we did not run multiple replicas with the best hyperparameter settings (as
was done in other models, such as the Sparse DNC, which demonstrated per-
formance ﬂuctuations with a standard deviation of more than ?3 tasks passed
for the best choice of hyperparameters). 5.5

Dynamic physical systems
Finally, we trained our model on two tasks requiring reasoning about the
dynamics of balls moving along a surface.
In the connection inference task,
our model correctly classiﬁed all the connections in 93% of the sample scenes
in the test set.
In the counting task, the RN achieved similar performance,
reporting the correct number of connected systems for 95% of the test scene
samples. In comparison, an MLP with comparable number of parameters was
unable to perform better than chance for both tasks. Moreover, using this task

10

to learn to infer relations results in transfer to unseen motion capture data,
where RNs predict the connections between body joints of a walking human
(see Supplementary Material for experimental details and example videos).

6
Discussion and Conclusions
RNs are powerful, versatile, and simple neural network modules with the
capacity for relational reasoning. The performance of RN-augmented networks
on CLEVR is especially notable; they signiﬁcantly improve upon current gen-
eral purpose, state-of-the-art models (upwards of 25%), indicating that previous
architectures lacked a fundamental, general capacity to reason about relations.
Moreover, these results unveil an important distinction between the often con-
founded notions of processing and reasoning. Powerful visual QA architectures
contain components, such as ResNets, which are highly capable visual processors
capable of detecting complicated textures and forms. However, as demonstrated
by CLEVR, they lack an ability to reason about the features they detect. 8

RNs can easily exploit foreknowledge of the relations that should be com-
puted for a particular task.
Indeed, especially in circumstances with strong
computational constraints, bounding the otherwise quadratic complexity of the
number of relations could be advantageous. Attentional mechanisms could re-
duce the number of objects fed as input to the RN, and hence reduce the number
of relations that need to be considered. Or, using an additional down-sampling
convolutional or pooling layer could further reduce the number of objects pro-
vided as input to the RN; indeed, max-pooling to 4 ? 4 feature maps reduces
the total number of objects, and hence computed relations, and results in 87%
performance on the validation set. RNs have a ﬂexible input format: a set of
objects. Our results show that, strikingly, the set of objects does not need to
be cleverly pre-factored. RNs learn to deal with ?object? representations pro-
vided by CNNs and LSTMs, presumably by inﬂuencing the content and form of
the object representations via the gradients they propagate. In future work it
would be interesting to apply RNs to relational reasoning across highly abstract
entities (for example, decisions in hierarchical reinforcement learning tasks).
Relation reasoning is a central component of generally intelligent behavior, and
so, we expect the RN to be a simple-to-use, useful and widely used neural mod-
ule. Acknowledgments We would like to thank Murray Shanahan, Ari Morcos,
Scott Reed, Daan Wierstra, and many others on the DeepMind team, for critical
feedback and discussions.

9

2 References

[1] Stanislaw Antol, Aishwarya Agrawal, Jiasen Lu, Margaret Mitchell, Dhruv
Batra, C Lawrence Zitnick, and Devi Parikh. Vqa: Visual question answer-
[2] Peter Battaglia, Razvan Pascanu, Matthew Lai,
ing.
Interaction networks for learning about ob-
Danilo Jimenez Rezende, et al.
jects, relations and physics. In NIPS, 2016.
[3] Marta Garnelo, Kai Arulku-

In ICCV, 2015.

11

maran, and Murray Shanahan. Towards deep symbolic reinforcement learn-
ing. arXiv:1609.05518, 2016. [4] Alex Graves, Greg Wayne, Malcolm Reynolds,
Tim Harley, Ivo Danihelka, Agnieszka Grabska-Barwi?nska, Sergio G?mez Col-
menarejo, Edward Grefenstette, Tiago Ramalho, John Agapiou, et al. Hybrid
computing using a neural network with dynamic external memory. Nature,
2016. [5] Stevan Harnad. The symbol grounding problem. Physica D: Nonlin-
ear Phenomena, 42(1-3):335?346, 1990. [6] Mikael Henaﬀ, Jason Weston, Arthur
Szlam, Antoine Bordes, and Yann LeCun. Tracking the world state with recur-
rent entity networks. In ICLR, 2017.
[7] Justin Johnson, Bharath Hariharan,
Laurens van der Maaten, Li Fei-Fei, C Lawrence Zitnick, and Ross Girshick.
Clevr: A diagnostic dataset for compositional language and elementary visual
reasoning. In CVPR, 2017. [8] Justin Johnson, Bharath Hariharan, Laurens van
der Maaten, Judy Hoﬀman, Li Fei-Fei, C Lawrence Zitnick, and Ross Girshick.
Inferring and executing programs for visual reasoning. arXiv:1705.03633, 2017.
[9] Kushal Kaﬂe and Christopher Kanan. arXiv:1703.09684, 2017.

An analysis of visual question answering algorithms.
[10] Charles Kemp and Joshua B Tenenbaum. The discovery of structural
form. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 105(31):10687?10692,
2008.
[11] Brenden M Lake, Tomer D Ullman, Joshua B Tenenbaum, and
Samuel J Gershman. Building machines that learn and think like people.
arXiv:1604.00289, 2016. [12] Yann LeCun, Yoshua Bengio, and Geoﬀrey Hinton.
Deep learning. Nature, 521(7553):436?444, 2015. [13] Yujia Li, Daniel Tarlow,
Marc Brockschmidt, and Richard Zemel. Gated graph sequence neural net-
works. ICLR, 2016. [14] Mateusz Malinowski and Mario Fritz. A multi-world
approach to question answering about real-world scenes based on uncertain in-
put. In NIPS, 2014.
[15] Mateusz Malinowski, Marcus Rohrbach, and Mario
Fritz. Ask your neurons: A deep learning approach to visual question answering.
arXiv:1605.02697, 2016. [16] Allen Newell. Physical symbol systems. Cognitive
science, 4(2):135?183, 1980.
[17] Jack Rae, Jonathan J Hunt, Ivo Danihelka,
Timothy Harley, Andrew W Senior, Gregory Wayne, Alex Graves, and Tim
Lillicrap. Scaling memory-augmented neural networks with sparse reads and
writes. In NIPS, 2016. [18] David Raposo, Adam Santoro, David Barrett, Raz-
van Pascanu, Timothy Lillicrap, and Peter Battaglia. Discovering objects and
their relations from entangled scene representations. arXiv:1702.05068, 2017.
[19] Mengye Ren, Ryan Kiros, and Richard Zemel.
Image question answer-
ing: A visual semantic embedding model and a new dataset. In NIPS, 2015.
[20] Franco Scarselli, Marco Gori, Ah Chung Tsoi, Markus Hagenbuchner, and
Gabriele Monfardini. The graph neural network model. IEEE Transactions on
Neural Networks, 2009.
[21] Emanuel Todorov, Tom Erez, and Yuval Tassa.
Mujoco: A physics engine for model-based control.
[22] Ja-
son Weston, Antoine Bordes, Sumit Chopra, and Tomas Mikolov. Towards ai-
complete question answering: A set of prerequisite toy tasks. arXiv:1502.05698,
2015.
[23] Jason Weston, Sumit Chopra, and Antoine Bordes. Memory net-
works. In ICLR, 2015. [24] Zichao Yang, Xiaodong He, Jianfeng Gao, Li Deng,
and Alex Smola. Stacked attention networks for image question answering. In
CVPR, 2016.

In IROS, 2012.

12

10

13

