K-Medoids For K-Means Seeding

Authored by:

Fran?ois Fleuret
James Newling

Abstract

We show experimentally that the algorithm CLARANS of Ng and
Han (1994) ﬁnds better K-medoids solutions than the Voronoi iteration
algorithm of Hastie et al. (2001). This ﬁnding, along with the similarity
between the Voronoi iteration algorithm and Lloyd’s K-means algorithm,
motivates us to use CLARANS as a K-means initializer. We show that
CLARANS outperforms other algorithms on 23/23 datasets with a mean
decrease over k-means++ of 30% for initialization mean squared error
(MSE) and 3% for ﬁnal MSE. We introduce algorithmic improvements to
CLARANS which improve its complexity and runtime, making it a viable
initialization scheme for large datasets.

1 Paper Body

K-means and K-medoids

The K-means problem is to ﬁnd a partitioning of points, so as to minimize
the sum of the squares of the distances from points to their assigned partition?s
mean. In general this problem is NP-hard, and in practice approximation al-
gorithms are used. The most popular of these is Lloyd?s algorithm, henceforth
lloyd, which alternates between freezing centers and assignments, while updat-
ing the other. Speciﬁcally, in the assignment step, for each point the nearest
(frozen) center is determined. Then during the update step, each center is set
to the mean of points assigned to it. lloyd has applications in data compression,
data classiﬁcation, density estimation and many other areas, and was recognised
in Wu et al. (2008) as one of the top-10 algorithms in data mining. The closely
related K-medoids problem diﬀers in that the center of a cluster is its medoid,
not its mean, where the medoid is the cluster member which minimizes the sum
of dissimilarities between itself and other cluster members. In this paper, as
our application is K-means initialization, we focus on the case where dissimi-
larity is squared distance, although K-medoids generalizes to non-metric spaces
and arbitrary dissimilarity measures, as discussed in ?SM-A. By modifying the
update step in lloyd to compute medoids instead of means, a viable K-medoids
algorithm is obtained. This algorithm has been proposed at least twice (Hastie

1

et al., 2001; Park and Jun, 2009) and is often referred to as the Voronoi iteration
algorithm. We refer to it as medlloyd. Another K-medoids algorithm is clarans
of Ng and Han (1994, 2002), for which there is no direct K-means equivalent. It
works by randomly proposing swaps between medoids and non-medoids, accept-
ing only those which decrease MSE. We will discuss how clarans works, what
advantages it has over medlloyd, and our motivation for using it for K-means
initialization in ?2 and ?SM-A. 1.2

K-means initialization
lloyd is a local algorithm, in that far removed centers and points do not
directly inﬂuence each other. This property contributes to lloyd?s tendency to
terminate in poor minima if not well initial31st Conference on Neural Informa-
tion Processing Systems (NIPS 2017), Long Beach, CA, USA.

initial: ﬁnal:
? ?
?
?
?
?
initial: ﬁnal:
?
?
? ?
? ?
Figure 1: N = 3 points, to be partitioned into K = 2 clusters with lloyd, with
two possible initializations (top) and their solutions (bottom). Colors denote
clusters, stars denote samples, rings denote means. Initialization with clarans
enables jumping between the initializations on the left and right, ensuring that
when lloyd eventually runs it avoids the local minimum on the left. ized. Good
initialization is key to guaranteeing that the reﬁnement performed by lloyd is
done in the vicinity of a good solution, an example showing this is given in
Figure 1. In the comparative study of K-means initialization methods of Celebi
et al. (2013), 8 schemes are tested across a wide range of datasets. Comparison
is done in terms of speed (time to run initialization+lloyd) and energy (ﬁnal
MSE). They ﬁnd that 3/8 schemes should be avoided, due to poor performance.
One of these schemes is uniform initialization, henceforth uni, where K samples
are randomly selected to initialize centers. Of the remaining 5/8 schemes, there
is no clear best, with results varying across datasets, but the authors suggest
that the algorithm of Bradley and Fayyad (1998), henceforth bf, is a good
choice. The bf scheme of Bradley and Fayyad (1998) works as follows. Samples
are separated into J (= 10) partitions. lloyd with uni initialization is performed
on each of the partitions, providing J centroid sets of size K. A superset of
JK elements is created by concatenating the J center sets. lloyd is then run J
times on the superset, initialized at each run with a distinct center set. The
center set which obtains the lowest MSE on the superset is taken as the ﬁnal
initializer for the ﬁnal run of lloyd on all N samples. Probably the most widely
implemented initialization scheme other than uni is k-means++ (Arthur and

2

Vassilvitskii, 2007), henceforth km++. Its popularity stems from its simplicity,
low computational complexity, theoretical guarantees, and strong experimental
support. The algorithm works by sequentially selecting K seeding samples. At
each iteration, a sample is selected with probability proportional to the square
of its distance to the nearest previously selected sample. The work of Bachem
et al.
(2016) focused on developing sampling schemes to accelerate km++,
while maintaining its theoretical guarantees. Their algorithm afk-mc2 results
in as good initializations as km++, while using only a small fraction of the
KN distance calculations required by km++. This reduction is important for
massive datasets. In none of the 4 schemes discussed is a center ever replaced
once selected. Such reﬁnement is only performed during the running of lloyd.
In this paper we show that performing reﬁnement during initialization with
clarans, before the ﬁnal lloyd reﬁnement, signiﬁcantly lowers K-means MSEs.
1.3

Our contribution and paper summary
We compare the K-medoids algorithms clarans and medlloyd, ﬁnding that
clarans ﬁnds better local minima, in ?3 and ?SM-A. We oﬀer an explanation
for this, which motivates the use of clarans for initializing lloyd (Figure 2).
We discuss the complexity of clarans, and brieﬂy show how it can be opti-
mised in ?4, with a full presentation of acceleration techniques in ?SM-D. Most
signiﬁcantly, we compare clarans with methods uni, bf, km++ and afk-mc2
for K-means initialization, and show that it provides signiﬁcant reductions in
initialization and ﬁnal MSEs in ?5. We thus provide a conceptually simple ini-
tialization scheme which is demonstrably better than km++, which has been
the de facto initialization method for one decade now. Our source code at
https://github.com/idiap/zentas is available under an open source license. It
consists of a C++ library with Python interface, with several examples for
diverse data types (sequence data, sparse and dense vectors), metrics (Leven-
shtein, l1 , etc.) and potentials (quadratic as in K-means, logarithmic, etc.).
1.4

Other Related Works
Alternatives to lloyd have been considered which resemble the swapping
approach of clarans. One is by Hartigan (1975), where points are randomly
selected and reassigned. Telgarsky and 2

Vattani (2010) show how this heuristic can result in better clustering when
there are few points per cluster. The work most similar to clarans in the K-
means setting is that of Kanungo et al. (2002), where it is indirectly shown that
clarans ﬁnds a solution within a factor 25 of the optimal K-medoids clustering.
The local search approximation algorithm they propose is a hybrid of clarans
and lloyd, alternating between the two, with sampling from a kd-tree during the
clarans-like step. Their source code includes an implementation of an algorithm
they call ?Swap?, which is exactly the clarans algorithm of Ng and Han (1994).

2
Two K-medoids algorithms
Like km++ and afk-mc2 , K-medoids generalizes beyond the standard K-
means setting of Euclidean metric with quadratic potential, but we consider

3

only the standard setting in the main body of this paper, referring the reader to
SM-A for a more general presentation. In Algorithm 1, medlloyd is presented.
It is essentially lloyd with the update step modiﬁed for K-medoids. Algorithm
1 two-step iterative medlloyd algo- Algorithm 2 swap-based clarans algorithm
(in rithm (in vector space with quadratic potential). a vector space and with
quadratic potential). 1: nr ? 0 1: Initialize center indices c(k), as distinct
elcenter indices C ? {1, . .
, N }, where index k ?
2: Initialize PN {1, . . . , K}. 3: ? ? ? i=1 mini0 ?C kx(i) ? x(i0 )k2 2: do
4: while nr ? Nr do 3: for i = 1 : N do 5: sample i? ? C and i+ ? {1, . . . ,
N } C PN 4: a(i) ? arg min kx(i)?x(c(k))k2 6: ? + ? i=1 k?{1,...,K} 7: mini0
?C{i? }?{i+ } kx(i) ? x(i0 )k2 5: end for 8: if ? + ¡ ? ? then 6: for k = 1 : K
do 9: C ? C {i? } ? {i+ } 7: c(k) ? X 10: nr ? 0, ? ? ? ? + kx(i)?x(i0 )k2 11:
8: arg min else i:a(i)=k

, N } ements of {1, . .

.

.

i0 :a(i0 )=k
12: nr ? nr + 1 13: end if 14: end while
9: end for 10: while c(k) changed for at least one k
In Algorithm 2, clarans is presented. Following a random initialization of
the K centers (line 2), it proceeds by repeatedly proposing a random swap
(line 5) between a center (i? ) and a noncenter (i+ ). If a swap results in a
reduction in energy (line 8), it is implemented (line 9). clarans terminates when
Nr consecutive proposals have been rejected. Alternative stopping criteria could
be number of accepted swaps, rate of energy decrease or time. We use Nr =
K 2 throughout, as this makes proposals between all pairs of clusters probable,
assuming balanced cluster sizes. clarans was not the ﬁrst swap-based K-medoids
algorithm, being preceded by pam and clara of Kaufman and Rousseeuw (1990).
It can however provide better complexity than other swap-based algorithms
if certain optimisations are used, as discussed in ?4. When updating centers
in lloyd and medlloyd, assignments are frozen.
In contrast, with swapbased
algorithms such as clarans, assignments change along with the medoid index
being changed (i? to i+ ). As a consequence, swap-based algorithms look one
step further ahead when computing MSEs, which helps them escape from the
minima of medlloyd. This is described in Figure 2.

3
A Simple Simulation Study for Illustration
We generate simple 2-D data, and compare medlloyd, clarans, and baseline
K-means initializers km++ and uni, in terms of MSEs. The data is described
in Figure 3, where sample initializations are also presented. Results in Figure
4 show that clarans provides signiﬁcantly lower MSEs than medlloyd, an ob-
servation which generalizes across data types (sequence, sparse, etc), metrics
(Levenshtein, l? , etc), and potentials (exponential, logarithmic, etc), as shown
in Appendix SM-A. 3

? x(3)
? x(1)
? x(2)
? x(5)
? x(4)

4

? x(6)
? x(7)
? = 2?2
? = 2?4
? = 2?6
Figure 2: Example with N = 7 samples, of which K = 2 are medoids. Current
medoid indices are 1 and 4. Using medlloyd, this is a local minimum, with ﬁnal
clusters {x(1)}, and the rest. clarans may consider swap (i? , i+ ) = (4, 7)
and so escape to a lower MSE. The key to swapbased algorithms is that cluster
assignments are never frozen. Speciﬁcally, when considering the swap of x(4) and
x(7), clarans assigns x(2), x(3) and x(4) to the cluster of x(1) before computing
the new MSE.

0
4
19
uni
medlloyd
++
clarans
Figure 3: (Column 1) Simulated data in R2 . For each cluster center g ? {0,
. . . , 19}2 , 100 points are drawn from N (g, ? 2 I), illustrated here for ? ? {2?6
, 2?4 , 2?2 }. (Columns 2,3,4,5) Sample initializations. We observe ?holes? for
methods uni, medlloyd and km++. clarans successfully ﬁlls holes by removing
distant, underutilised centers. The spatial correlation of medlloyd?s holes are
due to its locality of updating.

Complexity and Accelerations
lloyd requires KN distance calculations to update K centers, assuming no
acceleration technique such as that of Elkan (2003) is used. The cost of several
iterations of lloyd outweighs initialization with any of uni, km++ and afk-
mc2 . We ask if the same is true with clarans initialization, and ﬁnd that the
answer depends on how clarans is implemented. clarans as presented in Ng
and Han (1994) is O(N 2 ) in computation and memory, making it unusable
for large datasets. To make clarans scalable, we have investigated ways of
implementing it in O(N ) memory, and devised optimisations which make its
complexity equivalent to that of lloyd.

ﬁnal M SE/? 2
init M SE/? 2
clarans consists of two main steps. The ﬁrst is swap evaluation (line 6) and
the second is swap implementation (scope of if-statement at line 8). Proposing
a good swap becomes less probable as MSE decreases, thus as the number of
swap implementations increases the number of consecutive rejected proposals
(nr ) is likely to grow large, illustrated in Figure 5. This results in a larger
fraction of time being spent in the evaluation step.

216 212 28 24 20 2?4?10 ?9 ?8 ?7 ?6 ?5 ?4 ?3 ?2 ?1 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 ?
216 medlloyd uni 212 ++ 28 clarans 4 2 20 2?4?10 ?9 ?8 ?7 ?6 ?5 ?4 ?3 ?2

?1 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 ?

5

Figure 4: Results on simulated data. For 400 values of ? ? [2?10 , 2?1 ],
initialization (left) and ﬁnal (right) MSEs relative to true cluster variances. For
? ? [2?5 , 2?2 ] km++ never results in minimal MSE (M SE/? 2 = 1), while
clarans does for all ?. Initialization MSE with medlloyd is on average 4 times
lower than with uni, but most of this improvement is regained when lloyd is
subsequently run (ﬁnal M SE/? 2 ).

4
evaluations
Nr 210 20
0
500
1000 1500 accepted swaps (implementations)
2000
Figure 5: The number of consecutive swap proposal rejections (evaluations)
before one is accepted (implementations), for simulated data (?3) with ? =
2?4 . We will now discuss optimisations in order of increasing algorithmic com-
plexity, presenting their computational complexities in terms of evaluation and
implementation steps. The explanations here are high level, with algorithmic
details and pseudocode deferred to ?SM-D. Level -2 To evaluate swaps (line 6),
simply compute all KN distances. Level -1 Keep track of nearest centers. Now
to evaluate a swap, samples whose nearest center is x(i? ) need distances to
all K samples indexed by C {i? } ? {i+ } computed in order to determine
the new nearest. Samples whose nearest is not x(i? ) only need the distance
to x(i+ ) computed to determine their nearest, as either, (1) their nearest is
unchanged, or (2) it is x(i+ ). Level 0 Also keep track of second nearest cen-
ters, as in the implementation of Ng and Han (1994), which recall is O(N 2 ) in
memory and computes all distances upfront. Doing so, nearest centers can be
determined for all samples by computing distances to x(i+ ). If swap (i? , i+ )
is accepted, samples whose new nearest is x(i+ ) require K distance calculations
to recompute second nearests. Thus from level -1 to 0, computation is trans-
ferred from evaluation to implementation, which is good, as implementation is
less frequently performed, as illustrated in Figure 5. Level 1 Also keep track,
for each cluster center, of the distance to the furthest cluster member as well
as the maximum, over all cluster members, of the minimum distance to another
center. Using the triangle inequality, one can then frequently eliminate compu-
tation for clusters which are unchanged by proposed swaps with just a single
center-to-center distance calculation. Note that using the triangle inequality
requires that the K-medoids dissimilarity is metric based, as is the case in the
K-means initialization setting. Level 2 Also keep track of center-to-center dis-
tances. This allows whole clusters to be tagged as unchanged by a swap, without
computing any distances in the evaluation step. We have also considered opti-
misations which, unlike levels -2 to 2, do not result in the exact same clustering
as clarans, but provide additional acceleration. One such optimisation uses ran-
dom subsampling to evaluate proposals, which helps signiﬁcantly when N/K is
large. Another optimisation which is eﬀective during initial rounds is to not
implement the ﬁrst MSE reducing swap found, but to rather continue searching

6

for approximately as long as swap implementation takes, thus balancing time
between searching (evaluation) and implementing swaps. Details can be found
in ?SM-D.3. The computational complexities of these optimisations are in Table
1. Proofs of these complexities rely on there being O(N/K) samples changing
their nearest or second nearest center during a swap. In other words, for any
two clusters of sizes n1 and n2 , we assume n1 = ?(n2 ). Using level 2 complex-
ities, we see that if a fraction p(C) of proposals reduce MSE, then the expected
complexity is O(N (1 + 1/(p(C)K))). One cannot marginalise C out of the ex-
pectation, as C may have no MSE reducing swaps, that is p(C) = 0. If p(C) is
O(K), we obtain complexity O(N ) per swap, which is equivalent to the O(KN
) for K center updates of lloyd. In Table 2, we consider run times and distance
calculation counts on simulated data at the various levels of optimisation.

5
Results
We ﬁrst compare clarans with uni, km++, afk-mc2 and bf on the ﬁrst 23
publicly available datasets in Table 3 (datasets 1-23). As noted in Celebi et
al. (2013), it is common practice to run initialization+lloyd several time and
retain the solution with the lowest MSE. In Bachem et al. (2016) methods are
run a ﬁxed number of times, and mean MSEs are compared. However, when
comparing minimum MSEs over several runs, one should take into account that
methods vary in their time requirements. 5

1 evaluation 1 implementation K 2 evaluations, K implementations memory
-2 NK 1 K 3N N
-1 N 1 K 2N N
0 N N K 2N N
1 +K N N K + K3 N N K
2 N K
N KN N + K2
Table 1: The complexities at diﬀerent levels of optimisation of evaluation and
implementation, in terms of required distance calculations, and overall memory.
We see at level 2 that to perform K 2 evaluations and K implementations is
O(KN ), equivalent to lloyd.

-2 -1 0 1 2 log2 (# dcs ) 44.1 36.5 35.5 29.4 26.7 time [s] 407 19.2 15.6
Table 2: Total number of distance calculations (# dcs ) and time required
by clarans on simulation data of ?3 with ? = 2?4 at diﬀerent optimisation levels.
dataset # N dim K TL [s] a1 1 3000 2 40 1.94 a2 2 5250 2 70 1.37 a3 3
7500 2 100 1.69 birch1 4 100000 2 200 21.13 birch2 5 100000 2 200 15.29 birch3
6 100000 2 200 16.38 ConfLong 7 164860 3 22 30.74 dim032 8 1024 32 32 1.13
dim064 9 1024 64 32 1.19 dim1024 10 1024 1024 32 7.68 europe 11 169308 2
1000 166.08

dataset housec8 KDD? mnist Mopsi rna? s1 s2 s3 s4 song? susy? yeast
# N dim K TL [s] 12 34112 3 400 18.71 13 145751 74 200 998.83 14 10000
784 300 233.48 15 13467 2 100 2.14 16 20000 8 200 6.84 17 5000 2 30 1.20 18
5000 2 30 1.50 19 5000 2 30 1.39 20 5000 2 30 1.44 21 20000 90 200 71.10 22
20000 18 200 24.50 23 1484 8 40 1.23

7

Table 3: The 23 datasets. Column ?TL? is time allocated to run with each
initialization scheme, so that no new runs start after TL elapsed seconds. The
starred datasets are those used in Bachem et al.
(2016), the remainder are
available at https://cs.joensuu.ﬁ/sipu/datasets.

Rather than run each method a ﬁxed number of times, we therefore run each
method as many times as possible in a given time limit, ?TL?. This dataset
dependent time limit, given by columns TL in Table 3, is taken as 80? the
time of a single run of km+++lloyd. The numbers of runs completed in time
TL by each method are in columns 1-5 of Table 4. Recall that our stopping
criterion for clarans is K 2 consecutively rejected swap proposals. We have also
experimented with stopping criterion based on run time and number of swaps
implemented, but ﬁnd that stopping based on number of rejected swaps best
guarantees convergence. We use K 2 rejections for simplicity, although have
found that fewer than K 2 are in general needed to obtain minimal MSEs. We
use the fast lloyd implementation accompanying Newling and Fleuret (2016)
with the ?auto? ﬂag set to select the best exact accelerated algorithm, and run
until complete convergence. For initializations, we use our own C++/Cython
implementation of level 2 optimised clarans, the implementation of afk-mc2 of
Bachem et al. (2016), and km++ and bf of Newling and Fleuret (2016). The
objective of Bachem et al.
(2016) was to prove and experimentally validate
that afk-mc2 produces initialization MSEs equivalent to those of km++, and
as such lloyd was not run during experiments. We consider both initialization
MSE, as in Bachem et al.
(2016), and ﬁnal MSE after lloyd has run. The
latter is particularly important, as it is the objective we wish to minimize in
the K-means problem. In addition to considering initialization and ﬁnal MSEs,
we also distinguish between mean and minimum MSEs. We believe the latter
is important as it captures the varying time requirements, and as mentioned it
is common to run lloyd several times and retain the lowest MSE clustering. In
Table 4 we consider two MSEs, namely mean initialization MSE and minimum
ﬁnal MSE. 6

bf
cla rans
1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1
uni
29 7 4 5 6 4 46 19 16 18 4 4 5 4 4 4 25 30 24 24 4 4 6 8
afk mc2
km ++
8 5 6 28 27 23 38 5 5 24 15 21 56 83 7 28 5 7 6 6 67 67 5 14
km ++
cla rans
138 85 87 95 137 77 75 88 90 311 28 81 65 276 52 86 85 100 83 87 98 134 81

93

0.97 2 0.99 1.96 0.99 2.07 0.99 1.54 1 3.8 0.98 2.35 1 1.17 0.98 43.1 1.01 ¿102
0.99 ¿102 1 20.2 0.99 2.09 1 4 1 1 1 25 0.99 24.5 1.01 2.79 0.99 2.24 1.05 1.55
1.01 1.65 1 1.14 1 1.04 1 1.18 1 4.71

minimum ﬁnal mse cla rans

8

bf
65 24 21 27 22 22 66 29 29 52 25 27 74 43 23 28 31 39 36 36 52 48 31 34
0.63 0.62 0.63 0.69 0.62 0.67 0.73 0.65 0.66 0.72 0.72 0.77 0.77 0.87 0.6 0.62

0.7 0.69 0.71 0.71 0.8 0.81 0.74 0.7

0.59 0.6 0.6 0.66 0.62 0.64 0.64 0.65 0.66 0.62 0.67 0.7 0.69 0.6 0.57 0.62 0.66

0.65 0.65 0.65 0.67 0.69 0.65 0.64

0.58 0.59 0.61 0.66 0.62 0.64 0.64 0.65 0.66 0.61 0.67 0.7 0.69 0.6 0.57 0.61

0.65 0.65 0.65 0.64 0.66 0.69 0.65 0.64

0.59 0.61 0.62 0.66 0.64 0.68 0.64 0.66 0.66 0.62 2.25 0.73 0.75 0.6 3.71 2.18

0.67 0.66 0.66 0.64 0.71 0.69 0.65 0.79

0.61 0.63 0.63 0.66 0.63 0.68 0.64 0.66 0.69 0.62 2.4 0.74 0.75 0.61 3.62 2.42

0.69 0.66 0.67 0.65 0.7 0.69 0.67 0.8

0.57 0.58 0.59 0.66 0.59 0.63 0.64 0.63 0.63 0.59 0.64 0.69 0.69 0.6 0.51 0.56

0.65 0.64 0.65 0.64 0.65 0.69 0.64 0.62

uni
uni
135 81 82 79 85 68 84 84 81 144 70 80 102 88 91 107 84 100 88 88 96 116 82

90

afk mc2
afk mc2
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 gm
mean initial mse
km ++
runs completed
ﬁnal MSE
initialisation MSE
Table 4: Summary of results on the 23 datasets (rows). Columns 1 to
5 contain the number of initialization+lloyd runs completed in time limit TL.
Columns 6 to 14 contain MSEs relative to the mean initialization MSE of km++.
Columns 6 to 9 are mean MSEs after initialization but before lloyd, and columns
10 to 14 are minimum MSEs after lloyd. The ﬁnal row (gm) contains geometric
means of all columns. clarans consistently obtains the lowest across all MSE
measurements, and has a 30% lower initialization MSE than km++ and afk-mc2
, and a 3% lower ﬁnal minimum MSE.

1.1 1.0 0.9 0.8 0.7 0.6 0.5 1.1 1.0 0.9 0.8 0.7 0.6 0.5
(3) (2) (1)
km++ clarans
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9

9

10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22
23
dataset
Figure 6: Initialization (above) and ﬁnal (below) MSEs for km++ (left bars)
and clarans (right bars), with minumum (1), mean (2) and mean + standard
deviation (3) of MSE across all runs. For all initialization MSEs and most ﬁnal
MSEs, the lowest km++ MSE is several standard deviations higher than the
mean clarans MSE.

7
5.1
Baseline performance
We brieﬂy discuss ﬁndings related to algorithms uni, bf, afk-mc2 and km++.
Results in Table 4 corroborate the previously established ﬁnding that uni is
vastly outperformed by km++, both in initialization and ﬁnal MSEs. Table 4
results also agree with the ﬁnding of Bachem et al. (2016) that initialization
MSEs with afk-mc2 are indistinguishable from those of km++, and moreover
that ﬁnal MSEs are indistinguishable. We observe in our experiments that runs
with km++ are faster than those with afk-mc2 (columns 1 and 2 of Table 4).
We attribute this to the fast blas-based km++ implementation of Newling and
Fleuret (2016). Our ﬁnal baseline ﬁnding is that MSEs obtained with bf are in
general no better than those with uni. This is not in strict agreement with the
ﬁndings of Celebi et al. (2013). We attribute this discrepancy to the fact that
experiments in Celebi et al. (2013) are in the low K regime (K ¡ 50, N/K ¿ 100).
Note that Table 4 does not contain initialization MSEs for bf, as bf does not
initialize with data points but with means of sub-samples, and it would thus
not make sense to compare bf initialization with the 4 seeding methods. 5.2

clarans performance
Having established that the best baselines are km++ and afk-mc2 , and
that they provide clusterings of indistinguishable quality, we now focus on the
central comparison of this paper, that between km++ with clarans. In Figure 6
we present bar plots summarising all runs on all 23 datasets. We observe a very
low variance in the initialization MSEs of clarans. We speculatively hypothe-
size that clarans often ﬁnds a globally minimal initialization. Figure 6 shows
that clarans provides signiﬁcantly lower initialization MSEs than km++. The

10

ﬁnal MSEs are also signiﬁcantly better when initialization is done with clarans,
although the gap in MSE between clarans and km++ is reduced when lloyd
has run. Note, as seen in Table 4, that all 5 initializations for dataset 7 re-
sult in equally good clusterings. As a supplementary experiment, we considered
initialising with km++ and clarans in series, thus using the three stage clus-
tering km+++clarans+lloyd. We ﬁnd that this can be slightly faster than just
clarans+lloyd with identical MSEs. Results of this experiment are presented in
?SM-I. We perform a ﬁnal experiment measure the dependence of improvement
on K in ?SM-I, where we see the improvement is most signiﬁcant for large K.

6
Conclusion and Future Works
In this paper, we have demonstrated the eﬀectiveness of the algorithm clarans
at solving the kmedoids problem. We have described techniques for accelerating
clarans, and most importantly shown that clarans works very eﬀectively as an
initializer for lloyd, outperforming other initialization schemes, such as km++,
on 23 datasets. An interesting direction for future work might be to develop
further optimisations for clarans. One idea could be to use importance sam-
pling to rapidly obtain good estimates of post-swap energies. Another might be
to propose two swaps simultaneously, as considered in Kanungo et al. (2002),
which could potentially lead to even better solutions, although we have hypoth-
esized that clarans is already ﬁnding globally optimal initializations. All source
code is made available under a public license. It consists of generic C++ code
which can be extended to various data types and metrics, compiling to a shared
library with extensions in Cython for a Python interface. It can currently be
found in the git repository https://github. com/idiap/zentas.

Acknowledgments James Newling was funded by the Hasler Foundation un-

der the grant 13018 MASH2.

8

2 References

Arthur, D. and Vassilvitskii, S. (2007). K-means++: The advantages of careful
seeding. In Proceedings of the Eighteenth Annual ACM-SIAM Symposium on
Discrete Algorithms, SODA ?07, pages 1027?1035, Philadelphia, PA, USA. So-
ciety for Industrial and Applied Mathematics. Bachem, O., Lucic, M., Hassani,
S. H., and Krause, A. (2016). Fast and provably good seedings for k-means.
In Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS). Bradley, P. S. and Fayyad,
U. M. (1998). Reﬁning initial points for k-means clustering. In Proceedings of
the Fifteenth International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML ?98, pages
91?99, San Francisco, CA, USA. Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc. Celebi,
M. E., Kingravi, H. A., and Vela, P. A. (2013). A comparative study of eﬃ-
cient initialization methods for the k-means clustering algorithm. Expert Syst.
Appl., 40(1):200?210. Elkan, C. (2003). Using the triangle inequality to acceler-
ate k-means. In Machine Learning, Proceedings of the Twentieth International
Conference (ICML 2003), August 21-24, 2003, Washington, DC, USA, pages

11

147?153. Hartigan, J. A. (1975). Clustering Algorithms. John Wiley & Sons,
Inc., New York, NY, USA, 99th edition. Hastie, T. J., Tibshirani, R. J., and
Friedman, J. H. (2001). The elements of statistical learning : data mining,
inference, and prediction. Springer series in statistics. Springer, New York.
Kanungo, T., Mount, D. M., Netanyahu, N. S., Piatko, C. D., Silverman, R.,
and Wu, A. Y. (2002). A local search approximation algorithm for k-means
clustering. In Proceedings of the Eighteenth Annual Symposium on Computa-
tional Geometry, SCG ?02, pages 10?18, New York, NY, USA. ACM. Kaufman,
L. and Rousseeuw, P. J. (1990). Finding groups in data : an introduction to
cluster analysis. Wiley series in probability and mathematical statistics. Wiley,
New York. A WileyInterscience publication. Lewis, D. D., Yang, Y., Rose, T.
G., and Li, F. (2004). Rcv1: A new benchmark collection for text categoriza-
tion research. Journal of Machine Learning Research, 5:361?397. Newling, J.
and Fleuret, F. (2016). Fast k-means with accurate bounds. In Proceedings
of the International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), pages 936?944.
Ng, R. T. and Han, J. (1994). Eﬃcient and eﬀective clustering methods for
spatial data mining.
In Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on
Very Large Data Bases, VLDB ?94, pages 144?155, San Francisco, CA, USA.
Morgan Kaufmann Publishers Inc. Ng, R. T. and Han, J. (2002). Clarans:
A method for clustering objects for spatial data mining.
IEEE Transactions
on Knowledge and Data Engineering, pages 1003?1017. Park, H.-S. and Jun,
C.-H. (2009). A simple and fast algorithm for k-medoids clustering. Expert
Syst. Appl., 36(2):3336?3341. Telgarsky, M. and Vattani, A. (2010). Harti-
gan?s method: k-means clustering without voronoi. In AISTATS, volume 9 of
JMLR Proceedings, pages 820?827. JMLR.org. Wu, X., Kumar, V., Quinlan,
J. R., Ghosh, J., Yang, Q., Motoda, H., McLachlan, G., Ng, A., Liu, B., Yu,
P., Zhou, Z.-H., Steinbach, M., Hand, D., and Steinberg, D. (2008). Top 10
algorithms in data mining. Knowledge and Information Systems, 14(1):1?37.
Yujian, L. and Bo, L. (2007). A normalized levenshtein distance metric. IEEE
Trans. Pattern Anal. Mach. Intell., 29(6):1091?1095.

9

12

