Higher-Order Total Variation Classes on Grids:
Minimax Theory and Trend Filtering Methods

Authored by:

Yu-Xiang Wang

James L. Sharpnack

Veeranjaneyulu Sadhanala

Ryan J. Tibshirani

Abstract

We consider the problem of estimating the values of a function over
$n$ nodes of a $d$-dimensional grid graph (having equal side lengths
$n{1/d}$) from noisy observations. The function is assumed to be smooth,
but is allowed to exhibit diﬀerent amounts of smoothness at diﬀerent re-
gions in the grid. Such heterogeneity eludes classical measures of smooth-
ness from nonparametric statistics, such as Holder smoothness. Mean-
while, total variation (TV) smoothness classes allow for heterogeneity, but
are restrictive in another sense: only constant functions count as perfectly
smooth (achieve zero TV). To move past this, we deﬁne two new higher-
order TV classes, based on two ways of compiling the discrete derivatives
of a parameter across the nodes. We relate these two new classes to Holder
classes, and derive lower bounds on their minimax errors. We also ana-
lyze two naturally associated trend ﬁltering methods; when $d=2$, each
is seen to be rate optimal over the appropriate class.

1 Paper Body

In this work, we focus on estimation of a mean parameter deﬁned over the nodes
of a d-dimensional grid graph G = (V, E), with equal side lengths N = n1/d .
Let us enumerate V = {1, . . . , n} and E = {e1 , . . . , em }, and consider
data y = (y1 , . . . , yn ) ? Rn observed over V , distributed as yi ? N (?0,i , ?
2 ),

independently, for i = 1, . . . , n,
(1)
where ?0 = (?0,1 , . . . , ?0,n ) ? Rn is the mean parameter to be estimated,
and ? 2 ¿ 0 the common noise variance. We will assume that ?0 displays some
kind of regularity or smoothness over G, and are speciﬁcally interested in notions
of regularity built around on the total variation (TV) operator X kD?k1 = —?i
? ?j —, (2) (i,j)?E

1

.

.

.

, ?1, .

deﬁned with respect to G, where D ? Rm?n is the edge incidence matrix of
G, which has ‘th row D‘ = (0, .
, 0), with ?1 in
location i and 1 in location j, provided that the ‘th edge is e‘ = (i, j) with i ¡ j.
There is an extensive literature on estimators based on TV regularization, both
in Euclidean spaces and over graphs. Higher-order TV regularization, which,
loosely speaking, considers the TV of derivatives of the parameter, is much less
understood, especially over graphs. In this paper, we develop statistical theory
for higher-order TV smoothness classes, and we analyze 31st Conference on
Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017), Long Beach, CA, USA.

, 1, .

.

.

.

associated trend ﬁltering methods, which are seen to achieve the minimax
optimal estimation error rate over such classes. This can be viewed as an exten-
sion of the work in [22] for the zeroth-order TV case, where by ?zeroth-order?,
we refer to the usual TV operator as deﬁned in (2). Motivation. TV denoising
over grid graphs, speciﬁcally 1d and 2d grid graphs, is a well-studied problem
in signal processing, statistics, and machine learning, some key references being
[20, 5, 26]. Given data y ? Rn as per the setup described above, the TV de-
noising or fused lasso estimator over the grid G is deﬁned as 1 ?? = argmin ky
? ?k22 + ?kD?k1 , (3) n 2 ??R where ? ? 0 is a tuning parameter. The TV
denoising estimator generalizes seamlessly to arbitrary graphs. The problem of
denoising over grids, the setting we focus on, is of particular relevance to a num-
ber of important applications, e.g., in time series analysis, and image and video
processing. A strength of the nonlinear TV denoising estimator in (3)?where
by ?nonlinear?, we mean that ?? is nonlinear as a function of y?is that it can
adapt to heterogeneity in the local level of smoothness of the underlying signal
?0 . Moreover, it adapts to such heterogeneity at an extent that is beyond what
linear estimators are capable of capturing. This principle is widely evident in
practice and has been championed by many authors in the signal processing lit-
erature. It is also backed by statistical theory, i.e., [8, 16, 27] in the 1d setting,
and most recently [22] in the general d-dimensional setting. Note that the TV
denoising estimator ?? in (3) takes a piecewise constant structure by design,
i.e., at many adjacent pairs (i, j) ? E we will have ??i = ??j , and this will be
generally more common for larger ?. For some problems, this structure may not
be ideal and we might instead seek a piecewise smooth estimator, that is still
able to cope with local changes in the underlying level of smoothness, but oﬀers
a richer structure (beyond a simple constant structure) for the base trend. In
a 1d setting, this is accomplished by trend ﬁltering methods, which move from
piecewise constant to piecewise polynomial structure, via TV regularization of
discrete derivatives of the parameter [24, 13, 27]. An extension of trend ﬁltering
to general graphs was developed in [31]. In what follows, we study the statistical
properties of this graph trend ﬁltering method over grids, and we propose and
analyze a more specialized trend ﬁltering estimator for grids based on the idea
that something like a Euclidean coordinate system is available at any (interior)
node. See Figure 1 for a motivating illustration. Related work. The literature
on TV denoising is enormous and we cannot give a comprehensive review, but
only some brief highlights. Important methodological and computational con-
tributions are found in [20, 5, 26, 4, 10, 6, 28, 15, 7, 12, 1, 25], and notable

2

theoretical contributions are found in [16, 19, 9, 23, 11, 22, 17]. The literature
on higher-order TV-based methods is more sparse and more concentrated on
the 1d setting. Trend ﬁltering methods in 1d were pioneered in [24, 13], and
analyzed statistically in [27], where they were also shown to be asymptotically
equivalent to locally adaptive regression splines of [16]. An extension of trend
ﬁltering to additive models was given in [21]. A generalization of trend ﬁltering
that operates over an arbitrary graph structure was given in [31]. Trend ﬁltering
is not the only avenue for higher-order TV regularization: the signal process-
ing community has also studied higher-order variants of TV, see, e.g., [18, 3].
The construction of the discrete versions of these higher-order TV operators is
somewhat similar to that in [31] as well our Kronecker trend ﬁltering proposal,
however, the focus of the work is quite diﬀerent. Summary of contributions. An
overview of our contributions is given below. ? We propose a new method for
trend ﬁltering over grid graphs that we call Kronecker trend ﬁltering (KTF),
and compare its properties to the more general graph trend ﬁltering (GTF)
proposal of [31]. ? For 2d grids, we derive estimation error rates for GTF and
KTF, each of these rates being a function of the regularizer evaluated at the
mean ?0 . ? For d-dimensional grids, we derive minimax lower bounds for esti-
mation over two higherorder TV classes deﬁned using the operators from GTF
and KTF. When d = 2, these lower bounds match the upper bounds in rate
(apart from log factors) derived for GTF and KTF, ensuring that each method
is minimax rate optimal (modulo log factors) for its own notion of regularity.
Also, the KTF class contains a Holder class of an appropriate order, and KTF
is seen to be rate optimal (modulo log factors) for this more homogeneous class
as well. 2

Underlying signal and data ?
Laplacian smoothing, large ?
Laplacian smoothing, small ?
Graph trend ﬁltering
Kronecker trend ﬁltering
? ? ?
? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?
?? ? ? ?
? ?
?
? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ??
? ?? ? ? ??? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ??
? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ??? ??? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ?
?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?
? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ? ??? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ?? ? ?
??? ?? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ??
? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ?
??? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ????? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ??
? ?? ? ?? ? ??? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ??? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?
? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ??? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ??? ? ?? ? ?
? ? ? ?? ?? ? ?? ?? ? ??? ?? ?? ? ??? ? ???? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ??? ? ? ? ? ?? ??

3

?? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ??? ? ? ? ? ? ??
?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ??? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?
? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ?? ??? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ?
?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ??? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?
??? ? ? ?? ??? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ??? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ??
?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ??? ? ??? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ???
? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ??? ?? ???? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ? ??? ?? ??? ? ?
?? ?? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ????? ? ? ? ? ? ??? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ?
? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ??? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ?
?? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ???? ?
? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ??? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ? ?? ???? ?
?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ??? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ??
? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ??
? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ??? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ?? ??? ? ?
? ? ? ? ? ? ??? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?
? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ??? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ??? ??? ? ?
?? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ??? ?? ? ? ?
? ??? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ??? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?
? ?? ? ??? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ???? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ?
? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ??? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ?
?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ??? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ??
?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ??
?? ? ? ?? ???? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?
? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ?? ? ? ?? ? ?? ?? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?
? ? ? ? ?? ? ?? ? ? ? ? ? ? ? ?? ? ? ? ?

?
?
? ?
?
?? ?
?
? ? ?
?
? ?
?
? ? ? ? ?
? ?
?
?
?? ?
? ? ?
TV denoising
Figure 1: Top left: an underlying signal ?0 and associated data y (shown
as black points). Top middle and top right: Laplacian smoothing ﬁt to y, at
large and small tuning parameter values, respectively. Bottom left, middle,
and right: TV denoising (3), graph trend ﬁltering (5), and Kronecker trend

4

ﬁltering (5) ﬁt to y, respectively (the latter two are of order k = 2, with penalty
operators as described in Section 2).
In order to capture the larger of the
two peaks, Laplacian smoothing must signiﬁcantly undersmooth throughout;
with more regularization, it undersmooths throughout. TV denoising is able to
adapt to heterogeneity in the smoothness of the underlying signal, but exhibits
?staircasing? artifacts, as it is restricted to ﬁtting piecewise constant functions.
Graph and Kronecker trend ﬁltering overcome this, while maintaining local
adaptivity.

Notation. For deterministic sequences an , bn we write an = O(bn ) to denote
that an /bn is upper ?1 bounded for large enough n, and an bn to denote that
both an = O(bn ) and a?1 n = O(bn ). For random sequences An , Bn , we
write An = OP (Bn ) to denote that An /Bn is bounded in probability. Given
a d-dimensional grid G = (V, E), where V = {1, . . . , n}, as before, we will
sometimes index a parameter ? ? Rn deﬁned over the nodes in the following
convenient way. Letting N = n1/d and Zd = {(i1 /N, . . . , id /N ) : i1 , . . . ,
id ? {1, . . . , N }} ? [0, 1]d , we will index the components of ? by their lattice
positions, denoted ?(x), x ? Zd . Further, for each j = 1, . . . , d, we will deﬁne
the discrete derivative of ? in the jth coordinate direction at a location x by

?(x + ej /N ) ? ?(x) if x, x + ej /N ? Zd , (Dxj ?)(x) = (4) 0 else. Naturally,
we denote by Dxj ? ? Rn the vector with components (Dxj ?)(x), x ? Zd .
Higher-order discrete derivatives are simply deﬁned by repeated application of
the above deﬁnition. We use abbreviations (Dx2j ?)(x) = (Dxj (Dxj ?))(x), for
j = 1, . . . , d, and (Dxj ,x‘ ?)(x) = (Dxj (Dx‘ ?))(x), for j, ‘ = 1, . . . , d, and
so on. Given an estimator ?? of the mean parameter ?0 in (1), and K ? Rn ,
two quantities of interest are:

? ?0 ) = 1 k?? ? ?0 k2 and R(K) = inf sup E MSE(?, ? ?0 ) . MSE(?, 2 ? n
? ?0 ?K ? ?0 )] The ﬁrst quantity here is called the mean squared error (MSE)
of ?; we will also call E[MSE(?, ? the risk of ?. The second quantity is called
the minimax risk over K (the inﬁmum being taken over ? all estimators ?). 3

2
Trend ﬁltering methods
Review: graph trend ﬁltering. To review the family of estimators developed
in [31], we start by introducing a general-form estimator called the generalized
lasso signal approximator [28], 1 ?? = argmin ky ? ?k22 + ?k??k1 , 2 ??Rn

(5)
for a matrix ? ? Rr?n , referred to as the penalty operator. For an integer k
? 0, the authors [31] deﬁned the graph trend ﬁltering (GTF) estimator of order
k by (5), with the penalty operator being

DLk/2 for k even, (k+1) ? = (6) L(k+1)/2 for k odd. Here, as before, we
use D for the edge incidence matrix of G. We also use L = DT D for the graph
Laplacian matrix of G. The intuition behind the above deﬁnition is that ?(k+1)
? gives something roughly like the (k + 1)st order discrete derivatives of ? over
the graph G. Note that the GTF estimator reduces to TV denoising in (3) when
k = 0. Also, like TV denoising, GTF applies to arbitrary graph structures;
see [31] for more details and for the study of GTF over general graphs. Our
interest is of course its behavior over grids, and we will now use the notation

5

introduced in (4), to shed more light on the GTF penalty P operator in (6) over
a d-dimensional grid. For any signal ? ? Rn , we can write k?(k+1) ?k1 = x?Zd
dx , where at all points x ? Zd (except for those close to the boundary), ?

d d
X X ? ?
? ? Dxj1 ,x2j ,...,x2j ? (x) for k even, where q = k/2,
? q ? 2
j =1 j ,...,j =1
dx = 1 d 2 q (7)
? ? X
? ? Dx2j ,x2j ,...,x2j ? (x) for k odd, where q = (k + 1)/2. ? q ? 1 2
j1 ,...,jq =1
Written in this form, it appears that the GTF operator ?(k+1) aggregates
derivatives in somewhat of an unnatural way. But we must remember that for
a general graph structure, only ﬁrst derivatives and divergences have obvious
discrete analogs?given by application of D and L, respectively. Hence, GTF,
which was originally designed for general graphs, relies on combinations of D and
L to produce something like higher-order discrete derivatives. This explains the
form of the aggregated derivatives in (6), which is entirely based on divergences.
Kronecker trend ﬁltering. There is a natural alternative to the GTF penalty
operator that takes advantage of the Euclidean-like structure available at the
(interior) nodes of a grid graph. At a point x ? Zd (not close to the boundary),
consider using dx =

d X
D k+1 ? (x) x j
(8)
j=1
as a basic building block for penalizing derivatives, rather than (7). This
gives rise to a method we call Kronecker trend ﬁltering (KTF), which for an
integer order k ? 0 is deﬁned by (5), but now with the choice of penalty operator
? ? (k+1) D1d ? I ? ??? ? I ? ? (k+1) ? I ? D1d ? ??? ? I ? (k+1) e ? ?. ?
=? (9) .. ? ? ? . (k+1) I ? I ? ? ? ? ? D1d (k+1)

Here, D1d ? R(N ?k?1)?N is the 1d discrete derivative operator of order k +
1 (e.g., as used in univariate trend ﬁltering, see [27]), I ? RN ?N is the identity
matrix, and A ? B is the Kronecker product of matrices A, B. Each group of
rows in (9) features a total of d ? 1 Kronecker products. KTF reduces to TV
denoising in (3) when k = 0, and thus also to GTF with k = 0. But for k ? 1,
GTF and KTF are diﬀerent estimators. A look at the action of their penalty
operators, as displayed in 4

(7), (8) reveals some of their diﬀerences. For example, we see that GTF
considers mixed derivatives of total order k + 1, but KTF only considers direc-
tional derivatives of order k + 1 that are parallel to the coordinate axes. Also,
GTF penalizes aggregate derivatives (i.e., sums of derivatives), whereas KTF
penalizes individual ones. More subtle diﬀerences between GTF and KTF have
to do with the structure of their estimates, as we discuss next. Another subtle

6

diﬀerence lies in how the GTF and KTF operators (6), (9) relate to more clas-
sical notions of smoothness, particularly, Holder smoothness. This is covered
in Section 4. Structure of estimates. It is straightforward to see that the GTF
operator (6) has a 1-dimensional null space, spanned by 1 = (1, .
, 1) ?
Rn . This means that GTF lets constant signals pass through unpenalized, but
nothing else; or, in other words, it preserves the projection of y onto the space
of constant signals, y?1, but nothing else. The KTF operator, meanwhile, has
a much richer null space. Lemma 1. The null space of the KTF operator (9)
has dimension (k + 1)d , and it is spanned by a polynomial basis made up of
elements p(x) = xa1 1 xa2 2 ? ? ? xadd ,

.

.

x ? Zd ,
where a1 , .

.

.

.

.

, ad ? {0, .

, k}. The proof is elementary and (as
with all proofs in this paper) is given in the supplement. The lemma shows that
KTF preserves the projection of y onto the space of polynomials of max degree
k, i.e., lets much more than just constant signals pass through unpenalized.
Beyond the diﬀerences in these base trends (represented by their null spaces),
GTF and KTF admit estimates with similar but generally diﬀerent structures.
KTF has the advantage that this structure is more transparent: its estimates
are piecewise polynomial functions of max degree k, with generally fewer pieces
for larger ?. This is demonstrated by a functional representation for KTF, given
next. Lemma 2. Let hi : [0, 1] ? R, i = 1, . . . , N be the (univariate) falling
factorial functions [27, 30] of order k, deﬁned over knots 1/N, 2/N, . . . , N :
hi (t) =
i?1 Y
(t ? t‘ ),
t ? [0, 1], i = 1, . . . , k + 1,
‘=1
k Y i+‘ i+k hi+k+1 (t) = t? ?1 t¿ , N N
(10) t ? [0, 1], i = 1, . . . , N ? k ? 1.
‘=1
(For k = 0, our convention is for the empty product to equal 1.) Let Hd be
the space spanned by all d-wise tensor products of falling factorial functions,
i.e., Hd contains f : [0, 1]d ? R of the form f (x) =

N X
?i1 ,...,id hi1 (x)hi2 (x2 ) ? ? ? hid (xd ),
x ? [0, 1]d ,
i1 ,...,id =1
for coeﬃcients ? ? Rn (whose components we index by ?i1 ,...,id , for i1 , . .
. , id = 1, . . . , N ). Then the KTF estimator deﬁned in (5), (9) is equivalent
to the functional optimization problem k

d X X 2 1 X ? f (?, x?j ) ? f = argmin y(x) ? f (x) + ? TV , (11) 2 ?xkj f

?Hd j=1 x ?Z x?Z ?j

d
d?1
where f (?, x?j ) denotes f as function of the jth dimension with all other
dimensions ﬁxed at x?j , ? k /?xkj (?) denotes the kth partial weak derivative

7

operator with respect to xj , for j = 1, . . . , d, and TV(?) denotes the total
variation operator. The discrete (5), (9) and functional (11) representations are
equivalent in that f? and ?? match at all grid locations x ? Zd . Aside from
shedding light on the structure of KTF solutions, the functional optimization
problem in ? which (11) is of practical importance: the function f? is deﬁned
over all of [0, 1]d (as opposed to ?, is of course only deﬁned on the grid Zd ) and
thus we may use it to interpolate the KTF estimate to non-grid locations. It
is not clear to us that a functional representation as in (11) (or even a sensible
interpolation strategy) is available for GTF on d-dimensional grids. 5

3
Upper bounds on estimation error
In this section, we assume that d = 2, and derive upper bounds on the
estimation error of GTF and KTF for 2d grids. Upper bounds for generalized
lasso estimators were studied in [31], and we will leverage one of their key results,
which is based on what these authors call incoherence of the left singular vectors
of the penalty operator ?. A slightly reﬁned version of this result is stated below.
Theorem 1 (Theorem 6 in [31]). Suppose that ? ? Rr?n has rank q, and denote
by ?1 ? .
, uq be the
corresponding left singular vectors. Assume that these vectors, except for the
ﬁrst i0 , are incoherent, meaning that for a constant ? ? 1, ? kui k? ? ?/ n, i
= i0 + 1, . . . , q, q Pq Then for ? ? (log r/n) i=i0 +1 ?i?2 , the generalized
lasso estimator ?? in (5) satisﬁes v ! u q u log r X i ? 1 nullity(?) 0 ? ?0 ) =
OP ? k??0 k1 . MSE(?, + + t n n n n i=i +1 ?i2 0

. ? ?q its nonzero singular values. Also let u1 , .

.

.

.

For GTF and KTF, we will apply this result, an appropriate choice of i0
with the partial Pbalancing q sum of reciprocal squared singular values i=i0 +1
?i?2 . The main challenge, as we will see, is in establishing incoherence of the
singular vectors. Error bounds for graph trend ﬁltering. The authors in [31]
have already used Theorem 1 (their Theorem 6) in order to derive error rates
for GTF on 2d grids. However, their resultsP (speciﬁcally, q their Corollary 8)
can be reﬁned using a tighter upper bound for the partial sum term i=i0 +1
?i?2 . No real further tightening is possible, since, as we show later, the results
below match the minimax lower bound in rate, up to log factors. Theorem 2.
Assume that d = 2. For k = 0, Cn = k?(1) ?0 k1 (i.e., Cn equal to the TV of ?0
, as in (2)), and ? log n, the GTF estimator in (5), (6) (i.e., the TV denoising
estimator in (3)) satisﬁes

1 log n ? MSE(?, ?0 ) = OP + Cn . n n k
1
?
k
For any integer k ? 1, Cn = k?(k+1) ?0 k1 and ? n k+2 (log n) k+2 Cn

k+2 , GTF satisﬁes

2 2 1 1 ? k+2 k+2 ? k+2 +n . MSE(?, ?0 ) = OP (log n) Cn n Remark
1. The result for k = 0 in Theorem 2 was essentially already established by [11]
(a small diﬀerence is that the above rate is sharper by a factor of log n; though
to be fair, [11] also take into account ‘0 sparsity). It is interesting to note that
the case k = 0 appears to be quite special, in that the GTF estimator, i.e., TV

8

denoising estimator, is adaptive to the underlying smoothness parameter Cn
(the prescribed choice of tuning parameter ? log n does not depend on Cn ).
Pq The technique for upper bounding i=i0 +1 ?i?2 in the proof of Theorem 2
can be roughly explained as follows. The GTF operator ?(k+1) on a 2d grid
has squared singular values:

.

.

k+1 ?(i1 ? 1) ?(i2 ? 1) 4 sin2 + 4 sin2 , i1 , i2 = 1, .

, N. 2N 2N We
can upper bound the sum of squared reciprocal singular values with a integral
over [0, 1]2 , make use of the identity sin x ? x/2 for small enough x, and then
switch to polar coordinates to calculate the integral (similar to [11], in analyzing
TV denoising). The arguments to verify incoherence of the left singular vectors
of ?(k+1) are themselves somewhat delicate, but were already given in [31].
Error bounds for Kronecker trend ﬁltering. In comparison to the GTF case, the
application of Theorem 1 to KTF is a much more diﬃcult task, because (to the
best of our knowledge) the KTF e (k+1) does not admit closed-form expressions
for its singular values and vectors. This operator ? is true in any dimension
(i.e., even for d = 1, where KTF reduces to univariate trend ﬁltering). As it
turns out, the singular values can be handled with a relatively straightforward
application of the Cauchy interlacing theorem. It is establishing the incoherence
of the singular vectors that proves to be the real challenge. This is accomplished
by leveraging specialized approximation bounds for the eigenvectors of Toeplitz
matrices from [2]. 6

Theorem 3. Assume that d = 2. For k = 0, since KTF reduces to the GTF
with k = 0 (and to TV denoising), it satisﬁes the result stated in the ﬁrst part
of Theorem 2. k 1 ? k e (k+1) ?0 k1 and ? n k+2 For any integer k ? 1, Cn =
k? (log n) k+2 Cn k+2 , the KTF estimator in (5), (9) satisﬁes

2 1 2 1 ? k+2 k+2 ? k+2 (log n) Cn MSE(?, ?0 ) = OP +n . n The results
in Theorems 2 and 3 match, in terms of their dependence on n, k, d and the
smoothness parameter Cn . As we will see in the next section, the smoothness
classes deﬁned by the GTF and KTF operators are similar, though not exactly
the same, and each GTF and KTF is minimax rate optimal with respect to its
own smoothness class, up to log factors. Beyond 2d? To analyze GTF and KTF
on grids of dimension d ? 3, we would need to establish incoherence of the left
singular vectors of the GTF and KTF operators. This should be possible by
extending the arguments given in [31] (for GTF) and in the proof of Theorem
3 (for KTF), and is left to future work.

4
Lower bounds on estimation error
We present lower bounds on the minimax estimation error over smoothness
classes deﬁned by the operators from GTF (6) and KTF (9), denoted Tdk (Cn
) = {? ? Rn : k?(k+1) ?k1 ? Cn }, e (k+1) ?k1 ? Cn }, Tedk (Cn ) = {? ?
Rn : k?

(12) (13)
respectively (where the subscripts mark the dependence on the dimension d
of the underlying grid graph). Before we derive such lower bounds, we examine
embeddings of (the discretization of) the class of Holder smooth functions into
the GTF and KTF classes, both to understand the nature of these new classes,

9

and to deﬁne what we call a ?canonical? scaling for the radius parameter Cn
. Embedding of Holder spaces and canonical scaling. Given an integer k ? 0
and L ¿ 0, recall that the Holder class H(k + 1, L; [0, 1]d ) contains k times
diﬀerentiable functions f : [0, 1]d ? R, such that for all integers ?1 , . . . , ?d ?
0 with ?1 + ? ? ? + ?d = k,

? k f (x)
? k f (z) d ?
?x 1 ? ? ? ?x?d ? ?x?1 ? ? ? ?x?d ? Lkx ? zk2 , for all x, z ? [0, 1] . 1 1
d d To compare Holder smoothness with the GTF and KTF classes deﬁned in
(12), (13), we discretize the class H(k + 1, L; [0, 1]d ) by considering function
evaluations over the grid Zd , deﬁning

Hdk+1 (L) = ? ? Rn : ?(x) = f (x), x ? Zd , for some f ? H(k + 1, L; [0, 1]d
) . (14) Now we ask: how does the (discretized) Holder class in (14) compare to
the GTF and KTF classes in (12), (13)? Beginning with a comparison to KTF,
ﬁx ? ? Hdk+1 (L), corresponding to evaluations of f ? H(k + 1, L; [0, 1]d ),
and consider a point x ? Zd that is away from the boundary. Then the KTF
penalty at x is

D k+1 ? (x) = Dxk ? (x + ej /N ) ? Dxk ? (x) xj j j k
?
?k + N k ?(N ) ? N k k f (x + ej /N ) ? f (x)
k ?xj ?xj ? LN k?1 + cLN k?1 .
(15)
In the second line above, we deﬁne ?(N ) to be the sum of absolute errors in
the discrete approximations to the partial derivatives (i.e., the error in approxi-
mating ? k f (x)/?xkj by (Dxkj ?)(x)/N k , and similarly at x + ej /N ). In the
third line, we use Holder smoothness to upper bound the ﬁrst term, and we use
standard numerical analysis (details in the supplement) for the second term to
ensure that ?(N ) ? cL/N for a constant c ¿ 0 depending only on k. Summing
the bound in (15) over x ? Zd as appropriate gives a uniform bound on the
KTF penalty at ?, and leads to the next result. 7

Lemma 3. For any integers k ? 0, d ? 1, the (discretized) Holder and
KTF classes deﬁned in (14), (13) satisfy Hdk+1 (L) ? Tedk (cLn1?(k+1)/d ),
where c ¿ 0 is a constant depending only on k. This lemma has three purposes.
First, it provides some supporting evidence that the KTF class is an interesting
smoothness class to study, as it shows the KTF class contains (discretizations
of) Holder smooth functions, which are a cornerstone of classical nonparametric
regression theory. In fact, this containment is strict and the KTF class contains
more heterogeneous functions in it as well. Second, it leads us to deﬁne what we
call the canonical scaling Cn n1?(k+1)/d for the radius of the KTF class (13).
This will be helpful for interpreting our minimax lower bounds in what follows;
at this scaling, note that we have Hdk+1 (1) ? Tedk (Cn ). Third and ﬁnally, it
gives us an easy way to establish lower bounds on the minimax estimation error
over KTF classes, by invoking well-known results on minimax rates for Holder
classes. This will be described shortly. As for GTF, calculations similar to (15)
are possible, but complications ensue for x on the boundary of the grid Zd .
Importantly, unlike the KTF penalty, the GTF penalty includes discrete deriva-

10

tives at the boundary and so these complications have serious consequences, as
stated next. Lemma 4. For any integers k, d ? 1, there are elements in the
(discretized) Holder class Hdk+1 (1) in (14) that do not lie in the GTF class
Tdk (Cn ) in (12) for arbitrarily large Cn . This lemma reveals a very subtle
drawback of GTF caused by the use of discrete derivatives at the boundary of
the grid. The fact that GTF classes do not contain (discretized) Holder classes
makes them seem less natural (and perhaps, in a sense, less interesting) than
KTF classes. In addition, it means that we cannot use standard minimax theory
for Holder classes to establish lower bounds for the estimation error over GTF
classes. However, as we will see next, we can construct lower bounds for GTF
classes via another (more purely geometric) embedding strategy; interestingly,
the resulting rates match the Holder rates, suggesting that, while GTF classes
do not contain all (discretized) Holder functions, they do contain ?enough? of
these functions to admit the same lower bound rates. Minimax rates for GTF
and KTF classes. Following from classical minimax theory for Holder classes
[14, 29], and Lemma 3, we have the following result for the minimax rates over
KTF classes. Theorem 4. For any integers k ? 0, d ? 1, the KTF class deﬁned
in (13) has minimax estimation error satisfying 2d

2d R Tedk (Cn ) = ?(n? 2k+2+d Cn2k+2+d ). For GTF classes, we use
a diﬀerent strategy. We embed an ellipse, then rotate the parameter space
and embed a hypercube, leading to the following result. Theorem 5. For any
integers k ? 0, d ? 1, the GTF class deﬁned in (12) has minimax estimation
error satisfying 2d

2d R Tdk (Cn ) = ?(n? 2k+2+d Cn2k+2+d ). Several remarks are in order.
Remark 2. Plugging in the canonical scaling Cn n1?(k+1)/d in Theorems 4 and
5, we see that 2k+2

R(Tedk (Cn )) = ?(n? 2k+2+d ) and
2k+2
R(Tdk (Cn )) = ?(n? 2k+2+d ),
both matching the usual rate for the Holder class Hdk+1 (1). For KTF, this
should be expected, as its lower bound is constructed via the Holder embedding
given in Lemma 3. But for GTF, it may come as somewhat of a surprise?despite
the fact it does not embed a Holder class as in Lemma 4, we see that the GTF
class shares the same rate, suggesting it still contains something like ?hardest?
Holder smooth signals. Remark 3. For d = 2 and all k ? 0, we can certify that
the lower bound rate in Theorem 4 is tight, modulo log factors, by comparing
it to the upper bound in Theorem 3. Likewise, we can certify that the lower
bound rate in Theorem 5 is tight, up to log factors, by comparing it to the
upper bound in Theorem 2. For d ? 3, the lower bound rates in Theorems 4
and 5 will not be tight for some values of k. For example, when k = 0, at the
canonical scaling Cn n1?1/d , the lower bound rate (given by either theorem) is
n?2/(2+d) , however, [22] prove that the minimax error of the TV class scales
(up to log factors) as n?1/d for d ? 2, so we see there is a departure in the rates
for d ? 3. 8

GTFcl ass KTFcl ass H?l dercl ass
Figure 2: Illustration of the two higher-order TV classes, namely the GTF

11

and KTF classes, as they relate to the (discretized) Holder class. The horizon-
tally/vertically checkered region denotes the part of Holder class not contained
in the GTF class. As explained in Section 4, this is due to the fact that the GTF
operator penalizes discrete derivatives on the boundary of the grid graph. The
diagonally checkered region (also colored in blue) denotes the part of the Holder
class contained in the GTF class. The minimax lower bound rates we derive
for the GTF class in Theorem 5 match the well-known Holder rates, suggesting
that this region is actually sizeable and contains the ?hardest? Holder smooth
signals.

In general, we conjecture that the Holder embedding for the KTF class (and
ellipse embedding for GTF) will deliver tight lower bound rates, up to log factors,
when k is large enough compared to d. This would have interesting implications
for adaptivity to smoother signals (see the next remark); a precise study will be
left to future work, along with tight minimax lower bounds for all k, d. Remark
4. Again by comparing Theorems 3 and 4, as well as Theorems 2 and 5, we ﬁnd
that, for d = 2 and all k ? 0, KTF is rate optimal for the KTF smoothness class
and GTF is rate optimal for the GTF smoothness class, modulo log factors. We
conjecture that this will continue to hold for all d ? 3, which will be examined
in future work. Moreover, an immediate consequence of Theorem 3 and the
Holder embedding in Lemma 3 is that KTF adapts automatically to Holder
smooth signals, i.e., it achieves a rate (up to log factors) of n?(k+1)/(k+2) over
H2k+1 (1), matching the well-known minimax rate for the more homogeneous
Holder class. It is not clear that GTF shares this property.

5
Discussion
In this paper, we studied two natural higher-order extensions of the TV
estimator on d-dimensional grid graphs. The ﬁrst was graph trend ﬁltering
(GTF) as deﬁned in [31], applied to grids; the second was a new Kronecker
trend ﬁltering (KTF) method, which was built with the special (Euclidean-like)
structure of grids in mind. GTF and KTF exhibit some similarities, but are
diﬀerent in important ways. Notably, the notion of smoothness deﬁned using
the KTF operator is somewhat more natural, and is a strict generalization of the
standard notion of Holder smoothness (in the sense that the KTF smoothness
class strictly contains a Holder class of an appropriate order). This is not true
for the notion of smoothness deﬁned using the GTF operator. Figure 2 gives an
illustration. When d = 2, we derived tight upper bounds for the estimation error
achieved by the GTF and KTF estimators?tight in the sense that these upper
bound match in rate (modulo log factors) the lower bounds on the minimax
estimation errors for the GTF and KTF classes. We constructed the lower
bound for the KTF class by leveraging the fact that it embeds a Holder class;
for the GTF class, we used a diﬀerent (more geometric) embedding. While
these constructions proved to be tight for d = 2 and all k ? 0, we suspect this
will no longer be the case in general, when d is large enough relative to k. We
will examine this in future work, along with upper bounds for GTF and KTF
when d ? 3. Another important consideration for future work are the minimax
linear rates over GTF and KTF classes, i.e., minimax rates when we restrict

12

our attention to linear estimators. We anticipate that a gap will exist between
minimax linear and nonlinear rates for all k, d (as it does for k = 0, as shown
in [22]). This would, e.g., provide some rigorous backing to the claim that the
KTF class is larger than its embedded Holder class (the latter having matching
minimax linear and nonlinear rates). Acknowledgements. We thank Sivaraman
Balakrishnan for helpful discussions regarding minimax rates for Holder classes
on grids. JS was supported by NSF Grant DMS-1712996. VS, YW, and RT
were supported by NSF Grants DMS-1309174 and DMS-1554123. 9

2 References

[1] Alvaro Barbero and Suvrit Sra. Modular proximal optimization for multidi-
mensional totalvariation regularization. arXiv: 1411.0589, 2014.
[2] Johan M.
Bogoya, Albrecht Bottcher, Sergei M. Grudsky, and Egor A. Maximenko. Eigen-
vectors of Hermitian Toeplitz matrices with smooth simple-loop symbols. Linear
Algebra and its Applications, 493:606?637, 2016. [3] Kristian Bredies, Karl Ku-
nisch, and Thomas Pock. Total generalized variation. SIAM Journal on Imaging
Sciences, 3(3):492?526, 2010. [4] Antonin Chambolle and Jerome Darbon. On
total variation minimization and surface evolution using parametric maximum
ﬂows. International Journal of Computer Vision, 84:288?307, 2009. [5] Antonin
Chambolle and Pierre-Louis Lions. Image recovery via total variation minimiza-
tion and related problems. Numerische Mathematik, 76(2):167?188, 1997.
[6]
Antonin Chambolle and Thomas Pock. A ﬁrst-order primal-dual algorithm for
convex problems with applications to imaging. Journal of Mathematical Imag-
ing and Vision, 40:120?145, 2011.
[7] Laurent Condat. A direct algorithm for
1d total variation denoising. HAL: 00675043, 2012.
[8] David L. Donoho and
Iain M. Johnstone. Minimax estimation via wavelet shrinkage. Annals of Statis-
tics, 26(8):879?921, 1998. [9] Zaid Harchaoui and Celine Levy-Leduc. Multiple
change-point estimation with a total variation penalty. Journal of the American
Statistical Association, 105(492):1480?1493, 2010. [10] Holger Hoeﬂing. A path
algorithm for the fused lasso signal approximator. Journal of Computational
and Graphical Statistics, 19(4):984?1006, 2010.
[11] Jan-Christian Hutter and
Philippe Rigollet. Optimal rates for total variation denoising. Annual Con-
ference on Learning Theory, 29:1115?1146, 2016. [12] Nicholas Johnson. A dy-
namic programming algorithm for the fused lasso and l0 -segmentation. Journal
[13] Seung-
of Computational and Graphical Statistics, 22(2):246?260, 2013.
Jean Kim, Kwangmoo Koh, Stephen Boyd, and Dimitry Gorinevsky.
‘1 trend
ﬁltering. SIAM Review, 51(2):339?360, 2009. [14] Aleksandr P. Korostelev and
Alexandre B. Tsybakov. Minimax Theory of Image Reconstructions. Springer,
2003.
[15] Arne Kovac and Andrew Smith. Nonparametric regression on a
graph. Journal of Computational and Graphical Statistics, 20(2):432?447, 2011.
[16] Enno Mammen and Sara van de Geer. Locally apadtive regression splines.
Annals of Statistics, 25(1):387?413, 1997.
[17] Oscar Hernan Madrid Padilla,
James Sharpnack, James Scott, , and Ryan J. Tibshirani. The DFS fused lasso:
Linear-time denoising over general graphs. arXiv: 1608.03384, 2016. [18] Chris-

13

tiane Poschl and Otmar Scherzer. Characterization of minimizers of convex
regularization functionals.
In Frames and Operator Theory in Analysis and
Signal Processing, volume 451, pages 219?248. AMS eBook Collections, 2008.
[19] Alessandro Rinaldo. Properties and reﬁnements of the fused lasso. An-
nals of Statistics, 37(5): 2922?2952, 2009. [20] Leonid I. Rudin, Stanley Osher,
and Emad Faterni. Nonlinear total variation based noise removal algorithms.
Physica D: Nonlinear Phenomena, 60(1):259?268, 1992.
[21] Veeranjaneyulu
Sadhanala and Ryan J. Tibshirani. Additive models via trend ﬁltering. arXiv:
1702.05037, 2017. 10

[22] Veeranjaneyulu Sadhanala, Yu-Xiang Wang, and Ryan J. Tibshirani.
Total variation classes beyond 1d: Minimax rates, and the limitations of lin-
ear smoothers. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems, 29, 2016.
[23] James Sharpnack, Alessandro Rinaldo, and Aarti Singh. Sparsistency via
the edge lasso. International Conference on Artiﬁcial Intelligence and Statis-
tics, 15, 2012. [24] Gabriel Steidl, Stephan Didas, and Julia Neumann. Splines
in higher order TV regularization. International Journal of Computer Vision,
70(3):214?255, 2006. [25] Wesley Tansey and James Scott. A fast and ﬂexible
algorithm for the graph-fused lasso. arXiv: 1505.06475, 2015. [26] Robert Tib-
shirani, Michael Saunders, Saharon Rosset, Ji Zhu, and Keith Knight. Sparsity
and smoothness via the fused lasso. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society:
Series B, 67(1):91?108, 2005. [27] Ryan J. Tibshirani. Adaptive piecewise poly-
nomial estimation via trend ﬁltering. Annals of Statistics, 42(1):285?323, 2014.
[28] Ryan J. Tibshirani and Jonathan Taylor. The solution path of the gen-
[29] Alexandre B.
eralized lasso. Annals of Statistics, 39(3):1335?1371, 2011.
Tsybakov.
[30]
Yu-Xiang Wang, Alexander Smola, and Ryan J. Tibshirani. The falling facto-
rial basis and its statistical applications. International Conference on Machine
Learning, 31, 2014.
[31] Yu-Xiang Wang, James Sharpnack, Alex Smola, and
Ryan J. Tibshirani. Trend ﬁltering on graphs. Journal of Machine Learning
Research, 17(105):1?41, 2016.

Introduction to Nonparametric Estimation. Springer, 2009.

11

14

