Style Transfer from Non-Parallel Text by

Cross-Alignment

Authored by:

Tommi Jaakkola
Regina Barzilay
Tianxiao Shen

Tao Lei

Abstract

This paper focuses on style transfer on the basis of non-parallel text.
This is an instance of a broad family of problems including machine trans-
lation, decipherment, and sentiment modiﬁcation. The key challenge is to
separate the content from other aspects such as style. We assume a shared
latent content distribution across diﬀerent text corpora, and propose a
method that leverages reﬁned alignment of latent representations to per-
form style transfer. The transferred sentences from one style should match
example sentences from the other style as a population. We demonstrate
the eﬀectiveness of this cross-alignment method on three tasks: sentiment
modiﬁcation, decipherment of word substitution ciphers, and recovery of
word order.

1 Paper Body

Using massive amounts of parallel data has been essential for recent advances in
text generation tasks, such as machine translation and summarization. However,
in many text generation problems, we can only assume access to non-parallel
or mono-lingual data. Problems such as decipherment or style transfer are all
instances of this family of tasks. In all of these problems, we must preserve the
content of the source sentence but render the sentence consistent with desired
presentation constraints (e.g., style, plaintext/ciphertext). The goal of control-
ling one aspect of a sentence such as style independently of its content requires
that we can disentangle the two. However, these aspects interact in subtle ways
in natural language sentences, and we can succeed in this task only approxi-
mately even in the case of parallel data. Our task is more challenging here. We
merely assume access to two corpora of sentences with the same distribution
of content albeit rendered in diﬀerent styles. Our goal is to demonstrate that
this distributional equivalence of content, if exploited carefully, suﬃces for us

1

to learn to map a sentence in one style to a style-independent content vector
and then decode it to a sentence with the same content but a diﬀerent style. In
this paper, we introduce a reﬁned alignment of sentence representations across
text corpora. We learn an encoder that takes a sentence and its original style
indicator as input, and maps it to a style-independent content representation.
This is then passed to a style-dependent decoder for rendering. We do not use
typical VAEs for this mapping since it is imperative to keep the latent content
representation rich and unperturbed. Indeed, richer latent content representa-
tions are much harder to align across the corpora and therefore they oﬀer more
informative content constraints. Moreover, we reap additional information from
cross-generated (style-transferred) sentences, thereby getting two distributional
alignment constraints. For example, positive sentences that are style-transferred
into negative sentences should match, as a population, the given set of negative
sentences. We illustrate this cross-alignment in Figure 1. 1

Our code and data are available at https://github.com/shentianxiao/language-

style-transfer.

31st Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS 2017),

Long Beach, CA, USA.

Figure 1: An overview of the proposed cross-alignment method. X1 and X2
are two sentence domains with diﬀerent styles y1 and y2 , and Z is the shared
latent content space. Encoder E maps a sentence to its content representation,
and generator G generates the sentence back when combining with the original
style. When combining with a diﬀerent style, transferred X?1 is aligned with
X2 and X?2 is aligned with X1 at the distributional level. To demonstrate
the ﬂexibility of the proposed model, we evaluate it on three tasks: sentiment
modiﬁcation, decipherment of word substitution ciphers, and recovery of word
order. In all of these applications, the model is trained on non-parallel data.
On the sentiment modiﬁcation task, the model successfully transfers the senti-
ment while keeps the content for 41.5% of review sentences according to human
evaluation, compared to 41.0% achieved by the control-gen model of Hu et al.
(2017).
It achieves strong performance on the decipherment and word order
recovery tasks, reaching Bleu score of 57.4 and 26.1 respectively, obtaining 50.2
and 20.9 gap than a comparable method without cross-alignment.

2
Related work
Style transfer in vision Non-parallel style transfer has been extensively stud-
ied in computer vision (Gatys et al., 2016; Zhu et al., 2017; Liu and Tuzel, 2016;
Liu et al., 2017; Taigman et al., 2016; Kim et al., 2017; Yi et al., 2017). Gatys
et al. (2016) explicitly extract content and style features, and then synthesize a
new image by combining ?content? features of one image with ?style? features
from another. More recent approaches learn generative networks directly via
generative adversarial training (Goodfellow et al., 2014) from two given data do-
mains X1 and X2 . The key computational challenge in this non-parallel setting
is aligning the two domains. For example, CoupledGANs (Liu and Tuzel, 2016)
employ weight-sharing between networks to learn cross-domain representation,
whereas CycleGAN (Zhu et al., 2017) introduces cycle consistency which relies

2

on transitivity to regularize the transfer functions. While our approach has a
similar high-level architecture, the discreteness of natural language does not al-
low us to reuse these models and necessitates the development of new methods.
Non-parallel transfer in natural language In natural language processing, most
tasks that involve generation (e.g., translation and summarization) are trained
using parallel sentences. Our work most closely relates to approaches that do
not utilize parallel data, but instead guide sentence generation from an indirect
training signal (Mueller et al., 2017; Hu et al., 2017). For instance, Mueller
et al. (2017) manipulate the hidden representation to generate sentences that
satisfy a desired property (e.g., sentiment) as measured by a corresponding clas-
siﬁer. However, their model does not necessarily enforce content preservation.
More similar to our work, Hu et al. (2017) aims at generating sentences with
controllable attributes by learning disentangled latent representations (Chen
et al., 2016). Their model builds on variational auto-encoders (VAEs) and
uses independency constraints to enforce that attributes can be reliably in-
ferred back from generated sentences. While our model builds on distributional
cross-alignment for the purpose of style transfer and content preservation, these
constraints can be added in the same way. Adversarial training over discrete
samples Recently, a wide range of techniques addresses challenges associated
with adversarial training over discrete samples generated by recurrent networks
(Yu et al., 2016; Lamb et al., 2016; Hjelm et al., 2017; Che et al., 2017). In our
work, we employ the Professor-Forcing algorithm (Lamb et al., 2016) which was
originally proposed to close the gap between teacher-forcing during training and
self-feeding during testing for recurrent networks. This design ﬁts well with our
scenario of style transfer that calls for cross-alignment. By using 2

continuous relaxation to approximate the discrete sampling process (Jang et
al., 2016; Maddison et al., 2016), the training procedure can be eﬀectively opti-
mized through back-propagation (Kusner and Hern?ndez-Lobato, 2016; Goyal
et al., 2017).

3
Formulation
In this section, we formalize the task of non-parallel style transfer and discuss
the feasibility of the learning problem. We assume the data are generated by the
following process: 1. a latent style variable y is generated from some distribution
p(y); 2. a latent content variable z is generated from some distribution p(z); 3.
a datapoint x is generated from conditional distribution p(x—y, z). We observe
two datasets with the same content distribution but diﬀerent styles y1 and y2
, where (1) (n) y1 and y2 are unknown. Speciﬁcally, the two observed datasets
X1 = {x1 , ? ? ? , x1 } and X2 = (1) (m) {x2 , ? ? ? , x2 } consist of samples
drawn from p(x1 —y1 ) and p(x2 —y2 ) respectively. We want to estimate the
style transfer functions between them, namely p(x1 —x2 ; y1 , y2 ) and p(x2
—x1 ; y1 , y2 ). A question we must address is when this estimation problem
is feasible. Essentially, we only observe the marginal distributions of x1 and x2
, yet we are going to recover their joint distribution: Z p(x1 , x2 —y1 , y2 ) =
p(z)p(x1 —y1 , z)p(x2 —y2 , z)dz (1) z

As we only observe p(x1 —y1 ) and p(x2 —y2 ), y1 and y2 are unknown to

3

us. If two diﬀerent y and y 0 lead to the same distribution p(x—y) = p(x—y 0 ),
then given a dataset X sampled from it, its underlying style can be either y or y
0 . Consider the following two cases: (1) both datasets X1 and X2 are sampled
from the same style y; (2) X1 and X2 are sampled from style y and y 0 respec-
tively. These two scenarios have diﬀerent joint distributions, but the observed
marginal distributions are the same. To prevent such confusion, we constrain
the underlying distributions as stated in the following proposition: Proposition
1. In the generative framework above, x1 and x2 ?s joint distribution can be
recovered from their marginals only if for any diﬀerent y, y 0 ? Y, distributions
p(x—y) and p(x—y 0 ) are diﬀerent. This proposition basically says that X gen-
erated from diﬀerent styles should be ?distinct? enough, otherwise the transfer
task between styles is not well deﬁned. While this seems trivial, it may not hold
even for simpliﬁed data distributions. The following examples illustrate how
the transfer (and recovery) becomes feasible or infeasible under diﬀerent model
assumptions. As we shall see, for a certain family of styles Y, the more complex
distribution for z, the more probable it is to recover the transfer function and
the easier it is to search for the transfer. 3.1

Example 1: Gaussian
Consider the common choice that z ? N (0, I) has a centered isotropic
Gaussian distribution. Suppose a style y = (A, b) is an aﬃne transformation,
i.e. x = Az + b + , where is a noise variable. For b = 0 and any orthogonal
matrix A, Az + b ? N (0, I) and hence x has the same distribution for any
such styles y = (A, 0). In this case, the eﬀect of rotation cannot be recovered.
Interestingly, if z has a more complex distribution, such as a Gaussian mixture,
then aﬃne transformations can be uniquely determined. PK Lemma 1. Let z be
a mixture of Gaussians p(z) = k=1 ?k N (z; ?k , ?k ). Assume K ? 2, and there
are two diﬀerent ?i 6= ?j . Let Y = {(A, b)——A— = 6 0} be all invertible aﬃne
transformations, and p(x—y, z) = N (x; Az + b, 2 I), in which is a noise. Then
for all y 6= y 0 ? Y, p(x—y) and p(x—y 0 ) are diﬀerent distributions. Theorem
1. If the distribution of z is a mixture of Gaussians which has more than two
diﬀerent components, and x1 , x2 are two aﬃne transformations of z, then the
transfer between them can be recovered given their respective marginals. 3

3.2
Example 2: Word substitution
Consider here another example when z is a bi-gram language model and a
style y is a vocabulary in use that maps each ?content word? onto its surface
form (lexical form). If we observe two realizations x1 and x2 of the same lan-
guage z, the transfer and recovery problem becomes inferring a word alignment
between x1 and x2 . Note that this is a simpliﬁed version of language decipher-
ment or translation. Nevertheless, the recovery problem is still suﬃciently hard.
To see this, let M1 , M2 ? Rn?n be the estimated bi-gram probability matrix of
data X1 and X2 respectively. Seeking the word alignment is equivalent to ﬁnd-
ing a permutation matrix P such that P ¿ M1 P ? M2 , which can be expressed
as an optimization problem, min kP ¿ M1 P ? M2 k2 P

The same formulation applies to graph isomorphism (GI) problems given M1
and M2 as the adjacency matrices of two graphs, suggesting that determining

4

the existence and uniqueness of P is at least GI hard. Fortunately, if M as
a graph is complex enough, the search problem could be more tractable. For
instance, if each vertex?s weights of incident edges as a set is unique, then
ﬁnding the isomorphism can be done by simply matching the sets of edges. This
assumption largely applies to our scenario where z is a complex language model.
We empirically demonstrate this in the results section. The above examples
suggest that z as the latent content variable should carry most complexity of
data x, while y as the latent style variable should have relatively simple eﬀects.
We construct the model accordingly in the next section.

4
Method
Learning the style transfer function under our generative assumption is es-
sentially learning the conditional distribution p(x1 —x2 ; y1 , y2 ) and p(x2
—x1 ; y1 , y2 ). Unlike in vision where images are continuous and hence the
transfer functions can be learned and optimized directly, the discreteness of
language requires us to operate through the latent space. Since x1 and x2 are
conditionally independent given the latent content variable z, Z p(x1 —x2 ; y1
, y2 ) = p(x1 , z—x2 ; y1 , y2 )dz Zz (2) = p(z—x2 , y2 ) ? p(x1 —y1 , z)dz z
= Ez?p(z—x2 ,y2 ) [p(x1 —y1 , z)] This suggests us learning an auto-encoder
model. Speciﬁcally, a style transfer from x2 to x1 involves two steps?an encoding
step that infers x2 ?s content z ? p(z—x2 , y2 ), and a decoding step which
generates the transferred counterpart from p(x1 —y1 , z).
In this work, we
approximate and train p(z—x, y) and p(x—y, z) using neural networks (where
y ? {y1 , y2 }). Let E : X ? Y ? Z be an encoder that infers the content z for a
given sentence x and a style y, and G : Y ? Z ? X be a generator that generates
a sentence x from a given style y and content z. E and G form an auto-encoder
when applying to the same style, and thus we have reconstruction loss, Lrec (?E
, ?G ) = Ex1 ?X1 [? log pG (x1 —y1 , E(x1 , y1 ))] + Ex2 ?X2 [? log pG (x2
—y2 , E(x2 , y2 ))]

(3)
where ? are the parameters to estimate.

In order to make a meaningful
transfer by ﬂipping the style, X1 and X2 ?s content space must coincide, as our
generative framework presumed. To constrain that x1 and x2 are generated from
the same latent content distribution p(z), one option is to apply a variational
auto-encoder (Kingma and Welling, 2013). A VAE imposes a prior density
p(z), such as z ? N (0, I), and uses a KL-divergence regularizer to align both
posteriors pE (z—x1 , y1 ) and pE (z—x2 , y2 ) to it, LKL (?E ) = Ex1 ?X1
[DKL (pE (z—x1 , y1 )kp(z))] + Ex2 ?X2 [DKL (pE (z—x2 , y2 )kp(z))] 4

(4)
The overall objective is to minimize Lrec + LKL , whose opposite is the
variational lower bound of data likelihood. However, as we have argued in
the previous section, restricting z to a simple and even distribution and push-
ing most complexity to the decoder may not be a good strategy for non-parallel
style transfer. In contrast, a standard auto-encoder simply minimizes the recon-
struction error, encouraging z to carry as much information about x as possible.
On the other hand, it lowers the entropy in p(x—y, z), which helps to produce

5

meaningful style transfer in practice as we ﬂip between y1 and y2 . Without
explicitly modeling p(z), it is still possible to force distributional alignment of
p(z—y1 ) and p(z—y2 ). To this end, we introduce two constrained variants of
auto-encoder. 4.1

Aligned auto-encoder
Dispense with VAEs that make an explicit assumption about p(z) and align
both posteriors to it, we align pE (z—y1 ) and pE (z—y2 ) with each other,
which leads to the following constrained optimization problem: ? ? = arg min
Lrec (?E , ?G ) ?

(5)
d
s.t. E(x1 , y1 ) = E(x2 , y2 )
x1 ? X1 , x2 ? X2
In practice, a Lagrangian relaxation of the primal problem is instead op-
timized. We introduce an adversarial discriminator D to align the aggregated
posterior distribution of z from diﬀerent styles (Makhzani et al., 2015). D aims
to distinguish between these two distributions: Ladv (?E , ?D ) = Ex1 ?X1 [?
log D(E(x1 , y1 ))] + Ex2 ?X2 [? log(1 ? D(E(x2 , y2 )))]

(6)
The overall training objective is a min-max game played among the encoder
E, generator G and discriminator D. They constitute an aligned auto-encoder:
min max Lrec ? ?Ladv E,G

D
(7)
We implement the encoder E and generator G using single-layer RNNs with
GRU cell. E takes an input sentence x with initial hidden state y, and outputs
the last hidden state z as its content representation. G generates a sentence x
conditioned on latent state (y, z). To align the distributions of z1 = E(x1 , y1
) and z2 = E(x2 , y2 ), the discriminator D is a feed-forward network with a
single hidden layer and a sigmoid output layer. 4.2

Cross-aligned auto-encoder
The second variant, cross-aligned auto-encoder, directly aligns the transfered
samples from one style with the true samples from the other. Under the gener-
ative assumption, p(x2 —y2 ) = R p(x 2 —x1 ; y1 , y2 )p(x1 —y1 )dx1 , thus
x2 (sampled from the left-hand side) should exhibit the x1 same distribution as
transferred x1 (sampled from the right-hand side), and vice versa. Similar to
our ﬁrst model, the second model uses two discriminators D1 and D2 to align
the populations. D1 ?s job is to distinguish between real x1 and transferred x2 ,
and D2 ?s job is to distinguish between real x2 and transferred x1 . Adversarial
training over the discrete samples generated by G hinders gradients propagation.
Although sampling-based gradient estimator such as REINFORCE (Williams,
1992) can by adopted, training with these methods can be unstable due to the
high variance of the sampled gradient.
Instead, we employ two recent tech-
niques to approximate the discrete training (Hu et al., 2017; Lamb et al., 2016).
First, instead of feeding a single sampled word as the input to the generator
RNN, we use the softmax distribution over words instead. Speciﬁcally, during

6

the generating process of transferred x2 from G(y1 , z2 ), suppose at time step
t the output logit vector is vt . We feed its peaked distribution softmax(vt /?)
as the next input, where ? ? (0, 1) is a temperature parameter. Secondly,
we use Professor-Forcing (Lamb et al., 2016) to match the sequence of hidden
states instead of the output words, which contains the information about out-
puts and is smoothly distributed. That is, the input to the discriminator D1 is
the sequence of hidden states of either (1) G(y1 , z1 ) teacher-forced by a real
example x1 , or (2) G(y1 , z2 ) self-fed by previous soft distributions. 5

Figure 2: Cross-aligning between x1 and transferred x2 . For x1 , G is
teacher-forced by its words w1 w2 ? ? ? wt . For transfered x2 , G is self-fed
by previous output logits. The sequence of hidden ? 0, ? ? ? , h ? t are passed
to discriminator D1 to be aligned. Note that our ﬁrst states h0 , ? ? ? , ht and
h ? 0 , i.e. z1 and z2 , are variant aligned auto-encoder is a special case of this,
where only h0 and h aligned.

Algorithm 1 Cross-aligned auto-encoder training. The hyper-parameters are
set as ? = 1, ? = 0.001 and learning rate is 0.0001 for all experiments in this
paper. Input: Two corpora of diﬀerent styles X1 , X2 . Lagrange multiplier ?,
temperature ?. Initialize ?E , ?G , ?D1 , ?D2 repeat for p = 1, 2; q = 2, 1 do
(i) Sample a mini-batch of k examples {xp }ki=1 from Xp (i) (i) Get the latent
content representations zp = E(xp , yp ) (i) (i) (i) Unroll G from initial state (yp
, zp ) by feeding xp , and get the hidden states sequence hp (i) Unroll G from
initial state (yq , zp ) by feeding previous soft output distribution with temper?
(i) ature ?, and get the transferred hidden states sequence h p end for Compute
the reconstruction Lrec by Eq. (3) Compute D1 ?s (and symmetrically D2 ?s)
loss: Ladv1 = ?

k k 1X 1X (i) ? (i) )) log D1 (h1 ) ? log(1 ? D1 (h 2 k i=1 k i=1
(8)
Update {?E , ?G } by gradient descent on loss Lrec ? ?(Ladv1 + Ladv2 )
(9)
Update ?D1 and ?D2 by gradient descent on loss Ladv1 and Ladv2 respec-
tively until convergence Output: Style transfer functions G(y2 , E(?, y1 )) : X1
? X2 and G(y1 , E(?, y2 )) : X2 ? X1

The running procedure of our cross-aligned auto-encoder is illustrated in
Figure 2. Note that crossaligning strengthens the alignment of latent variable
z over the recurrent network of generator G. By aligning the whole sequence of
hidden states, it prevents z1 and z2 ?s initial misalignment from propagating
through the recurrent generating process, as a result of which the transferred
sentence may end up somewhere far from the target domain. We implement
both D1 and D2 using convolutional neural networks for sequence classiﬁcation
(Kim, 2014). The training algorithm is presented in Algorithm 1. 6

5
Experimental setup
Sentiment modiﬁcation Our ﬁrst experiment focuses on text rewriting with
the goal of changing the underlying sentiment, which can be regarded as ?style
transfer? between negative and positive sentences. We run experiments on
Yelp restaurant reviews, utilizing readily available user ratings associated with

7

each review. Following standard practice, reviews with rating above three are
considered positive, and those below three are considered negative. While our
model operates at the sentence level, the sentiment annotations in our dataset
are provided at the document level. We assume that all the sentences in a docu-
ment have the same sentiment. This is clearly an oversimpliﬁcation, since some
sentences (e.g., background) are sentiment neutral. Given that such sentences
are more common in long reviews, we ﬁlter out reviews that exceed 10 sentences.
We further ﬁlter the remaining sentences by eliminating those that exceed 15
words. The resulting dataset has 250K negative sentences, and 350K positive
ones. The vocabulary size is 10K after replacing words occurring less than 5
times with the ?¡unk¿? token. As a baseline model, we compare against the
control-gen model of Hu et al. (2017). To quantitatively evaluate the transfered
sentences, we adopt a model-based evaluation metric similar to the one used for
image transfer (Isola et al., 2016). Speciﬁcally, we measure how often a trans-
ferred sentence has the correct sentiment according to a pre-trained sentiment
classiﬁer. For this purpose, we use the TextCNN model as described in Kim
(2014). On our simpliﬁed dataset for style transfer, it achieves nearly perfect
accuracy of 97.4%. While the quantitative evaluation provides some indication
of transfer quality, it does not capture all the aspects of this generation task.
Therefore, we also perform two human evaluations on 500 sentences randomly
selected from the test set2 . In the ﬁrst evaluation, the judges were asked to rank
generated sentences in terms of their ﬂuency and sentiment. Fluency was rated
from 1 (unreadable) to 4 (perfect), while sentiment categories were ?positive?,
?negative?, or ?neither? (which could be contradictory, neutral or nonsensical).
In the second evaluation, we evaluate the transfer process comparatively. The
annotator was shown a source sentence and the corresponding outputs of the
systems in a random order, and was asked ?Which transferred sentence is se-
mantically equivalent to the source sentence with an opposite sentiment??. They
can be both satisfactory, A/B is better, or both unsatisfactory. We collect two
labels for each question. The label agreement and conﬂict resolution strategy
can be found in the supplementary material. Note that the two evaluations are
not redundant. For instance, a system that always generates the same gram-
matically correct sentence with the right sentiment independently of the source
sentence will score high in the ﬁrst evaluation setup, but low in the second one.
Word substitution decipherment Our second set of experiments involves deci-
pherment of word substitution ciphers, which has been previously explored in
NLP literature (Dou and Knight, 2012; Nuhn and Ney, 2013). These ciphers
replace every word in plaintext (natural language) with a cipher token according
to a 1-to-1 substitution key. The decipherment task is to recover the plaintext
from ciphertext. It is trivial if we have access to parallel data. However we are
interested to consider a non-parallel decipherment scenario. For training, we
select 200K sentences as X1 , and apply a substitution cipher f on a diﬀerent set
of 200K sentences to get X2 . While these sentences are nonparallel, they are
drawn from the same distribution from the review dataset. The development
and test sets have 100K parallel sentences D1 = {x(1) , ? ? ? , x(n) } and D2
= {f (x(1) ), ? ? ? , f (x(n) )}. We can quantitatively compare between D1 and

8

transferred (deciphered) D2 using Bleu score (Papineni et al., 2002). Clearly,
the diﬃculty of this decipherment task depends on the number of substituted
words. Therefore, we report model performance with respect to the percentage
of the substituted vocabulary. Note that the transfer models do not know that
f is a word substitution function. They learn it entirely from the data distri-
bution. In addition to having diﬀerent transfer models, we introduce a simple
decipherment baseline based on word frequency. Speciﬁcally, we assume that
words shared between X1 and X2 do not require translation. The rest of the
words are mapped based on their frequency, and ties are broken arbitrarily. Fi-
nally, to assess the diﬃculty of the task, we report the accuracy of a machine
translation system trained on a parallel corpus (Klein et al., 2017). 2

we eliminated 37 sentences from them that were judged as neutral by human

judges.

7
Method Hu et al.

(2017) Variational auto-encoder Aligned auto-encoder

Cross-aligned auto-encoder

accuracy 83.5 23.2 48.3 78.4
Table 1: Sentiment accuracy of transferred sentences, as measured by a

pretrained classiﬁer.

Method Hu et al. (2017) Cross-align
sentiment 70.8 62.6
ﬂuency 3.2 2.8
overall transfer 41.0 41.5
Table 2: Human evaluations on sentiment, ﬂuency and overall transfer qual-
ity. Fluency rating is from 1 (unreadable) to 4 (perfect). Overall transfer quality
is evaluated in a comparative manner, where the judge is shown a source sen-
tence and two transferred sentences, and decides whether they are both good,
both bad, or one is better.

Word order recovery Our ﬁnal experiments focus on the word ordering task,
also known as bag translation (Brown et al., 1990; Schmaltz et al., 2016). By
learning the style transfer functions between original English sentences X1 and
shuﬄed English sentences X2 , the model can be used to recover the original
word order of a shuﬄed sentence (or conversely to randomly permute a sen-
tence). The process to construct non-parallel training data and parallel testing
data is the same as in the word substitution decipherment experiment. Again
the transfer models do not know that f is a shuﬄe function and learn it com-
pletely from data.

6
Results
Sentiment modiﬁcation Table 1 and Table 2 show the performance of various
models for both human and automatic evaluation. The control-gen model of Hu
et al. (2017) performs better in terms of sentiment accuracy in both evaluations.
This is not surprising because their generation is directly guided by a sentiment
classiﬁer. Their system also achieves higher ﬂuency score. However, these gains
do not translate into improvements in terms of the overall transfer, where our
model faired better. As can be seen from the examples listed in Table 3, our

9

model is more consistent with the grammatical structure and semantic meaning
of the source sentence. In contrast, their model achieves sentiment change by
generating an entirely new sentence which has little overlap with the original.
The discrepancy between the two experiments demonstrate the crucial impor-
tance of developing appropriate evaluation measures for comparing methods for
style transfer. Word substitution decipherment Table 4 summarizes the perfor-
mance of our model and the baselines on the decipherment task, at various levels
of word substitution. Consistent with our intuition, the last row in this table
shows that the task is trivial when the parallel data is provided. In non-parallel
case, the diﬃculty of the task is driven by the substitution rate. Across all the
testing conditions, our cross-aligned model consistently outperforms its coun-
terparts. The diﬀerence becomes more pronounced as the task becomes harder.
When the substitution rate is 20%, all methods do a reasonably good job in
recovering substitutions. However, when 100% of the words are substituted (as
expected in real language decipherment), the poor performance of variational
autoencoder and aligned auto-encoder rules out their application for this task.
Word order recovery The last column in Table 4 demonstrates the performance
on the word order recovery task. Order recovery is much harder?even when
trained with parallel data, the machine translation model achieves only 64.6
Bleu score. Note that some generated orderings may be completely valid (e.g.,
reordering conjunctions), but the models will be penalized for producing them.
In this task, only the cross-aligned auto-encoder achieves grammatical reorder
to a certain extent, demonstrated by its Bleu score 26.1. Other models fail this
task, doing no better than no transfer. 8

From negative to positive consistently slow . consistently good . consistently
fast . my goodness it was so gross . my husband ?s steak was phenomenal . my
goodness was so awesome . it was super dry and had a weird taste to the entire
slice . it was a great meal and the tacos were very kind of good . it was super
ﬂavorful and had a nice texture of the whole side . From positive to negative i
love the ladies here ! i avoid all the time ! i hate the doctor here ! my appetizer
was also very good and unique . my bf was n?t too pleased with the beans .
my appetizer was also very cold and not fresh whatsoever . came here with
my wife and her grandmother ! came here with my wife and hated her ! came
here with my wife and her son . Table 3: Sentiment transfer samples. The ﬁrst
line is an input sentence, the second and third lines are the generated sentences
after sentiment transfer by Hu et al. (2017) and our cross-aligned auto-encoder,
respectively.

Method No transfer (copy) Unigram matching Variational auto-encoder Aligned

auto-encoder Cross-aligned auto-encoder Parallel translation

20% 56.4 74.3 79.8 81.0 83.8 99.0
Substitution decipher 40% 60% 80% 100% 21.4 6.3 4.5 0 48.1 17.8 10.7 1.2

59.6 44.6 34.4 0.9 68.9 50.7 45.6 7.2 79.1 74.7 66.1 57.4 98.9 98.2 98.5 97.2

Order recover 5.1 5.3 5.2 26.1 64.6
Table 4: Bleu scores of word substitution decipherment and word order

recovery.

7

10

Conclusion
Transferring languages from one style to another has been previously trained
using parallel data.
In this work, we formulate the task as a decipherment
problem with access only to non-parallel data. The two data collections are
assumed to be generated by a latent variable generative model. Through this
view, our method optimizes neural networks by forcing distributional alignment
(invariance) over the latent space or sentence populations. We demonstrate the
eﬀectiveness of our method on tasks that permit quantitative evaluation, such
as sentiment transfer, word substitution decipherment and word ordering. The
decipherment view also provides an interesting open question?when can the
joint distribution p(x1 , x2 ) be recovered given only marginal distributions?
We believe addressing this general question would promote the style transfer
research in both vision and NLP. 9

Acknowledgments We thank Nicholas Matthews for helping to facilitate hu-
man evaluations, and Zhiting Hu for sharing his code. We also thank Jonas
Mueller, Arjun Majumdar, Olga Simek, Danelle Shah, MIT NLP group and the
reviewers for their helpful comments. This work was supported by MIT Lincoln
Laboratory.

2 References

Peter F Brown, John Cocke, Stephen A Della Pietra, Vincent J Della Pietra,
Fredrick Jelinek, John D Laﬀerty, Robert L Mercer, and Paul S Roossin. A sta-
tistical approach to machine translation. Computational linguistics, 16(2):79?85,
1990. Tong Che, Yanran Li, Ruixiang Zhang, R Devon Hjelm, Wenjie Li,
Yangqiu Song, and Yoshua Bengio. Maximum-likelihood augmented discrete
generative adversarial networks. arXiv preprint arXiv:1702.07983, 2017. Xi
Chen, Yan Duan, Rein Houthooft, John Schulman, Ilya Sutskever, and Pieter
Abbeel.
Infogan: Interpretable representation learning by information maxi-
mizing generative adversarial nets. In Advances in neural information process-
ing systems, 2016. Qing Dou and Kevin Knight. Large scale decipherment
for out-of-domain machine translation. In Proceedings of the 2012 Joint Con-
ference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Compu-
tational Natural Language Learning, pages 266?275. Association for Compu-
tational Linguistics, 2012. Leon A Gatys, Alexander S Ecker, and Matthias
Bethge. Image style transfer using convolutional neural networks. In Proceed-
ings of the IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition,
pages 2414?2423, 2016.
Ian Goodfellow, Jean Pouget-Abadie, Mehdi Mirza,
Bing Xu, David Warde-Farley, Sherjil Ozair, Aaron Courville, and Yoshua Ben-
gio. Generative adversarial nets. In Advances in neural information processing
systems, pages 2672?2680, 2014. Kartik Goyal, Chris Dyer, and Taylor Berg-
Kirkpatrick. Diﬀerentiable scheduled sampling for credit assignment. arXiv
preprint arXiv:1704.06970, 2017. R Devon Hjelm, Athul Paul Jacob, Tong Che,
Kyunghyun Cho, and Yoshua Bengio. Boundaryseeking generative adversarial
networks. arXiv preprint arXiv:1702.08431, 2017. Zhiting Hu, Zichao Yang,

11

Xiaodan Liang, Ruslan Salakhutdinov, and Eric P Xing. Controllable text gen-
eration. arXiv preprint arXiv:1703.00955, 2017. Phillip Isola, Jun-Yan Zhu,
Tinghui Zhou, and Alexei A Efros. Image-to-image translation with conditional
adversarial networks. arXiv preprint arXiv:1611.07004, 2016. Eric Jang, Shixi-
ang Gu, and Ben Poole. Categorical reparameterization with gumbel-softmax.
arXiv preprint arXiv:1611.01144, 2016. Taeksoo Kim, Moonsu Cha, Hyunsoo
Kim, Jungkwon Lee, and Jiwon Kim. Learning to discover cross-domain rela-
tions with generative adversarial networks. arXiv preprint arXiv:1703.05192,
2017. Yoon Kim. Convolutional neural networks for sentence classiﬁcation.
arXiv preprint arXiv:1408.5882, 2014. Diederik P Kingma and Max Welling.
arXiv:1312.6114, 2013.

Auto-encoding variational bayes.
arXiv preprint
Guillaume Klein, Yoon Kim, Yuntian Deng, Jean Senellart, and Alexander
M Rush. Opennmt: Open-source toolkit for neural machine translation. arXiv
preprint arXiv:1701.02810, 2017. Matt J Kusner and Jos? Miguel Hern?ndez-
Lobato. Gans for sequences of discrete elements with the gumbel-softmax dis-
tribution. arXiv preprint arXiv:1611.04051, 2016. 10

Alex M Lamb, Anirudh Goyal ALIAS PARTH GOYAL, Ying Zhang, Saizheng
Zhang, Aaron C Courville, and Yoshua Bengio. Professor forcing: A new al-
gorithm for training recurrent networks.
In Advances In Neural Information
Processing Systems, pages 4601?4609, 2016. Ming-Yu Liu and Oncel Tuzel.
Coupled generative adversarial networks. In Advances in Neural Information
Processing Systems, pages 469?477, 2016. Ming-Yu Liu, Thomas Breuel, and
Jan Kautz. Unsupervised image-to-image translation networks. arXiv preprint
arXiv:1703.00848, 2017. Chris J Maddison, Andriy Mnih, and Yee Whye Teh.
The concrete distribution: A continuous relaxation of discrete random variables.
arXiv preprint arXiv:1611.00712, 2016. Alireza Makhzani, Jonathon Shlens,
Navdeep Jaitly, Ian Goodfellow, and Brendan Frey. Adversarial autoencoders.
arXiv preprint arXiv:1511.05644, 2015. Jonas Mueller, Tommi Jaakkola, and
David Giﬀord. Sequence to better sequence: continuous revision of combinato-
rial structures. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML), 2017.
Malte Nuhn and Hermann Ney. Decipherment complexity in 1: 1 substitution
ciphers. In ACL (1), pages 615?621, 2013. Kishore Papineni, Salim Roukos,
Todd Ward, and Wei-Jing Zhu. Bleu: a method for automatic evaluation of ma-
chine translation. In Proceedings of the 40th annual meeting on association for
computational linguistics, pages 311?318. Association for Computational Lin-
guistics, 2002. Allen Schmaltz, Alexander M. Rush, and Stuart Shieber. Word
ordering without syntax.
In Proceedings of the 2016 Conference on Empiri-
cal Methods in Natural Language Processing, pages 2319?2324. Association for
Computational Linguistics, 2016. Yaniv Taigman, Adam Polyak, and Lior Wolf.
Unsupervised cross-domain image generation. arXiv preprint arXiv:1611.02200,
2016. Ronald J Williams. Simple statistical gradient-following algorithms for
connectionist reinforcement learning. Machine learning, 8(3-4):229?256, 1992.
Zili Yi, Hao Zhang, Ping Tan Gong, et al. Dualgan: Unsupervised dual learning
for image-to-image translation. arXiv preprint arXiv:1704.02510, 2017. Lantao

12

Yu, Weinan Zhang, Jun Wang, and Yong Yu. Seqgan: sequence generative
adversarial nets with policy gradient. arXiv preprint arXiv:1609.05473, 2016.
Jun-Yan Zhu, Taesung Park, Phillip Isola, and Alexei A Efros. Unpaired image-
to-image translation using cycle-consistent adversarial networks. arXiv preprint
arXiv:1703.10593, 2017.

11
A
Proof of Lemma 1
PK Lemma 1. Let z be a mixture of Gaussians p(z) = k=1 ?k N (z; ?k , ?k
). Assume K ? 2, and there are two diﬀerent ?i 6= ?j . Let Y = {(A, b)——A—
= 6 0} be all invertible aﬃne transformations, and p(x—y, z) = N (x; Az + b,
2 I), in which is a noise. Then for all y 6= y 0 ? Y, p(x—y) and p(x—y 0 ) are
diﬀerent distributions. Proof. p(x—y = (A, b)) =

K X
?k N (x; A?k + b, A?k A¿ + 2 I)
k=1
For diﬀerent y = (A, b) and y 0 = (A0 , b0 ), p(x—y) = p(x—y 0 ) entails

that for k = 1, ? ? ? , K,

A?k + b = A0 ?k + b0 A?k A¿ = A0 ?k A0¿ Since all Y are invertible,
(A?1 A0 )?k (A?1 A0 )¿ = ?k
?1 0 Suppose ?k = Qk Dk Q¿ A k is ?k ?s orthogonal diagonalization. If k

= 1, all solutions for A have the form:

n o
QD 1/2 U D ?1/2 Q¿ U is orthogonal
However, when K ? 2 and there are two diﬀerent ?i 6= ?j , the only solution
is A?1 A0 = I, i.e. A = A0 , and thus b = b0 . Therefore, for all y 6= y 0 ,
p(x—y) 6= p(x—y 0 ).

12

13

